<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts about desperate plea)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/categories/desperate-plea.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 23:01:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Physics Challenge Update</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/physics-challenge-update/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mQtqC-5MmYk/Tq9MkU56O9I/AAAAAAAAAPE/iaFRwtMKwJ0/s1600/mary_mcwatch.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mQtqC-5MmYk/Tq9MkU56O9I/AAAAAAAAAPE/iaFRwtMKwJ0/s320/mary_mcwatch.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Marty McFly realizes he is running out of time to submit his solution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know that our &lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachine.php"&gt;Physics
Challenge&lt;/a&gt;
problem contest thingy is still up and going? It is! The contest will be
open until the end of the day this &lt;strong&gt;Friday, November 4th&lt;/strong&gt;. And, unlike
last time, the winning solution will be chosen and posted by the end of
the weekend. So even if you don't submit your own solution (though you
&lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; should), check back here Monday morning for the winning entry.
Why should you submit a solution to our problem? Lots of reasons! The
top ten reasons as decided by a random sample of me are given below the
break. &lt;strong&gt;Top Ten Reasons to Submit a Solution:&lt;/strong&gt; 1) You will win
super-awesome prizes! What kinds of prizes? Well how does a greeting
card with kittens on the front and a collection of encouraging haikus
from the entire Virtuosi staff written inside sound? It sounds awesome,
awesome to the max. 2) You get to show off your totally rad physics
skills! 3) You can put it on your resume/cv! The semi-annual Virtuosi
Physics Challenge problem winners are held to the same esteem as Fields
Medalists and Nobel Prize winners! 4) You will earn the respect and
admiration of your peers! Winners of this contest develop an aura that
all other people can see, fear, and respect. 5) You will become
stronger, faster, and more productive than ever before! This is a
scientifically proven fact perhaps. 6) You may gain the ability to talk
to animals! Have you ever wanted to discuss espionage-related topics
with a platypus (perhaps this
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ONgjXrOShlc"&gt;platypus&lt;/a&gt;)? Of course you
have! Winners can! 7) You will be in Presidential company! Did you know
William Henry Harrison won the very first Virtuosi physics challenge
contest shortly before becoming the ninth President of the United
States? Yep! Tippecanoe and so can you! 8) Alemi will salute in your
general direction. No questions asked. 9) You will give me work to do on
the weekend! This will give my dull and uninteresting life a small
glimmer of meaning! Hooray! 10) There's like a 50% chance that you will
get three wishes from a magical genie named David Bowie (no relation).
Seriously. Like 50%. That should get you properly motivated! So check
out the Challenge Problem
&lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachine.php"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;
and when you have a solution, send it to our email address (given up in
the sidebar). Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>desperate plea</category><category>hooray</category><category>physics challenge</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/physics-challenge-update/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2011 22:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>