<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts about end of the earth)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/categories/end-of-the-earth.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 23:01:57 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>End of the Earth VI: Nanobot destruction</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/end-of-the-earth-vi-nanobot-destruction/</link><dc:creator>Alemi</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-hGkMD-tB1RY/TbGfhRvcA6I/AAAAAAAAAQ4/eCaG-z1Zarc/s1600/612px-C60a.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-hGkMD-tB1RY/TbGfhRvcA6I/AAAAAAAAAQ4/eCaG-z1Zarc/s320/612px-C60a.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's destroy the earth with technology. A while ago, I read the novel
&lt;em&gt;Postsingular&lt;/em&gt; by Rudy Rucker, and in the first chapter the Earth gets
destroyed, and then undestroyed, and then the novel unfolds and the
Earth's likelihood is threatened again, and it looks like the Earth will
be destroyed, but it isn't. How does all of this craziness happen you
might ask: nanobots! The story revolves around little self-replicating
robots. The story explores what it would be like to live in a world
where every surface on Earth was coated in little computers, all of
which were networked together. It's certainly a neat idea, but whenever
you have self-replicating things, you need to worry a bit about what
might happen if they get out of control. So, let's assume we, evil
scientists that we are, have managed to create a little self-replicating
nanobot. This little guy can scurry around, running off something
ubiquitous, probably some combination of solar, and some kind of
infrared photovoltaics. This little guy, call him Bob, his only mission
in life is to create a friend. He scurries around collecting the various
ingredients necessary, and using his little robot arms, he slices and
dices up the pieces and welds them together to create another copy of
himself, Rob. Not satisfied with his work; Bob found Rob quite the bore,
and honestly Rob didn't too much like Bob either, both of them part ways
and try to fashion a new friend. How long until Bob and Rob and their
cohorts manage to chew through all of the material on Earth? What we
have here is the setup to a problem in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exponential_growth"&gt;Exponential
Growth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Exponential Growth&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's simplify things a bit and assume that the nanobots always take a
fixed amount to time to make a new copy of themselves, call that time T.
We'll start with one guy, so we know that at t =0, we have 1 bot $$ N(t
=0 ) = 1 $$ And we know that after T seconds we should have 2 $$ N(T) =
2 $$ and after 2T seconds, we've managed to double twice and get 4 $$
N(2T) = 4 $$ after 3T seconds we'll double again to 8, etc. In fact,
after nT seconds, so m repetitions we should have doubled m times $$
N(nT) = 2^n $$ So if we want to describe all times, we need only ask
how many doublings can fit into t seconds $$ t = n T $$ which gives us
$$ N(t) = 2^{t/T} $$ At this point you might object, as this formula
doesn't always give an integer, so we could ask things like how many
bots are there after 0.5T seconds? We know the true answer is still 1,
Bob hasn't finished Rob yet, but our formula tells us the answer is
1.414... What we've done is made a continuous approximation to a
discrete function. Certainly, we've paid a price, in that our new
formula doesn't get answers right in fractions of T, but its a small
price to pay for the mathematical simplicity afforded by the nice
continuous function, and as long as we don't really care about time
scales smaller than T in the long run, we haven't done any real harm.
These kinds of approximations show up all over the place in physics, and
going both ways too. Sometimes it is advantageous to treat some discrete
quantity as continuous, and sometimes it might be beneficial to treat
some continuous quantity as discrete. These kinds of approximations are
more than adequate, provided you don't really take the answers they give
you in the cases where your approximation starts to break too seriously.
In this case, as long as we don't try to seriously predict the number of
nanobots to an exact count in time scales less than a fraction of their
doubling time, we will have a nice prediction of the number of bots
running around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Earth Destruction&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As promised, we wanted to calculate the time it would take the nanobots
to devour the earth. For this we need a little bit more to our model.
How will the nanobots eat the earth, I reckon it will be through using
up its mass. Assuming the bots are made out of elements that are rich
enough, something like iron, they ought to have a field day on Earth,
seeing as it's composed of about 5% iron on the surface, and with an
interior that is probably about 32% iron overall
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abundance_of_the_chemical_elements#Abundance_of_elements_in_the_Earth"&gt;[ref]&lt;/a&gt;.
So, we need to estimate the mass of a single nanobot. Let's say the
nanobot is roughly a 1 micron sized cube, made out of iron. This gives
us a nanobot mass of $$ m = (\text{ density of iron }) * (\text{ 1
micron} )^3 = \rho_{\text{Fe}} L^3 \sim 8 \text{ picograms} $$
From here we can estimate the time it would take to chew through the
earth, as the time for the nanobots to be as massive as the earth. $$
\frac{M_{\oplus}}{\rho_{\text{Fe}} L^3 } = N(t) = 2^{t/T} $$
Solving for t we obtain $$ t = T \log_2 \frac{ M_{\oplus}}{
\rho_{\text{Fe}} L^3 } $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Solution&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's say it takes Bob one month to make Rob, which I don't think is a
completely unrealistic time for nanobot replication, assuming Bob and
Rob and all of their cohorts are 1 micron in size, I calculate that in
10 years time they would chew through the Earth. The power of
exponential growth! Even with a 1 month gestation, if left unabashed,
the self-replicating robots would eat the entire earth in 10 years time.
They could eat through Mars in about 2. In fact in &lt;em&gt;Postsingular&lt;/em&gt; this
is what the humans planned. They wanted a Dyson sphere, so they sent
some self-replicating robots to Mars, let them chew through it a couple
years, and they had 10^37 little robots to do their bidding. That is of
course until the nants set their sites on Earth as their next target...
In order to let you play around with the doubling time and bot size,
I've created a Wolfram Alpha widget that solves the above equation, feel
free to play around with the parameters and see how long Earth would
survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widget should be right above this text. If it isn't working for some
reason, here's a
&lt;a href="http://developer.wolframalpha.com/widgets/gallery/view.jsp?id=6a645314f9be6be7b902d4cc1f776d00"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>earth day</category><category>end of the earth</category><category>fun</category><category>nanobots</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/end-of-the-earth-vi-nanobot-destruction/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2011 13:11:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>End of the Earth V: There Goes the Sun</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/end-of-the-earth-v-there-goes-the-sun/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-LtXsyHxxSi0/TbDfL6l4tnI/AAAAAAAAAMg/l_12lafg6LQ/s1600/creepy_sun.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-LtXsyHxxSi0/TbDfL6l4tnI/AAAAAAAAAMg/l_12lafg6LQ/s320/creepy_sun.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  The Sun [photo courtesy of NASA]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People that know me well know that I have a lot in common with Robert
Frost. We both were born in March and we both employ rural New England
settings to explore complex social and philosophical themes in our
poetry. We also like the same rap groups. In honor of my literary
doppelganger, I will now, having already had the world end in
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-physics-i.html"&gt;fire&lt;/a&gt;,
try my hand at ice. Let's try to answer the question: "If the sun blinks
out of existence this instant, what is the temperature of the Earth as a
function of time?" The Sun, in addition to being the &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=haAhdtDmsOw"&gt;King of
Planets&lt;/a&gt;, is also what keeps
us all warm and toasty and alive. What happens if we turn that off?
Well, the Earth will cool by radiating its heat away into space. To see
how long this would take, let's make some assumptions. Let's model the
surface of the Earth as an ocean 1 km deep and let's pretend that all
the heat is stored in this ocean. Let's take the ocean to be liquid
water at T = 0 degrees Celsius. How long will it take this ocean to
freeze into ice at 0 degrees Celsius? Well, the amount of energy
released from the oceans as the water freezes is given by $$ Q = L_{w}
M_{ocean} $$ where L is the "latent heat of fusion" and M is the mass
of the water. The "latent heat of fusion" is a fancy way of saying "the
amount of energy released per unit mass as water turns to ice at
constant temperature." For water, we have that $$ L_{w} = 3.3 \times
10^5 \mbox{J/kg} $$ And for the mass of the ocean, it will be
convenient later to write it as $$ M_{ocean} = 4\pi {R_{\oplus}}^2
\Delta R \rho $$ Alright, so now we've got enough to say how much heat
energy we have, so how fast do we lose it? We can take the Earth to be a
blackbody radiator, so the power lost in such a case is: $$ P =4\pi
\sigma R_{\oplus}^2 T^4 $$ Since Power is just Energy per unit
Time, we now have all we need to get the time for total freezing of all
the oceans. We have: $$ t = \frac{Q}{P} = \frac{4\pi
{R_{\oplus}}^2 \Delta R \rho L_{w}}{4\pi \sigma R_{\oplus}^2
T^4} $$ Simplifying the above expression a bit, we get $$ t
=\frac{\Delta R \rho L_{w}}{\sigma T^4} $$ Now we can plug in some
numbers, $$ t =\frac{\left(10^3 \mbox{ m}\right) \times
\left(10^3 \frac{kg}{m^3}\right) \times \left(3.3 \times 10^5
\mbox{J/kg}\right)}{\left( 5.67 \times 10^{-8} J s^{-1} m^{-2}
K^{-4}\right) \times \left( 273 K\right)^4} $$ where we have made
sure to put our temperatures in Kelvin. Crunching the numbers with the
calculator we "borrowed" from Nic three months ago gives: $$ t = 10^9
\mbox{ s} $$ Remembering that a year is very nearly $$ 1 \mbox{ year}
= \pi \times 10^7 \mbox{ s}, $$ we find that the time for the oceans
to freeze after the sun disappears is about 30 years. Hooray! Now this
model was very simple. First of all, I assumed that the ocean
temperatures were already at 0 degrees, but they are a bit warmer. If
the oceans are about 300 K (ie 80 degrees in not-Yariv units), then we
get another 30 years to cool down to freezing temperatures. Secondly, I
have completely neglected the heat stored in the Earth. Will this change
my answer by an embarrassingly large factor? Lastly, I have ignored all
internal heating mechanisms (ie, radioactive decay) that will also heat
up the Earth. But ignoring all that.... So is there a way for anyone to
survive this? Well, for the most part it will mean the end of life on
Earth. There could potentially be a few exceptions, like by geothermal
vents and such. But for the most part, it's one quick cold spiral down
to eternal nothingness. But what about a few people, could they survive
for a bit even if the human race is doomed? I'm glad you asked! You see,
I have this plan involving mine shafts. Hunkering down underground with
a nuclear power plant and all the canned food food we can stomach should
allow us to at least ride the rest of our lives. Details can be found
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iesXUFOlWC0&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>end of the earth</category><category>scott bakula</category><category>sun</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/end-of-the-earth-v-there-goes-the-sun/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2011 09:42:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>End of the Earth IV - Shocking Destruction</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/end-of-the-earth-iv-shocking-destruction/</link><dc:creator>Jesse</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-aa4EF60W7m0/TbCwQ8Vc3WI/AAAAAAAAAEU/03HiJiGJ6hc/s1600/exploding-earth11.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-aa4EF60W7m0/TbCwQ8Vc3WI/AAAAAAAAAEU/03HiJiGJ6hc/s200/exploding-earth11.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Earth day is upon us once more. So many other namby-pamby bloggers out
there (don't hurt me!) are writing about how wonderful the earth is and
how great earth day is. We here at The Virtuosi take a more hardline
approach. Today I'm going to tell you how to destroy the earth.
Completely and totally. Unlike
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-physics-i.html"&gt;last&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory.html"&gt;year's&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-physics-iii-asteroids.html"&gt;methods&lt;/a&gt;,
this one should work. In fact, this method is so simple that I can tell
you what to do right now. Just tweak the charge on the electron so it is
a bit out of balance with the charge on the proton. Just a little bit.
How little a bit, you might ask? A very little bit. Really, this doesn't
sound hard. I mean, sure, you have to do it for all of the electrons in
the earth, but we're talking about a very very small percentage change.
Not convinced? Let me show you just how small a change we're talking. If
there is a charge imbalance in the electron and the proton, this will
give the earth a net charge, throughout it's volume. I've got to make a
few assumptions about the earth here, so hold on. I'm going to assume
that the earth is a uniform density everywhere, and I'm going to assume
that the earth is made entirely of iron.&lt;em&gt; Now, the net charge of any
iron atom will be $$ (q_e-q_p)Z=(q_e-q_p)26$$ where Z is the atomic
number of iron, the number of protons (and electrons) the atom has. The
net charge of the earth, Q, is the number of iron atoms, N, times this
charge, $$Q=(q_e-q_p)ZN$$ I've &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory.html"&gt;previously
estimated&lt;/a&gt;
that N is about 3&lt;/em&gt;10^50 atoms. Now, the electric potential energy of a
sphere of radius r with charge q uniformly distributed throughout it's
volume is $$U_e=\frac{3kq^2}{5r}$$ where k is the coulomb constant.
Dissolution of the earth will occur when the electrostatic energy of the
earth equals the gravitational potential energy of the earth. The
gravitational bound energy of the earth is given by
$$U_g=\frac{3GM^2}{5R}$$ Where M is the mass of the earth, G is
Newton's gravitational constant, and R is the radius of the earth.
Setting this equal to the electrostatic energy of the earth,
$$\frac{3GM^2}{5R}=\frac{3kQ^2}{5R}$$ $$Q^2=\frac{G}{k}M^2$$ so
$$(q_e-q_p)ZN=\left(\frac{G}{k}\right)^{1/2}M$$ Now, N is given,
in our approximations, by $$N=\frac{M_{earth}}{m_{iron}}$$ so
$$q_e-q_p=\left(\frac{G}{k}\right)^{1/2}\frac{m_{iron}}{Z_{iron}}$$
Now we can plug in some numbers. G=6.7&lt;em&gt;10^-11 m^3&lt;/em&gt;kg^-1&lt;em&gt;s^-2, k=
9&lt;/em&gt;10^9 m^3&lt;em&gt;kg&lt;/em&gt;s^-2&lt;em&gt;C^-2, m_iron=9&lt;/em&gt;10^-26 kg, Z=26. Thus,
$$q_e-q_p=3&lt;em&gt;10^{-37} C$$ To put this in perspective, the charge on
the electron is 1.6&lt;/em&gt;10^-19 C, so this is roughly 10^18 times less
than that charge. Put another way, if the charge on the electron was
imbalanced from that of the proton by roughly 1 part in 10^18, the
earth would cease to exist due to electrostatic repulsion.&lt;strong&gt; As I told
you at the beginning, you only have to change the charge by a very small
amount! So get working. There are only about
1000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000 electrons you need
to modify! *According to the internet, the density of the earth, on
average, is roughly 5.5 g/cm^3. The density of iron is 7.9 g/cm^3 at
room temperature, and the density of water is 1 g/cm^3 at room
temperature. So, while the earth is not entirely iron (of course), it is
a better approximation to assume the earth is iron than the earth is
water. And those, of course, were really our only two choices. &lt;/strong&gt; It
turns out that this is a good argument for the charge balance of the
electron and the proton.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>charge</category><category>electron</category><category>end of the earth</category><category>proton</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/end-of-the-earth-iv-shocking-destruction/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2011 07:54:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Why Black Holes from the Large Hadron Collider Won't Destroy the World</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/why-black-holes-from-the-large-hadron-collider-won-t-destroy-the-world/</link><dc:creator>Nic Eggert</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone. As this is my first post, I thought I'd introduce myself.
Like the rest of the Virtuosi, I'm a graduate student in physics at
Cornell University. I work in experimental particle physics, in
particular on the Compact Muon Solenoid, one of the detectors at the
Large Hadron Collider. I'll post more on what I actually do at some
point in the future, but I thought I'd start with a post in the spirit
of some of the other fun calculations that we've done. My goal is to
convince you that black holes created by the LHC cannot possibly destroy
the world.
To start with, the main reason no one working on the LHC is too
concerned about black holes is because of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawking_radiation"&gt;Hawking
radiation&lt;/a&gt;. While we
usually think of black holes as objects that nothing can escape from,
Stephen Hawking predicted that black holes actually do emit some light,
losing energy (and mass) in the process. In the case of the little bitty
black holes that the LHC could produce, they should just evaporate in a
shower of Hawking radiation.
That's great you say, but Hawking radiation has never actually been
observed. What if Hawking is wrong and the black holes won't evaporate?
Well, the usual next argument is that &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_ray"&gt;cosmic
rays&lt;/a&gt; from space bombard the
earth all the time, producing collisions many times more energetic than
what we'll be able to produce at the LHC. To me, this is a fairly
convincing argument. However, let's pretend we don't know about these
cosmic rays and that there's no Hawking radiation. We can calculate what
effect black holes produced by the LHC would have on the earth if they
do stick around.
To start out with, the most massive black hole the LHC could produce
would be around 10 Tera-electron-volts, or TeV. We're probably
overestimating here. The eventual goal is for the LHC collisions to be
14 TeV, but producing a particle with the entire collision energy is
incredibly unlikely (see &lt;a href="http://www.scientificblogging.com/quantum_diaries_survivor/fascinating_new_higgs_boson_search_dzero_experiment"&gt;Tomasso Dorigo's
post&lt;/a&gt;
for more details on why, along with more details than you probably
wanted to know about hadron colliders). However, we want to think about
the worst case scenario here, and we're just going to do an order of
magnitude calculation, so 10 TeV is a good number. Note that I'm using a
particle physics convention here of giving masses in terms of energies
using E=mc^2. For reference, 10 TeV is about 1000 times smaller than a
small virus.
Now from the mass of our black hole, we can get its size by calculating
something called the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwarzschild_radius"&gt;Schwarzschild
radius&lt;/a&gt;. The
Schwarzchild radius for a black hole of mass m is given by
$$r = \frac{2Gm}{c^2}\text{.}$$
Here G is Newton's gravitational constant and c is the speed of light.
Plugging our mass in gives us
$$r = 10^{-50} \text{meters.}$$
This is incredibly small! In fact as I was writing this, I realized that
it's actually smaller than the Planck length, which means our equation
for the Schwarzschild radius may be somewhat suspect. Nonetheless, let's
hope that if we ever figure out quantum gravity, it gives us a
correction of order one and proceed with our calculation, which is just
an order-of-magnitude affair anyway.
Now, anything that enters the Schwarzschild radius of the black hole is
absorbed by it. The lightest thing that we could imagine the black hole
swallowing is an electron. Let's figure out how long on average a black
hole would have to travel through material with the density of the earth
before it absorbs an electron. In the spirit of considering the worst
case scenario, we'll have the black hole travel at the speed of light,
and consider the earth to be the density of lead.
We could do a complicated cross-section calculation to find the rate at
which the black hole accumulates mass, but we can also get it right up
to factors of pi through unit analysis. We know that the answer should
involve the area of the black hole, the density of the earth, and the
speed of the black hole. We want our answer to have units of mass per
time to represent the mass accumulation rate of the black hole. The only
combination that gives the right units is
$$a=\frac{\text{mass}}{\text{time}} = \rho c
r^2=\frac{10,000\text{kg}}{\text{m}^3}\frac{3\times 10^8
\text{m}}{\text{s}}(10^{-50}\text{m})^2} =
10^{-88}\text{kg/s}\text{.}$$
Alright, now that we know how fast our black hole accumulates mass,
let's figure out how long it takes it to accumulate an electron. The
electron mass is
$$m_e = 10^{-30}\text{kg,}$$
so the time to accumulate an electron is
$$t = \frac{m_e}{a} = 10^{50}\text{s.}$$
Now, the current age of the universe is 10^17 seconds. The time it
takes our black hole to accumulate an electron is longer than the age of
the universe by many orders of magnitude! So, if the LHC produces black
holes, and if Hawking is wrong, the black holes will just fly straight
through the earth without interacting with anything. Even if we take the
size of the black hole to be the Planck length, our black hole
accumulates an electron in 10^25 seconds, which is still much longer
than the age of the universe.
So the moral of the story is that you should be excited about the new
discoveries that the LHC might produce, and you don't need to worry
about black holes.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>end of the earth</category><category>LHC</category><category>physics</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/why-black-holes-from-the-large-hadron-collider-won-t-destroy-the-world/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 16 May 2010 19:53:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>End of the Earth II - Blaze of Glory</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/end-of-the-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory/</link><dc:creator>Jesse</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S9CFFAkGooI/AAAAAAAAABM/2SpaTtw4ivI/s1600/Marvin_the_Martian.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S9CFFAkGooI/AAAAAAAAABM/2SpaTtw4ivI/s200/Marvin_the_Martian.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In honor of earth day today, many bloggers are posting things about how
to save the earth, or retrospectives on earth days past. We here at The
Virtuosi decided, what better way to celebrate the earth than to figure
out how to destroy it? So that is exactly what we intend to do. This
post will focus on the destruction of the earth by a laser beam. This is
a familiar concept. Whether it is Marvin the Martian or the Death Star,
destroying planets with lasers (or threatening to) is a common theme. We
will be considering two questions today. The first is fairly obvious:
how much power would the death star need to destroy the earth? The
second relates to a topic of continuing interest of mine: how much would
the death star recoil upon firing? First, the power we would need. Most
estimates of the death star's power seem to rely on simply overcoming
the gravitational binding energy of the earth. We're going to assume the
earth is a uniform density. We can easily calculate the gravitational
binding energy to be $$U_G=\frac{3GM_{earth}^2}{5R_{earth}}$$
$$U=2.3\cdot 10^{32} J$$ However, looking at the video of the death
star blast, it looks like the earth was more than just gravitationally
unbound. It looks like we've actually managed to atomize some of the
constituent molecules. Let us assume that about half of the earth gets
atomized. We're also going to assume that the earth is made entirely of
iron (not &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; bad an assumption). In a lattice, iron will have \~6
bonds, and the energy of each bond will be on the order of \~2 eV. We
can calculate the number of iron atoms, N, needed to give the mass of
the earth by: $$N=\frac{M_{earth}}{m_{iron}}$$ $$N=3\cdot 10^{50}
atoms$$ We assume half of these have all of their bonds broken, this
gives an energy required to break the bonds of $$E \approx
3N(2eV)=2.88\cdot 10^{32} J$$ This gives us a total destruction energy
of $$E_{tot}=5.2\cdot 10^{32} J$$ Analyzing the video of the firing
of the first death star tells us that the laser fired for about 4s, so
this is a power of 1.3&lt;em&gt;10^32 W! As an aside, that much energy is about
the total energy output of the sun over a day. That means the impulse
this laser delivered (momentum per second, or force) to the death star
must be the power over c, the speed of light (see my &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/today-id-like-to-approach-question-near.html"&gt;earlier
post&lt;/a&gt;
for a discussion of laser gun recoil). This is a force of 4.3&lt;/em&gt;10^23 N.
We now need to estimate the death star mass. According to &lt;a href="http://starwars.wikia.com/wiki/Death_Star"&gt;confidential
sources&lt;/a&gt; the death star had a
diameter of 150 km. The death star is made of metal, but it also has a
lot of empty space inside of it. We'll go ahead and assume it has the
density of water. This gives is a mass of $$M_{ds}=\tfrac{4}{3}\pi
r^3\rho=2.4\cdot 10^{13} kg$$ A quick glance at our numbers reveals
that we're going to need special relativity here! Otherwise we'd be
accelerating this thing well past the speed of light. We have a total
momentum change of 1.7&lt;em&gt;10^{24}kg&lt;/em&gt;m/s. This is a relativistic
momentum, which we can solve for v. The algebra is a tiny bit ugly, but
it turns out that velocity in terms of relativistic momentum is
$$v=\sqrt{\frac{p^2}{m^2+p^2/c^2}} \approx c $$ It turns out that
the death star would be moving so close to speed of light as to not
matter. That's fast! I think we can safely say that this laser recoil
would be noticed!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>end of the earth</category><category>lasers</category><category>marvin the martian</category><category>recoil</category><category>star wars</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/end-of-the-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 22 Apr 2010 14:26:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The End of Earth Physics I</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/the-end-of-earth-physics-i/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I was reading the Wikipedia page for the Hitchhiker's Guide books the
other day and found that it started as a series of radio shows called
"The Ends of Earth." At the end of each episode, the Earth would be
destroyed. Since I feel like this is the best way to end any TV
show/movie/book/news broadcast/Mayan calendar, I will shamelessly steal
the idea.
Since this is the first End of the Earth post, we will start small and
just consider the boiling off of all the world's oceans. To be precise,
we will consider how much energy it would take to turn all the world's
water at 0 degrees Celsius to water vapor at 100 degrees Celsius.
First we need to estimate the mass of all the water on earth. I will
make the assumptions that all water is fresh water and that the oceans
account for all water on earth. These are obviously not exactly true,
but will give the proper order of magnitude. The volume of a spherical
shell is given by
$$ \text{V} = 4 \pi R^{2} \Delta R $$
Taking the radius of the earth to be 6000 km, the ocean depth to be 1
km, and the fraction of earth covered by water to be 7/10 , we see that
$$ V_\text{water} = 4 \pi {R_{\text{earth}}^{2} \times
\text{height} \times \text{fraction}$$
$$ V_\text{water} = 4 \pi (6 \times 10^{6} \text{m})^{2} \times
10^{3} \text{m} \times (\frac{7}{10}) = 3 \times 10^{17}
\text{m}^{3}$$
Now we have the volume of the ocean. Now, since
$$ \text{Density} = \frac{Mass}{Volume}$$
we can calculate the mass of the oceans using the density of water to be
1000 kg / m^3.
$$ \text{Mass} = (\rho_\text{water})(V_\text{water}) = (1000
\frac{\text{kg}}{\text{m}^{3}})(3 \times 10^{17} \text{m}^{3}) =
3 \times 10^{20} \text{kg}$$
FUN FACT: The mass of all the water on earth is about 2% the mass of
that celestial punching bag known as Pluto.
Alright, now that we have the mass of the earth, we can start
calculating how much energy it would take to heat it up and boil it
away. The amount of heat Q required to raise the temperature of a given
material is
$$ Q_\text{heat} = \text{mc}\Delta\text{T} $$
where m is the mass of the thing we are heating, c is the specific heat
( the amount of energy required to heat our material up 1 degree
Celcius) and delta T is our change in temperature. This equation only
holds when there are no phase transitions, so we can use it to calculate
how much energy is needed to heat up the oceans from 0 degrees to 100
degrees:
$$ Q_\text{heat} = (3 \times 10^{20} \text{kg}) \times (4000
\frac{\text{J}}{\text{kg C}}) \times (100 \text{deg C}) = 10^{26}
\text{J} $$
where we have used the fact that the specific heat of water is about
4000 J/kg deg C.
So now we know how much energy it takes to bring water to its boiling
point, but this is not the same as boiling it off. To find that, we need
to calculate how much energy we have to add to liquid water at a
constant 100 degrees to turn it into water vapor. This is given by
$$ Q_{\text{boil}} = \text{mL} $$
where m is the mass again and L is the "latent heat of vaporization." It
tells us how much energy we need to add to turn a kilogram of liquid
water at 100 degrees to a kilogram of water vapor at 100 degrees. For
water, L is about 2*10^6 J/kg, so
$$ Q_{\text{boil}} = ( 3 \times 10^{20} \text{kg} ) \times (2
\times 10^{6} \frac{\text{J}}{\text{kg}}) = 6 \times 10^{26}
\text{J} $$
Comparing this to the energy calculated before, we see that amount of
energy needed to vaporize water at 100 degrees is about six times larger
than the amount of energy needed to heat up the water by 100 degrees!
Now we can calculate the total amount of energy to boil way the oceans:
$$ Q_{\text{total}} = Q_{\text{heat}} + Q_{\text{boil}} = 7
\times 10^{26} \text{J} $$
So how much energy is that really? Well the total power of the sun is
$$ L_{\text{sun}} = 4 \times 10^{26} \frac{\text{J}}{\text{s}} $$
Thus, it would take the entire energy output of the sun for about 2
seconds to boil away all the earth's oceans.
Now thats a lot of energy. To put this into the conventional unit of
destruction, this is equivalent to 10^11 Megatons of TNT. Typical
hydrogen bombs are 10 Megatons. So if you want to boil away the oceans
with H-bombs, you'd need about ten billion hydrogen bombs.
Luckily, short of constructing a reflecting Dyson sphere with a hole
that directs all the sun's radiation at the earth, these energies are
unobtainable. So don't panic.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>end of the earth</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/the-end-of-earth-physics-i/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 17 Apr 2010 16:25:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>