<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts about footprint)</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/categories/footprint.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 22:55:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>How Long Will a Bootprint Last on the Moon?</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-gEyp9bylwcQ/Tv5v7PlugjI/AAAAAAAAARU/OnVdFTPRGkI/s1600/bootprint_buzz.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-gEyp9bylwcQ/Tv5v7PlugjI/AAAAAAAAARU/OnVdFTPRGkI/s320/bootprint_buzz.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Buzz Aldrin's bootprint (source: Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I stumbled across a bunch of
&lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/apollo/revisited/index.html"&gt;pictures&lt;/a&gt;
of Apollo landing sites taken by one of the cameras onboard the Lunar
Reconnaissance Orbiter. The images have a resolution high enough that
you can resolve features on the surface down to about a meter. Looking
at the Apollo 17 &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/images/content/584392main_M168000580LR_ap17_area.jpg"&gt;landing
site&lt;/a&gt;,
you can see the trails of both astronauts and a moon buggy. It's pretty
cool. It also got me thinking about how long the landing sites would be
preserved. More specifically, I want to know how long Buzz Aldrin's
right bootprint (shown, incidentally, to the left) will last on the
Moon. Since the Moon has no atmosphere, the wind and rain that would
weather away a similar bootprint here on Earth are not present and it
seems as though the print would last a really long time. But how long?
Let's try to quantify it &lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#footnote-yariv"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Pick Your Poison
Before we get going, we need to figure out what physical process would
be most important in erasing a bootprint from the Moon. Although the
Moon lacks the conventional "weathering" we experience on Earth (due to
wind, rain, etc), it does experience something called "&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_weathering"&gt;space
weathering&lt;/a&gt;." Space
weathering is the changing of the lunar surface due to cosmic rays,
micrometeorite collisions, regular meteorite collisions, and the solar
wind &lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#footnote-wind"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Of these phenomena, the most apparent
and well-studied would be the meteorites which have covered the Moon in
craters. We adopt the meteorite impact as our primary means of wiping
out a bootprint and restate our question as follows: "How long would it
take for a meteorite to hit the Moon such that the resulting crater
wipes out Aldrin's right bootprint?" Background As it is currently
stated, we can answer our question if we knew the rate of formation and
size distribution of the craters on the Moon. We could count up all the
craters on the Moon (or a particular region of interest) and tabulate
their sizes. This would give us the size distribution. It would also
give us a headache and potentially drive us to lunacy
&lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#footnote-forced"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Luckily, someone has beat us to it. &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1966MNRAS.134..245C"&gt;Cross
(1966)&lt;/a&gt; used images
from the Ranger 7 and 8 missions to count craters and determine the size
distribution of craters in three regions of the Moon. The data for the
crater distribution in the Sea of Tranquility (where Apollo 11 landed)
are given in the figure below. Cross found that in the Sea of
Tranquility, the number of craters with diameters greater than X meters
(per million square kilometers) is given by: $$ N(d&amp;gt;X) =
10^{10}\left(\frac{X}{1\~\mbox{m}}\right)^{-2}, $$ which holds for
craters with diameters between 1 meter and 10 kilometers (see figure
below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-kHxcn_PTd5o/TwDg3XGAcqI/AAAAAAAAARg/jl-kb22JD-Y/s1600/fig2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-kHxcn_PTd5o/TwDg3XGAcqI/AAAAAAAAARg/jl-kb22JD-Y/s400/fig2.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 2 from Cross (1966)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also estimate the rate at which craters are formed from this
data. If we assume that the craters formed at a constant rate over the
age of the Moon (about 4 billion years), then we get about 2.5 craters
with diameters above 1 meter formed in a million square kilometer area
every year. This is a "crater flux" for the Moon. Written another way,
the crater flux in the Sea of Tranquility is $$F \approx
1\~{\mbox{km}}^{-2} \frac{1}{4\times10^5\~\mbox{yr}}, $$ so we get
that roughly one crater with diameter greater than 1 meter is formed on
a square kilometer of the Moon once every 400,000 years or so. We now
have enough information to do some simulations. Simulation I wrote up a
code that simulates craters being formed on a 1 square kilometer patch
of the Moon. A crater is randomly placed in the 1 square kilometer
region with a diameter pulled from the above distribution. The bootprint
is placed at the center of the grid and craters are formed until we get
a "hit." At that point, the time is recorded and the run stops. As a
sanity check, I thought it would be fun to just let the simulation run
without caring if the boot was hit or not. By simulating the craters in
this way for 4 billion years, I should get something that looks like the
Moon at the present day. Here's a 200 m square from my simulation:
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DoFPG23CGwg/TwDqo-7GoQI/AAAAAAAAARs/QJW3RxeXFWI/s1600/mymoon_wticks.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DoFPG23CGwg/TwDqo-7GoQI/AAAAAAAAARs/QJW3RxeXFWI/s400/mymoon_wticks.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
and here's a picture of the same-sized region on the surface of the
Moon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-qWW5dU-aEN8/TwDrDLPy93I/AAAAAAAAAR4/XGOywC79NFU/s1600/200metersquare.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-qWW5dU-aEN8/TwDrDLPy93I/AAAAAAAAAR4/XGOywC79NFU/s320/200metersquare.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Cropped from &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/images/content/584398main_M168353795RE_25cm_AP12_area.jpg"&gt;this image&lt;/a&gt; (Source: LRO)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just eyeballing it, things look pretty good. Now it's time for the
actual simulation. I ran the simulation 10,000 times and tabulated the
amount of time needed before the bootprint was hit. The figure below
gives the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumulative_distribution_function"&gt;CDF&lt;/a&gt; for
the hit times in the simulation. That is, for each time T, we find the
fraction of simulations in which the bootprint got hit in a time less
than or equal to T. The dashed lines in the plot indicate the amount of
time needed to pass for half of the simulations to have recorded a hit.
This time turns out to be about 24 billion years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-L2WLnCepUiw/TwDs7X_njkI/AAAAAAAAASE/jS_-I0Eem4k/s1600/hit_cdf.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-L2WLnCepUiw/TwDs7X_njkI/AAAAAAAAASE/jS_-I0Eem4k/s400/hit_cdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  (Click for larger, actually readable version)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions and Caveats Based on the simulations, the bootprint on the
Moon would have about even odds of lasting at least 20 billion years
&lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; the primary means of destruction is through the formation of a
crater from a meteorite. However, there are a few caveats that should be
addressed. These deal with either the details of the simulation or the
assumptions we have made. In the simulation, we just took at 1 km square
patch of the moon and scaled back the "crater flux" accordingly.
However, this does not fully account for all possible craters that can
form. For example, our simulation would miss an event that hit 50 km
away from the target, but had a diameter of 100 km. Obviously this would
hit the target, but we are only seeding craters in the 1 square km
region. This would mean that the actual lifetime of the bootprint would
be less than our 24 billion year figure. Re-running with a 10km by 10km
square region, we find a lifetime of 18 billion years. Thus, an increase
in area by a factor of 100 only reduces the age by 25%. Considering
areas much larger than this makes the simulation prohibitively slow, but
the order unity effect does not seem too significant. Additionally, we
have made a number of assumptions. The big one is that we have assumed
that the craters currently seen on the Moon were formed uniformly in
time. In fact, a large fraction of the craters may have been formed when
the Moon was still very young (see &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Late_Heavy_Bombardment"&gt;Late Heavy
Bombardment&lt;/a&gt;). If
this were the case, we would have greatly overestimated the rate of
crater formation and thus underestimated the time needed to hit the
bootprint. In spite of these caveats, let's take our value of 20 billion
years to be accurate. What else can we say? Well, if we are right then
we are wrong because the Moon may not last that long (and it's hard to
have bootprints on the Moon without a Moon). Current
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun#Life_cycle"&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; have that the
Sun will expand into a red giant and (potentially) destroy the Earth
(and the Moon) in about 5 billion years. So a record of the Apollo
astronauts' boot sizes could potentially last as long as the Moon
&lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#footnote-nixon"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Not bad. Footnotes and Such
[1] Now with linked footnotes so Yariv doesn't have to scroll!
&lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#back-yariv"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;
[2] There was a fairly recent press release about Coronal Mass Ejections
from the Sun "sandblasting" the lunar surface. For more info, check
&lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/topics/solarsystem/features/dream-cme.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
and note the acronymic acrobatics needed to make them the "DREAM team."
But it's totally worth it. &lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#back-wind"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;
[3] A horribly forced pun. But it's totally worth it.
&lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#back-forced"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;
[4] Also, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_plaque"&gt;Nixon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#back-nixon"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>footprint</category><category>moon</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 20:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>