<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts about how do i get free stuff?)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/categories/how-do-i-get-free-stuff.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 15:05:03 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Free data set of the month:  Imaging Spectroscopy</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/free-data-set-of-the-month-imaging-spectroscopy/</link><dc:creator>Alex</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;There's a lot of free data sets floating around the internet, and while
things like funny cat videos and the &lt;a href="http://blog.xkcd.com/2010/05/03/color-survey-results/"&gt;results of color-naming
surveys&lt;/a&gt; get a
lot of play, many others don't get used for much. Recently I've been
playing around with one such data set: images from the &lt;a href="http://aviris.jpl.nasa.gov/"&gt;Airborne
Visible/Infrared Imaging Spectrometer
(AVIRIS)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I've always found it interesting that the way we perceive color is very
different from how light actually works. Most of us have three different
types of cones in our eyes and we perceive different colors as different
combinations of stimuli to these three types of cones. In a very rough
sense, when we look at a color, our brain gets three different numbers
to figure out what it is. Light, on the other hand, is a bunch of
photons with some distribution of wavelengths. To fully describe the
light coming from an object you need a function that shows how many
photons are at any given wavelength, which is way more complicated than
just the three numbers we get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what about all that information that gets thrown away on the way to
our brain? Are we missing out on a magical world of super-duper colors
and wonder? Not really, but skip past the break anyways to find out
more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few things our eyes have a hard time distinguishing. For
example, take a look at this picture of a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sodium-vapor_lamp#Low_pressure_sodium"&gt;low-pressure sodium
lamp&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:LPS_Lamp_35W_running.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx02kW16bI/AAAAAAAABI0/vonaPzNiAag/s320/LPS_Lamp_35W_running.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you've ever been in a sketchy parking lot at night or an intro
physics class you've probably seen one of these in real life. It looks
just like the picture right? It does to us, but the light coming from
the picture and the light from the real lamp are totally different. All
the photons from the real lamp have wavelengths very close to 589
nanometers, while the ones coming from the picture on your screen have a
bunch of different wavelengths ranging from 500 to 700 nanometers,
depending on what type of monitor you have. (It's easy to &lt;a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/%7Ezhuxj/astro/html/spectrometer.html"&gt;build your
own
spectrometer&lt;/a&gt;
and see this for yourself.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?gl=us&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=37.432068,-122.017937&amp;amp;spn=0.196834,0.308647&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;z=12"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx1kWr0ZpI/AAAAAAAABI8/K7RQ-Qzxa50/s400/Moffett%2BField%2BCrop.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;This
is an extreme example since there are few objects that emit purely
monochromatic light. What do normal objects look like spectroscopically?
I wanted to find out, but unfortunately there's not too many
freely-available spectroscopic images of everyday objects floating
around the internet, and my attempts to make my own were stymied by the
fact that no one wanted to let me borrow $20,000 worth of optical
bandpass filters. However, there are a several orbital satellites and
planes which take spectroscopic images of the earth, and one of them,
AVIRIS, has a few sample data sets for people to play around with. I
recently wrote some code to help me look at one data set in particular –
a spectroscopic image of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moffett_Federal_Airfield"&gt;Moffett Federal
Airfield&lt;/a&gt; in
California, shown here in a normal picture from Google Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;AVIRIS acts much like a normal camera, but instead of three wide-band
filters for distinguishing color it uses 225 narrow bands ranging from
366 nanometers (near UV) to 2500 nanometers (near IR). Any of these
bands can be thought of as a single monochromatic image. Here I have
plotted two bands side by side for comparison. The right image is at 463
nanometers (a nice blue color) and the other is at 2268 nanometers, well
into the infrared. (Both images are false-colored to enhance the
contrast).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx2M29FDwI/AAAAAAAABJE/lSUTxxI4ZFw/s1600/Img10and200withInsets.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx2M29FDwI/AAAAAAAABJE/lSUTxxI4ZFw/s400/Img10and200withInsets.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scene looks a lot different at the two different wavelengths. In the
first image there's one area that's particularly bright – it is one of
several settling ponds belonging to a Morton Salt factory, although I
have no idea what is special about this one that makes it reflect blue
light so strongly. The second image highlights different features and
clearly shows the difference between the moving water in the creeks and
the standing water in the bay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just two of the bands, but you can see all of them fly by in
the movie below. (Note that the color scale is set for each band
individually, which is why there sometimes seems to be a large change
between adjacent bands).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you agree with me that the embedded video looks super-crappy you can
&lt;a href="http://gotfork.net/virtuosi/VariableGain.avi"&gt;download the original
here&lt;/a&gt; (6.4 MB).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that struck me about this video is that it seems like
much of the image doesn't change too much through the whole visual
range. Not surprisingly, it's a lot easier for us to distinguish between
the slight differences in color in a normal image than it is for us to
distinguish between the slight changes of intensity here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do the spectra of individual points in the image look like?
Let's focus on a few easily-identifiable objects. (I'll talk about how I
made the roughly-true color image below in a later post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx7dCumIAI/AAAAAAAABJk/9b8gXeMkqg4/s1600/FiveLocMapCombo.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx7dCumIAI/AAAAAAAABJk/9b8gXeMkqg4/s400/FiveLocMapCombo.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing that stands out is that there's a lot of features that
are common to all of the locations, such as the big gap near 1750
nanometers. While the sun sends photons with a distribution of
wavelengths roughly described by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck%27s_law"&gt;Planck's
Law&lt;/a&gt;, certain wavelengths
are strongly absorbed by gasses in the atmosphere as shown below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Solar_Spectrum.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4c/Solar_Spectrum.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the different spectra we can see that &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electromagnetic_absorption_by_water"&gt;liquid water absorbs
strongly in the
infrared&lt;/a&gt;,
and the green grass on the golf course reflects strongly in the
near-infrared (no clue why). There is also a clear difference in
intensities for each of the locations in the visual range, but the five
locations otherwise look quite similar, even though they are very
different colors in real life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'll look at a few more interesting things in this data set and talk a
bit about about how our eyes and brains process color in a later post.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>blackbody</category><category>free data sets</category><category>how do i get free stuff?</category><category>optics</category><category>reflection</category><category>spectra</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/free-data-set-of-the-month-imaging-spectroscopy/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 16:44:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>My Pepsi* Challenge</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/my-pepsi-challenge/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz2-SbRtAI/AAAAAAAAAFY/eaUWEFQHTDs/s1600/bottles.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz2-SbRtAI/AAAAAAAAAFY/eaUWEFQHTDs/s200/bottles.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The
basement of the Physics building has a Pepsi machine. Over the course of
two semesters Alemi and I have deposited roughly the equivalent of the
GDP of, say, Monaco to this very same Pepsi machine (see left, with most
of Landau and Lifshitz to scale). It just so happens that Pepsi is now
having a contest, called "Caps for Caps," in which it is possible to win
a baseball hat. There are several nice things about this contest.
Firstly, I drink a lot of soda. Secondly, I like baseball hats. So far
so good. Lastly (and most important for this post), is that it is fairly
straightforward to calculate the statistics of winning (or at least
simulate them).
So how does the game work? Well, on each soda cap the name of a Major
League Baseball team is printed. All thirty teams are (supposedly)
printed with the same frequency, so the odds of getting any particular
team are 1/30. You can win a hat by collecting three caps with the same
team printed on them. So if I had five caps, the following would be a
win:
Phillies Cubs Tigers Phillies Phillies
whereas the following would not win me anything:
Yankees Rays Blue Jays Orioles Royals
and I would also lose if I had:
Mets Nationals Braves Braves Mets.
In addition, one in eight caps gets you 15% off on some $50 dollar or
more purchase to MLB.com or something like that. For simplicity, I
ignored these 15% off guys, but all they will do is push back the number
of caps you need by one for every eight purchased. It should not be too
difficult to factor these ones in, but I was lazy and I already made all
these nice graphs, so...
The first thing I tried to do was just simulate the contest. I wrote a
little Python script that randomly generates a team for each cap and
counts my wins over a given number of caps purchased. Running this about
100,000 times for all number of caps between 1 and 61 (with 61
guaranteed to win) and averaging over the number of wins, I could
determine both the expected number of wins per cap value and the
probability of winning at least once. The results are shown below.
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAwPaC7VV-I/AAAAAAAAAEA/ei6DPQ09bmI/s1600/CapsforCaps(sim1).png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAwPaC7VV-I/AAAAAAAAAEA/ei6DPQ09bmI/s400/CapsforCaps(sim1"&gt;.png)&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxwinoE0FI/AAAAAAAAAFA/VTOnToOXcmM/s1600/WinsvsSodas.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxwinoE0FI/AAAAAAAAAFA/VTOnToOXcmM/s400/WinsvsSodas.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
But we can also exactly solve this game. This turned out to take longer
for me (I'm bad at probability) than just simulating the darn thing. I
had initially included my derivation in the post but it was long,
muddled, and none too illuminating, so I took it out. But I super-duper
promise I did it and can post if you really really want to know.
Otherwise, I have just plotted the predicted results below (as a red
curve) along with the simulated data (blue dots). Turns out they agree
pretty well!
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxxKz3m-MI/AAAAAAAAAFI/S6YpmCcO1Fs/s1600/CapsforCapsSimandPred.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxxKz3m-MI/AAAAAAAAAFI/S6YpmCcO1Fs/s400/CapsforCapsSimandPred.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Just eyeballing the graph, we see that after 18 or 19 sodas the chances
of winning are about a half. Beyond about 25 or so it appears to be
almost 90% that you'll win at least once. In reality, these percentages
would occur about 2 or 3 caps later to compensate for the 15% off
thingies. So now that we have some numbers and can trust our model a
bit, let's see how worth it this contest is for us.
First, we can ask: Is this a good way to get a hat cheaper than retail
value (about $15)? To quantify "worth it" I have chosen to find the
value of winnings (price of hat times expected number of wins) minus the
cost of caps (how much I spend on soda). I am fairly embarrassed to say
that the cost of each soda is $1.75. See plot below.
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxzBhvw-4I/AAAAAAAAAFQ/RiKEfFBDqig/s1600/ValueDifferential.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxzBhvw-4I/AAAAAAAAAFQ/RiKEfFBDqig/s400/ValueDifferential.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
From this plot, we see that it doesn't become "worth it" (that is, value
of winnings is greater than cost of sodas) until about 40 sodas
purchased. That's a lot! In fact, we see that just when I start feeling
pretty confident I'll win something (around 20-25 sodas), I'm right in a
big valley of "totally not worth it." So if I just want a baseball hat,
I'm better off forking over the $15 dollars.
Although, one does see from this plot that once I get above about 40 or
so sodas, it becomes much more cost effective to just keep buying sodas
and winning hats. However, Pepsi tries to stifle this a bit in the
&lt;a href="http://www.pepsiusa.com/capsforcaps/"&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt;, stating that "Limit one
(1) Official MLB® baseball cap per name, address or household." Unless I
either make a lot of friends real soon or develop a creative definition
of my address, it looks like I'm out of luck.
But what if I want a hat but I don't want to actually buy soda like a
chump? This contest, like many others, needs to have a "No Purchase
Necessary" clause for some legal reason or another (so they aren't
lotteries or gambling or something). I had assumed they (the nameless
overlords at Pepsi) would limit the number of caps possible from just
mailing in, but it doesn't seem that way. From the Official rules,
Chapter Two, verses nine to twenty-one:
"Limit one (1) free game piece per request, per stamped outer envelope."
That sounds to me like you could get as many as you want, as long as you
use different envelopes. So we can redo our cost analysis with the cost
of getting one cap as the cost of a stamp. Putting the value of a cap
now at the cost of a stamp (44 cents), we get the following:
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz3jfb-KcI/AAAAAAAAAFg/erU1nZU7ZCg/s1600/mailincaps.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz3jfb-KcI/AAAAAAAAAFg/erU1nZU7ZCg/s400/mailincaps.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Zooming in:
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz3tj6kg8I/AAAAAAAAAFo/MDHgjjjS2J0/s1600/mailinZoom.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz3tj6kg8I/AAAAAAAAAFo/MDHgjjjS2J0/s400/mailinZoom.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Hey, that seems worth it! And it should, since from above we saw that
the probability of winning after about 30 caps was in the high 90% 's.
The cost of getting 30 caps this way is the cost of 30 stamps, which is
less than the $15 that the hat is (supposedly) worth. So if I really
wanted a hat from this contest and didn't feel like drinking all my
money away, I'd just send away for the mail-in pieces.
I may try this method, since it seems to be allowed under the rules.
Although, even a strict constructionist reading of the contest rules
pretty much allows Pepsi to do whatever the heck it wants. Either way,
I'll be sure to update to see how well my model holds up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*NOTE: In no way is The Virtuosi blog affiliated in any way with Pepsi.
We may occasionally purchase Pepsi products (like sweet tasting Wild
Cherry Pepsi!), but we don't do it because we think it makes us look
"cool" or "hip" or "rad" (we KNOW it does). In fact, drinking too much
soda can have certain adverse health effects (like making you stronger,
faster, and in general more attractive). So if you want to have a Pepsi
product (like sweet tasting Wild Cherry Pepsi!) every now and then
(literally, EVERY INSTANT), go ahead. But drinking too many Pepsi
products (like sweet tasting Wild Cherry Pepsi!) could make you sick
(with awesome-itis).&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>baseball</category><category>how do i get free stuff?</category><category>pepsi</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/my-pepsi-challenge/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 08 Jun 2010 01:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>