<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts about order of magnitude)</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/categories/order-of-magnitude.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 22:55:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Pi-rithmetic</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/pi-rithmetic/</link><dc:creator>Alemi</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-7rfL9Iby34A/T2C3LhSj_6I/AAAAAAAAAa0/rXTR30c77bk/s1600/IMAG0200.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-7rfL9Iby34A/T2C3LhSj_6I/AAAAAAAAAa0/rXTR30c77bk/s320/IMAG0200.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: pi squared is very close to 10. How close? Well, &lt;a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=%2810+-pi%5E2+%29%2Fpi%5E2"&gt;Wolfram
Alpha&lt;/a&gt;
tells me that it is only about 1% off. I first realized this fact when
looking at my slide rule, pictured to the left (click to embiggen), just
another reason why slide rules are awesome. It turns out I use this fact
all of the time. How's that you ask? Well, I use this fast to enable me
to do very quick mental arithmetic. It goes like this. For every number
you come across in a calculation, drop all of the information save two
parts, first, what's its order of magnitude, that is, how many digits
does it have, and second, is it closest to 1, pi, or 10? The first part
amounts to thinking of every number you come across as it looks in
scientific notation, so a number like 2342 turns into 2.342 x 10^3, so
that I've captured its magnitude in a power of 10. As for the next part,
the rules I usually use are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the remaining bit is between 1 and 2, make it 1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If its between 2 and 6.5 make it pi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if its bigger than 6.5, make it another 10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to think of this is to estimate every number to be a power
of ten, and then either 1, a few, or 10. The reason I choose pi is
because if I use pi, I know how the rest of the arithmetic should work,
namely, I only need to know a few rules, plus when I use this to
estimate answers of physics formulae, making a bunch of pis show up
tends to help me cancel other natural pis that are in the formulae.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \pi \times \pi \sim10 \qquad \frac{1}{\pi} \sim
\frac{\pi}{10} \qquad \sqrt{10} \sim \pi $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which you might notice is just the same approximation written in 3
different ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's work an example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \begin{align&lt;em&gt;} 23 \times 78 / 13 \times 2133 &amp;amp;= ? \ \pi
\times 10 \times 100 / 10 \times \pi \times 10^3 &amp;amp;= ? \ \pi^2
\times 10^5 &amp;amp;\sim 10^6 \ \end{align&lt;/em&gt;}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of course the &lt;a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=23+*+78%2F13+*+2133"&gt;real
answer&lt;/a&gt; is
294,354, so you'll notice I got the answer wrong, but I only got it
wrong by a factor of 3, which is pretty good for mental arithmetic, and
in particular mental arithmetic that takes no time flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the average error I introduce by using this approximation is
just 30% or so for each number, which I've shown below [the script that
produced this plot for those interested is
&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/2037431"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-uwGlV6y_pps/T2C90lPhmQI/AAAAAAAAAbA/k_Hl8H-y2ys/s1600/pierr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-uwGlV6y_pps/T2C90lPhmQI/AAAAAAAAAbA/k_Hl8H-y2ys/s320/pierr.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there you go, now you can impress all of your friends with a simple
mental arithmetic that gets you within a factor of 3 or so on average.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>approximation</category><category>order of magnitude</category><category>pi day</category><category>pi-rithmetic</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/pi-rithmetic/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 11:52:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Grains of Sand</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/grains-of-sand/</link><dc:creator>Jesse</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-87-vnzGa9Po/TiRR2qFWprI/AAAAAAAAAF0/KsfRQhoL5Ds/s1600/SandUDunesUSoft.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-87-vnzGa9Po/TiRR2qFWprI/AAAAAAAAAF0/KsfRQhoL5Ds/s320/SandUDunesUSoft.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever sat on a beach and wondered how many grains of sand there
were? I have, but I may be a special case. Today we're going to take
that a step further, and figure out how many grains of sand there are on
the entire earth. (Caveat: I'm only going to consider sand above the
water level, since I don't have any idea what the composition of the
ocean floor is). I'm going to start by figuring out how much beach there
is in the world. If you look at a map of the world, there are four main
coasts that run, essentially, a half circumference of the world. We'll
say the total length of coast the world has is roughly two
circumferences. As an order of magnitude, I would say that the average
beach width is 100 m, and the average depth is 10 m. This gives a total
beach volume of $$ (100 m)(10 m)(4 \pi (6500 km) )= 82 km^3$$ That's
not a whole lot of volume. Let's think about deserts. The Sahara desert
is by far the largest sandy desert in the world. Just as a guess, we'll
assume that the rest of the sandy deserts amount to 20% (arbitrary
number picked staring at a map) as much area as the Sahara. According to
wikipedia the area of the Sahara is 9.4 million km^2. We'll take, to an
order of magnitude, that the sand is 100 m deep. 10 m seems to little,
and 1 km too much. That amounts to \~1 million km^3 of sand. We're
going to assume that a grain of sand is about 1 mm in radius The volume
occupied by a grain of sand is then 1 mm^3. Putting that together with
our previous number for the occupied volume gives $$ \frac{1\cdot
10^6 km^3}{1 mm^3}=\frac{1 \cdot 10^{15}}{1\cdot
10^{-9}}=1\cdot 10^{24}$$ That's a lot of grains of sand. Addendum:
Carl Sagan is quoted as saying&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"The total number of stars in the Universe is larger than all the
grains of sand on all the beaches of the planet Earth"&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we just use our beach volume, that gives a total number of grains of
sand as \~1*10^20, which is large, but not as large as what we found
above. Is that less than the number of stars in in the universe? Well,
that's a question for another day (or google), but the answer is, to our
best estimate/count, yes.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>carl sagan</category><category>order of magnitude</category><category>sand</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/grains-of-sand/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 18 Jul 2011 11:33:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lifetime of Liquid Water</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/lifetime-of-liquid-water/</link><dc:creator>Jesse</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-fyjvPBm_INs/ThpaZFszL5I/AAAAAAAAAFw/6sJBTUj905c/s1600/water_drop.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-fyjvPBm_INs/ThpaZFszL5I/AAAAAAAAAFw/6sJBTUj905c/s320/water_drop.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Apologies for the hiatus recently, it's been a busy time (when isn't
it). I hope to get back to talking about experiments soon, but for now I
wanted to write up a quick problem I thought up a while back. The
question is this: how long does a molecule of H2O on earth remain in the
liquid state, on average? I'm going to treat this purely as an order of
magnitude problem. I'm also going to have to start with one assumption
that is almost certainly inaccurate, but makes things a lot easier. I'm
going to assume perfect mixing of all of the water on earth. Given that
assumption, I really only need to figure out two things. The first is
how much liquid water there is on earth. The second is now much liquid
water leaves the liquid phase each year. Let's start with the total
amount of liquid water on earth. This is relatively easy to estimate. I
happen to know that about 70% of the earth's surface is covered in
water. Most all of that is ocean. To an order of magnitude, the average
depth of the ocean must be 1 km, as it is certainly not 100 m or 10 km
[1]. For a thin spherically shell, the volume of the shell is roughly $$
4 \pi r_e^2 \Delta r $$ where r_e is the radius of the earth. Thus,
the total volume of water on the earth is $$.7&lt;em&gt;4 \pi r_e^2 (1 km)$$
Now, we need to figure out how much H20 leaves the liquid phase every
year. To an order of magnitude, it rains 1 m everywhere on earth each
year, it's not .1 m or 10 m [2]. I'm going to ignore any
freezing/melting in the ice caps, assuming that is small fraction of the
water that leaves the liquid phase each year. Since we have a closed
system, all the water that rains must have left the liquid phase. So, on
average, the total volume of water that leaves the liquid phase is $$4
\pi r_e^2 (1 m) $$ Thus, the fraction of liquid water that changes
phase per year is $$ \frac{4 \pi r_e^2 (1m)}{.7&lt;/em&gt;4\pi r_e^2 (1
km)} = .0014 $$ This means that, given my assumption of perfect mixing,
in somewhere around 1/.0014 = 700 yr all of the water on earth will have
cycled through the vapor phase. Since we're only operating to an order
of magnitude, I'll call this 1000 years. This is the answer to our
question if every molecule has been in the vapor phase once in 1000
years, then we expect a molecule to stay in the liquid phase for 1000
years [1] According to wikipedia, this is really about 4 km, so we're
underestimating a bit. [2] According to wikipedia, this is spot on (.99
m on average).&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>fun</category><category>order of magnitude</category><category>physics</category><category>water</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/lifetime-of-liquid-water/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 10 Jul 2011 22:07:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Blown Away</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/blown-away/</link><dc:creator>Jesse</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-NFVShpYzscc/TYutYtPSIVI/AAAAAAAAAEM/vRA8KbFV6tc/s1600/wind-turbine-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-NFVShpYzscc/TYutYtPSIVI/AAAAAAAAAEM/vRA8KbFV6tc/s200/wind-turbine-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reading a discussion on green energy recently, in particular wind
power, where the following claim was made&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;enough wind turbines to power the world would cover the surface of
the world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this was quickly decried by supporters of wind power, but the claim
has stuck with me. The question on my mind today is: How much of the
earth's surface would have to be covered to power the earth with wind
turbines? We can't hope to put an exact number on this, the best we'll
be able to do is an order of magnitude. I also don't know much about
wind turbines, so I'll be making liberal use of
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wind_turbine"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; as I go. Let's
start with the size of the wind turbine. According to wikipedia the
largest wind turbine has a rotor sweep diameter of 128 m. To an order of
magnitude, we'll say that our average wind turbine has a diameter of 100
m. Next we need to know how much power this puts out. The maximum power
of this turbine is \~8 MW. However, it certainly wouldn't be producing
that at all times. Current wind farms produce around 20-30% maximum
capacity. However, these turbines are careful placed in areas of high
wind. We're not going to get that lucky with our wind dose when we place
our turbines haphazardly, so we'll assume they produce at 1% maximum
capacity. According to
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_energy_resources_and_consumption"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;,
the world energy consumption in 2008 was 474 EJ (exajoules), or an
average power use in 2008 of 15 TW. To an order of magnitude then, the
area we'd have to occupy with wind turbines to power the world would be:
$$\left( \frac{(100\text{ m})^2}{1\text{
turbine}}\right)\left(\frac{1\text{ turbine}}{.01&lt;em&gt;8 \text{
MW}}\right)15 \text{TW} = 2\cdot 10^{12}\text{ m}^2$$ That's
2&lt;/em&gt;10^6 km^2, or, in english, 2 million square kilometers. For
comparison, the land area of the united states is roughly 10 millon
square kilometers. So we'd only have to cover 1/5th of the united states
with wind turbines to power the entire world (in 2008, no doubt power
use has risen since then)! While that is a lot of space taken up, it is
nowhere near the entire surface of the world. There are, of course,
&lt;a href="http://xkcd.com/556/"&gt;other concerns&lt;/a&gt; about wind power. &lt;em&gt;Note: maybe
the wind turbines are less efficient overall. Also, I assumed that the
footprint was just the square area of the turbine diameter. I know this
is the size of the face of the turbine, but to an order of magnitude I
imagine it is correct for the space occupied on the ground.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>green power</category><category>order of magnitude</category><category>wind</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/blown-away/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 24 Mar 2011 17:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Fishy Calculation Followup &amp; New Contest</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/fishy-calculation-followup-new-contest/</link><dc:creator>Alemi</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_t2IHW-7EI/AAAAAAAAAKw/nbtBQnQnpWI/s1600/hamster.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_t2IHW-7EI/AAAAAAAAAKw/nbtBQnQnpWI/s200/hamster.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, some you may remember when I attempted to calculate how much the
oceans would lower if you took out all of the fish in an &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/fishy-calculation.html"&gt;earlier
post&lt;/a&gt;.
Well, the results came in a while ago, but I forgot to mention that &lt;a href="http://diaryofnumbers.blogspot.com/2010/05/we-have-winner.html"&gt;I
lost&lt;/a&gt;
the contest. I was about two orders of magnitude off from the winning
answer. In light of my failure, I'm going to try again in the &lt;a href="http://diaryofnumbers.blogspot.com/2010/05/hamster-powered-mansions.html"&gt;newest
contest&lt;/a&gt;.
This time the question is a bit stranger:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How many buff hamsters would it take to completely power a mansion?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I encourage all of The Virtuosi readers to enter as well, it only takes
a minute to come up with some number. Good luck one and all.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>contest</category><category>fermi problem</category><category>fish</category><category>order of magnitude</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/fishy-calculation-followup-new-contest/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 03:03:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Physics of Baseball: Batting</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/physics-of-baseball-batting/</link><dc:creator>Alemi</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_RkXXs4DpI/AAAAAAAAAKo/jPSgwpl4qHA/s1600/baseball.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_RkXXs4DpI/AAAAAAAAAKo/jPSgwpl4qHA/s320/baseball.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Summer is upon us, and so that means that we here at the Virtuosi have
started talking about baseball. In fact, Corky and I did some simple
calculations that illuminate just how impressive batting in baseball can
be. We were interested in just how hard it is to hit a pitch with the
bat. So we thought we'd model hitting the ball with a rather simple
approximation of a robot swinging a cylindrical bat, horizontally with
some rotational speed and at a random height. The question then becomes,
if the robot chooses a random height and a random time to swing, what
are the chances that it gets a hit?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Spatial Resolution&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the first thing to consider is how much of the strike zone the bat
takes up. In order to be a strike, the ball needs to be over home plate,
which is 17 inches wide, and between the knees and logo on the batters
jersey. Estimating this height as 0.7 m or 28 inches or so, we have the
area of the strike zone $$ A_S = (17") \times (0.7 m) = 0.3 \text{
m}^2 $$ when you swing, how much of this area does the bat take up?
Well, treat it as a cylinder, with a diameter of 10 cm, and assume it
runs the length of the strike zone, when the area that the bat takes up
is $$ A_B = (10\text{ cm}) \times (17" ) = 0.043 \text{ m}^2 $$ So
that the fractional area that the bat takes up during our idealized
swing is $$ \frac{A_B}{A_S} \approx 14\% $$ So already, if our
robot is guessing where inside the strike zone to place the bat, and
doing so randomly, assuming the pitch is a strike to begin with, it will
be able to bunt successfully about 14% of the time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Time Resolution&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But getting a hit on a swing is different than getting a bunt. Not only
do you have to have your bat at the right height, but you need to time
the swing correctly. Lets first look at how much time we are dealing
with here. Most major league pitchers pitch the ball at about 90 mph or
so. The pitchers mound is 60.5 feet away from home base. This means that
the pitch is in the air for $$ t = \frac{ 60.5 \text{ ft} }{ 90
\text{ mph} } \approx \frac{1}{2} \text{ second} $$ i.e. from the
time the pitcher releases the ball to the time it crosses home plate is
only about half a second. Compare this with human reaction times. My
drivers ed course told me that human reaction times are typically a
third of a second or so. So, baseball happens quick! Alright, but we
were interested in how well you have to time your swing. Successfully
hitting the ball means that you've made contact with the ball such that
it lands somewhere in the field. I.e. you've got a 90 degree play in
when you make contact. How does this translate to time? We would need to
know how fast you swing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Estimating the speed of a swing&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I don't know how fast you can swing a baseball bat, but I can estimate
it. I know that if you land your swing just right, you have a pretty
good shot at a home run. Fields are typically 300 feet long. So, I can
ask, if I launch a projectile at a 45 degree angle, how fast does it
need to be going in order to make it 300 feet. Well, we can solve this
projectile problem if we remember some of our introductory physics. We
decouple the horizontal and vertical motions of the ball, the ball
travels horizontally 300 feet, so we know $$ v_x t = 300 \text{ ft} $$
where t is the time the ball is in the air, similarly we know that it is
gravity that makes the ball fall, and so as far the vertical motion is
concerned, in half the total flight time, we need the vertical velocity
to go from its initial value to zero, i.e. $$ g \frac{t}{2} = v_y $$
where g is the acceleration due to gravity. Furthermore, I'm assuming
that I am launching this projectile at a 45 degree angle, for which I
know from trig that $$ v_x = v_y = \frac{v}{\sqrt 2} $$ So I can
stick these equations into one another and solve for the velocity needed
to get the ball going 300 feet. $$ \frac{v^2}{ g} = 300 \text{ ft} =
\frac{ v^2}{ 9.8 \text{ m/s}^2 } $$ $$ v \approx 30 \text{ m/s}
\sim 67 \text{ mph}$$ So it looks like the ball needs to leave the bat
going about 70 mph in order to clear the park. ( This was of course
neglecting air resistance, which ought to be important for baseballs ).
Great that tells us how fast the ball needs to be going when it leaves
the bat, but how fast was the bat going in order to get the ball going
that fast? Well, lets work worst case and assume that the baseball - bat
interaction is inelastic. I.e. I reckon that if I throw a baseball at
about 100 mph towards a wooden wall, it doesn't bounce a whole lot. In
that case, the bat needs to take the ball from coming at it at 90 mph to
leaving at 70 mph or so, i.e. the place where the ball hits the bat
needs to be going at about 160 mph. That seems fast, but when you think
about it, if a pitcher can pitch a ball at 90 mph, that means their hand
is moving at 90 mph during the last bits of the pitch, so you expect
that a batter can move their hands about that fast, and we have the
added advantage of the bat being a lever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Coming back to timing&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we have an estimate for how fast the bat is going. Knowing this and
estimating the length between the sweet spot and the pivot point of the
bat to be about 0.75 m or so, we can obtain the angular frequency of the
bat. $$ v = \omega r $$ $$ \omega = \frac{ 160 \text{ mph} }{ 0.75
\text{ m} } \approx 100 \text{ Hz} $$ So, if we need to have a 90
degree resolution in our swing timing to hit the ball in the park, this
means that if our swing near the end is happening at 100 \text{ Hz}, we
need to get the timing down to within $$ t = \frac{ 90 \text{
degree}}{ 100 \text{ Hz} } \sim 15 \text{ ms} $$ So we need to get
the timing of our swing to within about 15 milliseconds to land the hit.
So if our robot randomly swung at some point during the duration of the
pitch, it would only hit with probability $$ \frac{\text{time to land
hit} }{ \text{time of pitch}} = \frac{ 15 \text{ ms}}{500 \text{
ms}} \sim 3\% $$ or only 3% of the time. If we take both the spatial
placement, and timing of the swing as independent, the probability that
our robot gets a hit would be something about $$ p = 0.03 \times 0.14 =
0.004 = 0.4 \% $$ or our robot would only get a hit 1 time out of 250
tries. Suddenly hitting looks pretty impressive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Experiment&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Saying that the robot swings at some random time during the duration of
the pitch is pretty bad. So I decided to do a little experiment to see
how good people are at judging times on half second scales. I had some
friends of mine start a stop watch and while looking try to stop it as
close as they could at the half second mark. Collecting their
deviations, I obtained a standard deviation of about 41 milliseconds,
which suggests a window of about 100 milliseconds over which people can
reliably judge half second intervals. Now, I have to admit, this wasn't
done in any very rigorous sort of way, I had them do this while walking
to dinner, but it ought to give a rough estimate of the relevant time
scale for landing a hit. So instead of comparing our 15 millisecond 'get
a hit' window to the full half second pitch duration, lets compare it
instead to the 100 'humans trying to judge when to hit' window. This
gives us a temporal resolution of about $$ p = \frac{ 15}{100} = 15
\%. $$ So that now we obtain an overall hit probability of $$ p = 0.15
* 0.14 = 0.021 = 2 \% $$ So that it seems like a poor baseball player,
more or less randomly swinging should have a batting average of about
2\%. Compare this with typical baseball batting averages of 250 or so,
denoting 0.25 or 25% probability of a hit. I think this is a much better
estimate of how much better over random baseball players can do with
training. So it looks like practice can improve your ability to do a
task by about an order of magnitude or so. Either way, baseball is
pretty darn impressive when you think about it.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>baseball</category><category>fun</category><category>order of magnitude</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/physics-of-baseball-batting/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 19 May 2010 18:21:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Another Reason Why The Core is Stupid</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/another-reason-why-the-core-is-stupid/</link><dc:creator>Alemi</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8d8LoMoWHI/AAAAAAAAAJg/3HSwL_rBMFE/s1600/The_Core_poster.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8d8LoMoWHI/AAAAAAAAAJg/3HSwL_rBMFE/s320/The_Core_poster.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I assume everyone has heard of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_core"&gt;The
Core&lt;/a&gt;, the terrible scifi movie
from 2003. If you haven't you're missing out on what appears to be,
according to Discover magazine, &lt;a href="http://discovermagazine.com/2007/nov/none-found"&gt;the worst sci-fi film
ever&lt;/a&gt;. There are
already numerous sites that discuss the bad science in the core
(&lt;a href="http://geolor.com/The_Core_Movie-Facts_and_Fiction.htm"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, or over
at &lt;a href="http://www.badastronomy.com/bad/movies/thecore_review.html"&gt;Bad
Astronomy&lt;/a&gt;),
but they all seem to ignore another fundamental problem with the plot. I
don't think I'll give too much away if I tell you that the basic premise
of the movie is that the earth's core has stopped rotating, and so the
earth's magnetic field is collapsing, which they claim will mean that
all of the previously deflected microwaves (note: EM radiation is not
bent by a magnetic field) will cook us all. Now, a lot of people have
focused on the microwaves bit, which while bad science, one could argue
that we would still have some bad effects from loosing our magnetic
field. The problem I have is that the Earth's magnetic field cannot
change that abruptly. I'm currently teaching undergraduate honors E&amp;amp;M,
and we're working out of the fantastic texbook (unfortunately now out of
print) by
&lt;a href="http://books.google.com/books?ei=tn7HS87OGYKuygS9yqCNCw&amp;amp;cd=1&amp;amp;id=3LYRAQAAIAAJ&amp;amp;dq=Purcell+Electromagnetism&amp;amp;q=#search_anchor"&gt;Purcell&lt;/a&gt;.
And in the chapter on electromagnetic induction he has an illuminating
exercise. Lets try and estimate how quickly the magnetic field of the
earth can change. Well, lets sort of work backwards. We know that if we
have a conducting ring with a current flowing through it, this will
create a magnetic field. So, if we can try and model some sort of
circuit that approximates the earth, and then look at how quickly energy
is dissipated in that circuit, we can estimate how fast the magnetic
field decays. So lets imagine a thick torus with height and width a.
Flowing around this torus is some current I, distributed in a
complicated way. The torus is made out of a material with some
conductivity sigma. Now, we know that for a wire made out of some
material with a conductivity sigma, we can estimate its resistance as $$
R = \frac{ L }{ \sigma A } $$ where L is the length, and A is the
cross sectional area of the wire. Lets do that with our torus, calling
$$ A = a^2 \qquad L = 2 \pi a $$ giving us a resistance $$ R \sim
\frac{ 2 \pi }{ \sigma a } $$ To estimate the magnetic field of this
torus, lets just take the magnetic field of a loop with radius a/2. I.e.
$$ B = \frac{ \mu_0 I }{2 \pi (a/2) } $$ Now we know that the energy
stored in the magnetic field is $$ U = \frac{1}{2 \mu_0 } \int B^2
\ dV \sim \frac{1}{2 \mu_0} B V $$ where we take the magnetic field
to be the magnetic field of the simple loop and V to be the volume of a
fat cylinder or so, i.e. $$ V \sim \pi a^2 \times a $$ Now if we
have a circuit with a known resistance we know that the energy is
dissipated through the resistor $$ \frac{dU}{dt} = - I^2 R $$ so if we
just want an order of magnitude estimate for the characteristic decay
time, we can take $$ \tau \sim \frac{ U }{ I^2 R } $$ Putting in our
approximations from above we have $$ \tau \sim \frac{
\frac{1}{2\mu_0 } B^2 V }{ I^2 \frac{2 \pi }{ \sigma a } } =
\frac{ \frac{1}{2 \mu_0 } ( \pi a^3 ) \left( \frac{ \mu_0 I }{
2 \pi (a/2) } \right)^2 }{ I^2 \frac{ 2 \pi }{\sigma a} } =
\frac{ \mu_0 }{4 \pi^2 } \sigma a^2 $$ where we know $$ \mu_0 =
4 \pi \times 10^{-7} N/A^2 $$ we obtain roughly (i.e. ignoring the
other pi) $$ \tau \sim \sigma a^2 \times 10^{-7} (s) $$ Now, lets
take the radius of the core to be about half the radius of the earth, or
3000 km or so, and take the conductivity of the core to be about a tenth
of that of iron at room temperature (iron becomes a worse conductor when
its heated), i.e. $$ a \sim 3000 (km) \qquad \sigma \sim 10^6 (S/m)
$$ We obtain $$ \tau \sim 10^12 (s) = 300 (centuries) $$ So, even if
you could magically make the core of the earth stop spinning, the
magnetic field is not going to change instantaneously, in fact it would
only be able to change on the order of 300 centuries or so. This is
really short on geologic time scales, but nothing like the week or so
that the movie The Core takes place over. Just one more reason why one
of the worst sci-fi movies of all time is bad.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>bad physics</category><category>fermi problem</category><category>fun</category><category>magnetism</category><category>movie</category><category>order of magnitude</category><category>sci-fi</category><category>the core</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/another-reason-why-the-core-is-stupid/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 15 Apr 2010 17:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>