<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts about physics challenge)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/categories/physics-challenge.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 14:55:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Physics Challenge Award Show II</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-award-show-ii/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-KNDW4alRDDI/Tra8NaWqlcI/AAAAAAAAAQo/6REV_1iTv2o/s1600/time_machine.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-KNDW4alRDDI/Tra8NaWqlcI/AAAAAAAAAQo/6REV_1iTv2o/s320/time_machine.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Not a DeLorean. You're doing it wrong.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[&lt;em&gt;Update: Prize Update / Added link to full solutions&lt;/em&gt;] Welcome to the
second Physics Challenge Award show!
[APPLAUSE]
Our judges have deliberated for several units of time and I now have in
my hands the envelope holding our list of winners. I could easily just
tell you who won right now and save everyone some time, but award shows
need some suspense to work effectively, so let's first give some tedious
background information!
[APPLAUSE]
You may recall that the winner of the first &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2011/03/physics-challenge-award-show.html"&gt;Physics
Challenge&lt;/a&gt;
contest won a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/CRC_Handbook_of_Chemistry_and_Physics"&gt;CRC
Handbook&lt;/a&gt;.
We will not be giving out CRCs this time around. We felt that such a
prize was far too &lt;del&gt;expensive&lt;/del&gt; impersonal, so we have opted this year
for something &lt;del&gt;much cheaper&lt;/del&gt; from the heart. The following prizes will
be awarded to our top three solutions:
&lt;strong&gt;First Prize:&lt;/strong&gt; Our first prize winner will receive an actual
back-of-an-envelope used in one of our posts (gasp!) signed by all the
of the members of the Virtuosi that I can find at colloquium tomorrow.
But that's not all! Alemi will also salute in your general direction.
&lt;strong&gt;Second Prize:&lt;/strong&gt; For our second prize winner, we appear to have run out
of envelopes... but Alemi will still salute in your general direction.
You will not see him do this, but you will feel a major disturbance in
the Awesome Force (mediated, of course, through the midi-chlorian
boson).
&lt;strong&gt;Third Prize:&lt;/strong&gt; You will receive no material prize, but on your
deathbed you will receive &lt;em&gt;total consciousness&lt;/em&gt;. So you've got that
going for you, which is nice.
Let's first remind everyone what the Challenge problem was. The full
text of the problem can be found
&lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachine.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
but the gist is basically this: You've created a time machine and you're
biggest fear is that you'll be stuck back in the past without any way to
communicate to the future that your design worked and you deserve all
kinds of Nobel prizes. The solution should be able to last long periods
of time (who knows how far back in time you'll go?), should maximize the
chances of modern people finding it, and be able to convince people that
you have in fact gone back in time.
Alright, let's get to some solutions already!
&lt;strong&gt;First Place:&lt;/strong&gt; The first place solution comes from Christian, who uses
some biological wrangling to solve the time traveller conundrum. With
some information from the
&lt;a href="http://www.ted.com/talks/craig_venter_unveils_synthetic_life.html"&gt;announcement&lt;/a&gt;
of "synthetic life" and some bio how-to from an entity known only as
"steve," Christian plans to implant a message into the DNA of bacteria.
The message will contain his name, identifying information, and the url
of a website which will (presumably) contain a video of him with one
hand outstretched saying "Nobel prize please."
Let's see how this solution satisfies our criteria for a successful
solution. &lt;em&gt;Does it work for an arbitrary amount of time?&lt;/em&gt; It appears to,
so long as the bacteria manage to survive and the message doesn't become
too garbled over time (perhaps some error-correction might be useful).
Additionally, if one is worried about introducing non-native bacteria to
the wild you could bring back a bunch of bacteria that were known to
exist over wide periods of time and just release those alive at the
time. &lt;em&gt;Will modern humans find it?&lt;/em&gt; It seems that geneticists are
decoding just about any genome they can get their hands on, so this is a
strong possibility. &lt;em&gt;Would it convince people that someone travelled in
time?&lt;/em&gt; If the bacteria has dispersed enough, shows enough variation over
geographic regions, and contains specific identifying information about
a missing person who has allegedly created a time machine, I think
that's pretty strong evidence. Neato, gang!
&lt;strong&gt;Second Place:&lt;/strong&gt; The second place solution comes from Kyle, who offers
a space-based answer. Kyle suggests etching detailed plans of the time
travel mechanism (flux capacitor) onto a durable metal and putting that
bad boy into space. He suggests that anyone capable of building a fully
functional time machine should have no problem launching a small
satellite. Fair enough. Additionally, the satellite would use some kind
of solar power or the like to produce a low-power radio signal. In fact,
this signal would only need to spit something out once every year or ten
years or something. Since radio communication precedes space
exploration, the detection of an artificial satellite sending a message
would attract a fair deal of attention. The plans and successful
reproduction of the time machine would then seal the deal.
Does this solution satisfy the necessary conditions? I think so.
Assuming all goes according to plan, this would easily be detected by
modern people and, assuming the time machine plans are accurate, would
provide indisputable proof. My main concern would be that the satellite
could be launched and survive to the present. Modern satellites need
constant boosts to stay in orbit, without which they fall back onto
Earth and burn up. One potential solution would be to put it on the
Moon. This is technically much more difficult, but hey, you just created
a time machine! Also, putting it on the moon then allows for a totally
rad recreation of the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monolith_(Space_Odyssey)"&gt;Monolith&lt;/a&gt; scene
in &lt;em&gt;2001: A Space Odyssey&lt;/em&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;Third Place:&lt;/strong&gt; The third place solution comes from Yariv. Though Yariv
did not submit a solution through the proper channels (he follows no
one's rules, not even his own), he was overheard to give a solution.
While the Physics Challenge planning committee was discussing the
problem over lunch, Yariv flippantly dismissed the entire premise as
"trivial" and suggested a two-word solution: "radioactive paint."
Personally, I like the idea of bewildered archaeologists finding a cave
painting of Yariv riding a dinosaur done using a variety of radioactive
paints which all date back 200 million years. For this amusement, I
award Yariv the third place prize for this contest. As a member of the
Virtuosi, however, Yariv is ineligible to receive a prize and instead
receives 5 demerits on his record for his willful disregard of our
institution's rules and excessive flippancy. One more slip-up and you'll
lose your badge!
&lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachinesol.php"&gt;Full
solutions&lt;/a&gt;
are up on the Challenge website. Thanks for joining us for this episode
of Physics Challenge Award Show, and thanks to everyone who submitted a
response! &lt;strong&gt;First and Second Prize Winners:&lt;/strong&gt; We present the following
in partial fulfillment of our prize offer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-VdXMZhn5g6Q/TryZqc0wbVI/AAAAAAAAAQw/NBVdnG2oOrw/s1600/alemi_salute.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-VdXMZhn5g6Q/TryZqc0wbVI/AAAAAAAAAQw/NBVdnG2oOrw/s640/alemi_salute.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  For those who solve problems (he &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=xMUgmU_Hsjc&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;salutes&lt;/a&gt; you)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>excessive saluting</category><category>physics challenge</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-award-show-ii/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Nov 2011 23:22:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Physics Challenge Update</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-update/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mQtqC-5MmYk/Tq9MkU56O9I/AAAAAAAAAPE/iaFRwtMKwJ0/s1600/mary_mcwatch.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mQtqC-5MmYk/Tq9MkU56O9I/AAAAAAAAAPE/iaFRwtMKwJ0/s320/mary_mcwatch.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Marty McFly realizes he is running out of time to submit his solution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Did you know that our &lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachine.php"&gt;Physics
Challenge&lt;/a&gt;
problem contest thingy is still up and going? It is! The contest will be
open until the end of the day this &lt;strong&gt;Friday, November 4th&lt;/strong&gt;. And, unlike
last time, the winning solution will be chosen and posted by the end of
the weekend. So even if you don't submit your own solution (though you
&lt;em&gt;totally&lt;/em&gt; should), check back here Monday morning for the winning entry.
Why should you submit a solution to our problem? Lots of reasons! The
top ten reasons as decided by a random sample of me are given below the
break. &lt;strong&gt;Top Ten Reasons to Submit a Solution:&lt;/strong&gt; 1) You will win
super-awesome prizes! What kinds of prizes? Well how does a greeting
card with kittens on the front and a collection of encouraging haikus
from the entire Virtuosi staff written inside sound? It sounds awesome,
awesome to the max. 2) You get to show off your totally rad physics
skills! 3) You can put it on your resume/cv! The semi-annual Virtuosi
Physics Challenge problem winners are held to the same esteem as Fields
Medalists and Nobel Prize winners! 4) You will earn the respect and
admiration of your peers! Winners of this contest develop an aura that
all other people can see, fear, and respect. 5) You will become
stronger, faster, and more productive than ever before! This is a
scientifically proven fact perhaps. 6) You may gain the ability to talk
to animals! Have you ever wanted to discuss espionage-related topics
with a platypus (perhaps this
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ONgjXrOShlc"&gt;platypus&lt;/a&gt;)? Of course you
have! Winners can! 7) You will be in Presidential company! Did you know
William Henry Harrison won the very first Virtuosi physics challenge
contest shortly before becoming the ninth President of the United
States? Yep! Tippecanoe and so can you! 8) Alemi will salute in your
general direction. No questions asked. 9) You will give me work to do on
the weekend! This will give my dull and uninteresting life a small
glimmer of meaning! Hooray! 10) There's like a 50% chance that you will
get three wishes from a magical genie named David Bowie (no relation).
Seriously. Like 50%. That should get you properly motivated! So check
out the Challenge Problem
&lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachine.php"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt;
and when you have a solution, send it to our email address (given up in
the sidebar). Good luck!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>desperate plea</category><category>hooray</category><category>physics challenge</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-update/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2011 22:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Physics Challenge II:  Marty McPhysics</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-ii-marty-mcphysics/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-cuT_VPl_Yd8/TmQbG_7B5DI/AAAAAAAAAOs/DA9sTNI-nGk/s1600/greatscott.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-cuT_VPl_Yd8/TmQbG_7B5DI/AAAAAAAAAOs/DA9sTNI-nGk/s1600/greatscott.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Doc Brown didn't have a time-travel backup plan.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In light of the incredible success of our last Physics Challenge Problem
(we received &lt;em&gt;several&lt;/em&gt; responses), we here at the Virtuosi have decided
to reinstate what was nominally a "monthly" contest. In addition to a
brand-spankin'-new problem (with "prizes", see [1]), we have also tried
to make a nice collaborative environment for discussing interesting
physics problems and posting your own solutions. So I will discuss our
&lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachine.php"&gt;new
problem&lt;/a&gt;
and then I'll throw it over to Alemi to discuss the goal of our new
Physics Challenge webpage. Our last challenge problem
(&lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/archive.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
with winning solutions) was deemed a bit "unrealistic" by many because
it assumes that you were shipwrecked on a desert island &lt;em&gt;with a CRC
handbook!&lt;/em&gt; What a ridiculous situation! Fear not, dear readers, we have
heard your complaints and have adjusted accordingly. Our new problem
relies on a far less ridiculous assumption. Assume you have created a
time machine out of a DeLorean [2]. You are sure it will send you back
in time and, causality-be-damned, you are ready to give it a test drive.
But you are less confident in the machine's ability to take you exactly
&lt;em&gt;when&lt;/em&gt; you want. Additionally, the positive tachyonic chrono-coupler is
a bit finicky - meaning, of course, that there is a non-negligible
chance that once you go back in time, you may never be able to come
&lt;em&gt;Back to the Present&lt;/em&gt;. Thus, there is a chance that your time machine
will have worked but no one will ever know! As an unabashed narcissist,
you find this totally unacceptable! But first and foremost, you are a
scientist. As a scientist, your challenge is to design a strategy that
would allow you to convince your present-day scientific peers that you
did travel back in the time even if you are stuck in the past. What
could you build/make/leave in the past that would be most likely to
convince modern scientists that it &lt;em&gt;had&lt;/em&gt; to be from a time-traveler and
not just some hoaxer? How long would your strategy be effective? Would
it work if you were stuck ten thousand years in the past? What about a
million years in the past? What about 100 million? Though this is an
inherently silly problem, we feel that the idea behind it is a very
interesting one. What could one motivated person do/build/make that
would survive a long time into the future? Also, the winning solution
will be submitted as a policy White Paper for all future time-travelers.
So that's the new problem. You can find the "official" posting
&lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachine.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
I now cede the floor and my remaining time to the gentleman from
Wisconsin.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;A sense of community...&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we've had this blog going for a while now, and we get a decent
number of comments on our posts, but felt as though something has been
lacking. A certain sense of community. Over the past year, we've done
some neat things here, and now it's your turn. Step right up, because
we've just launched a google groups:
&lt;a href="https://groups.google.com/forum/#!forum/thevirtuosi"&gt;TheVirtuosi&lt;/a&gt; where
we hope people from all corners of the globe will gather to discuss
their kooky physics projects. Have you recently explored the physics of
cats? Launch a discussion. Do you have an idea but need some help
investigating it? Create a discussion and query us and all of our
fantastic readers. Have an idea for a blog post you want to see? Let us
know. Want to take a stab at solving one of the newly minted &lt;a href="http://bit.ly/physicschallenge"&gt;Physics
Challenge&lt;/a&gt; problems in public? Go for
it! I know the site is sparse now, but we'd really like to build a
little bit of a community here, so please, post away. You all have
already bookmarked it I'm sure, but a permanent link has been added to
the top of the sidebar as well. That is all. [1] These "prizes" will no
longer be as exciting as the CRC from last time, for several reasons.
First of all, we are all poor grad students and have no money. Secondly,
the winners from last time lived as far away from us as physically
possible and it's expensive to ship heavy things. So what can you expect
to win? Well, you could win a "certificate of accomplishment" which
would just be drawn in crayon by one of this. But it will be made with
love! Or you could win a floppy disk with a recording of my very own
version of the Jurassic Park theme. The surprise is part of the fun (I'm
told). [2] Quoth the most famous chrononaut of our time, Dr. Emmett
Brown: "The way I see it, if you're gonna build a time machine into a
car, why not do it with some style?"&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>great scott</category><category>physics challenge</category><category>time travel</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-ii-marty-mcphysics/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 05 Sep 2011 14:16:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Physics Challenge Award Show</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-award-show/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pyHug0rZ0X0/TYGM0O4fznI/AAAAAAAAAK0/ZTrk9NSTYuw/s1600/macgyver.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pyHug0rZ0X0/TYGM0O4fznI/AAAAAAAAAK0/ZTrk9NSTYuw/s320/macgyver.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  In an emergency, Richard Dean Anderson's mullet can be used as a flotation device and/or standard kilogram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the First Physics Challenge Problem Award Show! We received
an integer number of solutions to our challenge problem and at long last
and after much deliberation, we have chosen our winner. We had before
indicated vaguely that there may be some sort of prizes involved in this
competition. After consultation with our financial advisors and breaking
Alemi's piggy bank, we have decided on the following prizes: First
Place: A brand new CRC Handbook! Second Place: An autographed [1]
picture of Scott Bakula! Honorable Mention: Nothing! [2] So before we
officially announce our winner, let's backtrack and build up some
suspense. The challenge was to come up with a bunch of MacGyveresque
experiments to determine as closely as possible the standard second,
meter and kilogram using only the materials handy to you on a desert [3]
island. Just about every response we got successfully answered the
question, so we had to base our final result on robustness and
uncertainties. We also tended to favor those that did not rest on
precise knowledge of one's own height, weight, etc (though there is
nothing wrong with these approaches). So without further ado, the winner
is.... [pause] [unnecessarily long secondary pause] George from
Australia! George provided a list of no fewer than 11 different methods
for determining the second, meter and kilogram. The second was found by
timing (by means of a pendulum) the time it takes for the sun to move
through an a given angle measure. This measurement can be made each day
for a year to get the best results (remember, you've got all the time in
the world!). Now we have the time it takes the sun to go through a given
angle measured in "swings of a pendulum." We can calculate the transit
time of the sun into seconds and then we can find the number of seconds
per swing of the pendulum. So now we have a second. But since the period
of a pendulum is given by: $$ T = 2\pi \sqrt{l/g}, $$ we also have the
length of the pendulum in meters. From this we can make a standard
meter. Now all that is left is to find the kilogram. This can be done by
making a water-tight enclosure of volume 1000 cm^3 and filling it with
water, giving a kilogram that can be compared to other objects to get a
longer lasting standard kilogram. Any other knowledge you may have (i.e.
known height and weight) may be used to check the above measurements. A
very close second place goes to Alireza, who provided a very strong
submission and perhaps one of the best uses of snail mucus in the entire
competition! Alireza's solution was to use one's own known height to
construct the standard meter. From this you can make a pendulum to get
the second and a box o' water (sealed with tar, glue and snail mucus) to
get the kilogram. Both George and Alireza provided very detailed
responses with special attention paid toward reducing uncertainty and
checking their answers through several independent measurements. They
also both carried out parts of their experiments. Congratulations to you
both! In addition to the winning responses, we also received several
other submissions that merit honorable mention. They are.... Oliver, who
provided several acoustical experiments using his SUPERPOWER of perfect
pitch. Nicole, who noted that we were not correct in giving the Titanic
the designation
"&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Her_Majesty%27s_Ship"&gt;HMS&lt;/a&gt;" as this is
reserved for ships in the British Royal Navy. In fact, the Titanic was
designated "&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Mail_Ship"&gt;RMS&lt;/a&gt;" since
it carried mail. Thanks, Nicole! Gary, who completely ignored the
premise, used arbitrary units and left a very amusing note on his
deathbed giving all his arbitrary units to be found and converted by the
first enterprising explorer who lands on his island. I know you had
asked for your prize in cash and while I cannot directly accomodate that
wish, do know that Richard Dean Anderson smiles can be cashed in most
banks nationwide (see [2]). So thanks to everyone who submitted a
response to this Challenge. We enjoyed reading all of the solutions and
we hope you had fun thinking about it. And next time you go on a boat,
don't forget that CRC! [1] Autograph will be signed by me on an 8.5" x
11" picture of Scott Bakula printed by a laser printer on regular copy
paper. [2] Well, you receive nothing of monetary value but, know deep
down in your hearts that in the picture at the top of this post, Richard
Dean Anderson is smiling at you. So you've got that going for you, which
is nice. [3] Sadly, we did not choose a dessert island. That would have
been much more fun.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>macguyver</category><category>physics challenge</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-award-show/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 17 Mar 2011 23:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Problem of the Month: Gilligan Physics</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/problem-of-the-month-gilligan-physics/</link><dc:creator>Alemi</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/TU7ghJWo1oI/AAAAAAAAAQg/PCnPJ4aM9Ig/s1600/coconut.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/TU7ghJWo1oI/AAAAAAAAAQg/PCnPJ4aM9Ig/s320/coconut.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
So, some of us over here at Virtuosi Central have organized a challenge
problem for the physics community here at Cornell. Well, we thought we
would open up the challenge to the great wide world. The more
submissions the merrier. The deadline is March 1, and submissions can be
sent to our email. Details can be found at
&lt;a href="http://bit.ly/physicschallenge"&gt;bit.ly/physicschallenge&lt;/a&gt;. Good luck and
happy hunting.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>CRC</category><category>fun</category><category>gilligan</category><category>physics challenge</category><category>standards</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/problem-of-the-month-gilligan-physics/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2011 12:55:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>