<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts about politics)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/categories/politics.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 15:05:00 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Proofiness: A look into how mathematics relates to American political life</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/proofiness-a-look-into-how-mathematics-relates-to-american-political-life/</link><dc:creator>DTC</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Dearest readers,
This is my first post on The Virtuosi, so I thought I’d take a moment to
introduce myself. I’m a first year physics graduate student at Cornell,
recently joined after 2 years working as an engineer first at a private
firm and then at a national lab. I myself have had lots of fun following
the exploits of my estimable colleagues here on The Virtuosi, and I
thought I could bring a new angle to the content here. I would like to
use this space to discuss how science interacts with everyday life in a
cultural sense. How does science appear in popular culture? How do
political or social issues relate back to science? Those sorts of
questions. (I understand that there are plenty of other resources
elsewhere that offer far more intelligent insight into these matters
than I can, but in the very least this will give people a chance point
them out to me as they yell at me in the forum below.)
Enough intro, here begins my very first blog post:
Being interested in how science is communicated to the public, I am an
avid reader of popular science. While academic types sometimes dismiss
this kind of writing as shallow or otherwise uninteresting, I think
science writers perform a very important function serving as a way to
convey information about conceptually challenging topics to a general
audience. At their best, I find that these books serve as examples for
how I can communicate my own ideas better, and in addition challenge my
understanding of how science relates back to society in general.
This being said, I cannot recommend Charles Seife’s &lt;em&gt;Proofiness&lt;/em&gt; enough.
The basic premise of this book is to explore the way that good
mathematics is hijacked, twisted, or ignored in everyday life, and the
ugly consequences of the tendency to misunderstand numbers and
measurements.
Seife gives a number of fascinating examples of the ways in which
numbers and math connect to American democracy. American government
functions through representation, and so the
“&lt;a href="http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/constitution_transcript.html"&gt;enumeration&lt;/a&gt;”
of citizens and their opinions through the Census and elections is an
essential part of the democratic process. This “enumeration” is a
counting measurement, subject to errors like any other. And yet, the
laws that govern how Censuses and elections are run ignore this fact.
Seife’s discussion of elections (and in particular &lt;em&gt;Bush v. Gore&lt;/em&gt;) is
fascinating, but I won’t spoil that here. Here’s my take on the
discussion of the Census that appears in &lt;em&gt;Proofiness&lt;/em&gt;:
Consider a (vague) physics experiment. I want to know how many particles
are inside a box. To figure this out, I have a detector that goes
&lt;em&gt;ping&lt;/em&gt; every time a particle passes through it. I set up my detector
inside the box and count the number of times that it goes &lt;em&gt;ping&lt;/em&gt; in a
certain amount of time. I can then use that count to guess at the number
of particles that I have in my box. My measurement will let me estimate
N to within some margin of error. This process is perhaps unnecessary if
I have only five particles in my box (in which case, I might just open
the box and count what I see inside), but if I have 300 million
particles in my box, it would be totally impractical for me to reach
into the box 300 million times and count each one individually.
We can consider the Census to be just like this physics experiment. I
have N inhabitants (particles) living in my country (box), and I can use
my detector (census replies) to count a certain number of people. In
principle, using well-understood statistical techniques of regression
and error analysis, I can estimate to within a very good margin of error
how many people live in each region of the country. Instead, what the
Census requires is that we reach inside the box (send representatives to
every household that doesn’t reply by mail) and count every single
person. The whole process ignores the fact that even if we send a
representative to every single household there will still be some margin
of error in our counting measurements. No such measurement can be made
without errors.
The consequences of ignoring these errors, says Seife, can be that we
waste money in attempting the impossible and trying to count everybody.
From a civic-minded perspective, this attitude towards the perfection of
the Census can backfire. For example, if undercounting occurs (i.e.,
certain households do not respond for some reason), the Census has no
mechanism for correcting that miscount. Counter-intuitively, the Census
laws actually prohibit the use of any statistical techniques to correct
miscounting. The result is that those slow to respond are ignored and
not taken into account when allotting seats in the legislature to
represent them.
&lt;em&gt;Proofiness&lt;/em&gt; is a fascinating book and a fun read, and I recommend you
all look it up. In addition, it serves as an excellent example of
science writing that helped me to rethink how scientific ideas relate to
everyday life. I hope to invite consideration of these topics here and
in future posts. If you want to know more about the inspiration for this
post, go &lt;a href="http://journalism.nyu.edu/faculty/charles-seife/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Census</category><category>culture</category><category>elections</category><category>math</category><category>politics</category><category>Proofiness</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/proofiness-a-look-into-how-mathematics-relates-to-american-political-life/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2012 14:37:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Sense of Scale (in Dollars and Cents)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/a-sense-of-scale-in-dollars-and-cents-/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;I hate politics, but for some reason I obsessively read about it. I
don't know why I do this, but I assume it's the same reason people slow
down for car wrecks and pay to see the geek [1]. Anyway, the big thing
in political news now is that if Congress can't pass a budget [2] by the
end of the day Friday, the government will shut down. Shutting down the
government means that 800,000 federal employees will go without pay [3],
lots of services will be put on hold and you won't be able to go to the
Smithsonian or the Grand Canyon. So it's kind of a big deal. Since the
ramifications of a government shutdown are so serious, there must be
some really important disagreements holding it up, right? Right? A quick
search (for example,
&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/apr/07/us-congress-staff-government-shutdown"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;),
shows that the big hold-up in passing the budget comes over a
disagreement on how much money should be cut from the budget.
Republicans want to cut $40 billion dollars and Democrats are willing to
cut $34.5 billion dollars. So the hold-up is over $5.5 billion. Let's
consider how utterly and stupidly insignificant this is. We shall take
as our inspiration Alemi's
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/12/law-and-large-numbers.html"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;
a while back offering several ways to help visualize the large and scary
sounding numbers thrown around in government budgets. The first thing
we'd like to do is find out what fraction this $5.5 billion discrepancy
is compared to the total budget. Alemi cites the total budget of the
U.S. government in the 2010 fiscal year to be $3.55 trillion. Hot dog!
So we see that: $$ \frac{\mbox{Disputed Difference}}{\mbox{Total
Budget}} = \frac{\$5.5 \times 10^9}{\$3.55 \times 10^{12}} =
0.0015 $$ So the disputed part amounts to 0.15% of the total budget or
one and half parts in a thousand. Let's compare this to some things for
which we have a better sense of scale. Let's pretend we are looking to
buy a car. We need it to get to work and, you know, get stuff done. If
our car costs $10,000 dollars then 0.15% of our total costs will be $$
\mbox{\$10,000} \times 0.0015 = \$15 $$ So the current budget
situation is like arguing for 6 months over a $15 charge on your $10,000
car. Sounds reasonable! Now let's switch gears and consider a timescale.
Let's consider a 40 hour work week. What's 0.15% of 40 hours? This comes
to $$ 40 \mbox{ hr} \times 0.0015 = 0.06 \mbox{ hr} $$ or, if you
prefer, $$ 0.06 \mbox{ hr} \times \frac{60 \mbox{ min}}{1 \mbox{
hr}} = 3.6 \mbox{ minutes} $$ So the current budget problem is like
arguing for six months over about three and a half extra minutes to your
work week. Now let's consider a length scale. Consider the US $1 bill.
According to
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_one-dollar_bill#Small_size_notes"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;,
the dollar bill is 6.14 inches long, 2.61 inches wide and 0.0043 inches
thick. That means that the ratio of the thickness to the width of a
dollar bill is $$ \frac{\mbox{Thickness}}{\mbox{Width}} =
\frac{0.0043 \mbox{ inches}}{2.61 \mbox{ inches}} = 0.0016 $$ or
slightly &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than the disputed fraction of the budget. Hooray!
"That's all well and nice," you say, lowering your voice and leaning
over in a way that makes me uncomfortable, "but who is to &lt;em&gt;blame&lt;/em&gt;?"
That's a great question! My answer will take the form of an experiment.
First, get a coin. Got it? Great. Now if you're Republican, let heads be
"The Republicans" and tails be "The Democrats." If you're a Democrat,
let heads be "The Democrats" and tails be "The Republicans." If you are
neither, then randomly assign a party to heads and allow the other to be
tails. Ready? The coin is to blame. [1] I use this in its original
meaning. That is, the guy whose job it was to do horribly gross things
at a carnival for money, not the guy whose main form of social
interaction is debating scenes in Star Wars on internet forums. A more
up-to-date comparison would have been to say "for the same reason that
people watch &lt;em&gt;Jersey Shore&lt;/em&gt;." [2] That is, the budget for the 2011
fiscal year, which started on October 1st 2010. [3] Don't worry, all
members of Congress would be exempt from this and would still pick up
paychecks!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>large numbers</category><category>politics</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/a-sense-of-scale-in-dollars-and-cents-/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 07 Apr 2011 21:42:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Law and Large Numbers</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/the-law-and-large-numbers/</link><dc:creator>Alemi</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Human beings are not equipped for dealing with large numbers. Honestly,
7 thousand, 7 million, 7 billion and 7 trillion all register about the
same in my mind, namely 7 big. Unfortunately, there is a world a
different between each of these, three whole orders of magnitude, a
thousand, the difference between lifting me and a US quarter. This lack
of respect for orders of magnitude has really been rearing its head
recently with most of the political discussions surrounding the US
budget. Turns out the US Budget is really large. In 2010 it weighed in
at $3.55 trillion. Thats big. Really big. So big that I can't fathom it.
Without getting too political, there has been a site going around
recently; the &lt;a href="http://republicanwhip.house.gov/YouCut/week13.htm"&gt;You Cut
program&lt;/a&gt;, which
invites public suggestions for cuts to be made to the budget to try and
fix the deficit. Now, personally, I believe we ought to do something
about the deficit. To this end, I think it is useful to point out the
scales involved. In particular, the link I gave above is to one of the
suggested cuts: federal funding of NPR (Disclaimer alert: I love NPR),
which weighs in at 7 million dollars. Seven million dollars is a lot of
money. A lot of money, more than I can imagine having personally. But to
suggest that a 7 million dollar cut is any sort of progress towards
solving a $1.2 trillion dollar deficit is a little amusing. As a
fraction, this comes out to $$ \frac{ 7 \text{ million} }{ 3.55
\text{ trillion} } = 2 \times 10^{-6} $$ Two parts in a million. To
give a sense of scale to this, the gravitational influence of the moon
on my weight is: $$ \frac{ \frac{ G M_{\text{moon}} }{
R_{\text{earth-moon}}^2 } }{ 10 \text{ m/s}^2 } = 3 \times
10^{-6} $$ Three parts in a million. So, suggesting that you have made
real gains in reducing the US budget by cutting federal funding for NPR
is as silly as suggesting that if I want to lose weight, my first
concern should be the current tides. [I want to point out that I don't
really mean to get too political, and that I've noticed both parties
pulling these kinds of numbers tricks.] So, wanting to get a little
better understanding of the numbers at stake, I collected some data (all
from the 2010 budget). My goal is to attempt to represent how the US
government spends its money. Before I begin I need to plug two great
tools towards this end:
&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2010/02/01/us/budget.html"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt; the
NYTimes graphically represents government spending, helping to give a
sense of scale to different categories.
&lt;a href="http://www.nytimes.com/interactive/2010/11/13/weekinreview/deficits-graphic.html"&gt;Here&lt;/a&gt;
the NYTimes lets you try and balance the budget, not only for next year
but down the line, letting you choose from a wide array of proposed
changes. The Data So, below is a list of some of the relevant numbers I
could thing of, and some reference numbers (trillion, billion, million),
as well as the US debt, and total deficit. In addition to just reporting
the numbers (which you can find anywhere), in the second column I give
the fraction of total spending in scientific units.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Name             $               Fraction
  US Debt          13.8 trillion   3.9
  Total Spending   3.55 trillion   1.0
  Budget Deficit   1.17 trillion   3.3E-1
  1 trillion       1 trillion      2.8E-1
  SS / Def / MM    730 billion     2.1E-1
  Education        93 billion      2.6E-2
  Taxes (250G+)    54 billion      1.5E-2
  Science          31 billion      8.7E-3
  1 billion        1 billion       2.8E-4
  NPR              7 million       2.0E-6
  1 million        1 million       2.8E-7&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here, SS / Def / MM means each of Social Security, Defense spending
and Medicare and Medicaid, which each comes in at about the same per
program. We spend 730 billion on each of these. To first glance, these
three programs are how the US spends money, each of these coming in at
21%. Notice also just how large the deficit is, coming in at 33% of
total spending. The rather cryptic "Taxes (250G+)" is how much money
would be saved by letting the Bush tax cuts expire for those making more
than 250,000 a year, a currently hotly debated topic. Notice that it
would only ease the burden by 15%. So this alone would only cut the
budget deficit in half. The above table shows the power of scientific
notation. (Even though I had to use the ugly "E" notation). A number
like "2.8E-4" is really 2.9 x 10^(-4). But honestly, even a list like
this doesn't really make an impact for me. So, I thought of a couple
other ways to represent the same numbers, scaling them to some 'big'
things I can conceive of:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Barry's Budget&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this might not be a fair comparison, but let's scale down the US
budget to sizes that a person can understand. By scaling by a factor of
$100 million, we end up with the story of my friend Barry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Name             $               Fraction   Barry
  US Debt          13.8 trillion   3.9        $138,495.50
  Total Spending   3.55 trillion   1.0        $35,500.00
  Budget Deficit   1.17 trillion   3.3E-1     $11,690.0
  1 trillion       1 trillion      2.8E-1     $10,000.00
  SS / Def / MM    730 billion     2.1E-1     $7,296.67
  Education        93 billion      2.6E-2     $930.00
  Taxes (250G+)    54 billion      1.5E-2     $540.00
  Science          31 billion      8.7E-3     $310.00
  1 billion        1 billion       2.8E-4     $10.00
  NPR              7 million       2.0E-6     $0.07
  1 million        1 million       2.8E-7     $0.01&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you'll notice, Barry makes $23,810.00 a year (total receipts)[he's a
grad student], but spends $35,500 a year. This has created his current
debt problem. Barry has $138,495 in credit card debt, and still
overspends by $11,690 a year. How does Barry spend his money? Well,
every year Barry buys some $7,300 in guns, spends another $14,600 mostly
taking care of his grandma. He pays a tuition of $930 a year at school,
and $310 on science books. Every year he donates 7 cents to NPR. Every
million US dollars is 1 penny in Barry dollars.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Work Week&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That might not have been fair. This time, lets scale the US government
spending to a work week of 40 hours. I think a work week is a large
amount of time that I still have a real grasp for.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Name             $               Work Time      Guess at time
  US Debt          13.8 trillion   156 hours      Work month
  Total Spending   3.55 trillion   40 hours       Work week
  Budget Deficit   1.17 trillion   13 hours       All Mon and Tue morn
  1 trillion       1 trillion      11.3 hours     two days of good work
  SS / Def / MM    730 billion     8.2 hour       true work in a day
  Education        93 billion      63 minutes     lunch break
  Taxes (250G+)    54 billion      36 minutes     cooler chat
  Science          31 billion      21 minutes     Show on Hulu
  1 billion        1 billion       40 seconds     Stretching at desk
  NPR              7 million       0.3 seconds    mouse click
  1 million        1 million       0.04 seconds   blink&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Cross Country&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now lets scale to a distance. The longest drive I've ever done is from
Los Angeles, CA to Orlando, Fl, which was 2511 miles. In terms of this
scale, the budget breaks down as:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Name             $               Dist    &lt;br&gt;
  US Debt          13.8 trillion   9796 mi   NY - Sydney
  Total Spending   3.55 trillion   2511 mi   LA - Orlando
  Budget Deficit   1.17 trillion   827 mi    Texas
  1 trillion       1 trillion      707 mi  &lt;br&gt;
  SS / Def / MM    730 billion     516 mi    Orlando - Mobile
  Education        93 billion      66 mi   &lt;br&gt;
  Taxes (250G+)    54 billion      38 mi   &lt;br&gt;
  Science          31 billion      22 mi     Cross town
  1 billion        1 billion       0.7 mi    14 blocks
  NPR              7 million       9 yards &lt;br&gt;
  1 million        1 million       4 feet    &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(So I just want to point out again, claiming that cutting NPR funding
makes a dent in the US budget is similar to claiming you've moved closer
to Orlando (while in LA) by crossing the room.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Lesson&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, without getting too political... I'd just like to point out that if
our politicians are serious about solving the budget crisis, they need
to stop talking about million dollar programs, and start taking about
100 billion dollar ones. The problem is that it's hard to either slash
funding for large programs like defense, or social security, and it's
even harder raise taxes (really at all). But if we never consider those
options, we're never going to get out of the rut. In my undergraduate
physics lab, the instructor had a mantra: "A number without context is
meaningless". Now, he originally meant the statement to be a lesson on
how important it is to quote errors on your measurements, but I think I
can adapt it to apply to giving out numbers like 7 billion without a
sense of scale.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>budget</category><category>large numbers</category><category>politics</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/the-law-and-large-numbers/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 09 Dec 2010 22:34:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>