<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts about scott bakula)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/categories/scott-bakula.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 15:05:00 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>A Curious Footprint</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/a-curious-footprint/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;figure style="float:center; margin:0px 0px 10px 0px" width="50%"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/a-curious-footprint/msl_laser.jpg" alt="msl laser"&gt;
&lt;figcaption&gt; Lasers! &lt;i&gt;Credit: JPL/Caltech&lt;/i&gt; &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In less than two days, NASA's Mars Science Laboratory (MSL) / &lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt; 
rover will begin its harrowing descent to the Martian
surface. If everything goes according to the
kind-of-crazy-what-the-heck-is-a-sky-crane plan, this process will be
referred to as "landing" (otherwise, more crashy/explodey gerunds will
no doubt be used). The MSL mission is run through NASA's Jet Propulsion
Laboratory where, by coincidence, I happen to be at the moment. Now, I'm
not working on this project, so I don't have a lot to add that
&lt;a href="http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/msl/index.cfm"&gt;isn't&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/badastronomy/2012/08/02/curiositys-chem-lab-on-mars/"&gt;available&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/startswithabang/2012/07/20/43-years-later-were-seven-minutes-away-from-a-second-great-step-forward/"&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;.
BUT I do feel an authority-by-proximity kind of fallacy kicking in, so
how about a post why not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Preliminaries&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, I feel obligated to link to NASA's 
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ki_Af_o9Q9s"&gt;Seven Minutes of Terror&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;
video. If you haven't seen it yet, I highly recommend watching it right now (my
favorite part is the subtitles). It has over a million views on YouTube
and seems to have done a pretty good job at generating interest in the
mission. Although, it's a shame they had to interview the first guy in
what appears to be a police interrogation room. Oh well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;About the Rover&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thing is &lt;em&gt;big&lt;/em&gt;. It's the size of a car and is jam-packed with
&lt;a href="http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/msl/mission/instruments/"&gt;scientific equipment&lt;/a&gt;. 
There's a couple different spectrometers, a bunch of cameras, a drill for
collecting rock samples, and radiation detectors. Probably the coolest
instrument onboard &lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt; is called the ChemCam. The ChemCam uses a
laser to vaporize small regions of rock, which allows it to study the
composition of things about 20 feet away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the scientific payload, &lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt; also needs some way
to generate power. Previous rovers had been powered by solar panels, but
there don't appear to be any here. Instead, &lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt; is
&lt;a href="http://www.ne.doe.gov/pdfFiles/MMRTG_Jan2008.pdf"&gt;powered&lt;/a&gt; 
by the heat released from the radioactive decay of about 10 pounds of plutonium
dioxide. This source will power the rover for 
&lt;strike&gt;about a Martian year&lt;/strike&gt;
well beyond the currently planned mission duration of one Martian year
(about 687 Earth days) [Thanks to Nathan in the comments for pointing
this out!].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, the rover is a nuclear-powered lab-on-wheels that 
&lt;em&gt;shoots lasers out of its head&lt;/em&gt;. This is pretty cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure style="width:70%"&gt;
    &lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/a-curious-footprint/msl2.jpg" width="100%" alt="msl laser 2" align="center" style="margin:0px 0px 0px 0px"&gt;

   &lt;figcaption&gt;In non-SI units, the MSL is roughly one handsome man (1 hm) tall&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;h4&gt;A Curious Footprint&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's been a lot of preparation at JPL this week for the upcoming
landing. All the shiny rover models have been taken out of the visitor's
center and put in a tent outside, presumably so there will be a pretty
backdrop for press reports and the like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I was out taking pictures of the rovers at the end of the day
today when someone pointed out something cool about the tires on
&lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here's a close-up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;figure style="width:70%"&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/a-curious-footprint/MSL_tire.jpg" width="100%" alt="msl tire" align="center" style="margin:0px 0px 0px 0px"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt; Hole-y Tires &lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Each tire on the rover is has "JPL" punched out in 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:International_Morse_Code.svg"&gt;Morse code&lt;/a&gt;!
Makes sense, though. If you're going to spend $2.5 billion on something,
you might as well put your name on it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Watch the Landing&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to watch the landing, check out the 
&lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/multimedia/nasatv/index.html"&gt;NASA TV stream&lt;/a&gt;. 
The landing is scheduled for Sunday night at 10:31 pm PDT (1:31 am EDT). Until then,
it looks like they are showing a lot of interviews and other cool
behind-the-scenes kind of stuff.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>curiosity</category><category>mars</category><category>MSL</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/a-curious-footprint/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 04 Aug 2012 04:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Tales from the Transit of Venus</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/tales-from-the-transit-of-venus/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div style="float: center;"&gt;
&lt;figure&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/venus-transit/sad_transit.png" alt="sad old sun" width="30%"&gt;
  &lt;figcaption&gt;Sad Old Sun&lt;/figcaption&gt;
&lt;/figure&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today is the transit of Venus, which, aside from being a totally rad
astronomical event, is also the perfect excuse to tell my favorite story
of an unlucky Frenchman (I have many). This is by no means new and, if
you've ever taken an astronomy course, you've probably already heard it.
It is perhaps the closest thing Astronomy has to a ghost story, told
though the glow of a flashlight on moonless nights to scare the
children. This is the story of Guillaume Le Gentil, a dude that just
couldn't catch a break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- more --&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Joseph Hyacinthe Jean-Baptiste Le Gentil de la Galaisière was
a Frenchman with an incredibly long name. He was also an astronomer,
though he hadn't started out that way. Monsieur Le Gentil (as his
friends called him and so, then, shall we) had originally intended to
enter the priesthood. However, he soon began sneaking away to hear
astronomy lectures and quickly switched from studies of Heaven to those
heavens more readily observed in a telescope. Le Gentil happened to get
into the astronomy game at a very exciting time. The next pair of Venus
transits was imminent and astronomers were giddy with anticipation.
Though the previous transit of 1639 had been predicted, it was met with
little fanfare and only a few measurements. But the transits of 1761 and
1769 would be different. People would be ready. And the stakes were
higher this time, too. Soon after the 1639 transit, Edmund Halley (he of
the-only-comet-people-can-name fame) calculated that with enough
simultaneous measurements, the distance from the Earth to the Sun (the
so-called astronomical unit, or AU) could be measured fairly accurately.
Since almost all other astronomical distances were known in terms of the
AU, knowing its precise value would essentially set the scale for the
cosmos. Brand new telescopes in hand, the astronomers of Europe set sail
for locations all over the world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Gentil had been assigned to observe the transit from Pondicherry, a
French holding on the eastern side of India. On March 26th, 1760, he
began his long sea voyage around the Cape of Good Hope towards India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The voyage from France to India was a bit too long for the ship Le
Gentil hitched a ride on and he only made it as far as Mauritius (a
small island off Madagascar). Dropped off with all his equipment, Le
Gentil was left waiting for any ship at all to take him to Pondicherry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it was the Curse of the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dodo"&gt;Dodo&lt;/a&gt; or perhaps it was just bad
luck, but while he was waiting, Le Gentil learned that
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seven_Years'_War"&gt;war&lt;/a&gt; had broken out
between the French and the British, making a trip to British India very
difficult for a Frenchman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the monsoon season started, meaning that even if he could find a
ship, it would have to take a much longer route to India than initially
planned and that it would be very difficult to make the journey before
the transit occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, he caught dysentery for the first time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, after months of waiting, Le Gentil (barely recovered from his
illness) left Mauritius for India in February of 1761. Though time
appeared to be running out, the captain of the ship he was on promised
he would be there to observe the transit in June. About halfway to
India, the winds switched directions and the ship was forced to turn
back to Mauritius.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Gentil dutifully observed the transit of Venus in 1761 from a rocky
ship in the middle of the Indian Ocean. The data were useless and he
never attempted any analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although he missed the first transit, these things come in pairs
separated by eight years. There was still another chance. And with all
this time to prepare, there was no way he was going to miss the second
one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, there was a bit &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt; time. But as a world-traveling 18th
century man of science, Le Gentil had plenty of other interests to fill
his days. He was particularly interested in surveying the region around
Madagascar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So he made a really nice map of Madagascar. And then he ate some bad
kind of some kind of animal and came down with a terrible sickness. He
describes this illness and its "cure" in his journals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This sickness was a sort of violent stroke, of which several very
copious blood-lettings made immediately on my arm and my foot, and
emetic administered twelve hours afterwards, rid me of it quite
quickly. But there remained for seven or eight days in my optic nerve
a singular impression from this sickness; it was to see two objects in
the place of one, beside each other; this illusion disappeared little
by little as I regained my strength...&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After recovering from both his sickness and the treatment, Le Gentil
decided to begin his preparations for the 1769 transit of Venus. He
calculated that either Manila or the Mariana Islands would be the ideal
spot to observe. The Sun would be relatively high in the sky at both
places when Venus passed by, meaning that the view would be through less
atmosphere with a reduced chance of clouds passing through the line of
sight. Le Gentil packed up his stuff and headed off to Manila, where he
could catch another ship to get to the Mariana Islands. Arriving in
Manila in 1766, the astronomer found himself exhausted from months of
sickness and sea-voyage. So, when he was offered passage on a ship
heading to the Mariana Islands, he quickly declined. That he chose not
to depart Manila at that time was perhaps his one stroke of good luck in
the entire journey. The ship sunk. Writing in his journal, Le Gentil
appears to have developed that particular sense of humor that generally
accompanies constant disappointment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is true that only three or four people were drowned, those who
were the most eager to save themselves, which is what almost always
happens in shipwrecks. I cannot answer that I would not have
increased the number of persons eager to save themselves.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, Le Gentil was in Manila with plenty of time to prepare for
the next transit. Unfortunately, the astronomer may have over-prepared.
Having arrived three years before the event, he now had three years to
worry and second-guess his decision. It didn't help that the Spanish
governor of Manila was kind of a crazy person. Not wanting to miss the
observation of a lifetime owing to the whims of mildly insane strong
man, Le Gentil packed up his stuff and headed to Pondicherry. Finally in
Pondicherry, Le Gentil worked tirelessly to construct his observatory
and make plenty of astronomical observations in preparation for the
event. He had state of the art equipment and had fully calibrated and
double checked everything. It was now nine years since his journey began
and only a few days until the transit was scheduled to occur at sunrise
on June 4th. The entire month of May was beautiful weather and pristine
observing conditions, as were the first few days of June. Le Gentil
likely went to bed on the 3rd of June fully confident that the next
morning would be no different. He woke up early in the morning to begin
preparations for his sunrise observations only to find clouds on the
horizon. The clouds remained, obscuring the sun, all through the
duration of the transit. A few hours after the end of the transit, the
sun broke through the clouds and remained visible for the rest of the
day. Le Gentil had missed his second transit in Pondicherry. He sums it
up in his journal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That is the fate which often awaits astronomers. I had gone more
than ten thousand leagues; it seemed that I had crossed such a great
expanse of seas, exiling myself from my native land, only to be the
spectator of a fatal cloud which came to place itself before the sun
at the precise moment of my observation, to carry off from me the
fruits of my pains and of my fatigues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Manila, the Sun rose in perfectly clear skies. Distraught, Le Gentil
remained in bed for some weeks afterward. He soon caught a fever and
missed the ship that was supposed to take him home. He recovered, but
then came down with dysentery again. Barely recovered from his various
illnesses, he managed to get a ride back to Mauritius. He caught a ship
leaving the island in November of 1770. The ship was struck by a
hurricane and almost completely destroyed. It managed to limp back to
Mauritius. The second attempt proved more successful and Le Gentil
finally "set foot on France at nine o'clock in the morning, after eleven
years, six months and thirteen days of absence." Though he had finally
made it home, he was not out of the woods quite yet. In his absence, Le
Gentil's heirs had tried to declare him dead to gain their inheritance,
his accountant had mishandled (and lost) a large chunk of his holdings,
and the Academy of Sciences, which had sent him on his 11 year mission,
had given his seat to someone else. It was not quite the welcome home he
had hoped for. Despite his seemingly never-ending misfortune, things did
turn around for Le Gentil. He married, had a daughter, and was
reinstated into the Academy of Sciences. Presumably, he lived out the
rest of his days in relative happiness. Le Gentil died in 1792. Keeping
true to his style, this man who missed two of the most important
astronomical events of his time fortunately managed to also miss the
most important (and violent) &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reign_of_Terror"&gt;political
event&lt;/a&gt; of his time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have mainly used a very nice series of historical papers of Le
Gentil's misadventures with the transit of Venus written by Helen Sawyer
Hogg. The papers were originally published in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal
Astronomical Society of Canada&lt;/em&gt; and can be accessed through NASA's ADS 
(&lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1951JRASC..45...37S"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1951JRASC..45...89S"&gt;Part2&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1951JRASC..45..127S"&gt;Part 3&lt;/a&gt;, 
&lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1951JRASC..45..173S"&gt;Part 4&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More Transit of Venus:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to see the Transit of Venus without having to go on an
eleven year voyage (or even leaving your room), check out the NASA
&lt;a href="http://sunearthday.nasa.gov/transitofvenus/"&gt;live-feed&lt;/a&gt; from Mauna Kea.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>bummer</category><category>scott bakula</category><category>transit of venus</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/tales-from-the-transit-of-venus/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 05 Jun 2012 00:50:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Money for (almost) Nothing</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/money-for-almost-nothing/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-j1vgDeAaElw/T3O5K09X6XI/AAAAAAAAAW0/b3uIqmdtPl4/s1600/mega_millions.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-j1vgDeAaElw/T3O5K09X6XI/AAAAAAAAAW0/b3uIqmdtPl4/s320/mega_millions.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Five Hundred Mega Dollars, to be precise. (Image from Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not typically interested in lotteries. They seem silly and I am
seriously beginning to question their usefulness in bringing about a
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Lottery"&gt;good harvest&lt;/a&gt;. But this
morning I read in the news that the Mega Millions lottery currently has
a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mega_Millions#Record_jackpots_.28listed_by_cash_value.29"&gt;world
record&lt;/a&gt;
jackpot up for grabs. In fact, the jackpot is so big...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tonight Show Audience: &lt;em&gt;HOW BIG IS IT?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;so big&lt;/em&gt; that I decided to do a little bit of analysis on the
expected returns. Zing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Some Background&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a little background. The Mega Millions lottery is an aptly named
lottery in which numbered ping pong balls are pulled from a giant
rotating tub of randomization. Five of these are drawn from one tub of
56 balls, with no replacement. The sixth ball (the so-called "Mega
Ball") is drawn from a &lt;em&gt;separate&lt;/em&gt;tub of 46 balls. To play, one picks 5
different numbers (1-56) for the regular draws and one number (1-46) for
the Mega Ball. The first five can match in any order, but the last ball
has to match with the Mega Ball. Prizes are given out based on how many
numbers you match. Stolen from the Mega Millions website, the prizes and
odds are given in the table below. The current jackpot is listed at $500
million (if taken in annuity) or $359 million if taken in an up-front
lump sum. It costs $1 dollar to play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Zi3rSfNqtuI/T3PHTEaXmvI/AAAAAAAAAXE/y9Hs7fqWrgs/s1600/crummy_table.gif"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Zi3rSfNqtuI/T3PHTEaXmvI/AAAAAAAAAXE/y9Hs7fqWrgs/s320/crummy_table.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Don't worry about the asterisk. It just says CA is lame. (Source: &lt;a href="http://www.megamillions.com/howto/"&gt;Mega Millions&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot diggity daffodil, we're ready to get going!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Expected Winnings&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so it costs $1 to play and we could potentially win $500
million. It sure &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; like it is worth it to play (what's the harm?).
But we can do better than feelings, we have... MATH!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we have an exhaustive list of outcomes and their probabilities
(which is just the inverse of the big number in the "chances" column),
we can calculate the expectation value for our winnings. The expectation
value is just the sum over all the possible prize values times the
probability of winning that prize. In other words,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\langle W \rangle = \sum_i W_i \times p_i, $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where we denote our expected winnings in angled brackets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence, this value represents the average prize you would win if you
played this lottery over and over and over again (or played all the
combinations of numbers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting the jackpot to $500 million, we can now compute the expected
winnings as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \langle W \rangle = \frac{\$ 500,000,000}{175,711,536} +
\frac{\$ 250,000}{3,904,701} +\frac{\$ 10,000}{689,065} + \frac{\$
150}{15,313} + \frac{\$ 150}{13,781} $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$+ \frac{\$ 10}{844} + \frac{\$ 7}{306} + \frac{\$ 3}{141} +
\frac{\$ 2}{75}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few flicks of the abacus later, we find that the expectation value of
our prize is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\langle W \rangle = \$ 3.02,$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which means that after we subtract the dollar we paid for the ticket,
our expected return is $2.02.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we had chosen to take our winnings as a lump sum of $359
million instead of the $500 million paid out over a span of 26 years? In
that case we find&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$\langle W \rangle = \$ 2.22,$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which results in a $1.22 gain when we subtract the dollar we paid for
the ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least in a statistical sense for this particular jackpot, one is
better off playing than not playing. But are we forgetting anything?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;The Taxman&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you win a $500 million jackpot, do you &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; get a $500 million
jackpot? Well, no. For winnings in a lottery over $5000, the IRS
&lt;a href="http://www.irs.gov/instructions/iw2g/ar02.html#d0e401"&gt;withholds&lt;/a&gt; 25%
in federal income taxes. Additionally, the winnings are subject to state
taxes as well. For example, if I were to win, the great state of New
York would be entitled to about 6.8% (apparently also just for winnings
above $5000).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After applying federal and state taxes to the prizes above $5000, we now
have an expected winnings of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \langle W \rangle = \left[1-(0.25 +
0.068)\right]\times\left(\frac{\mbox{Jackpot}}{175,711,536} +
\frac{\$ 250,000}{3,904,701} +\frac{\$ 10,000}{689,065}\right) $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$+ \frac{\$ 150}{15,313} + \frac{\$ 150}{13,781}+ \frac{\$
10}{844} + \frac{\$ 7}{306} + \frac{\$ 3}{141} + \frac{\$
2}{75},$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which gives an expected net win (minus the $1 for the ticket) of $1.10
for the $500 million annuity prize and $0.55 for the $359 million
up-front lump sum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We're still in the black, but it's slowly slipping away. Is there
anything else we need to factor in? Well, yes. For one thing, winning
the jackpot qualifies us for the top tax bracket, so most of the
winnings would be taxed at the top marginal tax rate of 35%. Welcome to
the 1%, kids! &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/money-for-almost-nothing/#note"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changing the federal tax rate on the jackpot from 25% to 35% and
recalculating, we find net expected winnings of $0.81 for the $500
million annuity and $0.34 for the $359 million lump sum. Surprisingly,
it is still worth it in a statistical sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Is it always like this?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to keep in mind as we make these estimates is that this is a
&lt;em&gt;historically large&lt;/em&gt; jackpot. So even though it may be favorable to play
this time, this will not always be the case. In fact, we can find the
minimum jackpot value for which this is the case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The condition in which our expected return is a gain (rather than a
loss) is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \langle W \rangle - \$1.00 &amp;gt; 0. $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For simplicity, let's ignore the top marginal tax rate and just factor
in the 25% withholding and the 6.8% state tax. Solving for the minimum
jackpot using the expression for we found in the last section, we see
that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mbox{Jackpot}_{min} = \$217\~\mbox{million}.$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically, this would have to be the amount actually awarded by the
payment method of your choice. The &lt;em&gt;stated&lt;/em&gt; jackpot is always the
annuity method (because it looks higher). The lump sum offering is &lt;em&gt;at
most&lt;/em&gt; about 70% of the stated jackpot. So if you want to take the lump
sum offering the &lt;em&gt;stated&lt;/em&gt; jackpot will need to be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \mbox{Jackpot}_{min} = \$217\~\mbox{million} / 0.7 =
\$310\~\mbox{million}.$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, these values are likely a bit low, since we have not included
the increase to the marginal tax rate, nor have we included other
effects like having to split a prize (which seems to happen a lot) or
inflation effects if you take the prize in yearly installments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, a quick look through the &lt;a href="http://www.megamillions.com/winners/jackpothistory.asp"&gt;jackpot
history&lt;/a&gt; shows
that these threshold values are only met occasionally. An eyeball
estimate puts about one jackpot per year that exceeds the (absolute)
minimum $217 million threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;So am I going to win?&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. No, you will not. BUT if you played record setting lotteries
hundreds of millions of times, you might see decent (\~10%) returns.
Although, it may just be easiest to, you know, &lt;em&gt;invest&lt;/em&gt; that money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h5&gt;Only One Useless Footnote&lt;/h5&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Although, to be fair, the top marginal tax rate is currently at
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:MarginalIncomeTax.svg"&gt;historical
lows&lt;/a&gt;. It could
always be worse... &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/money-for-almost-nothing/#back"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>lottery</category><category>MEGABUCKS</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/money-for-almost-nothing/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 29 Mar 2012 01:27:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Moving Pi-ctures</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-YJBJw29pxZk/T1ribOQLS-I/AAAAAAAAAVA/xsJ-KAOJt5w/s1600/tv_pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-YJBJw29pxZk/T1ribOQLS-I/AAAAAAAAAVA/xsJ-KAOJt5w/s320/tv_pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  My TV celebrates without me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, as I'm sure you're aware, is Pi Day - a day for the festive
consumption of pies and quiet self-reflection. In the spirit of the
holiday, I'd like to present a point for discussion: &lt;em&gt;Everyone has a
great talent for at least one thing.&lt;/em&gt; That this is true for at least
&lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; people is seen through even a cursory glance at a history book:
George Washington was really good at leading revolutions, Michelangelo
was an outstanding ceiling painter &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/#note1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, and Batman was the
best at solving complex riddles (especially in English, pero
&lt;em&gt;especialmente&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RY1U_pXUxUo&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;en
español&lt;/a&gt;).
But I'm certain that this holds for everyone. What's your talent? Mine,
as those of you who read this blog should know very well by now, is
certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; doing physics. Nope, my talent is watching TV. Seriously
guys, I watch TV like a boss &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/#note2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. In light of this talent, I
thought I would describe a few instances in which I have seen pi
represented (for better or for worse) in TV and movies. Over the last
few months, I have been re-watching a lot of the TV show
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psych"&gt;Psych&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; with my good friend and
fellow Virtuosi contributor, Matt "TT" Showbiz &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/#note3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. For the
uninitiated, &lt;em&gt;Psych&lt;/em&gt; is a detective show where the main characters
(Shawn and Gus) run a (fake) psychic detective agency, which allows them
to solve mysteries, engage in various shenanigans, and make an
inordinate number of references to &lt;em&gt;Tears for Fears&lt;/em&gt; frontman Curt Smith
&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/#note4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. In one of the episodes, Shawn and Gus enter a room where
a long train of digits is written across the top of the wall. It soon
becomes evident that these are the digits of pi and the camera is sure
to zoom in on the famous first few digits to reassure us. But there are
hundreds of digits written out and I have very little faith in TV prop
people when it comes to background mathematical expressions. So I
decided to check it out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sIqwUS9wlog/T17KQ7mU7nI/AAAAAAAAAV4/1hiiMuN-yxA/s1600/pi_psych1.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sIqwUS9wlog/T17KQ7mU7nI/AAAAAAAAAV4/1hiiMuN-yxA/s400/pi_psych1.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Pi on the Wall (click to enhance for texture)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a neat little pi &lt;a href="http://www.angio.net/pi/piquery"&gt;searcher&lt;/a&gt;, I
checked to see if (and where) this sequence appeared in pi. Turns out
it's legit and (almost!) correct. The first 105 digits of pi (counting
after the three) are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.14159265358979323846264338327950288419716939937510582097494459230781640628620899862803482534211706&lt;strong&gt;798&lt;/strong&gt;2148&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where I have underlined the 99th, 100th, and 101st digits. Looking back
at the writing on the wall, we see that the 100th digit has been
duplicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6vQ2gmfNULw/T17Nb29jAvI/AAAAAAAAAWA/2hMW9vdU3S0/s1600/pi_psych.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6vQ2gmfNULw/T17Nb29jAvI/AAAAAAAAAWA/2hMW9vdU3S0/s400/pi_psych.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Very Almost Pi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So close! Oh well, nobody is perfect. Even though there is an error
here, I very much appreciate that whoever was doing the set design
decided to use the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; digits of pi. All too often I see
nonsensical equations in the background of TV shows and movies when it
would take &lt;em&gt;exactly the same&lt;/em&gt; amount of work to put real equations
there. So congratulations to you, O nameless prop-making intern!, for
giving an accurate (well, to a part in 10^100) value of pi. Neat, so
are there any other TV shows or movies that have pi in them? Well,
there's &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jo18VIoR2xU"&gt;Pi&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt; is film
by Darren Aronofsky (&lt;em&gt;Requiem for a Dream&lt;/em&gt;, etc) about a mathematician
looking for patterns in the stock market. It's a pretty good movie with
a really cool
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Cq_QO_4Cx4&amp;amp;feature=player_embedded"&gt;soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;
by Clint Mansell. It also appears to display the digits of pi in the
opening credits. But does it? To the Youtube-mobile! You can watch the
opening credits &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L61x5mbE-jc"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if
you like and here is a still image of the relevant section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pEbkgRx-PFw/T17UHYdfhwI/AAAAAAAAAWI/vsyzWd139pg/s1600/sad_pi.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pEbkgRx-PFw/T17UHYdfhwI/AAAAAAAAAWI/vsyzWd139pg/s400/sad_pi.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Pi?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks pretty cool, huh? But once we get past the slick aesthetics, we
see that something doesn't seem right. This number they are showing
appears at first glance to be our good friend pi, but after the 8th
digit the cover is blown and we see that this is actually some impostor
number!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-5afmhwZOhWk/T17U-d1okrI/AAAAAAAAAWQ/KB7NHwwOvQg/s1600/verysadpi.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-5afmhwZOhWk/T17U-d1okrI/AAAAAAAAAWQ/KB7NHwwOvQg/s400/verysadpi.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  More like Darren Aron-wrong-sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I fully understand that this has no bearing whatsoever on the film
and, in the grand scheme of things, is not a Big Deal. But it would have
been just as easy to put the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; digits of pi here instead of just
random filler. The only way that this could possibly be better than the
real deal would be if it is actually a secret code. I have not yet ruled
this out, as the movie is entirely about looking for meaning in
seemingly random numbers. Unfortunately, the difficulty in transcribing
the numbers from the screen greatly outweighs the very small chance that
this isn't just gibberish. Four hundred Quatloos to anyone who can tell
me if this is a code or not!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] And an above average Ninja Turtle to boot. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/#back1"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Yes, I am putting my TV watching skills on par with the talents of
George Washington. In fact, the stoic way in which I persevered through
the entirety of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terminator:_The_Sarah_Connor_Chronicles"&gt;The Sarah Connor
Chronicles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;in
under two weeks was described by historian David McCullough as
"Washingtonian." These are simply facts. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/#back2"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] The extra "T" is for extra talent. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/#back3"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] A duo can &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; have a frontman. For evidence, feel free to
ask the not-George-Michael-guy from &lt;em&gt;Wham!&lt;/em&gt; or the not-Paul-Simon-guy
from &lt;em&gt;Simon &amp;amp; Garfunkel&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/#back4"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>pi day</category><category>pineapple</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/moving-pi-ctures/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 08:35:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>A Very Small Slice of Pi</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/a-very-small-slice-of-pi/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q37nqPUh_t0/T2AJgUmFLKI/AAAAAAAAAWY/0rvkqKzmDBs/s1600/rhubarb.JPG"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q37nqPUh_t0/T2AJgUmFLKI/AAAAAAAAAWY/0rvkqKzmDBs/s320/rhubarb.JPG"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Rhubarb pie (Source: Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people know a &lt;em&gt;suspiciously&lt;/em&gt; large number of the digits of pi.
Perhaps you have met one of these people. They can typically be found
hiding behind bushes and under the counters at pastry shops, just...
&lt;em&gt;waiting&lt;/em&gt;. At the slightest hint of a mention of pi, they will jump out
and start reciting the digits like there's a prize at the end. After
rattling off numbers for a few minutes they abruptly come to an end,
grin like an idiot, and walk away. It is an unpleasant encounter. The
sheer uselessness of this kind of thing has always bothered me, so I'd
like to set a preliminary upper bound on the number of digits of pi that
could ever possibly potentially kind of be useful (maybe). For those
following along at home, now would be a good time to put on your
numerology hats. Alright, so I hear this thing pi is fairly useful when
dealing with circles. Let's say we want to make a really big circle and
have its diameter only deviate by a very small amount from the correct
value. To do this successfully, we will have to know pi fairly well.
Let's take this to extremes now. Suppose I want to put a circle around
the &lt;em&gt;entire visible universe&lt;/em&gt; such that the uncertainty in the diameter
is the size of a &lt;em&gt;single proton&lt;/em&gt;. What would be the fractional
uncertainty in the circumference in this case? If we know pi exactly,
then we have that $$\delta C = \frac{\partial C}{\partial d} \delta
d = \pi \delta d = C \frac{\delta d}{d}, $$ where d is the diameter
and C is the circumference. In other words, the fractional uncertainty
in the circumference is just $$\frac{\delta C}{C} = \frac{\delta
d}{d}. $$ Using a femtometer for the size of a proton and 90 billion
light years for the size of the Universe &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/a-very-small-slice-of-pi/#note"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, we get
$$\frac{\delta C}{C} = \frac{\delta d}{d} =
\frac{10^{-15}\mbox{m}}{(90\times10^9)(3\times10^7\mbox{s})(3\times10^8\mbox{m
s}^{-1})} \sim\frac{10^{-15}}{10^{27}}\sim10^{-42}.$$ Alright, so
how well do we need to know pi to get a similar fractional uncertainty?
Well, we have that $$\frac{\delta \pi}{\pi} = \frac{\delta C}{C} =
10^{-42}, $$ so we can afford an uncertainty in pi of $$ \delta \pi =
\pi \times 10^{-42}$$ and thus we'll need to know pi to about 42
digits. How's that for an
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phrases_from_The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy#Answer_to_the_Ultimate_Question_of_Life.2C_the_Universe.2C_and_Everything_.2842.29"&gt;answer&lt;/a&gt;?
So if we have a giant circle the size of the &lt;em&gt;entire visible universe&lt;/em&gt;,
we can find its diameter to within the size of a &lt;em&gt;single proton&lt;/em&gt; using
pi to 42 digits. Therefore, I adopt this as the maximal number of digits
that could ever prove useful in a physical sense (albeit under a
somewhat bizzarre set of circumstances). If reciting hundreds of digits
is what makes you happy, go for it. But 42 digits is more than enough pi
for me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] "But I thought the Universe was only 13.7 billion years! What voodoo
is this!?" Yeah, I know. See
&lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/startswithabang/2011/01/q_a_how_is_the_universe_so_big.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
for a nice explanation.&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/a-very-small-slice-of-pi/#back"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>42</category><category>pi day</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/a-very-small-slice-of-pi/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 08:22:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>F-91 Revisited</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/f-91-revisited/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-05FSvjIalzs/T11JuY0apyI/AAAAAAAAAVI/hHndDNPO5CE/s1600/dst_sam.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-05FSvjIalzs/T11JuY0apyI/AAAAAAAAAVI/hHndDNPO5CE/s400/dst_sam.jpeg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Farmer Uncle Sam...with a rifle. (Image Credit: Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was a sunny exception to the grey overcast rule of weather in
Ithaca. I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be overjoyed by this anomaly, spending the day
outside flying a kite or playing frisbee with a border collie in a
bandanna. Unfortunately, today was also the beginning of Daylight
Savings Time (DST) - my least favorite day of the year. For my
colleagues unfamiliar with this temporal travesty (I'm looking at you
Arizona), let me briefly explain DST. Once a year, the time lords steal
a single hour from us and place it in an escrow account for future
disbursement, presumably in some elaborate scheme to gain the favor of
hat-throwing farmer-clock hybrids (see image left). The details are a
bit murky, but the net result is that today I had one less hour to do my
very favorite thing in the whole wide world - sleep. It also means that
I have to set my watch, so I figured I'd check in and see how well my
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2012/02/time-keeps-on-slippin.html"&gt;previous
model&lt;/a&gt;
for time-loss in my watch has held up. About a month ago, I looked at
how my watch slowly deviated from the &lt;a href="http://nist.time.gov/timezone.cgi?Eastern/d/-5/java"&gt;official
time&lt;/a&gt; (the original
post can be found
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2012/02/time-keeps-on-slippin.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
and a helpful clarification by Tom can be found
&lt;a href="http://blogs.scienceforums.net/swansont/archives/11014"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Based
on a little over 50 days worth of data, I found that my watch lost about
0.35 seconds per day against the official time. About 50 days have
passed since my last measurement and today when I set the watch, so I
thought it would be interesting to see how well my model fit the new
data. The old data are presented in Figure 1 in blue, the old best fit
line is in red, and the new data point (taken this morning) is in green.
As always, click through the plot for a larger version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HqpuhvxXl8M/T1115Tz6lnI/AAAAAAAAAVQ/I1AUjQLXres/s1600/dst_update_long.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HqpuhvxXl8M/T1115Tz6lnI/AAAAAAAAAVQ/I1AUjQLXres/s400/dst_update_long.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new data point appears to be in fair agreement with the old best-fit
model, but it's a little hard to see here. Zooming in a bit, though, we
see that the model lies outside the error bar of the new data point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1euutOYSIrs/T1125Hi_XNI/AAAAAAAAAVY/tnWZ6N3mJJs/s1600/dst_update_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1euutOYSIrs/T1125Hi_XNI/AAAAAAAAAVY/tnWZ6N3mJJs/s400/dst_update_short.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is this a big deal? Not really. But if it will help you sleep at
night, we can redo the fitting with the new data point included to see
how much things change. The the plots with the updated model to include
all data points are provided below with the old data in blue and the new
point in green.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-oIeLFmzJgKI/T115TGf3laI/AAAAAAAAAVg/RHPJuP9UrKk/s1600/dst_newfit_long.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-oIeLFmzJgKI/T115TGf3laI/AAAAAAAAAVg/RHPJuP9UrKk/s400/dst_newfit_long.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new model looks a whole lot like the old one, except the best fit
line now appears to go through the new data point. Zooming in a little,
we see that it does indeed fall within the error bars of our new point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-EUf50O2-jjQ/T11514CpS_I/AAAAAAAAAVo/Ryt2v1LOeVk/s1600/dst_newfit_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-EUf50O2-jjQ/T11514CpS_I/AAAAAAAAAVo/Ryt2v1LOeVk/s400/dst_newfit_short.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so the new model fits with our new point, but how much did the
model have to change? Well, the fit to just the old data gave an offset
of 0.36 seconds and a loss rate of 0.35 seconds per day. The new model
has an offset of 0.40 seconds and a loss rate of 0.348 seconds per day.
Overall, not a significant change.
It looks as though I may continue to not worry about the accuracy of my
watch. I have set it to match the official time and have no intention of
fiddling with it until I have to set it again at the end of Daylight
Savings Time - my favorite day of the year.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>casio</category><category>daylight savings time</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/f-91-revisited/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 12 Mar 2012 00:57:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Time Keeps On Slippin'</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/time-keeps-on-slippin-/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-rtzREUF0wYM/TyX0orGHkpI/AAAAAAAAASk/hsRZAwtg7H4/s1600/casi_f91w.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-rtzREUF0wYM/TyX0orGHkpI/AAAAAAAAASk/hsRZAwtg7H4/s320/casi_f91w.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  This is picture of a watch. (Source: Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, the Virtuosi Action Team (VAT) assembled for
lunch and the discussion quickly and unexpectedly turned to watches. As
Nic and Alemi argued over the finer parts of fancy-dancy watch
ownership, I looked down at my watch: the lowly &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casio_F91W"&gt;Casio
F-91W&lt;/a&gt;. Though it certainly
isn't fancy, it is inexpensive, durable, and could potentially win me an
all-expense paid trip to the
&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/apr/25/guantanamo-files-casio-wristwatch-alqaida"&gt;Caribbean&lt;/a&gt;.
But how &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; of a watch is it? To find out, I decided to time it
against the official U.S. time for a couple of months. Incidentally,
about half-way in I found out that Chad over at &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/principles/"&gt;Uncertain
Principles&lt;/a&gt; had done essentially
the same thing
&lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/principles/2011/05/the_testing_of_time_measuring.php"&gt;already&lt;/a&gt;.
No matter, science is still fun even if you aren't the first person to
do it. So here's my "new-to-me" analysis. Alright, so how do we go about
quantifying how "good" a watch is? Well, there seem to be two main
things we can test. The first of these is accuracy. That is, how close
does this watch come to the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; time (according to some time
system)? If the official time is 3:00 pm and my watch claims it is 5:00
am, then it is not very accurate. The second measure of "good-ness" is
precision or, in watch parlance, stability. This is essentially a
measure of the consistency of the watch. If I have a watch that is
consistently off by 5 minutes from the official time, then it is not
accurate but it is still stable. In essence, a very consistent watch
would be just as good as an accurate one, because we can always just
subtract off the known offset. To test any of the above measures of how
"good" my cheap watch is, we will need to know the actual time. We will
adopt the official U.S. time as provided on the &lt;a href="http://nist.time.gov/timezone.cgi?Eastern/d/-5/java"&gt;NIST
website&lt;/a&gt;. This time
is determined and maintained by a collection of really impressive atomic
clocks. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NIST-F1"&gt;One of these&lt;/a&gt; is in
Colorado and the other is secretly guarded by an ever-vigilant Time Lord
(see Figure 1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EXMf5o9a4GI/TzCRcaMjjVI/AAAAAAAAASs/FlqyjHbJS9Q/s1600/flavor_flav.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EXMf5o9a4GI/TzCRcaMjjVI/AAAAAAAAASs/FlqyjHbJS9Q/s320/flavor_flav.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 1: Flavor Flav, Keeper of the Time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 9:00:00 am EST on November 30th, I synchronized my watch with the
time displayed on the NIST website. For the next 54 days, I kept track
of the difference between my watch an the NIST time. On the 55th day, I
forgot to check the time and the experiment promptly ended. The results
are plotted below in Figure 2 (and, as with all plots, click through for
a larger version).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hscjUIehrHQ/TzCYqNhcsYI/AAAAAAAAATE/eAz3O5KlAcY/s1600/time_fit_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hscjUIehrHQ/TzCYqNhcsYI/AAAAAAAAATE/eAz3O5KlAcY/s400/time_fit_short.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 2: Best-fit to time difference&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from Figure 2, the amount of time the watch lost over the
timing period appears to be fairly linear. There does appear to be a
jagged-ness to the data, though. This is mainly caused by the fact that
both the watch and the NIST website only report times to the nearest
second. As a result, the finest time resolution I was willing to report
was about half a second. Adopting an uncertainty of half a second, I did
a least-squares fit of a straight line to the data and found that the
watch loses about 0.35 seconds per day. As far as accuracy goes, that's
not bad! No matter what, I'll have to set my watch at least twice a year
to appease the Daylight Savings Gods. The longest stretch between
resetting is about 8 months. If I synchronize my watch with the NIST
time to "spring forward" in March, it will only lose about $$ t_{loss}
= 8\~\mbox{months} \times 30\frac{\mbox{days}}{\mbox{month}}
\times 0.35 \frac{\mbox{sec}}{\mbox{day}} = 84\~\mbox{sec} $$
before I have to re-synchronize to "fall back" in November. Assuming the
loss rate is constant, I'll never be more than about a minute and a half
off the "actual" time. That's good enough for me. Furthermore, if the
watch is &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt; losing 0.35 seconds per day and I know how long
ago I last synchronized, I can always correct for the offset. In this
case, I can always know the official time to within a second (assuming I
can add). But &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the watch consistent? That's a good question. The
simplest means of finding the stability of the watch would be to look at
the timing residuals between the data and the model. That is, we will
consider how "off" each point is from our constant rate-loss model. A
plot of the results is shown below in Figure 3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-13ULtvOlXuU/TzCpp6LGvfI/AAAAAAAAATM/8rybD1lxZOo/s1600/residuals.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-13ULtvOlXuU/TzCpp6LGvfI/AAAAAAAAATM/8rybD1lxZOo/s400/residuals.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 3: Timing residuals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Figure 3, we see that the data fit the model pretty well. There's a
little bit of a wiggle going on there and we see some strong short-term
correlations (the latter is an artifact of the fact that I could only
get times to the nearest second). To get some sense of the timing
stability from the residuals, we can calculate the standard deviation,
which will give us a figure for how "off" the data typically are from
the model. The standard deviation of the residuals is $$ \sigma_{res}
= 0.19\~\mbox{sec}. $$ A good guess at the fractional stability of the
watch would then just be the standard deviation divided by the sampling
interval, $$ \frac{\sigma_{res}}{T} = 0.19\~\mbox{sec} \times
\frac{1}{1\~\mbox{day}} \times
\frac{1\~\mbox{day}}{24\times3600\~\mbox{sec}} \approx
2\times10^{-6}.$$ In words, this means that each "tick" of the watch
is consistent with the average "tick" value to about 2 parts in a
million. That's nice...but isn't there something &lt;em&gt;fancier&lt;/em&gt; we could be
doing? Well, I have been wanting to learn about &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_variance"&gt;Allan
variance&lt;/a&gt; for some time
now, so let's try that. The Allan variance (refs: &lt;a href="http://www.ino.it/~azavatta/References/Allan.pdf"&gt;original
paper&lt;/a&gt; and a
&lt;a href="http://tf.boulder.nist.gov/general/pdf/118.pdf"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;) can be used to
find the fractional frequency stability of an oscillator over a wide
range of time scales. Roughly speaking, the Allan variance tells us how
averaging our residuals over different chunks of time affects the
stability of our data. The square root of the Allan variance,
essentially the "Allan standard deviation," is plotted against various
averaging times for our data below in Figure 4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-_zhCroHDoNE/TzC7XYkDZ1I/AAAAAAAAATU/mCaspxYhlxA/s1600/allan_variance.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-_zhCroHDoNE/TzC7XYkDZ1I/AAAAAAAAATU/mCaspxYhlxA/s400/allan_variance.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 4: Allan variance of our residuals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Figure 4, we see that as we increase the averaging time from one
day to ten days, the Allan deviation decreases. That is, the averaging
reduces the amount of variation in the frequency of the data, making it
more stable. However, at around 10 days of averaging time it seems as
though we hit a floor in how low we can go. Since the error bars get
really big here, this may not be a real effect. If it is real, though,
this would be indicative of some low-frequency noise in our oscillator.
For those who prefer colors, this would be
"&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colors_of_noise"&gt;red&lt;/a&gt;" noise. Since the
Allan deviation gives the fractional frequency stability of the
oscillator, we have that $$\sigma_A = \frac{\delta f}{f} =
\frac{\delta(1/t)}{1/t} = \frac{\delta t}{t}. $$ Looking at the
plot, we see that with an averaging time of one day, the fractional time
stability of the watch is $$\frac{\delta t}{t} \approx
2\times10^{-6}, $$ which corresponds nicely to our previously
calculated value. If we average over chunks that are ten days long
instead, we get a fractional stability of $$\frac{\delta t}{t}
\approx 10^{-7}, $$ which would correspond to a deviation from our
model of about 0.008 seconds. Not bad. The initial question that started
this whole ordeal was "How good is my watch?" and I think we can safely
answer that with "as good as I'll ever need it to be." Hooray for cheap
and effective electronics!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>allan variance</category><category>casio</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/time-keeps-on-slippin-/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 12 Feb 2012 22:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>How Long Will a Bootprint Last on the Moon?</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-gEyp9bylwcQ/Tv5v7PlugjI/AAAAAAAAARU/OnVdFTPRGkI/s1600/bootprint_buzz.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-gEyp9bylwcQ/Tv5v7PlugjI/AAAAAAAAARU/OnVdFTPRGkI/s320/bootprint_buzz.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Buzz Aldrin's bootprint (source: Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I stumbled across a bunch of
&lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/apollo/revisited/index.html"&gt;pictures&lt;/a&gt;
of Apollo landing sites taken by one of the cameras onboard the Lunar
Reconnaissance Orbiter. The images have a resolution high enough that
you can resolve features on the surface down to about a meter. Looking
at the Apollo 17 &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/images/content/584392main_M168000580LR_ap17_area.jpg"&gt;landing
site&lt;/a&gt;,
you can see the trails of both astronauts and a moon buggy. It's pretty
cool. It also got me thinking about how long the landing sites would be
preserved. More specifically, I want to know how long Buzz Aldrin's
right bootprint (shown, incidentally, to the left) will last on the
Moon. Since the Moon has no atmosphere, the wind and rain that would
weather away a similar bootprint here on Earth are not present and it
seems as though the print would last a really long time. But how long?
Let's try to quantify it &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#footnote-yariv"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Pick Your Poison
Before we get going, we need to figure out what physical process would
be most important in erasing a bootprint from the Moon. Although the
Moon lacks the conventional "weathering" we experience on Earth (due to
wind, rain, etc), it does experience something called "&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_weathering"&gt;space
weathering&lt;/a&gt;." Space
weathering is the changing of the lunar surface due to cosmic rays,
micrometeorite collisions, regular meteorite collisions, and the solar
wind &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#footnote-wind"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Of these phenomena, the most apparent
and well-studied would be the meteorites which have covered the Moon in
craters. We adopt the meteorite impact as our primary means of wiping
out a bootprint and restate our question as follows: "How long would it
take for a meteorite to hit the Moon such that the resulting crater
wipes out Aldrin's right bootprint?" Background As it is currently
stated, we can answer our question if we knew the rate of formation and
size distribution of the craters on the Moon. We could count up all the
craters on the Moon (or a particular region of interest) and tabulate
their sizes. This would give us the size distribution. It would also
give us a headache and potentially drive us to lunacy
&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#footnote-forced"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Luckily, someone has beat us to it. &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1966MNRAS.134..245C"&gt;Cross
(1966)&lt;/a&gt; used images
from the Ranger 7 and 8 missions to count craters and determine the size
distribution of craters in three regions of the Moon. The data for the
crater distribution in the Sea of Tranquility (where Apollo 11 landed)
are given in the figure below. Cross found that in the Sea of
Tranquility, the number of craters with diameters greater than X meters
(per million square kilometers) is given by: $$ N(d&amp;gt;X) =
10^{10}\left(\frac{X}{1\~\mbox{m}}\right)^{-2}, $$ which holds for
craters with diameters between 1 meter and 10 kilometers (see figure
below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-kHxcn_PTd5o/TwDg3XGAcqI/AAAAAAAAARg/jl-kb22JD-Y/s1600/fig2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-kHxcn_PTd5o/TwDg3XGAcqI/AAAAAAAAARg/jl-kb22JD-Y/s400/fig2.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 2 from Cross (1966)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also estimate the rate at which craters are formed from this
data. If we assume that the craters formed at a constant rate over the
age of the Moon (about 4 billion years), then we get about 2.5 craters
with diameters above 1 meter formed in a million square kilometer area
every year. This is a "crater flux" for the Moon. Written another way,
the crater flux in the Sea of Tranquility is $$F \approx
1\~{\mbox{km}}^{-2} \frac{1}{4\times10^5\~\mbox{yr}}, $$ so we get
that roughly one crater with diameter greater than 1 meter is formed on
a square kilometer of the Moon once every 400,000 years or so. We now
have enough information to do some simulations. Simulation I wrote up a
code that simulates craters being formed on a 1 square kilometer patch
of the Moon. A crater is randomly placed in the 1 square kilometer
region with a diameter pulled from the above distribution. The bootprint
is placed at the center of the grid and craters are formed until we get
a "hit." At that point, the time is recorded and the run stops. As a
sanity check, I thought it would be fun to just let the simulation run
without caring if the boot was hit or not. By simulating the craters in
this way for 4 billion years, I should get something that looks like the
Moon at the present day. Here's a 200 m square from my simulation:
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DoFPG23CGwg/TwDqo-7GoQI/AAAAAAAAARs/QJW3RxeXFWI/s1600/mymoon_wticks.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DoFPG23CGwg/TwDqo-7GoQI/AAAAAAAAARs/QJW3RxeXFWI/s400/mymoon_wticks.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
and here's a picture of the same-sized region on the surface of the
Moon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-qWW5dU-aEN8/TwDrDLPy93I/AAAAAAAAAR4/XGOywC79NFU/s1600/200metersquare.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-qWW5dU-aEN8/TwDrDLPy93I/AAAAAAAAAR4/XGOywC79NFU/s320/200metersquare.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Cropped from &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/images/content/584398main_M168353795RE_25cm_AP12_area.jpg"&gt;this image&lt;/a&gt; (Source: LRO)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just eyeballing it, things look pretty good. Now it's time for the
actual simulation. I ran the simulation 10,000 times and tabulated the
amount of time needed before the bootprint was hit. The figure below
gives the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumulative_distribution_function"&gt;CDF&lt;/a&gt; for
the hit times in the simulation. That is, for each time T, we find the
fraction of simulations in which the bootprint got hit in a time less
than or equal to T. The dashed lines in the plot indicate the amount of
time needed to pass for half of the simulations to have recorded a hit.
This time turns out to be about 24 billion years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-L2WLnCepUiw/TwDs7X_njkI/AAAAAAAAASE/jS_-I0Eem4k/s1600/hit_cdf.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-L2WLnCepUiw/TwDs7X_njkI/AAAAAAAAASE/jS_-I0Eem4k/s400/hit_cdf.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  (Click for larger, actually readable version)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions and Caveats Based on the simulations, the bootprint on the
Moon would have about even odds of lasting at least 20 billion years
&lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; the primary means of destruction is through the formation of a
crater from a meteorite. However, there are a few caveats that should be
addressed. These deal with either the details of the simulation or the
assumptions we have made. In the simulation, we just took at 1 km square
patch of the moon and scaled back the "crater flux" accordingly.
However, this does not fully account for all possible craters that can
form. For example, our simulation would miss an event that hit 50 km
away from the target, but had a diameter of 100 km. Obviously this would
hit the target, but we are only seeding craters in the 1 square km
region. This would mean that the actual lifetime of the bootprint would
be less than our 24 billion year figure. Re-running with a 10km by 10km
square region, we find a lifetime of 18 billion years. Thus, an increase
in area by a factor of 100 only reduces the age by 25%. Considering
areas much larger than this makes the simulation prohibitively slow, but
the order unity effect does not seem too significant. Additionally, we
have made a number of assumptions. The big one is that we have assumed
that the craters currently seen on the Moon were formed uniformly in
time. In fact, a large fraction of the craters may have been formed when
the Moon was still very young (see &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Late_Heavy_Bombardment"&gt;Late Heavy
Bombardment&lt;/a&gt;). If
this were the case, we would have greatly overestimated the rate of
crater formation and thus underestimated the time needed to hit the
bootprint. In spite of these caveats, let's take our value of 20 billion
years to be accurate. What else can we say? Well, if we are right then
we are wrong because the Moon may not last that long (and it's hard to
have bootprints on the Moon without a Moon). Current
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun#Life_cycle"&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; have that the
Sun will expand into a red giant and (potentially) destroy the Earth
(and the Moon) in about 5 billion years. So a record of the Apollo
astronauts' boot sizes could potentially last as long as the Moon
&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#footnote-nixon"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Not bad. Footnotes and Such
[1] Now with linked footnotes so Yariv doesn't have to scroll!
&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#back-yariv"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;
[2] There was a fairly recent press release about Coronal Mass Ejections
from the Sun "sandblasting" the lunar surface. For more info, check
&lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/topics/solarsystem/features/dream-cme.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
and note the acronymic acrobatics needed to make them the "DREAM team."
But it's totally worth it. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#back-wind"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;
[3] A horribly forced pun. But it's totally worth it.
&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#back-forced"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;
[4] Also, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_plaque"&gt;Nixon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/#back-nixon"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>footprint</category><category>moon</category><category>scott bakula</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 01 Jan 2012 20:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Betelgeuse, Betelgeuse, Betelgeuse!</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/betelgeuse-betelgeuse-betelgeuse-/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-6s6rSrItOdk/TrS6st3tdVI/AAAAAAAAAPk/GpGfjY5KZ3Y/s1600/betelgeuse.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-6s6rSrItOdk/TrS6st3tdVI/AAAAAAAAAPk/GpGfjY5KZ3Y/s320/betelgeuse.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  A very cold person points out Betelgeuse&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Betelgeuse is a massive star at the very end of its life and could
explode any second now!&lt;/em&gt; Every time I hear that I get really &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
excited. Like a kid in a candy store that's about to see a star blow up
like nobody's business. This giddiness will last for a solid minute
before I realize that "any second now" is taken on astronomical
timescales and roughly translates to "sometime in the next million years
maybe possibly." Then I feel sad. But you know what always cheers me up?
Calculating things! Hooray! So let's take a look at the ways Betelgeuse
could end its life (even if it's not going to happen tomorrow) and how
these would affect Earth. First, a little background. Betelgeuse is the
bright orangey-red star that sits at the head/armpit of Orion. It is one
of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_brightest_stars"&gt;brightest&lt;/a&gt;
stars in the night sky. Its distance has been measured by the
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hipparcos"&gt;Hipparcos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;satellite to be
about 200 parsecs [1] from Earth (about 600 light years). Betelgeuse is
at least 10 times as massive as our Sun and has a diameter that would
easily accomodate the orbit of Mars. In fact, the star is big enough and
close enough that it can actually be spatially resolved by the Hubble
Space Telescope! Being so big and bright, Betelgeuse is destined to die
young, going out with a bang as a
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supernova#Core_collapse"&gt;core-collapse&lt;/a&gt;
supernova. This massive explosion ejects a good deal of "star stuff"
into interstellar space [2] and leaves behind either a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neutron_star"&gt;neutron
star&lt;/a&gt; or a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_hole"&gt;black
hole&lt;/a&gt;. Alright, now that we're
all caught up, let's turn our focus on this "massive explosion" bit.
What kind of energy scale are we talking about if Betelgeuse blows up?
Well, a pretty good upper bound would be if all of the star's mass (10
solar masses worth!) were converted directly to energy, so $$ E_{max} =
mc^2 =
10M_{\odot}\times\left(\frac{2\times10^{30}\~\mbox{kg}}{1\~M_{\odot}}\right)\times
\left(3\times10^8\~\mbox{m/s}\right)^2 $$ which is about $$
E_{max} \sim 10^{48}\~\mbox{J} $$ and that's nothing to shake a
stick at. But remember, this is if the &lt;em&gt;entire star&lt;/em&gt; were converted
directly to energy, and that would be hard to do. Typical fusion
efficiencies are about \~1% [3], so let's say a reasonable estimate for
the total nuclear energy available is $$ E_{nuc} \sim \eta_{f}
\times E_{max} \sim 10^{-2} \times 10^{48}\~\mbox{J} \sim
10^{46}\~\mbox{J}. $$ This is the total energy released by a typical
supernova. As it turns out though, 99% of this energy is carried away in
the form of neutrinos and only about 1% is carried away in photons.
Since we are mainly concerned with how this explosion will affect Earth,
and the neutrinos will just pass on by, we will only consider the 1% of
energy released in photons that would reasonably interact with Earth.
That gives us $$ E_{ph} \sim 0.01 \times E_{nuc} \sim
10^{44}\~\mbox{J}. $$ Neato, so that's the total amount of energy
released in a supernova in the form of photons. How much of this energy
would be deposited at the Earth if Betelgeuse exploded? Well, if the
energy is deposited isotropically (that is, the same in all directions),
then the fluence (or time integrated energy flux) is given by $$ F_{ph}
= \frac{E_{ph}}{4\pi d^2}. $$ All this is saying is that the total
energy release by the supernova spreads out uniformly over a sphere of
radius d, so the fluence will give us the amount of energy deposited in
each square meter of that sphere (the units of fluence here are J/m^2).
The total energy deposited on Earth is then $$ E_{\oplus} = F_{ph}
\times \pi R^2_{\oplus}. $$ Hot dog! Let's plug in some numbers,
already. The total energy deposited on the Earth by a symmetrically
exploding Betelgeuse at a distance of d = 200 pc (where 1 pc = 3 &lt;em&gt;
10^16 m) is $$E_{\oplus}=\frac{E_{ph}}{4\pi d^2}\times\pi
R^2_{\oplus}\sim
10^{19}\~\mbox{J}\left(\frac{E_{ph}}{10^{44}\~\mbox{J}}\right)\left(\frac{d}{200\~\mbox{pc}}\right)^{-2}.$$
Well, 10^19 J certainly &lt;/em&gt;seems* like a lot of energy. In fact, it is
roughly the amount of energy contained in the entire nuclear arsenal of
the United States [4]. But it is spread over the entire atmosphere. Is
there a way to gauge how this would affect life on Earth? We could see
how much it would heat up the atmosphere using specific heats: $$ E =
m_{atm}c_{air}\Delta T $$ where c is the specific heat of air
(\~10^3 J per kg per K). Oops, looks like we need to know the mass of
the atmosphere. But we can figure this out, the answer is pushing right
down on our heads! We know the pressure at the surface of the Earth (1
atm = 101 kPa) and that pressure is just the result of the weight of the
atmosphere pushing down on us. Since pressure is just force / area, we
have $$ P = F/A = m_{atm}g / A_{\oplus} $$ So $$ m_{atm} =
\frac{P\times4\pi
R^2_{\oplus}}{g}=\frac{10^5\~\mbox{Pa}\times4\pi
(6\times10^6\~\mbox{m})^2}{9.8\~\mbox{m/s}^2}\approx4\times10^{18}\~\mbox{kg}.$$
Neato, gang. So we could see a temperature rise of about $$ \Delta T =
\frac{E_{ph}}{m_{atm}c_{air}}=\frac{10^{19}\~\mbox{J}}{4\times10^{18}\~\mbox{kg}\times10^3\~\mbox{J/
kg K}}\approx0.003\~\mbox{K}, $$ or three one-thousandths of a degree.
Remember, too, that this will be an upper bound since we are assuming
that all this energy is deposited into the atmosphere before it has a
chance to cool. In fact, if the energy is deposited over the course of
hours or days, this value will be much less. So it looks like we've
wrapped this thing up: Betelgeuse exploding will most certainly not put
the Earth in any danger. Or did we? We have considered the case of a
symmetric supernova, but there's more than one way to blow up a star.
Massive stars can also end their lives in a fantastic explosion called a
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-ray_burst"&gt;gamma-ray burst&lt;/a&gt; (GRBs to
the hep cats that study them, some fun facts relegated to [5]). GRBs are
still an intense area of current study, but the current picture (for one
type of GRB, at least) is that they are the result of a star blowing up
with the energy of the explosion focussed into two narrow beams (see
picture below). Since the flux isn't distributed over the whole sphere,
GRBs can be seen at much greater distances than a typical supernova.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-siXXiFnQWHY/TrITJA8z_sI/AAAAAAAAAPU/qStD4_9qLBI/s1600/grb.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-siXXiFnQWHY/TrITJA8z_sI/AAAAAAAAAPU/qStD4_9qLBI/s320/grb.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Example of a gamma-ray burst, with the explosion in two beams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how will this change our answer? Well, it's going to change the
fluence we calculated above. Instead of spreading the energy out over
the whole sphere, it's only going to go to some fraction of the 4pi
steradians. So we get $$ F_{ph} = \frac{E_{ph}}{4\pi f_{\Omega}
d^2}, $$ where f_{omega} is called the "beaming fraction" and tells us
what fraction of the sphere the energy goes through. Typical GRB beams
range from 1 to 10 degrees in radius. Converting this to radians, we can
find the beaming fraction as $$ f_{\Omega} = \frac{2 \times \pi
\theta^2}{4\pi} \approx
10^{-4}\left(\frac{\theta}{1^\circ}\right)^2,$$ so the beaming
fraction is 10^-4 and 10^-2 for a beam angle of 1 degree and 10
degrees, respectively. Alright, so now we can redo the calculations we
did for the supernova case, but keeping this beaming fraction around.
The total amount of energy that would hit Earth is then about
$$E_{\oplus}=\frac{E_{ph}}{4\pi f_{\Omega} d^2}\times\pi
R^2_{\oplus}\sim
10^{23}\~\mbox{J}\left(\frac{E_{ph}}{10^{44}\~\mbox{J}}\right)\left(\frac{d}{200\~\mbox{pc}}\right)^{-2}\left(\frac{\theta}{1^\circ}\right)^{-2}.$$
Holy sixth-of-a-moley! Continuing as we did above, we find that this
could potentially heat up the atmosphere by $$ \Delta T =
\frac{E_{ph}}{m_{atm}c_{air}}=\frac{10^{23}\~\mbox{J}}{4\times10^{18}\~\mbox{kg}\times10^3\~\mbox{J/
kg
K}}\approx3\~\mbox{K}\left(\frac{\theta}{1^\circ}\right)^{-2},
$$ which is certainly non-negligible. Now, this won't destroy the planet
[6], but it could make things really uncomfortable. This will be
especially true when you realize that a fair amount of the energy
carried away from a gamma-ray burst is in the form of (wait for it...)
gamma-rays, which will wreck havoc on your DNA. Remember, though, that
this is an absolute worst-case scenario since we have assumed the
smallest beaming angle. But this may still make us a little nervous, so
is there anyway to figure out if Betelgeuse could, in fact, beam a
gamma-ray burst towards Earth? Yes, yes there is. Jets and beams like
those in GRBs typically point along the rotation axis of the star [7].
If we could determine the rotational axis of Betelgeuse, then we could
say whether or not there's a chance it's pointed towards us. It just so
happens that Betelgeuse is the only star (aside from our Sun) that is
spatially resolved. If you could measure spectra along the star, you
could look for Doppler shifting of absorption lines and say something
about the velocity at the surface of the star. Luckily, this has already
been done for us (see, for example &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1998AJ....116.2501U"&gt;Uitenbroek et al.
1998&lt;/a&gt;). These
measurements are hard to do since the star is only a few pixels wide,
but it appears as though the rotation axis is inclined to the
line-of-sight by about 20 degrees (see figure below). That means this
would require a beam with at least a 20 degree radius to hit the Earth.
This appears to be outside the typical ranges observed. So even if
Betelgeuse were to explode in a gamma-ray burst, the beam would miss
Earth and hit some dumb other planet nobody cares about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-xYILwh0eLEM/TrSTBxflbxI/AAAAAAAAAPc/Amma1aQtmPU/s1600/rotation.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-xYILwh0eLEM/TrSTBxflbxI/AAAAAAAAAPc/Amma1aQtmPU/s400/rotation.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure reproduced from Uitenbroek et al. (1998)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so the moral of the story is that Betelgeuse is completely
harmless to people on Earth. When it does explode, it will be a
brilliant supernova that would likely be visible at least a little bit
during the day. It will be the coolest thing that anyone alive (if there
are people...) will ever see. Sadly, this explosion could take place at
just about any time during the next million years. Assuming a uniform
distribution over this time period and a human lifetime of order 100
years, there is something like a 1 in 10,000 chance you'll see this in
your life. Feel free to hope for a spectacular astronomical sight, but
don't lose sleep worrying about being hurt by Betelgeuse!
&lt;strong&gt;Semi-excessive Footnotes:&lt;/strong&gt; [1] This has nothing to do with the Kessel
Run. For a description of the actual distance unit see
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsec"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;. For a circuitous
retconning to correct for one throwaway line in &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;, see
&lt;a href="http://starwars.wikia.com/wiki/Kessel_Run"&gt;Wookieepedia&lt;/a&gt;. [2] This is
how anything heavier than helium gets distributed throughout the
universe. The hydrogen and helium formed after the Big Bang gets fused
into heavier elements in stars and then dispersed out through
supernovae. In fact, most things heavier than Iron actually &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt;
supernovae to even exist. If you have any gold on you right now (I'm
looking at you Mr. T), that only exists &lt;em&gt;because a star exploded!&lt;/em&gt; [3]
Let's consider the case of turning 4 protons into a Helium nucleus.
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helium-4"&gt;Helium-4&lt;/a&gt; has a binding energy
of about 28 MeV, which means that the total energy of a bound He-4
nucleus is 28 MeV less than its free protons and neutrons (in other
words, we need to put in 28 MeV to break it up). So the process of
turning 4 protons into a Helium nucleus gives off 28 MeV worth of
energy. But we had a total of 4 times 1000 MeV worth of matter we could
have turned into energy. Thus, the process was 28 MeV/4000 MeV \~ 0.7%
efficient at turning matter into energy. [4] Sometime last year, the
United States
&lt;a href="http://www.defense.gov/npr/docs/10-05-03_Fact_Sheet_US_Nuclear_Transparency__FINAL_w_Date.pdf"&gt;disclosed&lt;/a&gt;
that its nuclear arsenal as of Sept 2009 was something like 5000
warheads. Assume these to be Megaton warheads. A Megaton is about 4 &lt;em&gt;
10^15 J, so the total energy in the US arsenal is about 5000 * 4 &lt;/em&gt;
10^15 J = 2 * 10^19 J. [5] A fun fact about GRBs: They were
discovered by a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vela_(satellite)"&gt;military
satellite&lt;/a&gt; looking for
illegal nuclear tests, which would emit some gamma-rays. Instead of
seeing a signal on Earth, they saw bursts coming from space. I really
really hope that someone's first thought was that the Russians were
testing nukes on the Moon or something. &lt;em&gt;We must not allow a moon-nuke
gap!&lt;/em&gt; [6] We here at the Virtuosi are contractually obligated to only
destroy the Earth in our posts on Earth day. I apologize for any
inconvenience this may cause. [7] I am not exactly sure why this is the
case. It is certainly observed to be the case and I thought there was a
straightforward explanation for why this was the case, but I don't
really have a good explanation. Although, maybe there just &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polar_jet"&gt;isn't a good
one yet.&lt;/a&gt; [8] For comparison,
there is about a 1 in 3000
&lt;a href="http://www.lightningsafety.com/nlsi_pls/probability.html"&gt;chance&lt;/a&gt;
you'll be struck by lightning in your lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>betelgeuse</category><category>scott bakula</category><category>things that probs wont kill you</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/betelgeuse-betelgeuse-betelgeuse-/</guid><pubDate>Sat, 05 Nov 2011 01:25:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Futurama Physics</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/futurama-physics/</link><dc:creator>Corky</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6STZpSqRmJk/Tk1oSvdCgQI/AAAAAAAAAOc/M9wr0wJUlE8/s1600/global_warming.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6STZpSqRmJk/Tk1oSvdCgQI/AAAAAAAAAOc/M9wr0wJUlE8/s320/global_warming.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  The rotting corpses of sunbeams cause global warming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good news, everyone! While rummaging through all my old stuff at home, I
found my long-lost copy of &lt;em&gt;Toto IV&lt;/em&gt;. Huzzah for me! This is entirely
unrelated to what I wanted to talk about, but I have it on good
authority that Toto's
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=azVqekQBK8g"&gt;Africa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; syncs up &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
well with this post [1]. I'll tell you when to press play. Anyway, what
I really wanted to talk about was a fairly well-posed problem in
&lt;em&gt;Futurama.&lt;/em&gt; In the episode "Crimes of the Hot," all of the Earth's
robots vent their various "exhausts" into the sky at the same time,
using the thrust to push the Earth into an orbit slightly further away
from the sun. As a result of this new orbit, the year is made longer by
"exactly one week." Anything that quantitative is pretty much asking to
be analyzed. Let's explore this problem a bit more then, why not? [
&lt;em&gt;Those wishing to get the full aural experience of this post should
press&lt;/em&gt;play &lt;em&gt;on their cassette players ... now ]&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt; First, a little
background. In this episode, it is learned that all the robots
(especially Hedonism Bot) emit the greenhouse gases responsible for
Global Warming. The previous solution (detailed
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2taViFH_6_Y"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) is no longer viable,
so it is decided that all robots must be destroyed (especially Hedonism
Bot). The disembodied head of Richard Nixon rounds up all the world's
robots on the Galapagos [2] to have a "party" so that they may be
destroyed by a giant space-based electromagnetic pulse cannon. In a
last-ditch effort to save the robots, Professor Farnsworth has all the
robots blast their exhausts into the sky, using the thrust to push the
Earth into an orbit further away from the sun, thus solving the problem
of global warming once and for all. As a result of changing the Earth's
orbit, the year is "exactly one week longer." First Pass Through Ok, so
what can we say about the new orbit if all we know is that its orbital
period is exactly one week longer? Well, we know from our good buddy
Kepler that the square of the period of a bound orbit is proportional to
the cube of its semi-major axis [3], so $$\tau^2 \propto a^3.$$ We
already know the Earth's period (1 year) and semi-major axis (1
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astronomical_unit"&gt;AU&lt;/a&gt;) before the
robo-boost, so we can get rid of the proportionality by writing things
in terms of the initial values. In other words, $$
\left(\frac{\tau}{1\~\mbox{yr}}\right)^2=\left(\frac{a}{1\~\mbox{AU}}\right)^3.$$
Alright, so we know that our new orbital period is 1 year + 1 week, or
since there are 52 weeks in a year, 53/52 years. So our new semi-major
axis is $$ a = \left(\frac{1 +
1/52\~\mbox{yr}}{1\~\mbox{yr}}\right)^{2/3}\mbox{AU}\approx1.013\~\mbox{AU},$$
or a little over 1% larger than it is currently. Fair enough. So would
this fix Global Warming for ever and ever? Let's see. The solar flux at
some distance d is given by $$ S = \frac{L_{\odot}}{4\pi d^2}, $$
where L is the luminosity of the sun. So the ratio of the flux at the
new semi-major axis [4] to that before the orbit was changed is $$
\frac{S}{S_0}=\left(\frac{a_0}{a}\right)^2=\left(\frac{a}{1\~\mbox{yr}}\right)^{-2}.$$
OK, so we have the flux, but how do we relate this to temperature? Well,
we know that the power radiated by a blackbody of temperature T is given
by $$ P = \sigma A T^4, $$ where sigma is the Stefan-Boltzmann
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan%E2%80%93Boltzmann_law"&gt;constant&lt;/a&gt;, A
is the area of the emitting region and T is the temperature. For a
blackbody in equilibrium, the power coming in is going to be equal to
the power going out. The power coming in is just the solar flux times
the cross-section area of Earth, given by $$ P_{in} = S\times\pi
R^2_{\oplus} $$ and the power going out is just that radiated by the
Earth as a blackbody $$ P_{out} =\sigma \times 4\pi
R^2_{\oplus}\times T^4. $$ Equating the power in to the power out
gives $$ T = \left( \frac{S}{4\sigma}\right)^{1/4}. $$ Now we can
find the ratio of the new average Earth temperature to the temperature
before the orbital move. We have $$ \frac{T}{T_0} =\left(
\frac{S}{S_0}\right)^{1/4}=\left(
\frac{a_0}{a}\right)^{1/2}\approx0.994$$ If we take the initial
average Earth temperature to be something like T = 300 K, then we find a
new temperature of T = 298 K. Huzzah, a whole 2 degrees cooler! That may
not sound like a lot, but remember, that's the mean global temperature.
Apparently, it only takes a few degrees increase in global average
temperatures to make things a bit uncomfortable for people. The IPCC
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_warming"&gt;indicates&lt;/a&gt; that the
average global surface temperature on Earth in the next century is
likely to rise by about 1 to 2 degrees under optimistic scenarios or
about 3 to 6 degrees under pessimistic scenarios. So the robo-boost
option is at least in the right ballpark here. Neat! How Big Is The
Push? So how big of a push did the robots need to give the Earth to
boost it out to this new orbit? Is this possible? Let's find out! First
we need to find out how the Earth's velocity has changed. We can do this
by finding the change in energy. The total energy of a bound orbit is
given by $$ E = -\frac{k}{2a}$$ where &lt;/em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; is the semi-major axis of the
orbit and &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;= &lt;em&gt;GMm&lt;/em&gt;. So the difference in Earth's energy before and
after the robo-boost is $$ E_f - E_0
=-\frac{k}{2a_f}-\left(-\frac{k}{2a_0}\right)=\frac{k}{2a_0}\left(1-\frac{a_0}{a_f}\right).$$
But we also know that Earth's energy in the orbit is given by $$ E =
-\frac{k}{r} + \frac{1}{2}mv^2, $$ so the difference in energy before
and after is $$ E_f - E_0
=\frac{1}{2}m\left(v^2_f-v^2_0\right), $$ where we have found the
energies immediately before and immediately after the boost so Earth is
pretty much at the same distance from the sun, so the potential energy
terms cancel. Combining our expressions for the change in energy and
solving for the final velocity, we find $$ v_f =
\left[\frac{GM_{\odot}}{a_0}\left(1-\frac{a_0}{a_f}\right)+v^2_0\right]^{1/2}.$$
Taking the initial orbital velocity of the Earth to be 30 km/s, we find
that the final velocity of the Earth immediately after the robo-boost is
$$ v_f = 30.2\~\mbox{km/s}$$ So the robots just need to give a
"little" 200 m/s boost to the Earth, right? Well, we are adding velocity
vectors here, so it depends on which direction the robots are pushing.
The magnitude of the final velocity is given by $$v_f =
\sqrt{\left({\bf v_0}+{\bf \Delta v}
\right)^2}=\sqrt{v^2_0+\Delta v^2-2v_0\Delta v
\cos{\beta}},$$ where delta v is the boost in velocity caused by the
robots and beta is the angle between the initial orbital motion of the
Earth and the velocity boost from the robots. If they wanted to make it
slightly easier on themselves, the robots would have boosted the Earth
in the direction it was already moving. That would make the cosine beta
term equal to one and thus minimize the necessary boost. However, in the
show the robots appear to point their exhaust right at the sun (see
figure below). This is essentially at a 90 degree angle to the Earth's
orbital motion, so the cosine beta term goes to zero in our expression
above. Plugging it all in we find that the magnitude of the robo-boost
is $$\Delta v \approx 3.5\~\mbox{km/s}.$$ We see that this is a fair
bit larger than the 0.2 km/s needed for a boost parallel to Earth's
initial velocity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-w6j6RXF1QEo/TlFUG6hU8PI/AAAAAAAAAOg/lViVcBBpFSA/s1600/delta_v.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-w6j6RXF1QEo/TlFUG6hU8PI/AAAAAAAAAOg/lViVcBBpFSA/s400/delta_v.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Robots blasting from the Galapagos (which now appear to be in China...)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so how much effort would it take to give that kind of boost to
the Earth? We can quantify this effort in terms of a force or in terms
of the energy difference. Let's do both. For the force, we have $$ F =
\frac{\Delta p}{\Delta t}=\frac{M_{\oplus}\Delta v}{\Delta t}.$$
Here we are a little stuck unless we can figure out the duration of the
robo-boost. Watching the episode again, the robots are blasting up
exhaust for about a minute but then the show cuts to commercial. So we
don't really know how long they were pushing. Let's just say an hour,
but we'll leave the time in if we want to fiddle with that. Plugging in
numbers, the total force is $$ F =
6\times10^{24}\~\mbox{N}\left(\frac{\Delta
t}{1\~\mbox{hr}}\right)^{-1}.$$ If this force is spread evenly over
the billion robots present [5], then each robot would be applying a
force of $$ F = 6\times10^{15}\~\mbox{N},$$ which is roughly
equivalent to the force it would take to lift up Mount Everest [6]. That
wasn't terribly helpful. Let's look at the work then instead. The total
work done by the robots to move the Earth is $$ W =
\frac{1}{2}M_{\oplus}\left(v^2_f - v^2_0\right) \approx
4\times10^{31}\~\mbox{J}.$$ Well, that's a large number. Could a
billion robots feasibly do that much work? If the robots are each 100
kg, then if the mass of all billion robots were directly converted to
energy, we would get $$ E = mc^2 =
10^9\times10^2\~\mbox{kg}\times\left(3\times10^8\~\mbox{m/s}\right)^2
\approx 10^{28}\~\mbox{J},$$ or less than a thousandth the total
energy needed. So it looks unlikely that the robots would be able to
push the Earth, but that was to be expected. Changes to The Orbit
Let's take a look at how the robo-boost affects the entirety of the
Earth's new orbit. In our first pass through the problem, we ignored the
fact that the shape of the orbit changed and only focused on the new
semi-major axis. To see why we must also consider the changes to the
"shape" of the orbit, take a look at the figure below.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-3tRZVuztuF0/TlGMMLhegtI/AAAAAAAAAOo/3jzGbWvvM90/s1600/orbits.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-3tRZVuztuF0/TlGMMLhegtI/AAAAAAAAAOo/3jzGbWvvM90/s400/orbits.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In the figure, the initial orbit is plotted (black dashed line) as well
as two new orbits that each have the appropriate semi-major axis so that
the period of revolution is one year and one week. The difference
between the two final orbits comes from the robots pushing in different
directions. In the blue orbit, the boost was made in a direction
radially outward from the Sun (that is, perpendicular to the orbital
velocity of the Earth). This is the case shown in the &lt;em&gt;Futurama&lt;/em&gt;episode.
In the red orbit, the boost was made parallel to the orbital velocity of
the Earth. In each case, the boost was applied at the point labeled with
an "X." One thing that jumps out from this figure is that the Earth is
always further away from the sun on the red orbit than it was on the
initial (dashed black) orbit. But on the blue orbit, the Earth is
further away from the Sun than it was initially for only half the orbit.
On the other half, the blue orbit would actually make the Earth's
temperature &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; than it was on the old orbit! The temperature
calculation we made earlier should hold pretty well for the red orbit,
since it is essentially a circle. It would be a little more tricky for
the blue orbit, as one would need to get a time-averaged value of the
flux over the course of the whole orbit. A hundred Quatloos to anyone
that does the calculation. Wrap-Up So what have we found out here? Well,
it seems that there are certain scenarios in which boosting the Earth
out to a new orbit with period of 1 year + 1 week could cool the Earth
by a few degrees. Granted, we have made some simplifications (the Earth
is not a blackbody), but the general idea of the thing should still
hold. I had some fun playing around with this problem and I thought it
was neat that there was a good deal of information to get started with
from the episode. The &lt;em&gt;Futurama&lt;/em&gt; people gave an exact period and at
least a visual representation of the direction the robots apply their
push. So 600 Quatloos for the writers! Not Quite As Useless as Usual
Footnotes [1] At least I think it says so if you play this
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uUjIA3Rt7gk"&gt;song&lt;/a&gt; backwards. [2]
According to the Wikipedia page for the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crimes_of_the_Hot#Production"&gt;episode&lt;/a&gt;,
the location of the Galapagos for the party was chosen because the
writers felt that it would be most convenient to push the Earth near the
equator. [3] The semi-major axis of an ellipse is half of the longest
line cutting through the center of the ellipse. Likewise, the semi-minor
axis is half of the shortest line drawn through the center of the
ellipse. Check &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Ellipse.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; out for
some more fun stuff on ellipses. [4] This is technically incorrect,
since the semi-major axis is measured from the center of the ellipse,
but the sun is located on one of the foci. However, this requires
information on the eccentricity of the orbit, which we are currently
glossing over right now. Our method is then approximate, but becomes
exact in the case where both orbits are circles. The effect, however, is
minor. At worst, it is semi-minor. Zing! [5] My source for this billion
robots number comes from Professor Farnsworth himself. When it looks
like the robots will all be destroyed the Professor says "A billion
robot lives are about to be extinguished. Oh, the Jedis are going to
feel this one!" [6] Well, sort of. The height of Everest is \~10^4 m,
so this gives a volume of \~10^12 m^3. The density of most metals is
around \~10 g/cm^3, which is \~10^4 kg/m^3. This gives a mass of
\~10^16 kg. The weight is then \~10^17 N. Each robot exerts a force of
\~10^16 N. So not quite, but hey it was the first thing I thought of
and it almost worked out so I'm sticking with it!&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>hedonism bot</category><category>orbits</category><category>scott bakula</category><category>toto</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/futurama-physics/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 22 Aug 2011 23:44:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>