<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts by DTC)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/authors/dtc.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 07:58:13 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Special Brain</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/special-brain/</link><dc:creator>DTC</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;A colleague (and friend) of mine &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/thephysicsfactor"&gt;(hereafter referred to as Katie Mack the Physics Hack)&lt;/a&gt; 
produced a fun video last year that tried to show how people sometimes react when she 
tells them that she studies physics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/AAA25XQKCbY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved this video because I've had a number of experiences like this.  My
favorite reaction that I've ever gotten happened in 2007.  I was on a trip
during college with other college kids, and I was placed in a hotel room with
some guys who went to another school. We met for the first time while
unpacking, and naturally we asked each other what we were studying. Turns out
my new roommate was majoring in international business, something I knew
nothing about.  Not wanting to alienate a total stranger I was going to be
sleeping in the same room with, I asked him questions and told him that his
chosen major sounded interesting and important.  I told him that I studied
physics, and when he asked me what that meant I told him how I had worked on
modeling &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cytokinesis"&gt;cell division&lt;/a&gt;.  My new
roommate responded, "You must have a special kind of brain for that."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/special_brain/profx.jpg" alt="A special brain." id="back_up1"&gt; 
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style="text-align: center; color: #999"&gt;A special brain. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/special-brain/#footnote1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;This anecdote has stuck with me for a couple of reasons-- first because
"special kind of brain" is a funny turn of phrase, and second because I think
it's a perfect example of how an attempt at a flattering response can actually
create some uncomfortable social distance between people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;"Special kind of brain" was my roommate's way of expressing how intelligent he
thought I was. (Or, as Zach put it in Katie's video, "You must be soooooo
smart!")  His reaction hinged upon the assumption that what I was interested in
doing was so far beyond the understanding of ordinary folk that I could be set
apart as a member of an elite group.  Instead of being merely complimentary,
his comment held me at arms' length.  His reaction wasn't something I took
offense to, but it made me uncomfortable to hear that he considered me an
outsider of sorts based on my professed interests. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking more generally, the notion that scientific professionals are set apart
from other people as members of a professional group isn't so ridiculous. After
all, these days people's lives are often defined by their careers. (And of
course scientists aren't the only profession with associated negative
stereotypes-- Anyone know any good lawyer jokes?). But to me, thinking of
scientists as some kind of inscrutable cabal of geniuses is an exaggeration.
The truth is, not every scientist is a rocket-powered superbrain.  Quite the
opposite-- scientists make silly mistakes all the time.  Being a scientist is
a technical profession requiring years of training like law, medicine, or
accounting: there are a few practitioners who really are exceptionally smart,
while most of the others aren't. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The even more disappointing truth is that being a scientist is actually usually
pretty mundane.  Don't get me wrong-- the long-term goals of making new
discoveries and developing new insights into the world around us are exactly
why I like my job.  I just mean that the day-to-day labor involved can be as
tedious as any other profession.  I sit in my cubicle and code (debug)
endlessly on my laptop, or I read books and research papers to learn new things
about my field.  Most days don't get much more action-packed than that.  In a
lot of ways it's like any other office job.  Aside from the end goal of
research, working as a scientist is not so special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0021884/"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/special_brain/frankenstein.jpg" alt="My office definitely does not look like this." width="100%" height="auto" id="back_up2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style="text-align: center; color: #999"&gt;I work in a cubicle. Not here.&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/special-brain/#footnote2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;Another reaction that I get when I say I study physics is one of apprehensive
disappointment.  (Zach's pronunciation of 'ohhhhhh...' combining equal parts
boredom and distaste was dead on.) I don't think I need to dwell on this too
long-- it is undeniably unpleasant for me when I hear this. Upon hearing that
I'm a scientist, otherwise polite, kind people will suddenly lose their cool
and be unable to hide the fact that my profession conjures up memories of
boredom and frustration. ("Oh, man.  I HATED physics in high school.")  As
Katie Mack puts it at the end, "polite interest is the way to go."&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
  &lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/special_brain/big-bang-theory5.jpg" width="304" height="228" id="back_up3"&gt;
  &lt;/p&gt;&lt;p style="text-align: center; color: #999"&gt;"Have you ever seen the Big Bang Theory?  &lt;br&gt;Is that what physicists are really like?&lt;br&gt;  I bet it is.  I mean, no offense." &lt;/p&gt;


&lt;p&gt;There's another type of off-putting reaction that comes up sometimes, which is
commenting (jokingly or not) that I'm similar to familiar caricature of
scientists that appear in popular culture. "You're just like Sheldon Cooper!"
is a comment I've heard more times than I care to say. I know that The Big Bang
Theory is a popular show, but frankly I dislike being associated I with
characters that are cartoonishly depicted as condescending and socially
tone-deaf &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/special-brain/#footnote3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Now, I appreciate that some
people, when meeting others for the first time, like to demonstrate familiarity
with others' jobs, but to me it just seems that making a pop culture references
to another person's profession is just a bad way to go. I find this to be a
safe bet when meeting anyone, not just scientists, simply because popular
culture isn't a great way to learn about anyone else's job. Try telling the
next lawyer you meet that they remind you of &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YPR9ORpwBEU"&gt;Saul
Goodman&lt;/a&gt;, and see how they react.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is there for physicists (and other scientists) to do when this
happens? The most facile answer to this question is for us to grow a thicker
skin and suck it up.  Just ignore it when people have disparaging reactions
upon first meeting us, and find a way to get past this in conversation.  The
thing is, I personally am not good enough at hiding my own negative reaction
upon hearing these kinds of obnoxious remarks. Ideally, I'd like to make
conversation easier by finding a way to avoid them altogether. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can't change the way other people react to learning about my profession, but
I can change how I present myself. Personally, I have given up on telling
people that I'm in the physics department.  Instead, when asked "what do you
study in grad school?" I tell then exactly what I'm up to-- I study how
infectious diseases spread through human and animal communities.  I've found
that I get a much more relaxed reaction when I do this. The same people who may
have uncomfortable reactions to physics have enough familiarity with the idea
of epidemics to be a little more comfortable. And besides, everyone has some
amount of morbid curiosity about the next big plague that's going to kill us
all.  (I realize that this may not be a viable strategy for some of my
colleagues who study nanoscience, magnetic materials, high-energy particles, or
other mainstream physics topics.  I'm interested to hear if anyone else who
works in the sciences has come up with a different technique for breaking
through the "I'm a physicist" ice.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine once chastised me for doing this. "Why should you have to hide
what you're interested in?" he asked. "If they react badly to your profession,
is it really worth getting to know them?"  To that I say that I'm still telling
them honestly what I'm interested in, I just sidestep the potentially negative
associations carried by the word "physics." And besides, just because someone
has a bad or obnoxious reaction to finding out that I'm a physicist doesn't
mean they aren't worth meeting.  The fact remains that I've found this to be a
great way to keep the getting-to-know-you conversation light when meeting new
people for the first time. I wish I could wave a magic wand and make it so that
everyone was comfortable wih the idea of interacting with professional
scientists, but I can't. While I'm waiting for &lt;a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/2/4/5379246/watch-this-bill-nye-debates-evolution-with-the-founder-of-the-creation-museum"&gt;Bill
Nye&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="http://www.cosmosontv.com/"&gt;Neil DeGrasse Tyson&lt;/a&gt; and others to humanize
the profession for the public, this is how I'll be introducing myself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Katie Mack and Zach's video really got me thinking about how to talk to other
people about their jobs with more empathy-- avoiding flattery and
stereotyping, and doing my best to hide any negative visceral reactions evoked
by the thought of others' jobs and interests.  One question that has occurred
to me is whether there are people in completely different professions
experience similarly frustrating reactions when they say what their jobs are.
Programmers, actuaries, office administrators, copy editors, art dealers,
karate instructors, gravediggers, lion-tamers, etc.:  whoever you are, I want
to hear about any difficulties  you may have had with telling other people what
you do in the comments below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/special-brain/#back_up1"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; 
Image from New X-Men #121, written by Grant Morrison with art by Frank Quitely.
 You can see some more of this particularly trippy story &lt;a href="https://marswillsendnomore.wordpress.com/2011/09/04/inside-the-twisted-mind-of-the-professor/"&gt;
here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote2"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/special-brain/#back_up2"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt;
All of the imagery of Frankenstein's monster being brought to life with electricity
comes from James Whale's &lt;a href="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0021884/"&gt;Frankenstein from 1931.&lt;/a&gt; Mary Shelley's original book contained no mention of 
electricity, and instead remained eerily vague about the mechanisms for creating life.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote3"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/special-brain/#back_up3"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://scitation.aip.org/content/aip/magazine/physicstoday/news/10.1063/PT.4.0293"&gt;
Here &lt;/a&gt; is a really level-headed critique of The Big Bang Theory that I like a
lot.  There isn't a ton of hand-wringing, and the author does talk about what the
show might consider doing differently.  It was written three years ago.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
Watch what happens when &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=THNPmhBl-8I/"&gt;
a brain surgeon meets a rocket scientist for the first time &lt;/a&gt;.
To justify my linking to this skit (outside of the fact that I love it so much), 
I'll just say that &lt;i&gt;nobody&lt;/i&gt; is acting appropriately in this video. 
&lt;/li&gt;


&lt;li&gt;
(Sorry, lawyers.)
&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>culture</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/special-brain/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 20 Mar 2014 20:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Quantum Mechanics: Trying to Sort the Physical from the Mystical</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/quantum-mechanics-mysticism/</link><dc:creator>DTC</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://xkcd.com/1240/"&gt;
&lt;img src="http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/quantum_mechanics.png" title="You can also just ignore any science assertion where 'quantum mechanics' is the most complicated phrase in it." alt="You can also just ignore any science assertion where 'quantum mechanics' is the most complicated phrase in it." id="back_up1"&gt; 
&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/quantum-mechanics-mysticism/#footnote1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine (I’ll call him Ron), who knows that I study physics, 
likes to talk to me about quantum mechanics.  He’s an easy-going guy 
and likes to joke around. “Hey, is it a particle or is it a wave today?” 
he’ll say, or, “How many dimensions do we have now?” When the conversation 
turns more serious, he tells me how he believes 
in the “quantum universe,” which is greater than what we humans are 
able to ordinarily perceive.  He talks about consciousness, immortality, 
spirits, and the great cosmic grandeur of the universe, all of which he 
ties together with the label of “quantum.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These conversations are strange to me.  Both of us are using the same two words: 
quantum mechanics.  When Ron thinks about quantum mechanics, he associates it 
with nonphysical concepts, like spirits.  Through my time spent studying physics, 
I’ve come to understand quantum mechanics as a theory describing the behavior of 
atoms and subatomic particles.
&lt;!-- more --&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, one day our chatting turned to the topic of medicine and how the 
human body heals itself.  Ron told me that the biggest problem with modern 
medicine is that doctors think of the body as a physical object only. 
Healing, he said, was a “quantum” effect.  I told him that I could make a 
pretty strong physical argument for why that wasn’t the case.  He responded 
with this story:  Once, when playing football, he severely injured his knee. 
The injury was so bad that he couldn’t bend it or move it.  He didn’t have 
health insurance and didn’t have the cash on hand to pay for medical treatment. 
One day, he prayed to the universe that he would get better and a “tornado of 
light came down” and healed his leg.  Since then, Ron says, he’s always believed 
in and respected the quantum universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t tell Ron that what he described in his story didn’t happen, 
that his experience was wrong or incorrect in some way.  I wasn’t there, 
so I can’t comment on the accuracy of his narrative. And even the story 
of how his body healed out of the blue isn’t problematic: as far as I can 
tell, decades after the story took place, Ron is in good shape and his leg 
is doing fine.  What I found objectionable about the story was how, in the 
end, Ron attributed his healing to the miraculous intervention of quantum mechanics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quantum mechanics, in all of its glorious strangeness, is only relevant on 
inconceivably small scales and at very, very low temperatures.  One of the 
reasons it took humans so long to develop the theory of quantum mechanics is 
that quantum effects don’t readily appear in everyday life.  My &lt;a href="http://ultracold.lassp.cornell.edu/"&gt;colleagues&lt;/a&gt;
who work to observe quantum mechanics in their experiments use lasers to manipulate 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubidium/"&gt;atoms&lt;/a&gt; 
(objects that are 1/10,000,000,000th of a meter in size and weigh around 
1/10,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000th of a kilogram) at temperatures less than 
1 Kelvin (about -459 degrees Fahrenheit).  At larger sizes and temperatures 
quantum effects are negligible.  The human body is more than a meter long, 
usually weighs around 50-100 kilograms and, if healthy, maintains a toasty 
98 degrees Fahrenheit.  Quantum mechanics is important at the atomic level, 
but on the scales at which people interact with the world it hardly shows up 
at all.  So, even if Ron's leg heals as he said it did, I wouldn't give credit to quantum mechanics.&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/quantum-mechanics-mysticism/#footnote-1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span id="back_up2"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been studying physics for years and still quantum mechanics 
remains utterly baffling to me.  The fact that such an abstract theory can tell us so 
much about the world feels a little bit like a miracle.  Quantum mechanics carries 
with it a number of counterintuitive ideas like the 
&lt;a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/07/21/nothing-to-see-here-demoting-the-uncertainty-principle/"&gt;uncertainty principle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/quantum-mechanics-mysticism/#footnote-1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span id="back_up3"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
entanglement, or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Many-worlds_interpretation"&gt;parallel universes&lt;/a&gt;.
 These ideas are so abstracted from every day life that the subject begins to take 
 on a supernatural quality.  Physics no longer seems like physics- 
 it starts to sound like mysticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it makes sense that contemporary culture has seized upon quantum mechanics 
as a possible explanation for inexplicable things.  The theory has so many 
surprising results that it seems natural to extend it to encompass other things 
that confuse us, like questions of consciousness.  Furthermore, “quantum mechanics” 
is a term that carries with it the weight of scientific legitimacy.  If Ron had 
said that he had been healed through witchcraft, laying on of hands, or alchemy 
he would have sounded ridiculous, but attributing his experience to quantum effects 
allows the story to borrow from the credible reputation of fact-based 20th century 
science.  What my friend doesn’t realize is that terminology is not what makes 
quantum theory powerful: the scientific methodology supporting quantum mechanics 
is what matters.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to keep separate quantum mechanics the physical theory and 
quantum mechanics as a mystical cosmic principle.  Despite how confusing it 
is, quantum mechanics is an empirically motivated and mature theory that gives 
us a framework to understand physical phenomena like radiation and chemical 
bonding.  This is fundamentally different from applying quantum mechanical 
concepts to the nature of reality or consciousness.  To do so may be a fun 
philosophical parlor game, but it is baseless speculation without any evidence 
to motivate the connection between quantum mechanics and the supernatural 
that it begins with. This confusion is not just restricted to scientific laymen: there are 
trained researchers working at well-respected research institutions 
who also &lt;a href="http://www.quantumconsciousness.org/"&gt;make the same mistake&lt;/a&gt;
 my friend Ron does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, speculation that the soul, the afterlife, ESP, 
or whatever else are quantum effects is unscientific, but at least it 
isn’t dangerous or harmful in the same way as climate change denial or 
&lt;a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/health/measles-surges-uk-years-after-vaccine-scare-6C9997438/"&gt;refusing to vaccinate your children&lt;/a&gt;. 
It’s closer to something like &lt;a href="http://www.intelligentdesign.org/"&gt;intelligent design&lt;/a&gt;, which is 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kitzmiller_v._Dover_Area_School_District/"&gt;fundamentally confused about what science is&lt;/a&gt;.
(We physicists are truly thankful that there is no noisy political movement 
to teach &lt;a href="https://www.deepakchopra.com/blog/view/900/from_quanta_to_qualia:_the_mystery_of_reality/"&gt;Deepak Chopra&lt;/a&gt;
alongside physics in high school classrooms.) So I won’t object to my 
friends’ stories of sudden, unexpected recoveries from illness, but 
I will react skeptically when I hear that healing has anything to do with quantum mechanics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/quantum-mechanics-mysticism/#back_up1"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; Credit where credit is due: I took this from XKCD.  This may be one of 
my favorite comics Randall Munroe has ever done.  That it came out while 
I was thinking about this piece was a great coincidence.  (A cosmic 
coincidence explainable through quantum entanglement?  Probably not.) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/quantum-mechanics-mysticism/#back_up2"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; Quantum mechanics may be just as mundane as any other materialistic physical 
theory, but that doesn’t make it any less amazing.  My favorite example is 
how quantum mechanics allows us to understand &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gS1dpowPlE8/"&gt; why the sun works. &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote-1"&gt;&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/quantum-mechanics-mysticism/#back_up3"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; In case you didn't take the time to click on the link: Seriously, do 
yourself a favor and click on the &lt;a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/07/21/nothing-to-see-here-demoting-the-uncertainty-principle/"&gt; link &lt;/a&gt;. It's an essay from The Stone that very elegantly describes
how the uncertainty principle is far less cosmically mind-blowing than you 
may have come to believe.  It does a beautiful job bringing us back down to 
earth and carefully explaining the scope of the principle.  I must give it credit
for having inspired this piece in no small way. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>metaphysics</category><category>mysticism</category><category>quantum mechanics</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/quantum-mechanics-mysticism/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 00:00:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Re-evaluating the values of the tiles in Scrabble™</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble/</link><dc:creator>DTC</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/scrabble/scrabble.jpg" width="100%" alt="Scrabble Tiles" style="float:center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently I have seen quite a few blog posts written about re-evaluating
the points values assigned to the different letter tiles in the
Scrabble™ brand Crossword Game. The premise behind these posts is that
the creator and designer of the game assigned point values to the
different tiles according to their relative frequencies of occurrence in
words in English text, supplemented by information gathered while
playtesting the game. The points assigned to different letters reflected
how difficult it was to play those letters: common letters like E, A,
and R were assigned 1 point, while rarer letters like J and Q were
assigned 8 and 10 points, respectively. These point values were based on
the English lexicon of the late 1930’s. Now, some 70 years later, that
lexicon has changed considerably, having gained many new words (e.g.:
EMAIL) and lost a few old ones. So, if one were to repeat the analysis
of the game designer in the present day, would one come to different
conclusions regarding how points should be assigned to various letters?
&lt;a id="note1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided to add my own analysis to the recent development because I
have found most of the other blog posts to be unsatisfactory for a
variety of reasons&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble/#fnote1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;br&gt;
One &lt;a href="http://deadspin.com/5975490/h-y-and-z-as-concealed-weapons-we-apply-google+inspired-math-to-scrabbles-flawed-points-system"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt;
calculated letters’ relative frequencies by counting the number of times
each letter appeared in each word in the Scrabble™ dictionary. But this
analysis is faulty, since it ignores the probability with which
different words actually appear in the game. One is far less likely to
draw QI than AE during a Scrabble™ game (since there’s only one Q in the
bag, but many A's and E's). Similarly, very long words like
ZOOGEOGRAPHICAL have a vanishingly small probability of appearing in the
game: the A’s in the long words and the A’s in the short words cannot be
treated equally. A second &lt;a href="http://blog.useost.com/2012/12/30/valett/"&gt;article&lt;/a&gt; I saw calculated
letter frequencies based on their occurrence in the Scrabble™ dictionary
and did attempt to weight frequencies based on word length. The author
of this second article also claimed to have quantified the extent to
which a letter could “fit well” with the other tiles given to a player.
Unfortunately, some of the steps in the analysis of this second article
were only vaguely explained, so it isn’t clear how one could replicate
the article’s conclusions. In addition, as far as I can tell, neither of
these articles explicitly included the distribution of letters (how many
A’s, how many B’s, etc) included in a Scrabble™ game. Also, neither of
these articles accounted for the fact that there are blank tiles (that
act as wild cards and can stand in for any letter) that appear in the
game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what does one need to do to improve upon the analyses already
performed? We’re given the Scrabble™ dictionary and bag of &lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b8/Scrabble_tiles_en.jpg"&gt;100
tiles&lt;/a&gt;
with a set distribution, and we’re going to try to determine what a good
pointing system would be for each letter in the alphabet. We’re also
armed with the knowledge that each player is given 7 letters at a time
in the game, making words longer than 8 letters very rare indeed. Let’s
say for the sake of simplicity that words 9 letters long or shorter
account for the vast majority of words that are possible to play in a
normal game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on these constraints, how can one best decide what points to
assign the different tiles? As stated above, the game is designed to
reward players for playing words that include letters that are more
difficult to use. So, what makes an easy letter easy, and what makes a
difficult letter difficult? Sure, the number of times the letter appears
in the
&lt;a href="http://scrabblehelper2.googlecode.com/svn-history/r3/trunk/src/scrabble/dictionary.txt"&gt;dictionary&lt;/a&gt;
is important, but this does not account for whether or not, on a given
rack of tiles (a rack of tiles is to Scrabble™ as a hand of cards is to
poker), that letter actually can be used. The letter needs to combine
with other tiles available either on the rack or on the board in order
to form words. The letter Q is difficult to play not only because it is
used relatively few times in the dictionary, but also because the
majority of Q-words require the player to use the letter U in
conjunction with it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what criterion can one use to say how useful a particular tile is?
Let’s say that letters that are useful have more potential to be used in
the game: they provide more options for the players who draw them. Given
a rack of tiles, one can generate a list of all of the words that are
possible for the player to play. Then, one can count the number of times
that each letter appears in that list. Useful letters, by this
criterion, will combine more readily with other letters to form words
and so appear more often in the list than un-useful letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I would also like to take a moment to preempt &lt;a href="http://scrabbleplayers.org/w/Valett"&gt;criticism from the
competitive Scrabble™ community&lt;/a&gt; by
saying that strategic decisions made by the players need not be brought
into consideration here. The point values of tiles are an engineering
constraint of the game. Strategic decisions are made by the players,
given the engineering constraints of the game. Words that are “available
to be played” are different from “words that actually do get played.”
The potential usefulness of individual letter tiles should reflect
whether or not it is even possible to play them, not whether or not a
player decides that using a particular group of tiles constitutes an
optimal move.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="note2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
To give an example, suppose I draw the rack BEHIWXY. I can 
generate&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble/#fnote2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
the full list of words available to be played given this rack: BE, BEY,
BI, BY, BYE, EH, EX, HE, HEW, HEX, HEY, HI, HIE, IBEX, WE, WEB, WHEY,
WHY, WYE, XI, YE, YEH, YEW. Counting the number of occurrences of each
letter, I see that the letter E appears 18 times, while the letter W
only appears 7 times. This example tells me that the letter E is
probably much more potentially useful than the letter W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example above is only one of the many, many possible racks that one
can see in a game of Scrabble™. I can use a 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monte_Carlo_method"&gt;Monte Carlo&lt;/a&gt;-type simulation
to estimate the average usefulness of the different letters by drawing
many example racks.
&lt;a id="note3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Monte Carlo is a technique used to estimate
numerical properties of complicated things without explicit calculation.
For example, suppose I want to know the probability of drawing a
straight flush in poker.&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble/#fnote3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;  I can calculate that probability
explicitly by using combinatorics, or I can use a Monte Carlo method to
deal a large number of hypothetical possible poker hands and count the
number of straight flushes that appear. If I deal a large enough number
of hands, the fraction of hands that are straight flushes will converge
upon the correct analytic value. Similarly here, instead of explicitly
calculating the usefulness of each letter, I use Monte Carlo to draw a
large number of hypothetical racks and use them to count the number of
times each letter can be used. Comparing the number of times that each
tile is used over many, many possible racks will give a good
approximation of how relatively useful each tile is on average. Note
that this process accounts for the words acceptable in the Scrabble™
dictionary, the number of available tiles in the bag, as well as the
probability of any given word appearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my simulation, I draw 10,000,000 racks, each with 9 tiles
(representing the 7 letters the player actually draws plus two tiles
available to be played through to form longer words). I perform the
calculation two different ways: once with a 98-tile pool with no blanks,
and once with a 100-tile pool that does include blanks. In the latter
case, I make sure to not count the blanks used to stand in for different
letters as instances of those letters appearing in the game. The results
are summarized in the table below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/scrabble/scrabble_tiles_table.jpg" width="80%" alt="Scrabble Tiles" style="float:center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There are two key observations to be made here. First, it does not seem
to matter whether or not there are blanks in the bag! The results are
very similar in both cases. Second, it would be completely reasonable to
keep the tile point values as they are. Only the Z, H, and U appear out
of order. It’s only if one looks very carefully at the differences
between the usefulness of these different tiles that one might
reasonably justify re-pointing the different letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For fun, I have included in the table my own suggestions for what these
tiles’ values might be changed to based on the simulation results.
(&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: here's where any pretensions of scientific rigor go out the
window.) I have kept the scale of points between 1 and 10, as in the
current pointing system. I have assigned groups of letters the same
number of points based on whether they have a similar usefulness score.
Here are the significant changes: L and U, which are significantly less
useful than the other 1-point tiles may be bumped up to 2 points,
comparable to the D and G. The letter V is clearly less useful than any
of the other three 4-point tiles (W, Y, and F, all of which may be used
to form 2-letter words while the V forms no 2-letter words), and so is
undervalued. The H is comparable to the 3-point tiles, and so is
currently overvalued. Similarly, the Z is overvalued when one considers
how close to the J it is. Unlike in the previous two articles that I
mentioned, I don't find any strong reason to change the value of the
letter X compared to the other 8 point tiles. I suppose one could lower
its value from 8 points to 7, but I have (somewhat arbitrarily) chosen
not to do so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One may also ask the question whether or not the fact that a letter
forms 2- or 3-letter words is unfairly biasing that letter. In
particular, is the low usefulness of the C and V compared to
comparably-pointed tiles due to the fact that they form no 2-letter
words? Performing the simulation again without 2-letter words, I found
no changes in the results in any of the letters except for C, which
increased in usefulness above the B and the H. The letter V's ranking,
however, did not change at all, indicating that unlike the C the V is
difficult to use even when combining with letters to make longer words.
Repeating the simulation yet again without 2- or 3-letter words yielded
the same results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final note, I would like to respond directly to to Stefan Fatsis's
&lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/sports/gaming/2013/01/scrabble_tile_values_why_it_s_a_mistake_to_change_the_point_value_of_the.single.html"&gt;excellent article&lt;/a&gt;
about the so-called controversy surrounding re-calculating tile values
and say that I am fully aware that this is indeed a "statistical
exercise," motivated mostly by my desire to do the calculation made by
others in a way that made sense in the context of the game of Scrabble.
Similarly, I realize that these recommendations are unlikely to actually
change anything. Given that the original points values of the tiles are
still justifiably appropriate by my analysis, it's not like anybody at
Hasbro is going to jump to "fix" the game. Lastly, my calculations have
nothing to do with the strategy of the game whatsoever, and cannot be
used to learn how to play the game any better. (If anything, I've only
confirmed some things that many experienced Scrabble players already
know about the game, such as that the V is a tricky tile, or that the H,
X, and Z tiles, in spite of their high point values, are quite
flexible.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fnote1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
1. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble/#note1"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; To state my own credentials, I have played Scrabble™competitively for
4 years, and am quite familiar with the mechanics of the game, as well
as contemporary strategy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fnote2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
2. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble/#note2"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; Credit where credit is due: Alemi provided the code used to
generate the list of available words given any set of tiles. Thanks
Alemi!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fnote3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
3. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble/#note3"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; Monte Carlo has a long history of being used to estimate the
properties of games. As recounted by George Dyson in &lt;em&gt;Turing’s
Cathedral&lt;/em&gt;, in 1948 while at Los Alamos the mathematician Stanislaw Ulam
suffered a severe bout of encephalitis that resulted in an emergency
trepanation. While recovering in the hospital, he played many games of
solitaire and was intrigued by the question of how to calculate the
probability that a given deal could result in a winnable game. The
combinatorics required to answer this question proved staggeringly
complex, so Ulam proposed the idea of generating many possible solitaire
deals and merely counting how many of them resulted in victory. This
proved to be much simpler than an explicit calculation, and the rest is
history: Monte Carlo is used today in a wide variety of applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Additional References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photo at top of a Scrabble™ board was taken during the 2012 National
Scrabble™ Championship. Check out the 9-letter double-blank BINOCULAR.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone interested in learning more about the fascinating world of
competitive Scrabble™, check out &lt;em&gt;Word Freak&lt;/em&gt;, also by Stefan Fatsis.
This book has become more or less the definitive documentation upon this
subculture. If you don't have enough time to read, check out &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word_Wars"&gt;Word
Wars&lt;/a&gt;, a documentary that
follows many of the same people as Fatsis's book. (It still may be
available streaming on Netflix if you hurry.)&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>fun</category><category>monte carlo</category><category>Scrabble</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 22:52:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>The Skeleton Supporting Search Engine Ranking Systems</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/the-skeleton-supporting-search-engine-ranking-systems/</link><dc:creator>DTC</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/skeleton-search/Skeleton_image_1.jpg" width="100%" alt="octopus google" title="Octosearch!" style="float:center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A lot of the research I’m interested in relates to networks – measuring
the properties of networks and figuring out what those properties mean.
While doing some background reading, I stumbled upon some discussion of
the algorithm that search engines use to rank search results. The
automatic ranking of the results that come up when you search for
something online is a great example of how understanding networks (in
this case, the World Wide Web) can be used to turn a very complicated
problem into something simple.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ranking search results relies on the assumption that there is some
underlying pattern to how information is organized on the WWW- there are
a few core websites containing the bulk of the sought-after information
surrounded by a group of peripheral websites that reference the core.
Recognizing that the WWW is a network representation of how information
is organized and using the properties of the network to detect where
that information is centered are the key components to figuring out what
websites belong at the top of the search page.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Suppose you look something up on Google (looking for YouTube videos of
your favorite band, &lt;a href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/author/corky.html"&gt;looking for edifying science
writing&lt;/a&gt;, tips on octopus pet care,
etc): the search service returns a whole spate of results. Usually, the
pages that Google recommends first end up being the most useful. How on
earth does the search engine get it right?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First I’ll tell you exactly how Google does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; work. When you type in
something into the search bar and hit enter, a message is &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; sent to
a guy who works for Google about your query. That guy does &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; then
look up all of the websites matching your search, does not visit each
website to figure out which ones are most relevant to you, and does
&lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; rank the pages accordingly before sending a ranked list back to
you. That would be a very silly way to make a search engine work! It
relies on an individual human ranking the search results by hand with
each search that’s made. Maybe we can get around having to hire
thousands of people by finding a clever way to automate this process.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So here’s how a search engine &lt;em&gt;does&lt;/em&gt; work. Search engines use robots
that crawl around the World Wide Web (sometimes these robots are
referred to as “spiders”) finding websites, cataloguing key words that
appear on those webpages, and keeping track of all the other sites that
link into or away from them. The search engine then stores all of these
websites and lists of their keywords and neighbors in a big database.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing which websites contain which keywords allows a search engine to
return a list of websites matching a particular search. But simply
knowing which websites contain which keywords is not enough to know how
to order the websites according to their relevance or importance.
Suppose I type “octopus pet care” into Google. The search yields 413,000
results- far too many for me to comb through at random looking for the
web pages that best describe what I’m interested in.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Knowing the ways that different websites connect to one another through
hyperlinks is the key to how search engine rankings work. Thinking of a
collection of websites as an ordinary list doesn’t say anything about
how those websites relate to one another. It is more useful to think of
the collection of websites as a network, where each website is a node
and each hyperlink between two pages is a directed edge in the network.
In a way, these networks are maps that can show us how to get from one
website to another by clicking through links.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here is an example of what a network visualization of a website map of a
large portion of the WWW looks like. (Original full-size image
&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/d/d2/Internet_map_1024.jpg"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/skeleton-search/Internet_map_1024.jpg" width="100%" alt="internet map" style="float:center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Here is a site map for a group of websites that connect to the main page
of English Wikipedia. (Original image from
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Site_map"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.) This smaller site map is
closer to the type of site map used when making a search using a search
engine.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;
&lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/skeleton-search/Main_Page_Usability.png" width="100%" alt="internet map" style="float:center"&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, how does knowing the underlying network of the search results help
one to find the best website on octopus care (or any other topic)? The
search engine assumes that behind the seemingly random, hodgepodge
collection of files on the WWW, there is some organization in the way
they connect to one another. Specifically, the search engine assumes
that finding the websites most central to the network of search results
is the same as finding the search results with the best information.
Think of a well-known, trusted source of information, like the New York
Times. The NY Times website will have many other websites referencing it
by linking to it. In addition, the NY Times website, being a trusted
news source, is likely to refer to the best references for other sources
that it wants to refer to, such as Reuters. High-quality references will
also probably have many incoming links from websites that cite them. So
not only does a website like the NY Times sit at the center of many
other websites that link to it, but it also frequently connects to other
websites that themselves are at the center of many other websites. It is
these most central websites that are probably the best ones to look at
when searching for information.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When I search for “octopus pet care” using Google I am necessarily
assuming that the search results are organized according to this
core-periphery structure, with a group of important core websites
central to the network surrounded by many less important peripheral
websites that link to the core nodes. The core websites may also connect
to one another. There may also be websites disconnected from the rest,
but these will probably be less important to the search simply because
of the disconnection. Armed with the knowledge of the connections
between the different relevant websites and the core-periphery network
structure assumption, we may now actually find which of the websites are
most central to the network (in the core), and therefore determine which
websites to rank highly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="note1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Let’s begin by assigning a quantitative “centrality” score to each of
the nodes (websites) in the network, initially guessing that all of the
search results are equally important. (This, of course, is probably not
true. It’s just an initial guess.) Each node then transfers all of its 
centrality score to its neighbors, dividing it evenly between 
them&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/the-skeleton-supporting-search-engine-ranking-systems/#fnote1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.
(Starting with a centrality score of 1 with three neighbors, each of
those neighbors receives 1/3.) Each node also receives a some centrality
from each neighbor that links in to it. Following this first step, we
find that nodes with many incoming edges will have higher centrality
than nodes with few incoming edges. We can repeat this process of
dividing and transferring centrality again. Nodes with many incoming
links will have more centrality to share with their neighbors, and nodes
with many incoming links will themselves also receive more centrality.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After repeating this process many times, we begin to see a difference
between which nodes have the highest centrality scores: nodes with high
centrality are the ones that have many incoming links, or have links to
other central nodes, or both. This algorithm therefore differentiates
between the periphery and the core of the network. Core nodes receive
lots of centrality because they link to one another and because they
have lots of incoming links from the periphery. Peripheral nodes have
fewer incoming links and so receive less centrality than the nodes in
the core. Knowing the centrality scores of search results on the WWW
makes it pretty straightforward for us to quantitatively rank which of
those websites belongs at the top of the list.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Of course, there are more complex ways that one can add to and improve
this procedure. Google’s algorithm PageRank (named for founder Larry
Page, not because it is used to rank web pages) and the HITS algorithm
developed at Cornell are two examples of more advanced ways of ranking
search engine results. We can go even further: a search engine can keep
track of the links that users follow whenever a particular search is
made. (This is almost the same as the company hiring someone to order
sought-after web pages automatically whenever a search is made, except
all the company lets the user do it for free.) Over time, search engines
can improve their methods for helping us find what we need by learning
directly from the way users themselves prioritize which search results
they pursue. Still, these different search engine ranking systems may
operate using slightly different methods, but all of them depend on
understanding the list of search results within the context of a
network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fnote1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
1. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/the-skeleton-supporting-search-engine-ranking-systems/#note1"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; It's not always all - there are other variations where nodes only
transfer a fraction of their centrality score at each step.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Sources (and further reading)&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I wanted to include no mathematics in
this post simply because I cannot explain the mathematics behind these
algorithms and their convergence properties better than my sources can.
For those of you who want to see the mathematical side of the argument
for yourselves (which involves treating the network adjacency matrix as
a Markov process and finding its nontrivial steady state eigenvector),
do consult the following two textbooks:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Easley, David, and Jon Kleinberg. &lt;em&gt;Networks, Crowds, and Markets:
Reasoning about a Highly Connected World&lt;/em&gt;. Cambridge University Press,
2010 (&lt;a href="http://www.cs.cornell.edu/home/kleinber/networks-book/networks-book-ch14.pdf"&gt;Chapter 14&lt;/a&gt;
in particular) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Newman, Mark. &lt;em&gt;Networks: an Introduction&lt;/em&gt;. Oxford
University Press, 2010 (Chapter 7 in particular)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A popular book on the early development of network science that contains
a lot of information on the structure of the WWW:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Barabasi, Albert-Laszlo. &lt;em&gt;Linked: How Everything is Connected to
Everything Else and What It Means&lt;/em&gt;. Plume, 2003.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A book on the history of modern computing that contains an interesting
passage on how search engines learn adaptively from their users (that
deserves a shout-out in this blog post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dyson, George. &lt;em&gt;Turing's Cathedral&lt;/em&gt;. Pantheon, 2012.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>centrality measures</category><category>networks</category><category>octopodes</category><category>search engine ranking</category><category>search engines</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/the-skeleton-supporting-search-engine-ranking-systems/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 01 Jan 2013 19:09:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Batman, Helicopters, and Center of Mass</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/batman-helicopters-and-center-of-mass/</link><dc:creator>DTC</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;div style="float: right; margin: 0px 0px 0px 10px"&gt;
&lt;img src="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/images/batman/wiki_batman.jpg"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A couple weeks ago, I came home after a long day at work looking for a
break. I thought to myself, "What’s more fun than physics?" &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="note1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Batman.&lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/batman-helicopters-and-center-of-mass/#fnote1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I sat down to play the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkham_City"&gt;latest Batman
videogame&lt;/a&gt;, in which Batman’s
current objective was to use his grappling hook to jump onto an enemy
helicopter to steal an electronic MacGuffin. As awesome as this was, it
occurred to me that something was very wrong about the way the
helicopter moved while Batman zipped through the air. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://youtu.be/81qN-PHucqM?t=3m12s"&gt;See if you can spot it too&lt;/a&gt;. (Watch for about 5
seconds after the video starts. Ignore the commentary. Note: The
grunting noises are the sounds that Batman makes if you shoot him with
bullets.) &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What occurred to me was this: If the helicopter’s rotors
provided enough lift to balance the force of gravity, wouldn’t Batman’s
sudden additional weight cause the helicopter to fall out of the sky?
Also, to get lifted up into the air, the helicopter must be pulling up
on Batman: shouldn’t Batman also be pulling down on the helicopter? By
how much should we expect to see the helicopter’s altitude change? &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To address the first question, let's go to Newton's second law: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \sum \vec{F} = m\vec{a} $$ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let’s assume that the helicopter is hovering
stationary, minding its own business, when Batman jumps onto it. Let's
also assume the helicopter pilots are totally oblivious to Batman and
make no flight corrections after Batman jumps onto it. In order to
hover, the lift from the helicopter's rotors exactly matched the pull of
gravity. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \sum \vec{F} = \vec{F}&lt;em gravity&gt;{rotors} - \vec{F}&lt;/em&gt; = 0 $$ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Batman's sudden additional weight would cause the helicopter to
start falling, as the forces would no longer balance: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \sum \vec{F} = \vec{F}&lt;em gravity&gt;{rotors} - \vec{F}&lt;/em&gt; - \vec{F}_{Batman} &amp;lt; 0 $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the helicopter does accelerate (and move) when Batman jumps onto it.
How much does it move? Let’s assume there are no crazy winds or other
external forces acting on the helicopter or Batman while Batman grapples
onto the helicopter. “No external forces” means that momentum of
helicopter + Batman does not change during Batman's flight. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let's make
things a little simpler and assume that neither Batman nor the
helicopter had any vertical momentum before Batman used his grappling
hook. (I can choose to approach this problem from a reference frame
where the center of mass is stationary. Choosing a frame where the
center of mass moves won't change the results, it will just make the
calculation more complicated.) Because the momentum of helicopter +
Batman does not change, then the center of mass does not move while
Batman zips through the air: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \frac{d}{dt} y_{COM} = \frac{d}{dt} \frac{m_{Bat} y_{Bat} + m_{Copter} y_{Copter}}{m_{Bat} + m_{Copter}} = \frac{p}{m_{Bat} + m_{Copter}} = 0 $$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The center of mass must remain stationary, so we can find how much the
helicopter's height changes by if Batman starts on the ground (y = 0)
and both end up at the same height with Batman hanging from the
helicopter: &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ y_{COM} = \frac{m_{Copter} y_{Copter} + m_{Bat} (0)}{m_{Bat} + m_{Copter}} = \frac{m_{Copter} y_{final} + m_{Bat} y_{final}}{m_{Bat} + m_{Copter}} $$ &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;$$ \Delta y = y_{Copter} - y_{final} = \frac{m_{Bat}}{m_{Bat} + m_{Copter}} y_{Copter}$$&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, some numbers: The police helicopters in the game are pretty small,
probably about 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bell_206"&gt;1500 kg&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Batman is a big guy who works out and probably weighs around 100 kg (220 lb).
Plus, he’s wearing body armor (hence surviving when bullets hit him) and
a utility belt and all of those other Bat-gadgets, which probably adds
about 30 kg ($\sim 30$ lb for the gadgets, 
$\sim30$ lb for the &lt;a href="http://www.nationaldefensemagazine.org/archive/2011/February/Pages/ManufacturersAnswerMilitary%E2%80%99sCalltoReduceBodyArmorWeight.aspx"&gt;armor&lt;/a&gt;).
If Batman has to grapple onto a helicopter 30 meters above him, then the
helicopter should drop out of the air by about 2.4 m. This is greater
than the height of Batman himself, and would be noticeable if the
helicopter physics in the game were perfect. Of course, if the
helicopters appearing in the game were the giant army helicopters (they
do carry rockets, after all), their mass would be much larger
$(\sim 5000-10000~{\rm kg})$ so the effect of Batman’s additional weight would be
much smaller. None of these considerations detracted from the fun I had
playing the game, but it did seem odd that the helicopters appeared to
be nailed to the sky instead of moving freely through the air. I’ll be
writing the game developers a strongly-worded letter directly. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Notes&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a id="fnote1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
1. &lt;a href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/batman-helicopters-and-center-of-mass/#note1"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; The DC superhero, not the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batman,_Turkey"&gt;city&lt;/a&gt;
or the
&lt;a href="http://www.newcritters.com/2007/01/23/the-batman-fish-otocinclus-batmani/"&gt;fish&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Batman</category><category>Center of Mass</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/batman-helicopters-and-center-of-mass/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2012 11:10:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Proofiness: A look into how mathematics relates to American political life</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/proofiness-a-look-into-how-mathematics-relates-to-american-political-life/</link><dc:creator>DTC</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Dearest readers,
This is my first post on The Virtuosi, so I thought I’d take a moment to
introduce myself. I’m a first year physics graduate student at Cornell,
recently joined after 2 years working as an engineer first at a private
firm and then at a national lab. I myself have had lots of fun following
the exploits of my estimable colleagues here on The Virtuosi, and I
thought I could bring a new angle to the content here. I would like to
use this space to discuss how science interacts with everyday life in a
cultural sense. How does science appear in popular culture? How do
political or social issues relate back to science? Those sorts of
questions. (I understand that there are plenty of other resources
elsewhere that offer far more intelligent insight into these matters
than I can, but in the very least this will give people a chance point
them out to me as they yell at me in the forum below.)
Enough intro, here begins my very first blog post:
Being interested in how science is communicated to the public, I am an
avid reader of popular science. While academic types sometimes dismiss
this kind of writing as shallow or otherwise uninteresting, I think
science writers perform a very important function serving as a way to
convey information about conceptually challenging topics to a general
audience. At their best, I find that these books serve as examples for
how I can communicate my own ideas better, and in addition challenge my
understanding of how science relates back to society in general.
This being said, I cannot recommend Charles Seife’s &lt;em&gt;Proofiness&lt;/em&gt; enough.
The basic premise of this book is to explore the way that good
mathematics is hijacked, twisted, or ignored in everyday life, and the
ugly consequences of the tendency to misunderstand numbers and
measurements.
Seife gives a number of fascinating examples of the ways in which
numbers and math connect to American democracy. American government
functions through representation, and so the
“&lt;a href="http://www.archives.gov/exhibits/charters/constitution_transcript.html"&gt;enumeration&lt;/a&gt;”
of citizens and their opinions through the Census and elections is an
essential part of the democratic process. This “enumeration” is a
counting measurement, subject to errors like any other. And yet, the
laws that govern how Censuses and elections are run ignore this fact.
Seife’s discussion of elections (and in particular &lt;em&gt;Bush v. Gore&lt;/em&gt;) is
fascinating, but I won’t spoil that here. Here’s my take on the
discussion of the Census that appears in &lt;em&gt;Proofiness&lt;/em&gt;:
Consider a (vague) physics experiment. I want to know how many particles
are inside a box. To figure this out, I have a detector that goes
&lt;em&gt;ping&lt;/em&gt; every time a particle passes through it. I set up my detector
inside the box and count the number of times that it goes &lt;em&gt;ping&lt;/em&gt; in a
certain amount of time. I can then use that count to guess at the number
of particles that I have in my box. My measurement will let me estimate
N to within some margin of error. This process is perhaps unnecessary if
I have only five particles in my box (in which case, I might just open
the box and count what I see inside), but if I have 300 million
particles in my box, it would be totally impractical for me to reach
into the box 300 million times and count each one individually.
We can consider the Census to be just like this physics experiment. I
have N inhabitants (particles) living in my country (box), and I can use
my detector (census replies) to count a certain number of people. In
principle, using well-understood statistical techniques of regression
and error analysis, I can estimate to within a very good margin of error
how many people live in each region of the country. Instead, what the
Census requires is that we reach inside the box (send representatives to
every household that doesn’t reply by mail) and count every single
person. The whole process ignores the fact that even if we send a
representative to every single household there will still be some margin
of error in our counting measurements. No such measurement can be made
without errors.
The consequences of ignoring these errors, says Seife, can be that we
waste money in attempting the impossible and trying to count everybody.
From a civic-minded perspective, this attitude towards the perfection of
the Census can backfire. For example, if undercounting occurs (i.e.,
certain households do not respond for some reason), the Census has no
mechanism for correcting that miscount. Counter-intuitively, the Census
laws actually prohibit the use of any statistical techniques to correct
miscounting. The result is that those slow to respond are ignored and
not taken into account when allotting seats in the legislature to
represent them.
&lt;em&gt;Proofiness&lt;/em&gt; is a fascinating book and a fun read, and I recommend you
all look it up. In addition, it serves as an excellent example of
science writing that helped me to rethink how scientific ideas relate to
everyday life. I hope to invite consideration of these topics here and
in future posts. If you want to know more about the inspiration for this
post, go &lt;a href="http://journalism.nyu.edu/faculty/charles-seife/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Census</category><category>culture</category><category>elections</category><category>math</category><category>politics</category><category>Proofiness</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/proofiness-a-look-into-how-mathematics-relates-to-american-political-life/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 06 Mar 2012 14:37:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>