<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts by Holmes)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/authors/holmes.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 23:01:55 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Problem of the Week #2: Solution</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/problem-of-the-week-2-solution/</link><dc:creator>Holmes</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all who sent in solutions! We are very happy with the vast
number of responses, and we will put up a leader board shortly! Solution
Let A be the fraction of the rubber band that the ant has traversed.
$$A\left(t\right)=\frac{x\left(t\right)}{L+vt}.$$ The ant's
velocity relative to any point along the rubber band is equal to the
length of the rubber band times the first time derivative of A:
$$u=\left(L+vt\right)\frac{dA}{dt}=\left(L+vt\right)\left[\frac{\dot{x}}{L+vt}-\frac{vx}{\left(L+vt\right)^{2}}\right]=\dot{x}-\frac{vx}{L+vt}.$$
This gives us an inseparable, first-order differential equation for
x(t). The general differential equation of this type,
$$\dot{x}+p\left(t\right)x=q\left(t\right),$$ has the general
solution $$x\left(t\right)=e^{-\int_{0}^{t}
p\left(t\right)dt}\int_{0}^{t} q\left(t\right)e^{\int_{0}^{t}
p\left(t\right)dt}dt.$$ In our case,
$$p\left(t\right)=-\frac{v}{L+vt},\quad q\left(t\right)=u.$$
Therefore, $$x\left(t\right)&amp;amp;=&amp;amp;e^{\int\frac{v}{L+vt}dt}\int
ue^{-\int\frac{v}{L+vt}dt}dt=\frac{u}{v}\left(L+vt\right)\ln\left(1+\frac{vt}{L}\right).$$
When the ant has reached the other side, x(t) = L + vt, so
$$x\left(t\right)=L+vt=\frac{u}{v}\left(L+vt\right)\ln\left(1+\frac{vt}{L}\right).$$
Solving for t, we get $$t=\frac{L}{v}\left(e^{v/u}-1\right).$$ So
the ant always makes it to the other side (unless u = 0)! In the limit
as v -&amp;gt; 0, we get $$t\approx\frac{L}{u},$$ which is exactly what we
would expect. We can show that the ant will reach the other side without
doing any calculations. As the ant moves across the rubber band, the
velocity of the point on the rubber band that the ant is currently
walking on increases from 0 to v. Therefore, the ant is accelerating.
Since the other end of the rubber band is moving at a constant velocity,
the accelerating ant will always eventually catch up to the far end.
Another way to see this is that since the ant is accelerating, if it
makes it halfway, it will make it all the way to the other side; if it
makes it one-quarter of the way, it will make it halfway, and so on. We
know that since the ant is traveling at some nonzero velocity, it must
make it some nonzero fraction of the way to the other side. Therefore,
it must make it twice that far, and so on, all the way to the other
side. Thanks to Frank for pointing this out!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>problem of the week</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/problem-of-the-week-2-solution/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2010 17:46:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Problem of the Week #2</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/problem-of-the-week-2/</link><dc:creator>Holmes</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;As always, we welcome you to send in solutions, or even any ideas you
have about how to solve the problems
to&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;with
“problem of the week” in the subject line. We will keep track of the top
Virtuosi problem solvers.&lt;/em&gt;Why did the ant cross the rubber band?**
A rubber band is held fixed at one end. The other end is pulled at a
velocity v. At time t = 0, the rubber band has a length of L, and an ant
starts crawling from one end to the other at velocity u. Does the ant
reach the other side? If so, how long does it take to get there? Assume
that the rubber band is able to be stretched indefinitely without
breaking.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ants</category><category>problem of the week</category><category>rubber bands</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/problem-of-the-week-2/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2010 16:30:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Problem of the Week #1</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/problem-of-the-week-1/</link><dc:creator>Holmes</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;I thought we could spice things up a bit with a more interactive post
on The Virtuosi. Starting this week, a new problem of the week will be
posted each week. Solutions will be posted the following week. These
problems will be a collection of physics and math problems and riddles,
and although hopefully challenging enough to be fun and interesting,
they should mostly be solvable using concepts from introductory
undergraduate physics and math classes.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;We welcome you to ponder these problems, and send in solutions, or even
any ideas you have about how to solve the problems
to&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;&lt;em&gt;the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;with
“problem of the week” in the subject line. We will keep track of the top
Virtuosi problem solvers.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;em&gt;Here it goes…&lt;strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;Maximizing Gravity&lt;/em&gt;*
&lt;/strong&gt;
You are given a blob of Play-Doh (with a fixed mass and uniform density)
that you can shape however you choose. How can you shape it to maximize
the gravitational force at a given point &lt;/em&gt;P* on the surface of the
Play-Doh?
Solution
In cylindrical coordinates, where the point P is taken to be the origin,
the z-component of the gravitational field due to any point (s, z) felt
at the origin, is proportional to
$$\frac{1}{s^{2}+z^{2}}\frac{z}{\sqrt{s^{2}+z^{2}}},$$
where the second factor is necessary to take the z-component. If we have
azimuthal symmetry, the magnitude of the gravitational field is given by
the sum of all the z-components of the forces due to all points in the
planet. For a given contour
$$\frac{z}{\left(s^{2}+z^{2}\right)^{3/2}}=C,$$
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_kdZd6FJQtZQ/TN9Jgv8f9gI/AAAAAAAAAAM/qdRknJVbCT0/s1600/maxgravity.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_kdZd6FJQtZQ/TN9Jgv8f9gI/AAAAAAAAAAM/qdRknJVbCT0/s320/maxgravity.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
for some constant C, each point on the interior contributes more to the
total gravitational field than each point on the exterior. Thus, the
gravitational field is maximized if the surface of the planet takes the
shape of one of these contours. Solving for s(z), we
get$$s\left(z\right)=\sqrt{\left(\frac{z}{C}\right)^{2/3}-z^{2}}.$$
If the length of the planet in the z-direction is $$z_0,$$ we can
replace C in the above expression to get
$$s\left(z\right)=\sqrt{\left(z_{0}^{4}z^{2}\right)^{1/3}-z^{2}}.$$
As can be seen by the plot above, this shape looks a lot like a sphere,
but slightly smushed toward the point of interest P. We can rigorously
compare the field of the maximal gravity solid to that of a sphere with
the same volume. The volume of the maximal solid is given by
$$V=\pi\int_{0}^{z_{0}}s^{2}\left(z\right)dz=\pi\int_{0}^{z_{0}}\left[\left(z_{0}^{4}z^{2}\right)^{1/3}-z^{2}\right]dz=\frac{4\pi}{15}z_{0}^{3}$$
The volume of a sphere of radius r is of course $$V=\frac{4}{3}\pi
r^{3},$$ so in order for the volumes to be the same, the sphere must
have a radius of $$r=z_{0}/5^{1/3}.$$
The acceleration due to the maximal solid is proportional to
$$a_{max}=\int dVa_{z}=2\pi
G\rho\int_{0}^{z_{0}}dz\int_{0}^{s\left(z\right)}sds\frac{z}{\left(s^{2}+z^{2}\right)^{3/2}}=\frac{4\pi
G\rho z_{0}}{5},$$
while the acceleration due to the sphere is just
$$a_{sphere}=\frac{G\rho\frac{4}{3}\pi r^{3}}{r^{2}}=\frac{4\pi
G\rho z_{0}}{3\cdot5^{1/3}}.$$
Thus, we have
$$\frac{F_{max}}{F_{sphere}}=\frac{4\pi G\rho z_{0}/5}{4\pi
G\rho
z_{0}/\left(3\cdot5^{1/3}\right)}=\frac{3}{5^{2/3}}\approx1.026.$$
So the solid that gives the maximum gravitational field at a point is
only about 3% better than a sphere.
For a more detailed discussion, see &lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/%7Eaalemi/random/planet.pdf"&gt;Alemi's
solution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>gravity</category><category>problem of the week</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/problem-of-the-week-1/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 19:39:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>