<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts by Jared)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/authors/jared.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 15:05:01 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Life in the Infrared</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/life-in-the-infrared/</link><dc:creator>Jared</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4egR75ENI/AAAAAAAAAJU/eEFirBEL2xY/s1600/authors.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4egR75ENI/AAAAAAAAAJU/eEFirBEL2xY/s320/authors.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Corky, Matt, and Jared, with the experimental apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There's a place where TV remotes are flashlights, Wii's are torches, and
Snuggies are translucent. It's our kitchen. We modified a 3 dollar
webcam to view in the infrared portion of the electromagnetic spectrum.
We'll show you how, and what you can do with it. First, a little bit of
background. If you read the previous post by Alex, you'd know that
visible light waves are the same kind of waves as radio waves,
microwaves, and x-rays; they just wave at different frequencies. Light
that has a frequency just below what we can see is called "infrared",
which apparently derives from the latin &lt;em&gt;infra--&lt;/em&gt;below red (thanks
wikipedia!). So we know that if we get an object hot enough, it will
glow visibly. However, warm objects (say, humans, cars, tanks) while not
emitting enough visible light to glow, will emit easily detectable
infrared light. This makes infrared imaging a handy technology for
finding warm things in the dark. And, since many opaque things in the
visible are transparent in the infrared (or vice versa), you can dream
up a lot of fun to be had if you could only see in the infrared. Well,
it turns out that the CCDs in many common webcams are sensitive to the
infrared (IR). However, since an infrared signal would make for a weird
looking visible light picture, it is simply filtered out. Well, we
(mostly Matt) got our hands on such a
&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/gp/product/B0019WF4FE/ref=oss_product"&gt;webcam&lt;/a&gt;,
for a whopping 3 dollars, and removed the filter. Then we turned the
tables, and inserted a visible light filter. For this we used the
darkest part of a developed film roll, and while not getting rid of all
the visible, it did a pretty good job with the lights down low. You can
get a junk roll from your local Rite Aid photo center for free, just ask
for Sue. She is very helpful. So we took some pictures of whatever we
could find that was a strong IR source. It turns out that our particular
camera wasn't sensitive to detect the signal of a warm human (or a cold
one for that matter). We had to get something just a little hotter. So
we lit a stick on fire, and then blew it out. Here's what it looks like
in the now very pedestrian visible spectrum, with the lights out:
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4e6vuACII/AAAAAAAAAJY/gD53zNX1nDI/s1600/stick+visible.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4e6vuACII/AAAAAAAAAJY/gD53zNX1nDI/s320/stick+visible.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
It's just barely glowing. Now, let's look at it in what I'll call
"enhanced" visible with the lights on, meaning that it's sensitive to
both IR and visible at the same time.
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4ff9P0ljI/AAAAAAAAAJc/X5a75LQKr-Q/s1600/stick+enhanced.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4ff9P0ljI/AAAAAAAAAJc/X5a75LQKr-Q/s320/stick+enhanced.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The infared obviously dominates the output. It looks like an IR
sparkler. Now, let's shut the lights off, and see only IR:
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4g8q5tiZI/AAAAAAAAAJk/qLct2HN-ZuQ/s1600/stick+infra.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4g8q5tiZI/AAAAAAAAAJk/qLct2HN-ZuQ/s320/stick+infra.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
It's bright enough to "light up" my hand, which it certainly couldn't do
in the visible. Okay, so we had to light this thing on fire, and it was
already glowing. Well, my response to that is...this spoon:
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4iF8qPjjI/AAAAAAAAAJo/kywO7JDYG3Q/s1600/hot+spoon+vis.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4iF8qPjjI/AAAAAAAAAJo/kywO7JDYG3Q/s400/hot+spoon+vis.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Normal spoon. But actually we heated it up a bit on the stove. Here it
is in enhanced visible:
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4iR1HraFI/AAAAAAAAAJs/qjk-xDgyFkM/s1600/hot+spoon+enhanced.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4iR1HraFI/AAAAAAAAAJs/qjk-xDgyFkM/s320/hot+spoon+enhanced.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
And now, lights off, infrared only:
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4ikGGMEfI/AAAAAAAAAJw/gYsusNx8RNw/s1600/hot+spoon+dark.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4ikGGMEfI/AAAAAAAAAJw/gYsusNx8RNw/s320/hot+spoon+dark.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Apparently we only heated up the tip significantly.
Now, we have a super high tech flashlight that has three modes. It can
produce green LED light, white LED light, or incandescent white light.
Corky pointed each one at me. White LED light, visible:
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4jmRe24EI/AAAAAAAAAJ0/c4h7wMdW_7c/s1600/jared+white.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4jmRe24EI/AAAAAAAAAJ0/c4h7wMdW_7c/s320/jared+white.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Creepy, eh? It's the shaved head.
Now, white LED light in the IR:
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4kEKAtnEI/AAAAAAAAAJ4/RKKCmhRxu5Q/s1600/dark.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4kEKAtnEI/AAAAAAAAAJ4/RKKCmhRxu5Q/s320/dark.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Nuthin' doin'. Similarly for green LED light. This is included only for
its creepiness. First, in the visible:
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4kTWeT2-I/AAAAAAAAAJ8/ZAJ3aUCC2qY/s1600/jared+green.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4kTWeT2-I/AAAAAAAAAJ8/ZAJ3aUCC2qY/s320/jared+green.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Corky calls this "the most palatable [pronounced incorrectly] picture of
Jared we could find." In the IR, nada:
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4kkgkjufI/AAAAAAAAAKA/I8kV2SZKpiE/s1600/dark+2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4kkgkjufI/AAAAAAAAAKA/I8kV2SZKpiE/s320/dark+2.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
But for incandescent white, in visible:
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4kvV7Z5fI/AAAAAAAAAKE/0jHh-_5huRg/s1600/jared+incan.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4kvV7Z5fI/AAAAAAAAAKE/0jHh-_5huRg/s320/jared+incan.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
And IR:
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4k7_LZAbI/AAAAAAAAAKI/eTZdYYArUdc/s1600/jared+infra.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4k7_LZAbI/AAAAAAAAAKI/eTZdYYArUdc/s320/jared+infra.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I am aglow! Matt is clearly shocked. This happens because light
generated by LED's occurs because of electrons hopping around
semi-definite energy states of a material, making semi-definite
frequencies of light. However, incandescent light is due to the filament
being glowing hot, emitting radiation over a wide range of frequencies,
and we know that it's got a strong contribution in the IR.
So much for hot things. You have a bunch of IR dedicated sources around
your house that maybe you didn't know about. One such source is many TV
remote controls. Here we are, in the visible, with the lights low,
pointing remotes at our faces.
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4mbYxxVWI/AAAAAAAAAKM/bR-WdOFTQ0o/s1600/remotes+vis.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4mbYxxVWI/AAAAAAAAAKM/bR-WdOFTQ0o/s320/remotes+vis.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
This is actually a promo pic for our 80's new wave band. Here's what
this looks like, with buttons depressed, in the IR:
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4nENHKUoI/AAAAAAAAAKQ/waQc1sh3AS4/s1600/remotes+infra.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4nENHKUoI/AAAAAAAAAKQ/waQc1sh3AS4/s320/remotes+infra.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
A personal favorite.
These remotes weren't the brightest source we could find. It turns out
that the Wii sensor bar (which actually transmits, rather than receives
data) is a freakin' beacon (say that out loud). Here it is, on top of
our TV, which Corky is apparently flying towards.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4oAdkkSQI/AAAAAAAAAKU/HVn-di40lSA/s1600/corky+flying.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4oAdkkSQI/AAAAAAAAAKU/HVn-di40lSA/s320/corky+flying.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Unassuming little guy in the visible. But with the Wii on and in IR
mode:
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4ocjPYcBI/AAAAAAAAAKY/eJkV5XE4GAs/s1600/wii+dark.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4ocjPYcBI/AAAAAAAAAKY/eJkV5XE4GAs/s320/wii+dark.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
There's a person in there too, IR bathing. But I promised you
translucent Snuggies. (Yes, we own a Snuggie, and highly recommend
them.) Here's Matt hiding behind one, whilst I angrily supervise:
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4o-dCYcdI/AAAAAAAAAKc/ppkhs3o9nKc/s1600/snuggie+visible.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4o-dCYcdI/AAAAAAAAAKc/ppkhs3o9nKc/s320/snuggie+visible.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Now, let's look behind the curtain with IR:
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4pM05CabI/AAAAAAAAAKg/lNEwZMLrL2g/s1600/snuggie+infra.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TU4pM05CabI/AAAAAAAAAKg/lNEwZMLrL2g/s320/snuggie+infra.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Look, I told you it was a Snuggie, the sleeve is visible! Now, if we had
more resolution, we could even pick out a person in a dark room, and
look at the temperature variations of objects. However, with
approximately an hour of fiddling and 3 dollars, I think we did pretty
good. We're not hard to entertain, but this definitely did the trick.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>camera</category><category>infrared</category><category>well-spent saturdays</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/life-in-the-infrared/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 06 Feb 2011 00:47:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Ask a Physicist: Volume I</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/ask-a-physicist-volume-i/</link><dc:creator>Jared</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/67/Convection-snapshot.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;We
have received our first &lt;em&gt;Ask a Physicist&lt;/em&gt; e-query! An entity known only
to us as "Hungry" writes:
"We had a dispute at a dinner party about whether blowing on hot food
actually makes it cool down faster, or only gives you something to do
while you wait for your food to cool."
While it is questionable whether or not I am indeed a physicist (but
people do pay me to do physics) and whether I will answer definitively
(there'll be some hand-waving), I'll give it my darndest.
Let's imagine a hot baked potato you just sliced open. The mass of
potato is capable of transferring energy as heat to the surrounding air
(and therefore cooling down) via a number of mechanisms. The most common
we hear about are conduction, radiation, and convection. Conduction is
the process by which two objects in intimate contact exchange heat.
Radiation is a bit more mysterious, but in the same way that a poker in
the fire can glow white hot, all things at non-zero temperature emit
electromagnetic radiation, which carries away energy from your potato.
Convection is even more complicated, but is one of the most important
processes by which solids exchange heat with gases. Convection in our
case occurs when the potato heats up the gas at its surface. The random
motion of air molecules (now a little hotter) will "randomly" dissipate
heat. However, the hotter gas is less dense than the room temperature
gas, and buoyant forces (think Helium balloon) will create a current of
hot gas upwards from the potato surface. Both of these processes
constitute convection.
Convection is REALLY hard to describe with physical models. You can do
some computer simulations of the motion of the gas in convection. I
found this cool picture on Wikipedia of someone who did just that:
&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/67/Convection-snapshot.gif"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/6/67/Convection-snapshot.gif"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Pretty cool. Now! To actually answer your question. To get a qualitative
answer, we don't even need to consider models of convection, etc. Isaac
Newton was kind enough to find an empirical relation for the process of
cooling, aptly named "Newton's law of cooling". If we call the amount of
heat transferred from the potato Q, the found that the rate of heat
being lost by the potato is proportional to the temperature difference
between the surrounding gas and the potato itself:
$$ \text{Rate of Heat Loss}=\frac{\text{Amount of Heat
Loss}}{\text{Amount of time}}=\frac{\Delta Q}{\Delta t} \propto
T_{\text{Potato}}-T_{\text{Air }} $$ So the quantity which is of
primary importance is the temperature difference between your potato and
the surrounding air. Now we can answer the question. If you let your
potato cool down naturally, then the potato heats the air which then
starts to convect. This means that the air immediately above the potato
is quite hot. If you blow on the potato, however, you get the air
circulating faster than it would by convection alone, effectively
replacing the hot air with slightly cooler air. And since the cooling
rate is proportional to to temperature difference; this will result in a
faster cooling rate. To first order, blowing on your food should help.
So, Hungry, feel free to blow on your food, Miss Manners be damned.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>ask a physicist</category><category>conduction</category><category>potato</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/ask-a-physicist-volume-i/</guid><pubDate>Mon, 17 May 2010 11:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Lessons in Prohibition: One</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/lessons-in-prohibition-one/</link><dc:creator>Jared</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;"Holy lack of self control, Batman!"
Cornell University Department of Physics-A P6510 Auxiliary Report
&lt;strong&gt;Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;
I feel terrible. Batman made me feel terrible. Batman also cost me 20
bucks.
&lt;strong&gt;Theoretical Background:&lt;/strong&gt;
You see, it's pretty natural for humans to place the mind and body
within hypothetical constraints. "What would it be like to be
deaf/blind? What if you didn't have an arm? What if you were forced to
watch reruns of Quantum Leap for 24 hours straight?". I guess this is in
some way a thinking-man's survival instinct. It's always prudent to be
prepared, even if just emotionally, and Scott Bakula can be kinda pushy.
We here at the Virtuosi believe in preparation. That's why we've decided
to convert one of our own (me) into a guinea pig. It is our goal to
apply some actual constraints to a real mind (mine) and to observe the
results, thereby gleaning valuable insights into how humans (me) respond
to adverse conditions (psychological torture).
&lt;strong&gt;Experimental Procedure:&lt;/strong&gt;
This week we started small. My task was the simple omission of a single
word from my written and spoken vocabulary. The word should be innocuous
enough that I wouldn't usually say it, but common enough not to be
obscure. The word chosen was BATMAN. I was to expressly abstain from the
use of BATMAN, else risk a monetary penalty (20 bucks), and if I were
successful after 1 week, I would gain a monetary reward (20 bucks). This
experiment (bet) began two days ago. I have obviously failed.
&lt;strong&gt;Data Tables:&lt;/strong&gt;
Data in this case, and always, will be presented with the utmost
objectivity (stream of consciousness).
&lt;strong&gt;Day one:&lt;/strong&gt;
Ha This is really easy Everybody keeps mentioning Shatfan&lt;strong&gt; though I
don't even know what we're testing I do kinda wanna say it though 20
bucks Shatfan feels kinda dirty Whatever this is dumb I have homework
maybe I should just stop thinking about Shatfan Nah This is kinda fun I
don't wanna lose 20 bucks I liked Val Kilmer as Shatfan, I can't believe
Nic disagrees Catban Batmatt HA thought I lost it there NOWP there are
so many alternatives Shut the hell up Corky [possessor of said $20] Oh
man everybody knows about this bet I might lose What if someone asks me
about fratcan in class?
&lt;/strong&gt;Day two:&lt;strong&gt;
I actually feel kinda gross thinking about Shatfan he's like in my mouth
please get him out this is all people talk about when I'm around oh yeah
thanks for that this week will at least be comical hey this might offset
the 500 bucks I owe corky maybe I could just say it and not tell anybody
ah but no that's not science and this is very obviously science&lt;em&gt;manbat
tabnam batfarm man of bats shatbat&lt;/em&gt; oh hey dad whats up yea we're doing
this thing where I cant say BATMAN...
Dad: oops! uh....
Me: crap. I have phone calls to make. I'll talk to you later dad.
&lt;em&gt;click&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;Post Failure Data:**
Batman is dirty. I don't even want to say it now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;Shatfan is the preferred euphemism for BATMAN.
&lt;/strong&gt;Analysis:&lt;strong&gt;
We therefore conclude it is impossible (for me) not to say BATMAN for
longer than approximately two days. It was assumed by observers that the
continual substitution of Shatfan and derivatives (highlighted above)
for BATMAN was purely cavalier. This is false. While a bit of joviality
was included in the experiment, a vast majority of euphemisms used were
to assuage psychological tension. This was accompanied by laughter to
maximize psychological relief. Obviously experimental procedures must be
altered. We propose now an alternate method of success, via locking the
subject in his office for a week.
&lt;/strong&gt;Conclusions:&lt;strong&gt;
In this report we find that I am a weakling, and that the experiment was
kind of lame. However, as a test run for future Prohibitive Tests (PTs)
we find the concept promising, in that when Scott Bakula comes around,
I'll be the only one ready to take him on.
Current developments in PTs include subject which are not fit for print,
and thus the authors invite suggestions in which a mundane aspect of my
life will be removed for the greater good of mankind.
&lt;/strong&gt;Acknowledgements:**
The authors would like to acknowledge that Corky is a shatfan. Stay
tuned for more.
-Jared&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Batman</category><category>cognitive dissonance</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/old/lessons-in-prohibition-one/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2010 20:56:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>