<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts by Matt)</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/authors/matt.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Thu, 24 Jan 2019 14:55:25 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Day in the life of Clicky</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/day-in-the-life-of-clicky/</link><dc:creator>Matt</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-og-KOzfbR1s/TeepA_j_e3I/AAAAAAAAB64/jboORBAZGsQ/s1600/soslow.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-og-KOzfbR1s/TeepA_j_e3I/AAAAAAAAB64/jboORBAZGsQ/s400/soslow.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Remember
when you first learned about other planets and their many fun facts? You
were probably bombarded by such truisms as: "Jupiter is approximately
the mass of 318 Earths, has a orbital period that is 4,300 Earth days,
is made out of pure love, and is mostly transparent." Well, I was
curious about what Clicky's day was like in terms of Earth days. When
did Clicky get to sleep, when did he eat dinner, what is his orbital
radius and eccentricity? To do this, I looked at only the 3rd column of
the data that you may or may not have downloaded yesterday from
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2011/05/clickin-night-away.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
Starting out, it should be noted that this is not an ordinary time
series where you have some value measured at given intervals. It is
actually a series of time points at which a click was entered. I thought
it would be most natural to go ahead and bins these to give a sense of
the access to Clicky over the past two months. It looks something like
this:
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-CGv4NMXIA_Y/TeenyMR2SEI/AAAAAAAAB6g/_GymFecaR4c/s1600/rawtimehist.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-CGv4NMXIA_Y/TeenyMR2SEI/AAAAAAAAB6g/_GymFecaR4c/s400/rawtimehist.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Well, that wasn't as informative as I had hoped. We see some spikes here
and there with a general trend toward neglect and abandonment towards
the end of the second month. What if we take these days and bin them
into one single day worth of traffic? We get this:
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bmZb_JtN4yg/TefICYE6zMI/AAAAAAAAB7I/xqsCiUjBtQE/s1600/oneday-hist.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-bmZb_JtN4yg/TefICYE6zMI/AAAAAAAAB7I/xqsCiUjBtQE/s400/oneday-hist.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Again, not so informative yet, but we are definitely starting to see
some structure in the day. In particular, there is a lot of activity in
the afternoon and evening with a definite lull around 5pm. There is also
a distinct minima around 5am. It appears that Clicky is on the average
most active between noon and 9pm, getting a break through most of the
night.
Next, let's look at the autocorrelation of the times. For standard time
series, the autocorrelation is defined to be
$$ C_{ss}(\tau) = \int_{-\infty}^{\infty}s(t) * \bar s(t-\tau)
dt $$
which measures the amount of similarity in a signal as a function of the
time separation between two points. Again, we don't have a continuous
signal, so our autocorrelation function is instead a histogram of the
all-pairs differences in the data points that we do have. That is, start
at the first time point and subtract it from all of the other time
points in the series. Then, move to the next data point and subtract it
from all the subsequent times while keeping tracking of all of these
differences. This is our autocorrelation in real space.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-TcTlLQL4ccw/TefSgRN3KrI/AAAAAAAAB7Q/aLHgDXT-ZOU/s1600/time-time2-raw.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-TcTlLQL4ccw/TefSgRN3KrI/AAAAAAAAB7Q/aLHgDXT-ZOU/s400/time-time2-raw.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
We can also zoom in and smooth the data a bit
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-VRWxWGORJt0/TefSrrD-DHI/AAAAAAAAB7Y/FncLYViZ3Jw/s1600/time-time2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-VRWxWGORJt0/TefSrrD-DHI/AAAAAAAAB7Y/FncLYViZ3Jw/s400/time-time2.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Ah,
now there we go. We see a distinct over-abundance of time differences
around 1 day, 2 days, etc. What is the primary oscillation we see in the
correlation? To see that, let's look at the frequency space
autocorrelation and plot its power, or square.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-CKFrfzY37Uc/TefTfvhS5pI/AAAAAAAAB7g/njevnB4JPac/s1600/time-time-power.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-CKFrfzY37Uc/TefTfvhS5pI/AAAAAAAAB7g/njevnB4JPac/s400/time-time-power.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Finally,
we get the primary component of the variation of Clicky's visits
throughout the 2 month period that he was in operation. It occurs, to
within error, at 1 day. No very surprising at all. I'm sure we could
look more closely at the peak and its width, but I am satisfied to say
that Clicky's day is defined by the Earth day to within a few percent.
*In response to more messages in Clicky, we agree that it is "So slow."
Rest assured, management is looking into the problem.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>autocorrelation</category><category>clicky</category><category>fourier</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/day-in-the-life-of-clicky/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 01 Jun 2011 16:34:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Clicky Data v1.0</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/clicky-data-v1-0/</link><dc:creator>Matt</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-2c6Bjhd3XmI/TeUNGvesUiI/AAAAAAAAB6I/5ndWL1d8AXQ/s1600/snap.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-2c6Bjhd3XmI/TeUNGvesUiI/AAAAAAAAB6I/5ndWL1d8AXQ/s400/snap.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
As we sift through the Clicky data Corky presented yesterday, let us not
forget the Clicky that came before.
Let us not forget the Great Server Move of 2011 and the great pains we
felt while waiting for Clicky to come back to us: Corky sat in his room
crying into his pillow, Alex was pressing his arrow keys longingly, and
I just couldn't seem to get up in the morning. Let us not forget the
many hours in which untold numbers of anonymous internet users tried in
vain to spell simple words using only discrete steps on a finite
lattice. Let us not forget the Great Server Crash that caused the
physics department to be charged extra for data usage. Let us not forget
Clicky v1.0.
So today we remember him, our beloved Clicky v1.0, by releasing his data
as well. It can be found close to the other Clicky data dump from
yesterday at this location:
&lt;a href="http://www.mattbierbaum.com/clicky/clickydat2.tar.bz2"&gt;Download Clicky
v1.0&lt;/a&gt;
Be warned, this was actually available to the anonymous internet and
there are a few things that may surprise you. That being said, the last
half of this data set is actually comprised of multiple users
interacting with Clicky at once so it should have different statistics
than yesterday's data, though we have yet to sort through that too. More
of our analysis is to follow..
Also, props to whoever made the dinosaur.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>clicky</category><category>not absurdly large images</category><category>picopixels</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/clicky-data-v1-0/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 31 May 2011 11:36:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Exploration of Cameras I</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/exploration-of-cameras-i/</link><dc:creator>Matt</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;In the next posts, I'd like to attempt to make a camera from 'scratch.'
And by that, I mean explore the creation of cameras from their
components and then create a very primitive one from readily available
materials.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In terms of history and simplicity, we should start with the pinhole
camera. I've heard stories that Newton used a pinhole camera to look at
the sun though I don't know if this was before or after he stared
directly at it for 8 minutes. The pinhole is neat because it is so
simple. With a pinhole, light is focused simply by restricting the paths
which an incident ray may take to hit our film. Typically, diffuse and
specular scattering sends light bouncing every which way off an object.
The pinhole just restricts which directions hit the film. I think a
picture is a better guide to this concept.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtOYzRfZAI/AAAAAAAAB3Y/MoKfumAjRTs/s400/pinholes2.png"&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For a small hole (aperture) there is approximately one area of the
object that will send rays to a particular part of the image. Of course
there is a very small angle of error for pinhole cameras made with
millimeter sized pins. As the hole increases in size, more rays are
incident to the same section of film. And finally, when the hole is big
enough for the whole object to be seen through it (think window), no
cohesive image is formed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we make the hole small enough, then we can have all the clarity we
want, right? Well, I guess so. It would have to be a very circular hole
and it would only let in a very tiny amount of light making exposure
times long. How to fix this?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Yea, you guessed it. A lens is the answer. It is able to focus light on
its own. Now we can collect more light and still make clear images. But
the catch is that it only works for a range of distances. So again, lets
consider a lens and the images of two objects at different distances.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtO6Js1a6I/AAAAAAAAB3g/6s0Nh2XYoFY/s1600/lenses2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtO6Js1a6I/AAAAAAAAB3g/6s0Nh2XYoFY/s400/lenses2.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Ray drawing can be done with 3 simple rules (though two are needed in
practice).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rays that go in parallel to the axis go out through the focal point&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rays that go in through the focal point go out parallel (time
    reversal symmetry)&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;rays that go through the center are not altered&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using these rules, the first object which is at the proper distance for
the film position and focal length of the lens is in focus. However, the
rays from the object further away do not converge at the film and so are
out of focus.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here its time for two experiments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\1) &lt;strong&gt;The Window Camera&lt;/strong&gt; Go to a room with a single window and cover it
with thick paper that has a single hole in it. Given enough light, you
should see an image on the far wall. If not, hold a piece of white paper
up close to the hole. [Edit: I just learned this has a name: &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Camera_obscura"&gt;camera
obscura&lt;/a&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;\2) &lt;strong&gt;The Doorway Camera&lt;/strong&gt; Now, find a lens and a doorway. In one room,
leave the light on and go to the far wall in the dark room. Bring the
lens to the wall until you can see an image. The doorway is the
aperature, lens the lens, and wall the film. This demonstration is very
simple and not too surprising. BUT SO COOL. I encourage it &lt;em&gt;vigorously&lt;/em&gt;.
The following pictures were taken of my images in case you can't find a
lens. [Edit: I guess this falls under camera obscura too]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtR0FcieuI/AAAAAAAAB3o/AETwbMrWO_A/s1600/bailey-real.JPG"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtR0FcieuI/AAAAAAAAB3o/AETwbMrWO_A/s400/bailey-real.JPG"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Bailey Hall through a window in the physics building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtSCaBSQZI/AAAAAAAAB3w/YePJ9Jy-Qj0/s1600/bailey-lens.JPG"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtSCaBSQZI/AAAAAAAAB3w/YePJ9Jy-Qj0/s400/bailey-lens.JPG"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Same scene as imaged with a lens using the window as an aperture.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtS-MYX9RI/AAAAAAAAB34/VSLnyE4Gbs8/s1600/light%2Bfixture.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtS-MYX9RI/AAAAAAAAB34/VSLnyE4Gbs8/s320/light%2Bfixture.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Image of a ceiling light with a smaller lens&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtTSBzC1LI/AAAAAAAAB4A/W6xD0OEykkk/s1600/psb.JPG"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtTSBzC1LI/AAAAAAAAB4A/W6xD0OEykkk/s320/psb.JPG"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Physical
Sciences Building imaged on wood.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtTqmUzTPI/AAAAAAAAB4I/rDMMFj5AsJE/s1600/small.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TUtTqmUzTPI/AAAAAAAAB4I/rDMMFj5AsJE/s320/small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;An
extra small image (\~1cm on a side) from the lens that will be in next
post's camera.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Together, these two elements – aperture and lens – make a very good
camera. The lens is able to collect a lot of light and focus it on the
film. The aperture can enhance clarity by reducing the number of paths
that light rays can take to your lens. It also provides higher order
corrections that come from the fact that the lens is probably not
perfect. That is, lenses are notorious for misbehaving around the edges
and introduce displacements in the whole image as well as between the
colors. The aperture helps keep light from traveling through these
edges.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next time, a very simple camera.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/exploration-of-cameras-i/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 03 Feb 2011 19:50:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Zombpocalypse</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/zombpocalypse/</link><dc:creator>Matt</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Here at the Virtuosi, we're concerned. We are concerned that perhaps the
world is really not ready for a zombie apocalypse. You know, the kind of
zombie apocalypse that you may have seen in such classics as "Night of
the Living Dead", "Shaun of the Dead", or perhaps the even more recent
"Zombieland" (sweet cameo by the way). The kind of zombpocalypse that
could leave major cities void of life and the country plagued with the
undead.
Well, Alemi and I were curious as to how likely such a pandemic was to
occur and what it would look like in the simplest of models. In typical
Virtuosi fashion, we threw some physics at it and this is what we came
up with.
&lt;strong&gt;The Model&lt;/strong&gt;:
Taking cues from the epidemiologists, we feel that the spread of
zombie-ism might fall into a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Compartmental_models_in_epidemiology"&gt;compartmental
model&lt;/a&gt;
that is much like the heavily studied SIR model. Here, there are
susceptibles, S, that get infected, I, and can subsequently infect other
susceptibles or recover, R, and not play a part in the disease dynamics
anymore. Our analogous model is the SZR model in which there are
susceptibles, S, once again that can be bitten by a zombie to become
another zombie, Z. However, this is a huge difference - a susceptible
must then kill a zombie (by destroying the brain of cause) to make it
removed, R. Hence, we have the SZR disease model.
Like with the compartmental models, one can write down a set of
differential equations that govern the dynamics of disease in a
population. However, these might not be the best option for simulation
as the population is represented as a continuous variable. After all,
there can't be 1/100th of a zombie roaming around biting ankles causing
a new epidemic after all of this partners have been killed off. To get
around this, we set up a discrete contact network where each node is one
of the three states of the model and there are set probabilities of the
three states interacting when they are neighbors. In particular if there
is a susceptible with a zombie neighbor then there is a probability
&lt;strong&gt;b&lt;/strong&gt; that the zombie will bite the susceptible turning the node into a
zombie. In the same time step, there is a probability &lt;strong&gt;k&lt;/strong&gt; that the
susceptible will kill the zombie putting it in the removed class. Both
of these actions can happen in one time step of the simulation. However,
the two actions can't happen sequentially to the same node. That is, a
newly bitten susceptible must be a zombie for at least one time step
before it can be removed adding a latent period for the infection.
&lt;strong&gt;Simulations:&lt;/strong&gt;
With these rules, we created networks with average connectivity k=8
(probably way too low) with up to N=40,000 susceptibles. Patient zero
was seeded at a random location and the simulation run until there were
no more susceptible - zombie neighbor pairs.
A typical simulation looks something like:
Here, the blue represent the susceptibles and red zombies. More subtly,
the removed are shown in black. You may also notice that the zombies
actually wrap around as they spread due to periodic boundary conditions.
And so we ran many of these simulations for various values of N, b, and
k to see what type of dynamics arise. As the ratio of b/k is increased
and zombies become proportionally better at biting susceptibles than
they are at killing the zombies, we see a transition from little to no
infection to mass pandemic in what appears to be a sort of percolation
transition.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TC1xAXdRNKI/AAAAAAAAB04/4_SC8vFPUF0/s1600/cp.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TC1xAXdRNKI/AAAAAAAAB04/4_SC8vFPUF0/s320/cp.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In the figure red is the fraction of zombies in the final population and
green is the amount of time that the simulation took to run. The spike
in time around the critical point shows critical slowing down as also
seen in the length of the movie above. Also, the ending configuration of
zombies shows a fractal like structure near the critical point. Using
the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Minkowski%E2%80%93Bouligand_dimension"&gt;box-counting&lt;/a&gt;
method, we actually calculated the fractal dimension:
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TC1zP2doE3I/AAAAAAAAB1I/Hfsl9e-TIaI/s1600/fractal.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/TC1zP2doE3I/AAAAAAAAB1I/Hfsl9e-TIaI/s320/fractal.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
This helps us pinpoint the epidemic transition at a ratio of b/k = 1.4.
This means for our particular network type and assumptions on the
infectious nature of zombie-ism that zombies must be 40% better at
biting than we are at lopping heads for an epidemic to take off. Even
then, there must be a much larger ratio of b/k for more than 50% of the
population to become part of the undead.
I trust that we the living would be at least as capable as the undead so
any potential zombie scenario would seem to be stifled in our model. But
then again, what about fast zombies? Now those things are scary.
&lt;strong&gt;Update:&lt;/strong&gt;
I had a quick thought that mobile zombies might be a bit more realistic.
I made a quick movie where zombies pursue the closest susceptible while
the susceptibles run away from the zombies at the same speed. You will
see an area clear around the initial infection as the zombies give
chase. By accident, two zombies will collide providing the spark for an
epidemic. An explosion of zombies results. More to follow!&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>monte carlo</category><category>simulation</category><category>video</category><category>zombies</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/zombpocalypse/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 01 Jul 2010 23:48:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Bubbles!</title><link>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/bubbles-/</link><dc:creator>Matt</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/S8TMvnGGX6I/AAAAAAAABzU/_o0PHaRQLmg/s1600/good-small.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_qY9DSyjj8Ro/S8TMvnGGX6I/AAAAAAAABzU/_o0PHaRQLmg/s320/good-small.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Ever wonder why don't you see a standard rainbow when looking at a thin
film such as soap stretched across a membrane ready for bubble making?
Well, I encountered this problem when I presented my intro physics
section with a quiz question today. Properly stated, the question was...
"Suppose white light is incident on a thin film (a soap bubble of
n=1.33) hanging vertically inside of a square loop. The minimum
thickness of the film at the top of the loop is 900nm and it increases
linearly (due to gravity) to 1300nm by the bottom of the loop which is
10cm away. This means that the thickness as a function of distance from
the top of the loop is
$$ d(x) = \text{900nm} + \text{400nm} * \left(
\frac{x}{\text{10cm}} \right) $$
What wavelengths will be most strongly reflected as a function of
distance along our bubble film?"
So I got to thinking - don't the partially interfering wavelengths also
contribute to the image that our eyes see? Isn't there a better mass
profile to use such as an exponential? Linear is just silly.
As for the first question, if you consider a single ray entering the
thin film and reflecting off both the first interface as well as the
second, then there is a phase difference between the two reflected
waves,
$$ \Delta \phi = \pi + 2\pi * \frac{2d}{\lambda} $$
where d is the thickness of the film and lambda is the wavelength. If we
consider these two waves as two standing waves added together with a
phase then we see that the superposition of their electric fields, for
example, is
$$ E_{tot} = E_0 \cos(\omega t) + E_0 \cos(\omega t + \Delta
\phi) $$
$$ E_{tot} = E_0 \sin(\omega t) \cos(\Delta \phi) $$
The intensity that our eyes see then goes like the square of this giving
an effective damping to certain wavelengths as given by
$$ \delta = \cos^2(\Delta \phi) $$
Using a more realistic exponential mass profile and this damping factor
for wavelengths in the visible spectrum, I created the top image using
OpenIL (maybe it's called DevIL, hard to say).&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>bubbles</category><category>interference</category><category>thin films</category><guid>https://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/bubbles-/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 13 Apr 2010 15:33:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>