<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts by Nik Zhelev)</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/authors/nik-zhelev.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 22:55:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Entropy and the Arrow of Time</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/entropy-and-the-arrow-of-time/</link><dc:creator>Nik Zhelev</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Somebody I talked to yesterday about what should the topic of my post be
suggested that I should write something about cosmology, in particular
the Big Bang and the ultimate fate of the universe. Being mostly
interested in condensed matter, I am by no means an expert in cosmology
(I’ll leave that to Corky). However, I will not abandon the request, but
instead, spin it in a more condensed matter direction, by talking about
Entropy.
Entropy is a quantity that measures disorder. The more ordered your
system is, i.e. the less ways you can arrange the constituents of your
system, the less entropy you have and vice versa. I like to use the
example of how messy my room is to visualize this. When I clean my room,
I would pick up the random articles of clothing, books, etc and put them
in the places where they belong. Now imagine, I stopped cleaning my room
for a couple of weeks. This would result in clothes on the ground, books
on my bed, empty bottles on my desk, etc. anything can be anywhere. This
means that there are more ways for my personal belongings to be arranged
when my room is messy than when my room is clean (when everything would
be at its place), so the entropy increases as the messiness of my room
increases. Now, notice that left on its own (i.e. if I don’t put the
conscious effort to put some order in my room once in a while) the
entropy of the system that is my room increases with time. This is, in
fact, the essence of one of the most fundamental (if not the most
fundamental) laws of nature – The Second Law of Thermodynamics, which
states that left on its own, the entropy of any system increases with
time.
I know what you are thinking, “What does this talk about the messiness
of your room and the law of increasing entropy has to do with the
universe, the Big Bang and the universe’s ultimate fate?” Ok, here you
go, read this short story by the greatest sci-fi writer Isaac Asimov:
&lt;a href="http://bit.ly/84LN"&gt;The Last Question.&lt;/a&gt;
Now that you’ve read this story (if you haven’t, please do), we can
discuss some physics (or actually, some philosophy, but you know,
sometimes there isn’t that much difference between the two). Einstein,
with his Theory of Relativity, showed that the concept of time is not
absolute, and time can be treated simply as another coordinate, much
like the three spatial coordinates that define the three dimensional
space we are used to. (A more in-depth explanation of the Theory of
Relativity will be the topic of one of the next posts.) However, despite
the relativity of time, the arrow of time is always well-defined. We can
always tell future from past by measuring the entropy and applying the
Second Law of Thermodynamics. At the instance of the Big Bang, the
entropy was zero. Since then (about 13.8 billion years ago) the entropy
of the universe has been increasing until it will eventually reach its
maximum value, at which point all the matter of the universe would be
evenly distributed and no physical process would be possible. Time
eventually stops, resulting in the “heat death” of the universe.
I believe that one of the most unsettling parts of the Bing Bang theory
is the question of what caused the Big Bang, and what was there before
the Bing Bang. Having the arrow of time defined with regards to entropy,
however, makes this question nonsensical… unless, of course, a Cosmic AC
(or God) has managed to find the answer of how the entropy can be
reversed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/entropy-and-the-arrow-of-time/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2010 21:27:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Physics for non-physicists</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/physics-for-non-physicists/</link><dc:creator>Nik Zhelev</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;This is my first (but certainly not the last) post in this blog, so let
me introduce myself. My name is Nikolay, and as most of the others
contributing to the blog, I am also a first-year graduate student in
physics at Cornell.
So, what is my motivation to join the team headed by Mr. Alemi in
contributing to the blog? I happen to have many friends that are not in
physics. In fact, probably due to the fact that I graduated from a
liberal arts college, many of my friends have never taken any physics
beyond that one class in high school, which due to both the inherent
difficulty of teaching physics at introductory level and the lack of
good high school physics teachers was often an unpleasant experience
that scared them away from physics for life. Now, imagine what my
difficulty is when on a daily basis I have to answer the question: “So
what do you study/work on as a graduate student?” I usually try to come
up with a sentence or two describing the essence of what I am doing
without going into too many details, but even that is a daunting task.
There seems to be a disconnect between the world in which a physicist
lives and the general public. As Chad Orzel pointed out in the talk that
motivated the creation of this blog, this is not the general public’s
fault, but our fault as physicists of not really committing enough
effort in relating our knowledge to the rest of the world.
In short, my goal is to create a series of posts about physics geared to
people with no physics background that would build upon each other and
culminate with a post providing an answer to the question of what my
research project is beyond the generic words I would often resort to
that would rather leave most people confused. I plan to use as little
math as possible, which will not be an easy task considering that math
is the language of choice for physics. However, mathematics is just a
tool, and physics is not about equations and complicated algebra, but
about how nature works, which we should be able to formulate in plain
English. I know I am embarking on a difficult task, so wish me luck, and
please leave your thoughts in the remarks section of the blog, since any
feedback would be appreciated.&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/physics-for-non-physicists/</guid><pubDate>Fri, 16 Apr 2010 16:36:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>