<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<?xml-stylesheet type="text/xsl" href="../assets/xml/rss.xsl" media="all"?><rss version="2.0" xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Virtuosi (Posts by Sam)</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/authors/sam.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"></atom:link><language>en</language><copyright>Contents © 2019 &lt;a href="mailto:thephysicsvirtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;The Virtuosi&lt;/a&gt; </copyright><lastBuildDate>Wed, 23 Jan 2019 22:55:56 GMT</lastBuildDate><generator>Nikola (getnikola.com)</generator><docs>http://blogs.law.harvard.edu/tech/rss</docs><item><title>Paradigm Shifts 3: With a Vengence</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/paradigm-shifts-3-with-a-vengence/</link><dc:creator>Sam</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;The last shift I wanted to present is best explained at
&lt;a href="http://tauday.com/"&gt;http://tauday.com/&lt;/a&gt; . There you will find a
manifesto (yes, a manifesto) about why we should change from using $$
\pi = \text{180 degrees} $$ as the circle constant to $$ \tau = 2
\pi = \text{360 degrees} $$ It's quite a convincing argument, and it's
a shift that can easily be made. Check the website for more. TAU VS PI
&lt;a href="http://tauday.com/images/figures/tau-angles.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://tauday.com/images/figures/tau-angles.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/paradigm-shifts-3-with-a-vengence/</guid><pubDate>Thu, 21 Oct 2010 14:32:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Paradigm Shifts 2: Paradigm ShiftER</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/paradigm-shifts-2-paradigm-shifter/</link><dc:creator>Sam</dc:creator><description>&lt;div&gt;&lt;p&gt;Last time, I presented reasons why it would be economically infeasible
for the US to switch to the metric system. This time, I'd like to talk
about a change that could relatively easily be brought about soon. A
change that would barely cost a thing, but could improve efficiency
dramatically in many jobs and in every day life for many people. A
change of this type would be very handy. Puns aside though, what I'm
talking about is this: DVORAK SIMPLIFIED KEYBOARD (again lots from
Wikipedia)
&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/500px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/500px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/1000px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/1000px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/1000px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Look down at your keyboard. Chances are very good that if you bought
your keyboard in an English speaking country, you're using the QWERTY
keyboard layout. You'll also probably know (or else you'll learn from
me) that the letter "E" is the most common in the English language. You
might wonder then, why it's not in the "home row" (the row of keys in
the middle of the keyboard that would be right under your fingers if
you're typing in the standard way). You might also wonder why other
common letters like "T" were exiled to the top row while less common
letters like "J" and "K" sit right under your fingertips as they rest
idle. You may then think about how slow it is to type words like
"December" which require you to use the same finger for consecutive
letters. You may even get to thinking that a lot of words require using
the same hand for consecutive letters, but it would be much nicer to
alternate hands as you type. The reasons for the slow speed of QWERTY
are not entirely clear. There are stories floating around about the
inventor of the typewriter deliberately laying out the keyboard this way
to keep typing speeds down so that the mechanical keys wouldn't jam. The
authenticity of these stories are disputed, but you'd be hard pressed to
argue that QWERTY is the most efficient layout there could be. One
competitor for the title that has stood out is called Dvorak, named
after its creator. Some statistics from Wikipedia (sources given there):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"the Dvorak layout uses about 63% of the finger motion required by
    QWERTY"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"the vast majority of the Dvorak layout's key strokes (70%) are done
    in the home row" whereas QWERTY "has only 32% of the strokes done in
    the home row"&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"The QWERTY layout has more than 3,000 words that are typed on the
    left hand alone and about 300 words that are typed on the right hand
    alone", but "with the Dvorak layout, only a few words can be typed
    on the left hand and not one syllable can be typed with the right
    hand alone, much less a word."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"On QWERTY keyboards, 56% of the typing strokes are done by the left
    hand. As the left hand is weaker for the majority of people, the
    Dvorak keyboard puts the more often used keys on the right hand
    side, thereby having 56% of the typing strokes done by the right
    hand."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"Because the Dvorak layout requires less finger motion from the
    typist compared to QWERTY, many users with repetitive strain
    injuries have reported that switching from QWERTY to Dvorak
    alleviated or even eliminated their repetitive strain injury."&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;"The fastest English language typist in the world, according to The
    Guinness Book of World Records" achieved "a peak speed of 212 wpm"
    using Dvorak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so maybe by now you see that Dvorak can be more efficient. So why
hasn't it been implemented yet? Well, back in the typewriter era, it was
one layout or the other, and people picked QWERTY. Look at Wikipedia for
a summary. But now, assuming you're not using a typewriter or a 386 or
something equivalently ancient, it's actually quite easy to switch back
and forth between QWERTY and Dvorak. Check out your control panel if
you're on a PC (or the equivalent on a mac or linux or what have you)
and I bet you'll find the setting for changing the keyboard layout
pretty easily, and I bet that Dvorak will be one of the layouts you can
choose. So it's easy enough to switch all the devices to the new system,
with pretty much no cost. The problem is of course that hardly anybody
can type with Dvorak. Everybody is used to QWERTY! And I'm sure there
are people out there who are happy to try to learn Dvorak, but I'm not
one of them. I'm used to QWERTY and I'm pretty sure if I tried to
switch, I'd get confused and completely jumble the two systems. I just
can't see the slight increase in my typing speed being worth the hassle.
Maybe some can, but I'm sure that many feel the same way I do,
especially those who, like me, don't do a lot of transcribing or the
like, and so rarely need to type very fast. The key? (sorry, no more
puns, I promise) Get 'em while they're young. That's right, all the
young typists out there can be trained on Dvorak instead of QWERTY. If
they never learn QWERTY, they'll never be confused. And they can use the
same keyboards as everyone else. All that we'd have to do is make it
easier to switch the keyboard layout (put something a little closer than
the control panel, maybe right on the keyboard), and print two sets of
characters on the keyboard when they are made (note that I've neglected
cell phones and other devices that also have keyboards, but they can be
updated in the same way). It would be as easy as that to implement the
change. Give it maybe 5-10 years to phase in keyboards and operating
systems with the easy-switch built in (in this case, it's nice that
computers have such short life spans), then have schools start teaching
kids to use Dvorak in typing classes. In a generation, hardly anyone
will even remember QWERTY except as a weird hiccup along the way to
efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</description><category>Dvorak</category><category>puns</category><category>QWERTY</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/paradigm-shifts-2-paradigm-shifter/</guid><pubDate>Sun, 19 Sep 2010 23:55:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Quantum Chess!</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/quantum-chess-/</link><dc:creator>Sam</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.showiphonewallpapers.com/iPhonewallpapers/20102/iphonewallpapers/Chess-20100726.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://www.showiphonewallpapers.com/iPhonewallpapers/20102/iphonewallpapers/Chess-20100726.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Ever find out when you're playing chess that the Queen you reached for
is actually a pawn? Probably not. But most chess games aren't affected
by the weirdness of the quantum world. This one is:
&lt;a href="http://research.cs.queensu.ca/Parallel/QuantumChess/QuantumChess.html"&gt;http://research.cs.queensu.ca/Parallel/QuantumChess/QuantumChess.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/quantum-chess-/</guid><pubDate>Wed, 08 Sep 2010 21:48:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title>Paradigm Shifts 1</title><link>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/paradigm-shifts-1/</link><dc:creator>Sam</dc:creator><description>&lt;p&gt;Hi everybody, I'm Sam, and this will be my first contribution to the
blog! (cue applause) It will not be a physical modeling exercise;
instead I will be writing a little bit about about paradigm shifts in a
series of a few posts. I hope it will provoke some interesting
discussion. "But Sam," you ask, "Isn't 'paradigm shift' just a buzzword
that people use to sound important?" Well, maybe, but it's also useful
phrase used to describe a substantial change in the way something is
done. Consider, for example, THE METRIC SYSTEM (many details from
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Metric_system"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;)
&lt;a href="http://www.debateitout.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/metric-system.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://www.debateitout.com/wp-content/uploads/2009/11/metric-system.jpg"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In 1791, in the wake of revolution, France became the first country to
adopt the recently developed metric system. Since then, every nation in
the world has officially adopted the metric system except Liberia,
Burma, and the United States. It is the standard measurement system for
most physical science, even in the US (as far as I know, no other unit
system even has a measurement for quantities like electric field or
magnetic field) (also, when I say metric, I of course include cgs and
mks and ignore systems that are not meant for measurement, like natural
units and Planck units). It has the advantages of easy unit conversion
(1 km = 1000 m vs 1 mile = 5280 ft, a value which I had to look up from
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/09/remembering-two-things.html"&gt;Yariv's
post&lt;/a&gt;),
and lack of ambiguity in units (mass = kg, force = N vs mass = lbs_mass
or stones, force = lbs_force). The strong preference of scientists for
the metric system is evident from past experiences: From
&lt;a href="http://www.cnn.com/TECH/space/9909/30/mars.metric.02/"&gt;CNN&lt;/a&gt;, September
1999: "NASA lost a $125 million Mars orbiter because a Lockheed Martin
engineering team used English units of measurement while the agency's
team used the more conventional metric system for a key spacecraft
operation" This story also illustrates the equally strong preference of
engineers for the English system. Ah, and herein lies the problem. You
see, when the metric system was first adopted in Europe, it created a
standardized unit system. This proved useful to merchants selling their
wares by weight, but more relevant to myself as a scientist, it provided
a means for creating scientific recipes, for providing the utterly
essential aspect of reproducibility to scientific experiments. However,
now the standardization exists even with the English system, given a
simple unit conversion. But why not adopt the metric system to avoid
situations like the Mars orbiter and make me less confused when I cross
the border to Canada and see speed limit signs telling me to do 80?
&lt;em&gt;Because it would be too huge of a paradigm shift&lt;/em&gt;. Allow me to
illustrate my point.
One of the most (if not the most) strongly affected groups by a change
in measurement systems is manufacturers, ie people who make stuff. I
will use a typical example of a manufacturer, the kind who I interact
with in my lab: the noble machinist (keep in mind that machinists are
very important, as they are required to make many, many products). If
you have ever worked with a machinist in the states, chances are he or
she will be totally confused if you try to give them dimensions in
millimeters (I have done this, and they weren't very happy with me
because it meant they had to convert all the dimensions I gave them into
English). It would be extremely difficult to retrain people who have
used the English system all their lives. It would be like learning a new
language. Inevitably, it would cause a large number of mistakes. More
significantly, they would have to get ENTIRELY new equipment. Every
machine shop would have to completely replace their tools (drill bits,
screwdrivers, wrenches etc) and materials (standardized sizes of bolts,
nuts, sheet and bulk material, pipes, connectors, cables, etc etc). You
could say, "Come on, it wouldn't be so bad! Listen, we could gradually
phase out the old English equipment and just make everything in metric
from now on!" However, I would counter that this is not a realistic
plan. For starters, there's the problem of having to keep around two
sets of equipment (one for the old English stuff and one for the new
metric stuff), which would require double the space and double the
maintenance. Second, there would be compatibility issues between new and
old equipment (e.g. my old 3/4" ipod port wouldn't mate with my new 2 cm
connector). Third, the previous two problems would likely be around for
a long time, considering the age of some of the equipment that I've seen
in labs and elsewhere.
And I haven't even mentioned the economics. If basic parts manufacturers
(the people who make the screws, the bolts, and the sheet metal that
will later be made into products) began to offer metric parts (now that
I think about it, maybe they already do?), I doubt anybody would buy
them. It would cost them too much to replace all their machinery
infrastructure. There would be no market for them. Maybe you would then
ask "Well, what if the government made everybody switch to metric?"
Well, other than the backlash this would cause towards whichever
administration suggested this, it would likely hurt and maybe even
bankrupt companies who were forced to switch. As far as I can tell, it
would definitely hurt the US economy in the short term (but it might
help other countries who could sell their metric wares here) and not
help it at all in the long term. To me, the economic loss (not to
mention the difficulty in convincing the US population to swallow the
change) outweighs the advantages of switching. At this point, exhausted
from my challenging you at every turn, you may finally say, "Well hey,
SPEAKING of Canada, they changed to the metric system only in 1973. How
did THEY do it??" The answer is that, well, they didn't. Not entirely
anyway. Sure, the country may package food and make road signs in metric
(which the US could probably do, if people could somehow be convinced to
go along with it), but in fact their engineering materials, which mostly
come from the states, are still in English units. Even Canada couldn't
justify completely converting to the metric system Which just goes to
show how difficult it is to pull off a paradigm shift. Next time, I'll
present an example of a paradigm shift that I think COULD work.&lt;/p&gt;</description><category>Canada</category><category>English</category><category>metric</category><category>Paradigm shift</category><guid>https://virtuosi.alexalemi.com/posts/old/paradigm-shifts-1/</guid><pubDate>Tue, 07 Sep 2010 23:01:00 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>