<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/pages.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2010-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><entry><title>About Us</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/about-us.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>The Virtuosi</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-01-01:posts/about-us.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;We are a bunch of Physics Graduate students at Cornell. Our interests vary. Our
aim is to share a bit of the fun of physics with the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A note on the name: The virtuosi was the original name for the members of the
original Royal Society, they were a bunch of interested individuals who would
meet twice monthly in London to discuss the topics of interest in the budding
field of science. The Royal Society would go on to become the premier
scientific institution in the coming years, but they had rather humble
beginnings, one of their early meetings being dedicated to testing whether
unicorn horn powder could deter&amp;nbsp;spiders.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A note on the masthead: &amp;#8220;Giving some account of the undertakings, studies, and
labors of the ingenious in many considerable parts of the Cornell physics
department.&amp;#8221; is a ripoff of the masthead for the original Royal Society
publication Philosophical Transactions, whose masthead read: &amp;#8220;Giving some
account of the undertakings, studies, and labors of the ingenious in many
considerable parts of the world.&amp;#8221; Seen&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="philisophical transactions" src="/static/images/philosophical-transactions.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is in this spirit that we aim to share some physics. Some of it silly, some
of it serious, but all of it&amp;nbsp;interesting. &lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry><entry><title>Contributors</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/contributors.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-01-01T00:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>The Virtuosi</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-01-01:posts/contributors.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alemi&lt;/em&gt; is a PhD physics graduate student at Cornell University.  I will be
working this summer with the Sethna Group working on a project related to
inter-atomic potentials in metals.  I got my Bachelor&amp;#8217;s from Caltech majoring
in physics.  I enjoy reading the interwebs, thinking about crazy physics
problems, dimensional analysis, and fermi problems.  I have a real thirst for
arcane and interesting&amp;nbsp;trivia..&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Alex&lt;/em&gt; is an experimental solid state physics graduate student in the Ralph Group
at Cornell.  He enjoys physics, but hopes to eventually switch fields into
giant&amp;nbsp;robot-building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Corky&lt;/em&gt; was discovered by Czech explorers in Greenland in the early 13th century
writing autobiographical sketches in the 3rd person.  He is now a PhD physics
graduate student at Cornell&amp;nbsp;University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DTC&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt; is a physics graduate student at Cornell.  He enjoys network science,
infectious disease dynamics, the history of science, word games, hiking,
traveling, octopodes, and&amp;nbsp;Batman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jared&lt;/em&gt; was made by other people.  He makes accelerators.  Start a band with him.
Addendum by Jesse:  He is a PhD physics graduate student at Cornell&amp;nbsp;University.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Jesse&lt;/em&gt; is a PhD physics graduate student at Cornell University.  He is working
with Rob Thorne&amp;#8217;s group.  He did his undergraduate at Oberlin College, where he
majored in physics and mathematics.  In his spare time, he reads lots of books,
and when the weather is nice he likes to go on hikes.  He also likes cats, and
has two cats of his very&amp;nbsp;own.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Both illusive and aloof, &lt;em&gt;Js&lt;/em&gt; (short for Jesse, as in tie-Jesse, and as in not
the other Jesse) has the amazing super-human ability to offend people at faster
than light speed.  Little is known about this creature, for sightings are rare
and brief.  However, when he does emerge from the lab, be sure to ask about the
time he (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CENSORED&lt;/span&gt;) (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CENSORED&lt;/span&gt;) (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CENSORED&lt;/span&gt;) with a massive (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CENSORED&lt;/span&gt;) (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CENSORED&lt;/span&gt;).
You won&amp;#8217;t believe this true tale!  Oh, also, Jesse graduated from Northeastern
University with &lt;span class="caps"&gt;B.S.&lt;/span&gt; degrees in physics, math and philosophy.  He now continues
his studies at the Cornell physics&amp;nbsp;department.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Like the rest of the Virtuosi, &lt;em&gt;Nic Eggert&lt;/em&gt; is a PhD student at Cornell. He works
on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CMS&lt;/span&gt; experiment, one of the detectors at the Large Hadron Collider. Nic
got his undergraduate degree in physics from the University of Minnesota. In
his spare time (not that he has much), he enjoys reading, playing video games,
playing bass guitar, and brewing&amp;nbsp;beer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Sam&lt;/em&gt; came to the Cornell physics department to try to find a way to fight the
merciless enemy of his Canadian homeland: the polar bear. The day they took his
pet beaver was the day he swore he&amp;#8217;d have his revenge. Then he got into
accelerator physics which was much more interesting so now he mostly does&amp;nbsp;that.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Yariv&lt;/em&gt; is a PhD physics graduate student at Cornell University. He is as old as
the Earth and as wise as the sky. He came across the sea in a great machine
made of metal and plastic accompanied by a mysterious cat who sees the future.
In physics he&amp;#8217;s bounced from neutron form factors to percolation models,
through deuteron beams to high-dimensional black holes. Sometimes he thinks he
should have stuck with one of these&amp;nbsp;subjects.&lt;/p&gt;</summary></entry></feed>