<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/physics.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2014-03-20T20:00:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Special Brain</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/special-brain.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2014-03-20T20:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>DTC</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2014-03-20:posts/special-brain.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;A colleague (and friend) of mine &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/user/thephysicsfactor"&gt;(hereafter referred to as Katie Mack the Physics Hack)&lt;/a&gt; 
produced a fun video last year that tried to show how people sometimes react when she 
tells them that she studies&amp;nbsp;physics:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;iframe width="560" height="315" src="//www.youtube.com/embed/AAA25XQKCbY" frameborder="0" allowfullscreen&gt;&lt;/iframe&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I loved this video because I&amp;#8217;ve had a number of experiences like this.
My favorite reaction that I&amp;#8217;ve ever gotten happened in 2007.&lt;br /&gt;
I was on a trip during college with other college kids, and 
I was placed in a hotel room with some guys who went to another 
school. We met for the first time while unpacking, and naturally 
we asked each other what we were studying. Turns out my new roommate was 
majoring in international business, something I knew nothing about.&lt;br /&gt;
Not wanting to alienate a total stranger I was going to be sleeping 
in the same room with, I asked him questions and told him that his 
chosen major sounded interesting and important.  I told him that I 
studied physics, and when he asked me what that meant I told him how 
I had worked on modeling &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cytokinesis"&gt;cell division&lt;/a&gt;. 
 My new roommate responded, &amp;#8220;You must have a special kind of brain for&amp;nbsp;that.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;img src = "/static/images/special_brain/profx.jpg" alt="A special brain." id="back_up1"&gt; 
&lt;a href="#footnote1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This anecdote has stuck with me for a couple of reasons&amp;#8212;- first because 
&amp;#8220;special kind of brain&amp;#8221; is a funny turn of phrase, and second because 
I think it&amp;#8217;s a perfect example of how an attempt at a flattering response can 
actually create some uncomfortable social distance between&amp;nbsp;people.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Special kind of brain&amp;#8221; was my roommate&amp;#8217;s way of expressing how intelligent 
he thought I was. (Or, as Zach put it in Katie&amp;#8217;s video, &amp;#8220;You must be soooooo 
smart!&amp;#8221;)  His reaction hinged upon the assumption that what I was interested 
in doing was so far beyond the understanding of ordinary folk that I could 
be set apart as a member of an elite group.  Instead of being merely 
complimentary, his comment held me at arms&amp;#8217; length.  His reaction wasn&amp;#8217;t 
something I took offense to, but it made me uncomfortable to hear that 
he considered me an outsider of sorts based on my professed&amp;nbsp;interests. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Speaking more generally, the notion that scientific professionals are 
set apart from other people as members of a professional group isn&amp;#8217;t 
so ridiculous. After all, these days people&amp;#8217;s lives are often defined 
by their careers. (And of course scientists aren&amp;#8217;t the only profession 
with associated negative stereotypes&amp;#8212;- Anyone know any good lawyer 
jokes?). But to me, thinking of scientists as some kind of inscrutable 
cabal of geniuses is an exaggeration.  The truth is, not every scientist 
is a rocket-powered superbrain.  Quite the opposite&amp;#8212;- scientists make 
silly mistakes all the time.  Being a scientist is a technical profession 
requiring years of training like law, medicine, or accounting: there are 
a few practitioners who really are exceptionally smart, while most of 
the others&amp;nbsp;aren&amp;#8217;t. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The even more disappointing truth is that being a scientist is actually 
usually pretty mundane.  Don&amp;#8217;t get me wrong&amp;#8212;- the long-term goals of 
making new discoveries and developing new insights into the world 
around us are exactly why I like my job.  I just mean that the day-to-day 
labor involved can be as tedious as any other profession.  I sit in my 
cubicle and code (debug) endlessly on my laptop, or I read books and 
research papers to learn new things about my field.  Most days don&amp;#8217;t 
get much more action-packed than that.  In a lot of ways it&amp;#8217;s like any 
other office job.  Aside from the end goal of research, working as a 
scientist is not so&amp;nbsp;special.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href = "http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0021884/"&gt;
&lt;img src = "/static/images/special_brain/frankenstein.jpg" alt="My office definitely does not look like this."
width="240" height="180" id="back_up2"/&gt;&lt;/a&gt; 
&lt;a href="#footnote2"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Another reaction that I get when I say I study physics is one of apprehensive 
disappointment.  (Zach&amp;#8217;s pronunciation of &amp;#8216;ohhhhhh&amp;#8230;&amp;#8217; combining equal parts 
boredom and distaste was dead on.) I don&amp;#8217;t think I need to dwell on this too 
long&amp;#8212;- it is undeniably unpleasant for me when I hear this. Upon hearing that 
I&amp;#8217;m a scientist, otherwise polite, kind people will suddenly lose their cool 
and be unable to hide the fact that my profession conjures up memories of boredom 
and frustration. (&amp;#8220;Oh, man.  I &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HATED&lt;/span&gt; physics in high school.&amp;#8221;)  As Katie Mack 
puts it at the end, &amp;#8220;polite interest is the way to&amp;nbsp;go.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p align="center"&gt;
  &lt;img src="/static/images/special_brain/big-bang-theory5.jpg" width="304" height="228" id="back_up3"&gt;
  &lt;p style="text-align: center; color: #999"&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Have you ever seen the Big Bang Theory?  &lt;br/&gt;Is that what physicists are really like?&lt;br/&gt;  I bet it is.  I mean, no&amp;nbsp;offense.&amp;#8221; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s another type of off-putting reaction that comes up sometimes, which is 
commenting (jokingly or not) that I&amp;#8217;m similar to familiar caricature of scientists 
that appear in popular culture. &amp;#8220;You&amp;#8217;re just like Sheldon Cooper!&amp;#8221; is a comment 
I&amp;#8217;ve heard more times than I care to say. I know that The Big Bang Theory is a 
popular show, but frankly I dislike being associated I with characters that are 
cartoonishly depicted as condescending and socially tone-deaf &lt;a href="#footnote3"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Now, I appreciate 
that some people, when meeting others for the first time, like to demonstrate 
familiarity with others&amp;#8217; jobs, but to me it just seems that making a pop culture 
references to another person&amp;#8217;s profession is just a bad way to go. I find this to 
be a safe bet when meeting anyone, not just scientists, simply because popular 
culture isn&amp;#8217;t a great way to learn about anyone else&amp;#8217;s job. Try telling the next 
lawyer you meet that they remind you of &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YPR9ORpwBEU"&gt;Saul Goodman&lt;/a&gt;, 
and see how they&amp;nbsp;react.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what is there for physicists (and other scientists) to do when this 
happens? The most facile answer to this question is for us to grow a thicker 
skin and suck it up.  Just ignore it when people have disparaging reactions 
upon first meeting us, and find a way to get past this in conversation.&lt;br /&gt;
The thing is, I personally am not good enough at hiding my own negative 
reaction upon hearing these kinds of obnoxious remarks. Ideally, I&amp;#8217;d like 
to make conversation easier by finding a way to avoid them&amp;nbsp;altogether. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can&amp;#8217;t change the way other people react to learning about my profession, 
but I can change how I present myself. Personally, I have given up on 
telling people that I&amp;#8217;m in the physics department.  Instead, when asked 
&amp;#8220;what do you study in grad school?&amp;#8221; I tell then exactly what I&amp;#8217;m up to&amp;#8212;- 
I study how infectious diseases spread through human and animal communities. 
I&amp;#8217;ve found that I get a much more relaxed reaction when I do this. The same 
people who may have uncomfortable reactions to physics have enough familiarity 
with the idea of epidemics to be a little more comfortable. And besides, 
everyone has some amount of morbid curiosity about the next big plague 
that&amp;#8217;s going to kill us all.  (I realize that this may not be a viable 
strategy for some of my colleagues who study nanoscience, magnetic materials, 
high-energy particles, or other mainstream physics topics.  I&amp;#8217;m interested 
to hear if anyone else who works in the sciences has come up with a different 
technique for breaking through the &amp;#8220;I&amp;#8217;m a physicist&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;ice.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine once chastised me for doing this. &amp;#8220;Why should you have to 
hide what you&amp;#8217;re interested in?&amp;#8221; he asked. &amp;#8220;If they react badly to your 
profession, is it really worth getting to know them?&amp;#8221;  To that I say that 
I&amp;#8217;m still telling them honestly what I&amp;#8217;m interested in, I just sidestep 
the potentially negative associations carried by the word &amp;#8220;physics.&amp;#8221; 
And besides, just because someone has a bad or obnoxious reaction to 
finding out that I&amp;#8217;m a physicist doesn&amp;#8217;t mean they aren&amp;#8217;t worth meeting.&lt;br /&gt;
The fact remains that I&amp;#8217;ve found this to be a great way to keep the 
getting-to-know-you conversation light when meeting new people for the 
first time. I wish I could wave a magic wand and make it so that everyone 
was comfortable wih the idea of interacting with professional scientists, 
but I can&amp;#8217;t. While I&amp;#8217;m waiting for &lt;a href="http://www.theverge.com/2014/2/4/5379246/watch-this-bill-nye-debates-evolution-with-the-founder-of-the-creation-museum"&gt;Bill Nye&lt;/a&gt;
 and &lt;a href="http://www.cosmosontv.com/"&gt;Neil DeGrasse Tyson&lt;/a&gt; and 
others to humanize the profession for the public, this is how I&amp;#8217;ll be introducing&amp;nbsp;myself. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Katie Mack and Zach&amp;#8217;s video really got me thinking about how to talk 
to other people about their jobs with more empathy&amp;#8212;- avoiding flattery 
and stereotyping, and doing my best to hide any negative visceral reactions 
evoked by the thought of others&amp;#8217; jobs and interests.  One question that has 
occurred to me is whether there are people in completely different professions 
experience similarly frustrating reactions when they say what their jobs are. 
Programmers, actuaries, office administrators, copy editors, art dealers, 
karate instructors, gravediggers, lion-tamers, etc.:  whoever you are, 
I want to hear about any difficulties  you may have had with telling other 
people what you do in the comments&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote1"&gt;&lt;a href="#back_up1"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; 
Image from New X-Men #121, written by Grant Morrison with art by Frank Quitely.
 You can see some more of this particularly trippy story &lt;a href="https://marswillsendnomore.wordpress.com/2011/09/04/inside-the-twisted-mind-of-the-professor/"&gt;
here&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote2"&gt;&lt;a href="#back_up2"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt;
All of the imagery of Frankenstein&amp;#8217;s monster being brought to life with electricity
comes from James Whale&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href ="http://www.imdb.com/title/tt0021884/"
&lt;i&gt;Frankenstein&lt;/i&gt; from 1931.&lt;/a&gt; Mary Shelley&amp;#8217;s original book contained no mention of 
electricity, and instead remained eerily vague about the mechanisms for creating&amp;nbsp;life.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote3"&gt;&lt;a href="#back_up3"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://scitation.aip.org/content/aip/magazine/physicstoday/news/10.1063/PT.4.0293"&gt;
Here &lt;/a&gt; is a really level-headed critique of The Big Bang Theory that I like a
lot.  There isn&amp;#8217;t a ton of hand-wringing, and the author does talk about what the
show might consider doing differently.  It was written three years&amp;nbsp;ago.
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;
Watch what happens when &lt;a href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=THNPmhBl-8I/"&gt;
a brain surgeon meets a rocket scientist for the first time &lt;/a&gt;.
To justify my linking to this skit (outside of the fact that I love it so much), 
I&amp;#8217;ll just say that &lt;i&gt;nobody&lt;/i&gt; is acting appropriately in this&amp;nbsp;video. 
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;


&lt;li&gt;
(Sorry,&amp;nbsp;lawyers.)
&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="culture"></category></entry><entry><title>Quantum Mechanics: Trying to Sort the Physical from the Mystical</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/quantum-mechanics-mysticism.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2013-09-23T00:00:00-04:00</updated><author><name>DTC</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2013-09-23:posts/quantum-mechanics-mysticism.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://xkcd.com/1240/"&gt;
&lt;img src = "http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/quantum_mechanics.png" title="You can also just ignore any science assertion where 'quantum mechanics' is the most complicated phrase in it." alt="You can also just ignore any science assertion where 'quantum mechanics' is the most complicated phrase in it." id="back_up1"&gt; 
&lt;a href="#footnote1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine (I’ll call him Ron), who knows that I study physics, 
likes to talk to me about quantum mechanics.  He’s an easy-going guy 
and likes to joke around. “Hey, is it a particle or is it a wave today?” 
he’ll say, or, “How many dimensions do we have now?” When the conversation 
turns more serious, he tells me how he believes 
in the “quantum universe,” which is greater than what we humans are 
able to ordinarily perceive.  He talks about consciousness, immortality, 
spirits, and the great cosmic grandeur of the universe, all of which he 
ties together with the label of&amp;nbsp;“quantum.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These conversations are strange to me.  Both of us are using the same two words: 
quantum mechanics.  When Ron thinks about quantum mechanics, he associates it 
with nonphysical concepts, like spirits.  Through my time spent studying physics, 
I’ve come to understand quantum mechanics as a theory describing the behavior of 
atoms and subatomic particles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, one day our chatting turned to the topic of medicine and how the 
human body heals itself.  Ron told me that the biggest problem with modern 
medicine is that doctors think of the body as a physical object only. 
Healing, he said, was a “quantum” effect.  I told him that I could make a 
pretty strong physical argument for why that wasn’t the case.  He responded 
with this story:  Once, when playing football, he severely injured his knee. 
The injury was so bad that he couldn’t bend it or move it.  He didn’t have 
health insurance and didn’t have the cash on hand to pay for medical treatment. 
One day, he prayed to the universe that he would get better and a “tornado of 
light came down” and healed his leg.  Since then, Ron says, he’s always believed 
in and respected the quantum&amp;nbsp;universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t tell Ron that what he described in his story didn’t happen, 
that his experience was wrong or incorrect in some way.  I wasn’t there, 
so I can’t comment on the accuracy of his narrative. And even the story 
of how his body healed out of the blue isn’t problematic: as far as I can 
tell, decades after the story took place, Ron is in good shape and his leg 
is doing fine.  What I found objectionable about the story was how, in the 
end, Ron attributed his healing to the miraculous intervention of quantum&amp;nbsp;mechanics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quantum mechanics, in all of its glorious strangeness, is only relevant on 
inconceivably small scales and at very, very low temperatures.  One of the 
reasons it took humans so long to develop the theory of quantum mechanics is 
that quantum effects don’t readily appear in everyday life.  My &lt;a href="http://ultracold.lassp.cornell.edu/"&gt;colleagues&lt;/a&gt;
who work to observe quantum mechanics in their experiments use lasers to manipulate 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubidium/"&gt;atoms&lt;/a&gt; 
(objects that are 1/10,000,000,000th of a meter in size and weigh around 
1/10,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000th of a kilogram) at temperatures less than 
1 Kelvin (about -459 degrees Fahrenheit).  At larger sizes and temperatures 
quantum effects are negligible.  The human body is more than a meter long, 
usually weighs around 50-100 kilograms and, if healthy, maintains a toasty 
98 degrees Fahrenheit.  Quantum mechanics is important at the atomic level, 
but on the scales at which people interact with the world it hardly shows up 
at all.  So, even if Ron&amp;#8217;s leg heals as he said it did, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t give credit to quantum mechanics.&lt;a href="#footnote-1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span id="back_up2"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been studying physics for years and still quantum mechanics 
remains utterly baffling to me.  The fact that such an abstract theory can tell us so 
much about the world feels a little bit like a miracle.  Quantum mechanics carries 
with it a number of counterintuitive ideas like the 
&lt;a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/07/21/nothing-to-see-here-demoting-the-uncertainty-principle/"&gt;uncertainty principle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote-1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span id="back_up3"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
entanglement, or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Many-worlds_interpretation"&gt;parallel universes&lt;/a&gt;.
 These ideas are so abstracted from every day life that the subject begins to take 
 on a supernatural quality.  Physics no longer seems like physics- 
 it starts to sound like&amp;nbsp;mysticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it makes sense that contemporary culture has seized upon quantum mechanics 
as a possible explanation for inexplicable things.  The theory has so many 
surprising results that it seems natural to extend it to encompass other things 
that confuse us, like questions of consciousness.  Furthermore, “quantum mechanics” 
is a term that carries with it the weight of scientific legitimacy.  If Ron had 
said that he had been healed through witchcraft, laying on of hands, or alchemy 
he would have sounded ridiculous, but attributing his experience to quantum effects 
allows the story to borrow from the credible reputation of fact-based 20th century 
science.  What my friend doesn’t realize is that terminology is not what makes 
quantum theory powerful: the scientific methodology supporting quantum mechanics 
is what&amp;nbsp;matters.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to keep separate quantum mechanics the physical theory and 
quantum mechanics as a mystical cosmic principle.  Despite how confusing it 
is, quantum mechanics is an empirically motivated and mature theory that gives 
us a framework to understand physical phenomena like radiation and chemical 
bonding.  This is fundamentally different from applying quantum mechanical 
concepts to the nature of reality or consciousness.  To do so may be a fun 
philosophical parlor game, but it is baseless speculation without any evidence 
to motivate the connection between quantum mechanics and the supernatural 
that it begins with. This confusion is not just restricted to scientific laymen: there are 
trained researchers working at well-respected research institutions 
who also &lt;a href="http://www.quantumconsciousness.org/"&gt;make the same mistake&lt;/a&gt;
 my friend Ron&amp;nbsp;does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, speculation that the soul, the afterlife, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESP&lt;/span&gt;, 
or whatever else are quantum effects is unscientific, but at least it 
isn’t dangerous or harmful in the same way as climate change denial or 
&lt;a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/health/measles-surges-uk-years-after-vaccine-scare-6C9997438/"&gt;refusing to vaccinate your children&lt;/a&gt;. 
It’s closer to something like &lt;a href="http://www.intelligentdesign.org/"&gt;intelligent design&lt;/a&gt;, which is 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kitzmiller_v._Dover_Area_School_District/"&gt;fundamentally confused about what science is&lt;/a&gt;.
(We physicists are truly thankful that there is no noisy political movement 
to teach &lt;a href="https://www.deepakchopra.com/blog/view/900/from_quanta_to_qualia:_the_mystery_of_reality/"&gt;Deepak Chopra&lt;/a&gt;
alongside physics in high school classrooms.) So I won’t object to my 
friends’ stories of sudden, unexpected recoveries from illness, but 
I will react skeptically when I hear that healing has anything to do with quantum&amp;nbsp;mechanics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote1"&gt;&lt;a href="#back_up1"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; Credit where credit is due: I took this from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XKCD&lt;/span&gt;.  This may be one of 
my favorite comics Randall Munroe has ever done.  That it came out while 
I was thinking about this piece was a great coincidence.  (A cosmic 
coincidence explainable through quantum entanglement?  Probably&amp;nbsp;not.) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote-1"&gt;&lt;a href="#back_up2"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; Quantum mechanics may be just as mundane as any other materialistic physical 
theory, but that doesn’t make it any less amazing.  My favorite example is 
how quantum mechanics allows us to understand &lt;a href ="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gS1dpowPlE8/"&gt; why the sun&amp;nbsp;works. &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote-1"&gt;&lt;a href="#back_up3"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; In case you didn&amp;#8217;t take the time to click on the link: Seriously, do 
yourself a favor and click on the &lt;a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/07/21/nothing-to-see-here-demoting-the-uncertainty-principle/"&gt; link &lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s an essay from The Stone that very elegantly describes
how the uncertainty principle is far less cosmically mind-blowing than you 
may have come to believe.  It does a beautiful job bringing us back down to 
earth and carefully explaining the scope of the principle.  I must give it credit
for having inspired this piece in no small&amp;nbsp;way. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="quantum mechanics"></category><category term="metaphysics"></category><category term="mysticism"></category></entry></feed>