<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/physics.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Quantum Mechanics: Trying to Sort the Physical from the Mystical</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/quantum-mechanics-mysticism.html</link><description>&lt;p align="center"&gt;
&lt;a href="http://xkcd.com/1240/"&gt;
&lt;img src = "http://imgs.xkcd.com/comics/quantum_mechanics.png" title="You can also just ignore any science assertion where 'quantum mechanics' is the most complicated phrase in it." alt="You can also just ignore any science assertion where 'quantum mechanics' is the most complicated phrase in it." id="back_up1"&gt; 
&lt;a href="#footnote1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[1]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A friend of mine (I’ll call him Ron), who knows that I study physics, 
likes to talk to me about quantum mechanics.  He’s an easy-going guy 
and likes to joke around. “Hey, is it a particle or is it a wave today?” 
he’ll say, or, “How many dimensions do we have now?” When the conversation 
turns more serious, he tells me how he believes 
in the “quantum universe,” which is greater than what we humans are 
able to ordinarily perceive.  He talks about consciousness, immortality, 
spirits, and the great cosmic grandeur of the universe, all of which he 
ties together with the label of&amp;nbsp;“quantum.”&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These conversations are strange to me.  Both of us are using the same two words: 
quantum mechanics.  When Ron thinks about quantum mechanics, he associates it 
with nonphysical concepts, like spirits.  Through my time spent studying physics, 
I’ve come to understand quantum mechanics as a theory describing the behavior of 
atoms and subatomic particles.
&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For example, one day our chatting turned to the topic of medicine and how the 
human body heals itself.  Ron told me that the biggest problem with modern 
medicine is that doctors think of the body as a physical object only. 
Healing, he said, was a “quantum” effect.  I told him that I could make a 
pretty strong physical argument for why that wasn’t the case.  He responded 
with this story:  Once, when playing football, he severely injured his knee. 
The injury was so bad that he couldn’t bend it or move it.  He didn’t have 
health insurance and didn’t have the cash on hand to pay for medical treatment. 
One day, he prayed to the universe that he would get better and a “tornado of 
light came down” and healed his leg.  Since then, Ron says, he’s always believed 
in and respected the quantum&amp;nbsp;universe.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I can’t tell Ron that what he described in his story didn’t happen, 
that his experience was wrong or incorrect in some way.  I wasn’t there, 
so I can’t comment on the accuracy of his narrative. And even the story 
of how his body healed out of the blue isn’t problematic: as far as I can 
tell, decades after the story took place, Ron is in good shape and his leg 
is doing fine.  What I found objectionable about the story was how, in the 
end, Ron attributed his healing to the miraculous intervention of quantum&amp;nbsp;mechanics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Quantum mechanics, in all of its glorious strangeness, is only relevant on 
inconceivably small scales and at very, very low temperatures.  One of the 
reasons it took humans so long to develop the theory of quantum mechanics is 
that quantum effects don’t readily appear in everyday life.  My &lt;a href="http://ultracold.lassp.cornell.edu/"&gt;colleagues&lt;/a&gt;
who work to observe quantum mechanics in their experiments use lasers to manipulate 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Rubidium/"&gt;atoms&lt;/a&gt; 
(objects that are 1/10,000,000,000th of a meter in size and weigh around 
1/10,000,000,000,000,000,000,000,000th of a kilogram) at temperatures less than 
1 Kelvin (about -459 degrees Fahrenheit).  At larger sizes and temperatures 
quantum effects are negligible.  The human body is more than a meter long, 
usually weighs around 50-100 kilograms and, if healthy, maintains a toasty 
98 degrees Fahrenheit.  Quantum mechanics is important at the atomic level, 
but on the scales at which people interact with the world it hardly shows up 
at all.  So, even if Ron&amp;#8217;s leg heals as he said it did, I wouldn&amp;#8217;t give credit to quantum mechanics.&lt;a href="#footnote-1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[2]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span id="back_up2"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have been studying physics for years and still quantum mechanics 
remains utterly baffling to me.  The fact that such an abstract theory can tell us so 
much about the world feels a little bit like a miracle.  Quantum mechanics carries 
with it a number of counterintuitive ideas like the 
&lt;a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/07/21/nothing-to-see-here-demoting-the-uncertainty-principle/"&gt;uncertainty principle&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="#footnote-1"&gt;&lt;sup&gt;[3]&lt;/sup&gt;&lt;/a&gt; &lt;span id="back_up3"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
entanglement, or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Many-worlds_interpretation"&gt;parallel universes&lt;/a&gt;.
 These ideas are so abstracted from every day life that the subject begins to take 
 on a supernatural quality.  Physics no longer seems like physics- 
 it starts to sound like&amp;nbsp;mysticism.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So it makes sense that contemporary culture has seized upon quantum mechanics 
as a possible explanation for inexplicable things.  The theory has so many 
surprising results that it seems natural to extend it to encompass other things 
that confuse us, like questions of consciousness.  Furthermore, “quantum mechanics” 
is a term that carries with it the weight of scientific legitimacy.  If Ron had 
said that he had been healed through witchcraft, laying on of hands, or alchemy 
he would have sounded ridiculous, but attributing his experience to quantum effects 
allows the story to borrow from the credible reputation of fact-based 20th century 
science.  What my friend doesn’t realize is that terminology is not what makes 
quantum theory powerful: the scientific methodology supporting quantum mechanics 
is what&amp;nbsp;matters.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It’s important to keep separate quantum mechanics the physical theory and 
quantum mechanics as a mystical cosmic principle.  Despite how confusing it 
is, quantum mechanics is an empirically motivated and mature theory that gives 
us a framework to understand physical phenomena like radiation and chemical 
bonding.  This is fundamentally different from applying quantum mechanical 
concepts to the nature of reality or consciousness.  To do so may be a fun 
philosophical parlor game, but it is baseless speculation without any evidence 
to motivate the connection between quantum mechanics and the supernatural 
that it begins with. This confusion is not just restricted to scientific laymen: there are 
trained researchers working at well-respected research institutions 
who also &lt;a href="http://www.quantumconsciousness.org/"&gt;make the same mistake&lt;/a&gt;
 my friend Ron&amp;nbsp;does.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the end of the day, speculation that the soul, the afterlife, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ESP&lt;/span&gt;, 
or whatever else are quantum effects is unscientific, but at least it 
isn’t dangerous or harmful in the same way as climate change denial or 
&lt;a href="http://www.nbcnews.com/health/measles-surges-uk-years-after-vaccine-scare-6C9997438/"&gt;refusing to vaccinate your children&lt;/a&gt;. 
It’s closer to something like &lt;a href="http://www.intelligentdesign.org/"&gt;intelligent design&lt;/a&gt;, which is 
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Kitzmiller_v._Dover_Area_School_District/"&gt;fundamentally confused about what science is&lt;/a&gt;.
(We physicists are truly thankful that there is no noisy political movement 
to teach &lt;a href="https://www.deepakchopra.com/blog/view/900/from_quanta_to_qualia:_the_mystery_of_reality/"&gt;Deepak Chopra&lt;/a&gt;
alongside physics in high school classrooms.) So I won’t object to my 
friends’ stories of sudden, unexpected recoveries from illness, but 
I will react skeptically when I hear that healing has anything to do with quantum&amp;nbsp;mechanics. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote1"&gt;&lt;a href="#back_up1"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; Credit where credit is due: I took this from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XKCD&lt;/span&gt;.  This may be one of 
my favorite comics Randall Munroe has ever done.  That it came out while 
I was thinking about this piece was a great coincidence.  (A cosmic 
coincidence explainable through quantum entanglement?  Probably&amp;nbsp;not.) &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote-1"&gt;&lt;a href="#back_up2"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; Quantum mechanics may be just as mundane as any other materialistic physical 
theory, but that doesn’t make it any less amazing.  My favorite example is 
how quantum mechanics allows us to understand &lt;a href ="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=gS1dpowPlE8/"&gt; why the sun&amp;nbsp;works. &lt;/a&gt; &lt;/p&gt;&lt;/li&gt;

&lt;li&gt;&lt;p id="footnote-1"&gt;&lt;a href="#back_up3"&gt;^&lt;/a&gt; In case you didn&amp;#8217;t take the time to click on the link: Seriously, do 
yourself a favor and click on the &lt;a href="http://opinionator.blogs.nytimes.com/2013/07/21/nothing-to-see-here-demoting-the-uncertainty-principle/"&gt; link &lt;/a&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s an essay from The Stone that very elegantly describes
how the uncertainty principle is far less cosmically mind-blowing than you 
may have come to believe.  It does a beautiful job bringing us back down to 
earth and carefully explaining the scope of the principle.  I must give it credit
for having inspired this piece in no small&amp;nbsp;way. &lt;/p&gt; &lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">DTC</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 23 Sep 2013 00:00:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2013-09-23:posts/quantum-mechanics-mysticism.html</guid><category>quantum mechanics</category><category>metaphysics</category><category>mysticism</category></item></channel></rss>