<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.earth-day.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2011-04-22T13:11:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>End of the Earth VI: Nanobot destruction</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/end-of-the-earth-vi-nanobot-destruction.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-22T13:11:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-04-22:posts/end-of-the-earth-vi-nanobot-destruction.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-hGkMD-tB1RY/TbGfhRvcA6I/AAAAAAAAAQ4/eCaG-z1Zarc/s1600/612px-C60a.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-hGkMD-tB1RY/TbGfhRvcA6I/AAAAAAAAAQ4/eCaG-z1Zarc/s320/612px-C60a.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s destroy the earth with technology. A while ago, I read the novel
&lt;em&gt;Postsingular&lt;/em&gt; by Rudy Rucker, and in the first chapter the Earth gets
destroyed, and then undestroyed, and then the novel unfolds and the
Earth&amp;#8217;s likelihood is threatened again, and it looks like the Earth will
be destroyed, but it isn&amp;#8217;t. How does all of this craziness happen you
might ask: nanobots! The story revolves around little self-replicating
robots. The story explores what it would be like to live in a world
where every surface on Earth was coated in little computers, all of
which were networked together. It&amp;#8217;s certainly a neat idea, but whenever
you have self-replicating things, you need to worry a bit about what
might happen if they get out of control. So, let&amp;#8217;s assume we, evil
scientists that we are, have managed to create a little self-replicating
nanobot. This little guy can scurry around, running off something
ubiquitous, probably some combination of solar, and some kind of
infrared photovoltaics. This little guy, call him Bob, his only mission
in life is to create a friend. He scurries around collecting the various
ingredients necessary, and using his little robot arms, he slices and
dices up the pieces and welds them together to create another copy of
himself, Rob. Not satisfied with his work; Bob found Rob quite the bore,
and honestly Rob didn&amp;#8217;t too much like Bob either, both of them part ways
and try to fashion a new friend. How long until Bob and Rob and their
cohorts manage to chew through all of the material on Earth? What we
have here is the setup to a problem in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exponential_growth"&gt;Exponential
Growth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exponential&amp;nbsp;Growth&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s simplify things a bit and assume that the nanobots always take a
fixed amount to time to make a new copy of themselves, call that time T.
We&amp;#8217;ll start with one guy, so we know that at t =0, we have 1 bot &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N(t
=0 ) = 1 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; And we know that after T seconds we should have 2 &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N(T) =
2 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and after 2T seconds, we&amp;#8217;ve managed to double twice and get 4 &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
N(2T) = 4 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; after 3T seconds we&amp;#8217;ll double again to 8, etc. In fact,
after nT seconds, so m repetitions we should have doubled m times &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
N(nT) = 2^n $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So if we want to describe all times, we need only ask
how many doublings can fit into t seconds &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = n T $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which gives us
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N(t) = 2^{t/T} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; At this point you might object, as this formula
doesn&amp;#8217;t always give an integer, so we could ask things like how many
bots are there after 0.5T seconds? We know the true answer is still 1,
Bob hasn&amp;#8217;t finished Rob yet, but our formula tells us the answer is
1.414&amp;#8230; What we&amp;#8217;ve done is made a continuous approximation to a
discrete function. Certainly, we&amp;#8217;ve paid a price, in that our new
formula doesn&amp;#8217;t get answers right in fractions of T, but its a small
price to pay for the mathematical simplicity afforded by the nice
continuous function, and as long as we don&amp;#8217;t really care about time
scales smaller than T in the long run, we haven&amp;#8217;t done any real harm.
These kinds of approximations show up all over the place in physics, and
going both ways too. Sometimes it is advantageous to treat some discrete
quantity as continuous, and sometimes it might be beneficial to treat
some continuous quantity as discrete. These kinds of approximations are
more than adequate, provided you don&amp;#8217;t really take the answers they give
you in the cases where your approximation starts to break too seriously.
In this case, as long as we don&amp;#8217;t try to seriously predict the number of
nanobots to an exact count in time scales less than a fraction of their
doubling time, we will have a nice prediction of the number of bots
running&amp;nbsp;around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Earth&amp;nbsp;Destruction&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As promised, we wanted to calculate the time it would take the nanobots
to devour the earth. For this we need a little bit more to our model.
How will the nanobots eat the earth, I reckon it will be through using
up its mass. Assuming the bots are made out of elements that are rich
enough, something like iron, they ought to have a field day on Earth,
seeing as it&amp;#8217;s composed of about 5% iron on the surface, and with an
interior that is probably about 32% iron overall
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abundance_of_the_chemical_elements#Abundance_of_elements_in_the_Earth"&gt;[ref]&lt;/a&gt;.
So, we need to estimate the mass of a single nanobot. Let&amp;#8217;s say the
nanobot is roughly a 1 micron sized cube, made out of iron. This gives
us a nanobot mass of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ m = (\text{ density of iron }) * (\text{ 1
micron} )^3 = \rho_{\text{Fe}} L^3 \sim 8 \text{ picograms} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
From here we can estimate the time it would take to chew through the
earth, as the time for the nanobots to be as massive as the earth. &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
\frac{M_{\oplus}}{\rho_{\text{Fe}} L^3 } = N(t) = 2^{t/T} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Solving for t we obtain &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = T \log_2 \frac{ M_{\oplus}}{
\rho_{\text{Fe}} L^3 } $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s say it takes Bob one month to make Rob, which I don&amp;#8217;t think is a
completely unrealistic time for nanobot replication, assuming Bob and
Rob and all of their cohorts are 1 micron in size, I calculate that in
10 years time they would chew through the Earth. The power of
exponential growth! Even with a 1 month gestation, if left unabashed,
the self-replicating robots would eat the entire earth in 10 years time.
They could eat through Mars in about 2. In fact in &lt;em&gt;Postsingular&lt;/em&gt; this
is what the humans planned. They wanted a Dyson sphere, so they sent
some self-replicating robots to Mars, let them chew through it a couple
years, and they had 10^37 little robots to do their bidding. That is of
course until the nants set their sites on Earth as their next target&amp;#8230;
In order to let you play around with the doubling time and bot size,
I&amp;#8217;ve created a Wolfram Alpha widget that solves the above equation, feel
free to play around with the parameters and see how long Earth would&amp;nbsp;survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The widget should be right above this text. If it isn&amp;#8217;t working for some
reason, here&amp;#8217;s a
&lt;a href="http://developer.wolframalpha.com/widgets/gallery/view.jsp?id=6a645314f9be6be7b902d4cc1f776d00"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="fun"></category><category term="nanobots"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category><category term="earth day"></category></entry><entry><title>Earth Day - Earth Units</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/earth-day-earth-units.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-22T16:18:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-22:posts/earth-day-earth-units.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In honor of Earth day, I thought I would take a look at what it would
mean to do physics in &amp;#8216;Earth&amp;#8217; units. What do I mean by that? Well lets
be anti-Copernican here, in fact lets assume the opposite of the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Copernican_principle"&gt;Copernican
principle&lt;/a&gt;, and state
that the Earth is privileged in the universe and define all of our units
around the&amp;nbsp;Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S9Cu1nxGXDI/AAAAAAAAAKU/JTtr_QKqdR8/s1600/50px-Earth_symbol.svg.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S9Cu1nxGXDI/AAAAAAAAAKU/JTtr_QKqdR8/s320/50px-Earth_symbol.svg.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I will put a little subscript earth on all of the &amp;#8216;earth&amp;#8217; units.
They are to be read as &amp;#8216;earth meters&amp;#8217; or &amp;#8216;earth amps&amp;#8217;, etc. We will take
as our starting point the mass, radius and day of the earth, normalizing
all of our standards to that. This gives us our initial conversion
factors &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1 g_{\oplus} = M_{\oplus} = 5.9742 \times 10^{34}
\text{ kg} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1 m_{\oplus} = R_{\oplus} = 6378.1 \text{ km} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1 s_{\oplus} = T_{\oplus} = 86,400 \text{ s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; From this, we
can figure out what all of the other &amp;#8216;earth&amp;#8217; units would&amp;nbsp;be.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lengths&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some things we are used to talking about start to look a little simpler
in these units. The surface area of the earth would be &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 4 \pi\
m_{\oplus}^2 \sim 12.6\ m_{\oplus}^2 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and the volume of the
earth would be &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{4\pi}{3}\ m_{\oplus}^3 \sim 4.2\
m_{\oplus}^3 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; One earth velocity would be &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\ \frac{
m_{\oplus} }{ s_{\oplus} } = 73.8\ \frac{ m }{ s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so that the
velocity of a person standing at the equator would be about &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 2 \pi\
\frac{ m_{\oplus }}{s_{\oplus} } \sim 6.3\ \frac{ m_{\oplus }
}{ s_{\oplus } } $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and one earth acceleration would be &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\ \frac{
m_{\oplus} }{ s_{\oplus}^2 } = 8.5 \times 10^{-4} \frac{
m}{s^2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so that the gravitational acceleration we feel on the earth
in earth accelerations would be &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ g \sim 1.15 \times 10^4\
\frac{m_{\oplus}}{s_{\oplus}^2 } $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which is a little more awkward
than the 10 that it is in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SI&lt;/span&gt;. After this all of the numbers start to get
pretty&amp;nbsp;silly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Mechanics&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One earth energy is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\ J_{\oplus} = 3.3 \times 10^{28}\ J $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
and earth force &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\ N_{\oplus} = 5.1\times 10^{21}\ N $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; the
gravitational constant becomes &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ G = 3.88 \times 10^{-25} \
\frac{m_{\oplus}^3 }{ g_{\oplus} s_{\oplus}^2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; earth power
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\ W_{\oplus} = 3.8 \times 10^{23} \ W $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; earth pressure &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\
Pa_{\oplus} = 1.2 \times 10^8 \ Pa $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Electrical and&amp;nbsp;Thermal&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additionally if I take the Boltzmann constant and electrical constant as
fundamental dimensionfull quantities, and set them equal to 1 (i.e.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CGS&lt;/span&gt;-type Earth units), I can use them to discover earth units dealing
with electrical or thermal phenomenon. An earth kelvin is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\
K_{\oplus} = 3.2 \times 10^{28} \ K $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; earth coulomb &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\
C_{\oplus} = 4.6 \times 10^{17} \ C $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; earth amp &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\
A_{\oplus} = 5.3 \times 10^{12} \ A $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; an earth volt &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\
V_{\oplus} = 7.1 \times 10^{10} \ V $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; an earth farad &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\
F_{\oplus} = 6.4\times 10^6 \ F $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; an earth ohm &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\
\Omega_{\oplus} = 14 m\Omega$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; a earth henry &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\ H_{\oplus} =
1170 \ H $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; an earth electric field &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\
\frac{V_{\oplus}}{m_{\oplus}} = 11200\ \frac{V}{m} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; an earth
tesla &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1\ T_{\oplus} = 152 \ T $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; etc&amp;#8230;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Lessons&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, it looks like if we really decide to fly in the face of the
Copernican principle and look to the earth as something fundamental in
the universe, these considerations can suggest a bunch of other relevant
values for other kinds of dimensionfull quantities in the world. If the
earth really was something super special in the universe, and if somehow
its design was intimately connected with the properties of physics at
large, then all of these different values ought to have some kind of
deep meaning. Unfortunately, as far as I can tell, they are just a bunch
of random numbers. Looks like the Copernican principle wins again.
Nobody should tell the earth. Its feelings might get&amp;nbsp;hurt.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="units"></category><category term="fun"></category><category term="dimensional analysis"></category><category term="earth day"></category></entry></feed>