<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/tag.sand.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2011-07-18T11:33:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Grains of Sand</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/grains-of-sand.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-07-18T11:33:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-07-18:posts/grains-of-sand.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-87-vnzGa9Po/TiRR2qFWprI/AAAAAAAAAF0/KsfRQhoL5Ds/s1600/SandUDunesUSoft.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-87-vnzGa9Po/TiRR2qFWprI/AAAAAAAAAF0/KsfRQhoL5Ds/s320/SandUDunesUSoft.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Have you ever sat on a beach and wondered how many grains of sand there
were? I have, but I may be a special case. Today we&amp;#8217;re going to take
that a step further, and figure out how many grains of sand there are on
the entire earth. (Caveat: I&amp;#8217;m only going to consider sand above the
water level, since I don&amp;#8217;t have any idea what the composition of the
ocean floor is). I&amp;#8217;m going to start by figuring out how much beach there
is in the world. If you look at a map of the world, there are four main
coasts that run, essentially, a half circumference of the world. We&amp;#8217;ll
say the total length of coast the world has is roughly two
circumferences. As an order of magnitude, I would say that the average
beach width is 100 m, and the average depth is 10 m. This gives a total
beach volume of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ (100 m)(10 m)(4 \pi (6500 km) )= 82 km^3$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; That&amp;#8217;s
not a whole lot of volume. Let&amp;#8217;s think about deserts. The Sahara desert
is by far the largest sandy desert in the world. Just as a guess, we&amp;#8217;ll
assume that the rest of the sandy deserts amount to 20% (arbitrary
number picked staring at a map) as much area as the Sahara. According to
wikipedia the area of the Sahara is 9.4 million km^2. We&amp;#8217;ll take, to an
order of magnitude, that the sand is 100 m deep. 10 m seems to little,
and 1 km too much. That amounts to \~1 million km^3 of sand. We&amp;#8217;re
going to assume that a grain of sand is about 1 mm in radius The volume
occupied by a grain of sand is then 1 mm^3. Putting that together with
our previous number for the occupied volume gives &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{1\cdot
10^6 km^3}{1 mm^3}=\frac{1 \cdot 10^{15}}{1\cdot
10^{-9}}=1\cdot 10^{24}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; That&amp;#8217;s a lot of grains of sand. Addendum:
Carl Sagan is quoted as&amp;nbsp;saying&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;The total number of stars in the Universe is larger than all the
grains of sand on all the beaches of the planet&amp;nbsp;Earth&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we just use our beach volume, that gives a total number of grains of
sand as \~1*10^20, which is large, but not as large as what we found
above. Is that less than the number of stars in in the universe? Well,
that&amp;#8217;s a question for another day (or google), but the answer is, to our
best estimate/count,&amp;nbsp;yes.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sand"></category><category term="order of magnitude"></category><category term="carl sagan"></category></entry></feed>