<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.bike.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2010-08-12T17:23:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Terminal Velocity 2: A Theorist’s Experimental Experiment</title><link href="/posts/terminal-velocity-2-a-theorist-s-experimental-experiment.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-08-12T17:23:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Yariv</name></author><id>tag:,2010-08-12:posts/terminal-velocity-2-a-theorist-s-experimental-experiment.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Yesterday we rode down Ithaca&amp;#8217;s hills in an attempt to estimate the
terminal velocity of a bike rider braving the city&amp;#8217;s potholes. But
estimations are easy, and we relied on a number of factors - the drag
coefficient and area of the bicyclist, in particular - to get them. To
see how well we did, it&amp;#8217;s time to move on to the experimental portion
this exercise. Our tools? My bike (figure 1), and my beloved
accelerometer (figure 2), with Google&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://mytracks.appspot.com/"&gt;My
Tracks&lt;/a&gt; app&amp;nbsp;installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRzmU_-t0I/AAAAAAAACFA/6JFhG9Z9YiA/s1600/bike.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRzmU_-t0I/AAAAAAAACFA/6JFhG9Z9YiA/s200/bike.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure
1: Our&amp;nbsp;vehicle&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRn_JN3A6I/AAAAAAAACEQ/b02aLvN9_ys/s1600/Droid+2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRn_JN3A6I/AAAAAAAACEQ/b02aLvN9_ys/s200/Droid+2.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 2: Our&amp;nbsp;instrumentation&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I took data twelve times while driving down two paths (&lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=University+and+Cornell,+Ithaca+NY&amp;amp;sll=42.44395,-76.485014&amp;amp;sspn=0.016721,0.038581&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;hq=&amp;amp;hnear=University+Ave+%26+Cornell+Ave,+Ithaca+College,+Tompkins,+New+York+14850&amp;amp;ll=42.447243,-76.493082&amp;amp;spn=0.01672,0.038581&amp;amp;t=p&amp;amp;z=15"&gt;University
avenue&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=State+and+Stewart,+Ithaca,+NY&amp;amp;sll=42.447243,-76.493082&amp;amp;sspn=0.01672,0.038581&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;hq=&amp;amp;hnear=E+State+St+%26+Stewart+Ave,+Ithaca+College,+Tompkins,+New+York+14850&amp;amp;ll=42.439262,-76.489692&amp;amp;spn=0.016722,0.038581&amp;amp;t=p&amp;amp;z=15"&gt;State
street&lt;/a&gt;),
measuring both the speed and elevation as a function of time. I came up
with a lot of noisy data, some of it useful and a lot of it not. A
typical plot out of the software looks something like (figure 3); out of
those I identified moments of what seemed to be free acceleration, where
I was not applying the brakes. I then calculated the slope and the
acceleration at each point by subtracting subsequent measurements; this
resulted in much noisier data, as seen on (figure&amp;nbsp;4).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRoiavSb4I/AAAAAAAACEY/3Yee3_k-TiY/s1600/University7.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRoiavSb4I/AAAAAAAACEY/3Yee3_k-TiY/s400/University7.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure
3: Typical data riding downhill
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRo0pVcbSI/AAAAAAAACEg/qdGFWsUS4X8/s1600/University7DiffFocus.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRo0pVcbSI/AAAAAAAACEg/qdGFWsUS4X8/s400/University7DiffFocus.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure
4:&amp;nbsp;Derivatives&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next question was what to fit these graphs to. I can&amp;#8217;t compare
directly to the formula I had for terminal velocity, since I don&amp;#8217;t
believe I achieve it at any point and we never see the velocity graph
plateau. What we do have is the formula for the acceleration, which
depends on both the angle and the velocity: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ a = g\\sin\\theta -
\\frac{1}{2}\\frac{\\rho A C\_d}{m} v\^2. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; It&amp;#8217;s a little hard to plot
three-dimensional surfaces like this, but I can try to plot the
acceleration as a function of the velocity squared. Assuming that the
slope of each of my routes is constant and that they are both different,
this should give me two straight lines offset by a constant. Seen in
(figure 5), this yields less than optimal result. A first correction
would be to account for the differing slope at different measurement
points. Once we do that the data looks a little more linear, and we can
fit a line through it, as seen in (figure&amp;nbsp;6).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRpFDSXYbI/AAAAAAAACEo/pce7SNz6s_U/s1600/avv.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRpFDSXYbI/AAAAAAAACEo/pce7SNz6s_U/s400/avv.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure
5: Acceleration vs.&amp;nbsp;velocity&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRpIHtielI/AAAAAAAACEw/-MuDiahJbxg/s1600/avvfixed.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGRpIHtielI/AAAAAAAACEw/-MuDiahJbxg/s400/avvfixed.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Figure
6: Adjusted for slope and&amp;nbsp;fitted&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The fits are given by: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ a = (1.022 \\rm{m}) - (0.00427 \\rm{1/m})
v\^2\\;\\; \\rm{(University)} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ a = (1.465 \\rm{m}) - (0.00572
\\rm{1/m}) v\^2\\;\\; \\rm{(State)} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and we can quickly extract the
terminal velocity out of the coefficients to get a factor of 47.9 m/s
for the first line and 41.4 m/s for the second. These both fall within
20% of our initial estimate, which is quite satisfying considering how
bad the data looks. A few final&amp;nbsp;thoughts:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Why is the data so noisy? I can think of a lot of reasons. My Droid
    phone is not quite a scientific measuring device to begin with, and
    we did some numerical derivation of the initial data we got from it.
    On top of that, the way I sit on the bike, the weight of the bag I
    carry with me and other factors like the wind changed from ride to&amp;nbsp;ride.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;I tried to avoid biasing the analysis and I was quite relieved when
    the final numbers came out so close to my original estimate. I did
    play around a little with a different presentation that didn&amp;#8217;t look
    linear at all, but other than that I think what I did was pretty&amp;nbsp;straightforward.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;The one thing that I don&amp;#8217;t like about the final results is the
    constant addition to both acceleration fits, or put another way, the
    fact that after subtracting the gravitational pull from the
    acceleration I still get positive numbers, while the drag force
    should work to reduce it. I suspect this implies that my
    cancellation of the sinθ term was less than&amp;nbsp;perfect.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Can you figure out what the trajectory the bike as a function of
    time looks like? There&amp;#8217;s a (non-trivial) analytic&amp;nbsp;expression.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;</summary><category term="data"></category><category term="bike"></category><category term="measurement"></category><category term="fun"></category></entry><entry><title>Teminal Velocity</title><link href="/posts/teminal-velocity.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-08-11T14:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Yariv</name></author><id>tag:,2010-08-11:posts/teminal-velocity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The impetus for this post lies with three facts. First, I like to bike
to work. Second, Cornell sits on a
&lt;a href="http://www.cornell.edu/search/index.cfm?tab=facts&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;id=272"&gt;hill&lt;/a&gt;. And
finally, I&amp;#8217;m not very brave. As a result of all of these, along with
Ithaca&amp;#8217;s less-than-optimal road maintenance, my semi-daily rides home
tend to produce a lot of wear on my brakes as I cruise downhill at what
appears to me to be very high speeds. I began to ponder just how high
this speed really is, and if I could reduce my use of the brakes or if
I&amp;#8217;m going to end up using them anyway at the bottom of the hill.
&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGLwOVisUAI/AAAAAAAACD4/V9TvWzmEv9k/s200/200px-Free_body.svg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 1: An inclined&amp;nbsp;plane&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I asked myself, what do I remember about bikes going down the hill?
Well, I remember the good old inclined plane (figure 1), and I remember
that air resistance is proportional to velocity, so that the equation of
motion is given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ma = mg\\sin\\theta - \\alpha v. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; I had no idea
what α was, though. My first stop in considering it was naturally
Wikipedia. A quick
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terminal_velocity"&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; came up with
the formula &lt;mathjax&gt;$$m a = mg\\sin\\theta - \\frac{1}{2}\\rho A C\_d v\^2$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where ρ is the density of air, A the projected area of the body and C~d~
the drag coefficient The first thing to notice here is that I was wrong
- drag in a fluid acts like the velocity squared, and not the velocity.
Second, we can easily determine terminal velocity out of this formula -
it&amp;#8217;s the speed at which the sum of the forces equals to zero, or &lt;mathjax&gt;$$v\_t
= \\sqrt{\\frac{2mg\\sin\\theta}{\\rho A C\_d}}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; We can throw in some
numbers into that. ρ = 1.2 kg/m^3^ for air; Wikipedia estimates C~d~ =
0.9 for a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drag_coefficient"&gt;cyclist&lt;/a&gt;. For
the mass, we need to add up mine (\~75 kg), the bike&amp;#8217;s (15-20 kg) and my
bag&amp;#8217;s (let&amp;#8217;s say 5 kg). We come to about 100 kg, give or take 5%. A is a
little harder to estimate, but height times width gives me an initial
guess of 0.62 m^2^, which I&amp;#8217;ll revise to 0.7 m^2^ to account for the
bike, flailing arms and fashionable helmet, up to about 10% accuracy.
We&amp;#8217;re left with sinθ, which varies by road, but in general we expect the
terminal velocity to look like &lt;mathjax&gt;$$v\_t \\approx \\left(50 \\pm 3
\\rm{m/s}\\right) \\sqrt{\\sin\\theta}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; This appears not-unreasonable.
For an 8% grade like we have down University avenue this yields about 50
km/h and for a 13% grade like we have down Buffalo street this will
bring us up to a respectable 65
&lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/post-edit.g?blogID=8807287158334608095&amp;amp;postID=6743488546064317383#miles" title="That's - sigh - about 30 mph and 40 mph, respectively, in crazy units"&gt;km/h&lt;/a&gt;.
Both, incidentally, are faster than I&amp;#8217;m willing to go down a badly
maintained, not entire straight road. So we have some numbers, and I
begin to feel justified about pressing those breaks often, but all of
this is really an introduction for the next post, in which I go against
all my theorist instincts and take some data in the field. Stay&amp;nbsp;tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/post-edit.g?blogID=8807287158334608095&amp;amp;postID=6743488546064317383"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;That&amp;#8217;s&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sigh - about 30 mph and 40 mph, respectively, in crazy&amp;nbsp;units&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="analysis"></category><category term="guestimation"></category><category term="bike"></category><category term="wiki"></category><category term="equations"></category></entry><entry><title>Letting Air Out of Tires II</title><link href="/posts/letting-air-out-of-tires-ii.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-05-04T14:52:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:,2010-05-04:posts/letting-air-out-of-tires-ii.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/05/letting-air-out-of-tires.html"&gt;recent
post&lt;/a&gt;
I calculated how cold air coming out of bike tires should feel. However,
at the end of the post, I did note that there are competing explanations
for why the air cools. There&amp;#8217;s the approach I took, which is adiabatic
cooling, but there&amp;#8217;s also something called the Joule-Thomson effect. The
Joule-Thomson effect has the interesting property that helium being let
out of a bike tire would actually be warmer, which suggests an immediate
way to test which effect is dominant. We pressurize a bike tire with
helium, and see if the valve gets cold or hot. This is exactly what I
did. With the help of Mark and Vince, our local equipment gurus, I was
able to pressurize a bike tire to 26 psi with helium. Using one of those
little thermal measurers you can buy at radio shack, we measured the
initial temperature of the valve as 80 F. We then released the helium,
and measured the temperature of the valve as 73 F. The adiabatic
approach is the winner! Our experiment confirms that the dominant effect
of the cooling is the adiabatic cooling I talked about yesterday. The
Joule-Thomson effect may be at play, but if so it takes a secondary role
to the adiabatic cooling. Now, some of you may be saying: wait a second,
you predicted the air would be -100 F! It doesn&amp;#8217;t feel that cold! Nor
did your valve cool down to -100 F! To which I reply: Yes, I did predict
very cold air. But you have to remember that it is mixing with a lot of
room temperature air, so it won&amp;#8217;t feel as cold as I predicted. Nor will
it transfer much heat to the valve (recall, we predicted this would be
an adiabatic process, with absolutely no heat transfer, something that
is obviously false). Also, I didn&amp;#8217;t have 60 psi of pressure. If we do
the calculation, 26 psi only gives a temperature of 250K = - 10 F.
Hopefully that answers your question. And now, dear reader, as I&amp;#8217;ve
wanted to say for a while: Myth&amp;nbsp;Busted!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bike"></category><category term="tire"></category><category term="thermodynamics"></category><category term="gas"></category><category term="cold"></category><category term="experiment"></category><category term="busted"></category></entry><entry><title>Letting Air Out of Tires</title><link href="/posts/letting-air-out-of-tires.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-05-03T23:21:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:,2010-05-03:posts/letting-air-out-of-tires.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Have you ever noticed how when you let air out of a bike tire (or, I
suppose, a car tire) it feels rather cold? Today we&amp;#8217;re going to explore
why that is, and just how cold it is. Many people consider the air
escaping from a tire as a classic example of an adiabatic process. What
is an adiabatic process? It is a process that happens so quickly there
is no time for heat flow to occur. For our air in the bike tire this
means we&amp;#8217;re letting it out of the tire so quickly that no energy can
move into it from the surrounding air. This may not be exactly true,
there may be a little energy flow, but there is little enough that we
can ignore it. Given that, how do we talk about temperature change?
Let&amp;#8217;s give a physical motivation first. Imagine a gas as a collection of
hard spheres, like baseballs. Envision this bunch of baseballs in a box.
Suppose you make the volume of the box smaller, you move the walls in.
The baseballs will start to bounce around faster. Having trouble
thinking of this? Think of a single baseball in a box. Imagine it hits a
wall moving towards it. What happens? That&amp;#8217;s just like what happens when
a baseball hits a baseball bat moving towards it, it goes flying. That
is, it starts moving faster. The speed with which these gas particles
are moving is what we measure as temperature. So shrinking our box
increases the temperature. Likewise, expanding our box will decrease the
temperature. The same principle holds here. Our gas is expanding from a
small volume (the bike tire) into a larger volume (the surrounding
world). Thus we expect the temperature to decrease.
Got all that? Good. Now for some math. It turns out that using the ideal
gas law, we can derive that for an (reversible) adiabatic process
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$PV\^\\gamma=constant$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where P is the pressure of the gas, V is the volume of the gas, and
gamma is (for our purposes) just a number. The ideal gas law states that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$PV=NkT$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Where N is the number of gas molecules we have, T is the temperature of
the gas, and k is a constant. Since N doesn&amp;#8217;t change in the process
we&amp;#8217;re considering, we can use this to rewrite the above equation, by
substituting for V. This gives
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$P\^{1-\\gamma}T\^{\\gamma}=constant$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Where the constant is not the same as above.
Because this is equal to a constant, we can say that our initial
pressure and temperature are related to our final pressure and
temperature by
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$P\_i\^{1-\\gamma}T\_i\^{\\gamma}=P\_f\^{1-\\gamma}T\_f\^{\\gamma}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
We can solve this for the final temperature giving
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$T\_f=T\_i\\left(\\frac{P\_i}{P\_f}\\right)\^{\\tfrac{1-\\gamma}{\\gamma}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Finally, we can plug in some numbers. Gamma is 7/5 for diatomic gases
(which is most of air). If we assume the air is about room temperature,
20 C, and the tire is at 60 psi, this gives (1 atmosphere of pressure is
15 psi):
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$T\_f=293K\\left(\\frac{60 psi}{15
psi}\\right)\^{\\tfrac{1-7/5}{7/5}}=197K$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Converting back from Kelvin to C, this is -76 C or -105 F. That&amp;#8217;s cold!
&lt;strong&gt;For the Expert:&lt;/strong&gt;
There is actually a debate as to whether or not adiabatic cooling is
responsible for the chill of air upon being let out of a tire. The
argument for it is fairly straightforward. The released air does work on
the surrounding atmosphere as it leaves, lowering the energy of the gas.
If this is the primary effect, then the change in temperature is given
above. However, it is possible that we can consider this a free
adiabatic expansion. In a free adiabatic expansion (like a gas expanding
into a vacuum), there is no work done, because gas is not acting
&amp;#8216;against&amp;#8217; anything.
The other possibility is the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joule%E2%80%93Thomson_effect"&gt;Joule-Thomson
effect&lt;/a&gt;. I
don&amp;#8217;t claim to understand this effect very thoroughly, but it is another
mechanism for cooling when air is let out of a well insulated valve.
I&amp;#8217;ve seen claims both ways as to which process is actually responsible
for cooling.
Fortunately, a simple experiment suggests itself. Helium heats up
through the Joule-Thomson effect (when it starts abot \~50K). It will
cool down through the above described adiabatic cooling. So, fill a bike
tire with Helium gas, and let it out. See if the valve/gas feels hot or
cold. This will determine the dominant effect. As an experimentalist,
this &lt;a href="http://www.brightlywound.com/?comic=42"&gt;appeals greatly to me&lt;/a&gt;.
But if any theorists out there have ideas, please speak&amp;nbsp;up.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bike"></category><category term="tire"></category><category term="thermodynamics"></category><category term="gas"></category><category term="cold"></category><category term="experiment"></category></entry></feed>