<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.feynman.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2010-09-14T20:06:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Visualizing Quantum Mechanics</title><link href="/posts/visualizing-quantum-mechanics.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-14T20:06:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:,2010-09-14:posts/visualizing-quantum-mechanics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Or how I learned to stop worrying and love the&amp;nbsp;computer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[Note:  There&amp;#8217;s a neat video below the fold.&amp;nbsp;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A&amp;nbsp;Confession&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was recently rereading the &lt;a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=_6XvAAAAMAAJ&amp;amp;q=Feynman+lectures+on+physics&amp;amp;dq=Feynman+lectures+on+physics&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;ei=6wmQTPzsDIG78gbAp_joDQ&amp;amp;sa=X&amp;amp;oi=book_result&amp;amp;ct=result&amp;amp;resnum=2&amp;amp;ved=0CDgQ6AEwAQ"&gt;Feynman Lectures on Physics&lt;/a&gt;.  If you haven&amp;#8217;t read them lately, I highly recommend them.  Feynman is always a pleasure to read.  As usual, I was surprised.  This time the surprise came in lecture 9, which the way the course was laid out meant that this was something like the last lecture in the third week that these students had ever received of university level&amp;nbsp;physics.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The lecture is on Newton&amp;#8217;s laws of dynamics.  The start is of course Newton&amp;#8217;s &lt;strike&gt;first&lt;/strike&gt; (second) law,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F = \frac{d }{dt } (mv ) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
which, provided the mass is constant takes the more familiar form
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F = ma $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After discussing the meaning of the equation and how in general it can give you a set of equations to solve, he naturally uses an example to illustrate the kinds of problems you can&amp;nbsp;solve.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What system does he choose to use as the first illustration of a dynamical system?&lt;br /&gt;
&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The Solar&amp;nbsp;System.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That&amp;#8217;s right.  Let that settle for a second.  The sad thing is that if you caught me off guard before I read the lecture, caught me in an honest moment and asked me how you would solve the solar system, I would probably have launched into a discussion of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/N-body_problem"&gt;N-body problem&lt;/a&gt; and how there is no closed form solution to newtonian gravity that involves 3 or more bodies.  (Depending on who you are, I might have then mentioned the &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1991CeMDA..50...73W"&gt;recent caveat&lt;/a&gt;, namely that there is a closed form solution to the N-body problem, but that it involves a very very very slowly convergent&amp;nbsp;series).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, how can Feynman use the Solar System as his first example of solving Newtonian dynamics and I have told you that it&amp;#8217;s impossible as my first words on the subject?  Well, the answer of course is that Feynman was much smarter than I am.  Perhaps another way to say it is that in a lot of ways Feynman was a more contemporary physicist than I&amp;nbsp;am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A&amp;nbsp;Realization&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Physics education has changed very little in the last 50 years or so.  Now in some ways this isn&amp;#8217;t a problem.  The laws of nature also haven&amp;#8217;t changed in the last 50 years.  What&amp;#8217;s unfortunate is that the tools available to physicists to answer their questions have changed remarkably.  Namely,&amp;nbsp;computers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Computers are great.  They permeate daily life nowadays.  They are capable of performing millions of computations per second.  This is great for physics.  You see, a lot of the time, as you all know, the way you achieve answers to specific questions about the evolution of a system is to do a lot of&amp;nbsp;computation.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what did physicists do before computers?  Well, a lot of time they would have to do a lot of calculations out by hand, but no one enjoys that, so a lot of times you would have to make sacrifices, make assumptions that meant that your analytical investigations were simple enough to yield tiddy little equations.  This is reflected in the kinds of problems we still solve in our physics classes.  I never solved the solar system in my mechanics class.  I never did it because there isn&amp;#8217;t a closed form analytical solution to the solar&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But you know what&amp;#8230;  that doesn&amp;#8217;t matter.  It doesn&amp;#8217;t matter in the least.  Because while there doesn&amp;#8217;t exist a closed form solution to the problem, it is very easy to come up with a numerical approximation scheme (see &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Euler_method"&gt;Euler Method&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, the point of physics is to get answers to questions.  And the fact of the matter is that those answers don&amp;#8217;t have to be &amp;#8216;exact&amp;#8217;, they don&amp;#8217;t have to be perfect.  They need to be good enough that we can&amp;#8217;t tell the difference between them being &amp;#8216;exact&amp;#8217; and them being an&amp;nbsp;approximation.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To do this numerically with a pad of paper and a pencil is a heroic task.  Do do this with a computer takes a couple of lines of python code and a couple&amp;nbsp;seconds.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;An&amp;nbsp;example&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As an example of the neat things you can do with a few lines of python code and a few minutes on your hand, check this&amp;nbsp;out.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object height="385" width="480"&gt;&lt;param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/XItlfxaZ9sQ?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/XItlfxaZ9sQ?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="480" height="385"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=J4Wg_b8bVm8"&gt;and&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=idpQOJKOh6Y"&gt;there&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Z9121zwpbBs"&gt;more&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This video depicts time dependent quantum mechanics.  I set up a gaussian wavepacket, inside of a potential that includes a hard wall on the sides and is proportional to x.  That sounds fancy but what it means is that this is the quantum mechanics equivalent of a bouncing ball.  The amplitude of the wave function corresponds to the probability of finding the particle at any location.  That is, imagine picking one of the colored pixels at random.  If you pick any of the colored pixels at random, and look down at the x position, that is what measuring the position of the particle would&amp;nbsp;do.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what are the colors?  Quantum mechanical wave functions are complex.  This means you can represent them either with a real and imaginary part, or with a magnitude and a phase.  Here it&amp;#8217;s the latter.  Like I said the amplitude is shown with the height (actually the amplitude squared).  The color corresponds to the phase, where the phase is mapped to a location on the color wheel, just like the one that pops up in Photoshop or&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GIMP&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And theres sound too!  The sound is what the wave function would sound like if it was making noise.  Its the real part of the wave function played as a sound.  To that end, in this video it is very low frequency, because I made the movie slow enough to see the colors changing&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its fun to watch the video and listen to the sound.  For this movie the sound correlates nicely to when the &amp;#8216;ball&amp;#8217; reaches its maximum&amp;nbsp;height. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whats also cool is that you can hear the &amp;#8216;ball&amp;#8217; delocalize after each bounce.  The sound and function start off being nice and sharp, but after a few bounces it starts to spread&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can also see how momentum is encoded in quantum mechanics.  Funny thing is that instead of being something separate that you need to specify like in classical mechanics, in quantum mechanics the wave function is a complete description of the evolution of the system.  I.e. if I showed you just one frame of this bouncing ball, you would be able to recreate the entire movie.  If I showed you just one frame of a classical basketball, you&amp;#8217;d have no idea what frame came next since you&amp;#8217;d only know its position, not its&amp;nbsp;velocity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In quantum mechanics the momentum gets encoded in the wave function, and as you can tell its encoded as a complex twist.  A phase gradient.  A crazy&amp;nbsp;rainbow.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you look closely, you can even see that you can tell the difference between whether the particle is falling left or right.  When it goes left the rainbow pattern goes (reading left to right) blue red green.  When its moving right it goes blue green red.  It twists one way then the other in the complex plane.  The colors are a little hard to see in this one, they&amp;#8217;re a little easier to see in this&amp;nbsp;one:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object height="385" width="480"&gt;&lt;param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/Z9121zwpbBs?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/Z9121zwpbBs?fs=1&amp;amp;hl=en_US&amp;amp;rel=0" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="480" height="385"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This second one I dressed up a bit, labelling the axes with units, putting a time counter, superimposing the potential I was talking about, and marking the average expected position with a tracer black dot on the&amp;nbsp;bottom.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Call to&amp;nbsp;Arms&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Any student who has taken a first course in quantum mechanics knows enough physics to make these movies.  The physics isn&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;complicated.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But the movies really neat, right?  More than neat.  Making these videos taught me things about quantum mechanics I should have learned a long time&amp;nbsp;ago.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I really think computers are underestimated in physics education.  They can be a great tool.  A picture is worth a thousand words, so a movie must be worth&amp;nbsp;millions*.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*: denotes stolen&amp;nbsp;quote&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;More than just as an illustrative tool, the fact that even students in the first introductory mechanics physics course can solve for something like the solar system shouldn&amp;#8217;t be hidden from them.  Classical mechanics after all is the physics of pretty much every object we can see and touch, but classics mechanics classes only ever talk about &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Atwood_machine"&gt;Atwood machines&lt;/a&gt; and frictionless planes.  Often the closest they come to realism is in discussing projectile motion, where the laws you learn in the book (neglecting air resistance) are very good at describing the trajectories of very dense large objects (i.e. cannonballs).  I can&amp;#8217;t remember the last time I&amp;#8217;ve fired a cannon.  But air resistance serves little trouble to my computer. Or &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/tag/air-resistance/"&gt;Rhett&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; (of Dot Physics, which has just moved to&amp;nbsp;Wired). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Basically, if you give a student an intro physics course and an intro programming course, suddenly you have a human being who is better equipped to answer questions about natural phenomenon than 99% of human beings that have ever&amp;nbsp;lived.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So lets take a tip from Feynman and teach physics students how to solve the solar&amp;nbsp;system.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Code&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As per request, here is the python code I used to generate the videos.  Its rather messy, so I apologize in&amp;nbsp;advance.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/leaf?id=0B8Il0b2saix4NzYzMmRhZDUtODFhZS00YTE1LTgzZWYtMzVhODI5YzRhNWJm&amp;hl=en&amp;authkey=CPrk9IUM"&gt;schrod.py&lt;/a&gt;  - A general script which finds the eigenvalues and eigenbasis for a 1D particle with an arbitrary&amp;nbsp;potential.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/leaf?id=0B8Il0b2saix4ZDYxZmFlNzQtYzdkNC00YTVkLWJhNWMtN2IxM2ZmZDg4Mzg4&amp;hl=en&amp;authkey=CJ3m4ogJ"&gt;qmsolver-bouncy.py&lt;/a&gt; - Code to generate the movie.  You need to create a directory with the same name as the name in the script in the save folder as the script.  The last two lines make the sound and the directory full of images.  I used ffmpeg to wrap the two&amp;nbsp;together.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="fun"></category><category term="feynman"></category><category term="quantum mechanics"></category><category term="solar system"></category><category term="movie"></category><category term="bouncing ball"></category></entry><entry><title>Some of the Best Advice You’ll Ever Receive</title><link href="/posts/some-of-the-best-advice-you-ll-ever-receive.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-25T20:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:,2010-04-25:posts/some-of-the-best-advice-you-ll-ever-receive.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across what might be the best advice any student (nay any human being) could possibly ever receive reading a book today&amp;#8230;
&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;Now there are two ways in which you can increase your understanding of these issues.  One way is to remember the general ideas and then go home and try to figure out what commands you need and make sure you don&amp;#8217;t leave one out.  Make the set shorter or longer for convidence and try to understand the tradeoffs by trying to do problems with your choice.  This is the way I would do it because I have that kind of personality!  It&amp;#8217;s the way I study &amp;#8212; to understand somethingby trying to work it out or, in other words, to understand something by creating it.  Not creating it one hundred percent, of course; but taking a hint as to which direction to go but not remembering the details.  These you work out for&amp;nbsp;yourself.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The other way, which is also valuable, is to read carefully how someone else did it.  I find the first method best for me, once I have understood the basic idea.  If I get stuck I look at a book that tells me how someone else did it.  I turn the pages and then I say &amp;#8220;Oh, I forgot that bit&amp;#8221;, then close the book and carry on.  Finally, after you&amp;#8217;ve figured out how to do it you read how they did it and find out how dum your solution is and how much more clever and efficient theirs is!  But this way you can understand the cleverness of their ideas and have a framework in which to think about the problem.  When I start straight off to read someone else&amp;#8217;s solution I find it boring and uninteresting, with no way of putting the whole picture together.  &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AT&lt;/span&gt; least, thats the way it works for&amp;nbsp;me!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Throughout the book, I will suggest some problems for you to play with.  You might feel tempted to skip them.  If they&amp;#8217;re too hard, fine.  Some of them are pretty difficult!  But you might skip them thinking that, well, they&amp;#8217;ve probably been done by somebody else; so what&amp;#8217;s the point?  Well, of &lt;i&gt;course&lt;/i&gt; they&amp;#8217;ve been done! But so what?  Do them for the &lt;i&gt;fun&lt;/i&gt; of it.  That&amp;#8217;s how to learn the knack of doing things when you have to do them.  Let me give you an example.  Suppose I wanted to add up a series of&amp;nbsp;numbers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1 + 2 + 3 + 4 + 5 + 6 + 7&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;up to say, 62.  No doubt you know how to do it; but when you play with this sort of problem as a kid, and you haven&amp;#8217;t been shown the answer &amp;#8230; it&amp;#8217;s &lt;i&gt;fun&lt;/i&gt; trying to figure out how to do it.  Then, as you go into adulthood, you develop a certain confidence that you can discover things&amp;#8217; but if they&amp;#8217;ve already been discovered, that shouldn&amp;#8217;t bother you at all. &lt;b&gt;What one fool can do, so can another, and the fact that some other fool beat you to it shouldn&amp;#8217;t disturb you: you should get a kick out of having discovered something.&lt;/b&gt;  Most of the problems I give you in this book have been worked over many times, and many ingenious solutions have been devised for them.  But if you keep proving stuff that other s have done, getting confidence, increasing the complexities of your solution for the fun of it &amp;#8212; then one day you&amp;#8217;ll turn around and discover that &lt;i&gt;nobody actually did that one!&lt;/i&gt;  And that&amp;#8217;s the way to become a scientist.&lt;/blockquote&gt;
The quote is from none other than &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_feynman"&gt;Richard Feynman&lt;/a&gt; in his &lt;a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=-olQAAAAMAAJ&amp;q=feynman+lectures+on+computation&amp;dq=feynman+lectures+on+computation&amp;ei=4dLUS4HBC43aygSIqaXoCQ&amp;cd=1"&gt;Lectures on Computation&lt;/a&gt; (a great read by the way). [reproduced without&amp;nbsp;permission]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Honestly I think that&amp;#8217;s one of the biggest problems with science and math education in this country.  They have taken something which is fun and challenging, a path of discovery, and reduced it to memorizing a list of dogmatic equations handed down from high.  Students are all but taught that the men and women that discovered these laws are somehow above the rest of&amp;nbsp;us.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the best kept secrets of science is that scientists are in fact mere mortals.  They have their faults, and deficiencies just like the rest of us.  You don&amp;#8217;t need anything special to do science, all you need is a sense of curiosity and wonder, and the resolve to spend some time working at it.  The more time you work at it, the better you&amp;nbsp;get.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Science is not a list of facts.  It is not plugging numbers into equations.  It is neither history nor accounting.  It is, in its purest form, the recognition that as human beings we are each endowed with the power to come to understand the world around&amp;nbsp;us.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I firmly believe that anyone of a sane mind is capable of becoming a physicist.  I&amp;#8217;m not saying that everyone should be; people should follow their passions, but I worry that too many students are turned away thinking they aren&amp;#8217;t cut out to be scientists, and that&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;rubbish.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;#8217;s my two&amp;nbsp;cents.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="education"></category><category term="feynman"></category><category term="advice"></category></entry></feed>