<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.pi-day.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2012-03-14T15:13:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Pi storage</title><link href="/posts/pi-storage.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T15:13:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:,2012-03-14:posts/pi-storage.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-4x2fD-exJns/T2DAEJqroqI/AAAAAAAAAbI/8_9quiDP4p0/s1600/floppies.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="155" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-4x2fD-exJns/T2DAEJqroqI/AAAAAAAAAbI/8_9quiDP4p0/s320/floppies.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let me share my worst &amp;#8220;best idea ever&amp;#8221; moment.  Sometime during my undergraduate I thought I had solved all the world&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;problems.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You see, on this fateful day, my hard drive was full. I hate it when my hard drive fills up, it means I have to go and get rid of some of my stuff.  I hate getting rid of my stuff.  But what can someone&amp;nbsp;do?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And then it hit me, I had the bright idea:
&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;What if we didn&amp;#8217;t have to &lt;i&gt;store&lt;/i&gt; things, what if we could just &lt;i&gt;compute&lt;/i&gt; files whenever we wanted them back?&lt;/blockquote&gt;Sounds like an awesome idea, right?  I know.  But how could we compute our files?  Well, as you may know pi is conjectured to be a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normal_number"&gt;normal number&lt;/a&gt;, meaning its digits are probably random.  We also know that it is irrational, meaning pi never&amp;nbsp;ends&amp;#8230;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Since its digits are random, and they never end, in principle any sequence you could ever imagine should show up in pi eventually.  In fact there is a nifty website &lt;a href="http://pi.nersc.gov/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that will let you search for arbitrary strings (using a 5-bit format) in first 4 billion digits, for example &amp;#8220;alemi&amp;#8221; &lt;a href="http://pi.nersc.gov/cgi-bin/pi.cgi?word=alemi&amp;amp;format=char"&gt;seems to show up&lt;/a&gt; at around digit&amp;nbsp;3149096356.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So in principle, I could send you just an index, and a length, and you could compute the resulting&amp;nbsp;file.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But wait you cry, isn&amp;#8217;t computing digits of pi hard, don&amp;#8217;t people work really hard to compute pi farther and farther?  Hold on I claim, first of all, I&amp;#8217;m imagining a future where computation is cheap.  Secondly, there is a really neat algorithm, the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bailey%E2%80%93Borwein%E2%80%93Plouffe_formula"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BBP&lt;/span&gt; algorithm&lt;/a&gt;, that enables you to compute the kth binary digit of pi without knowing any of the preceding digits.  In other words, in principle if you wanted to know the 4 billionth digit of pi, you can compute it without having to first compute the first 4 billion other&amp;nbsp;digits.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Cool, this is beginning to sound like a really good idea.  What&amp;#8217;s the&amp;nbsp;catch?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps you&amp;#8217;ve already gotten a taste of it.  Let&amp;#8217;s try to estimate just how far along in pi we would have to look before our message of interest shows&amp;nbsp;up. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s assume we have written our file in binary, and are computing pi in binary&amp;nbsp;e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;11.
00100100 00111111 01101010 10001000 10000101 10100011 00001000 11010011&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;etc.  So, if the sequence is random, there is a 1/2 chance that at any point we get the right starting bit of our file, and then a 1/2 chance we get the next one, etc.  So the chance that we would create our file if we were randomly flipping coins would be
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P = \left( \frac{1}{2} \right)^N = 2^{-N} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
if our file was N bits&amp;nbsp;long.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So where do we expect this sequence to first show up in the digits of pi?  Well, this turns out to be a &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/CoinTossing.html"&gt;subtle problem&lt;/a&gt;, but we can get a feel for it by assuming that we compute N digits of pi at a time and see if its right or not.  If its not, we move on to the next group of N digits, if its right, we&amp;#8217;re done.  If this were the case, we should expect to have to draw about
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{1}{P} = 2^N $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
times until we have a success, and since each trial ate up N digits, we should expect to see our file show up after about
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N 2^N $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
digits of&amp;nbsp;pi.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great, so instead of handing you the file, I could just hand you the index the file is located.  But how many bits would I need to tell you that index.  Well, just like we know that 10^3 takes 4 digits to express in decimal, and 6 x 10^7 takes 8 digits to express, in general it takes
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ d = \log_b x + 1 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
digits to express a number in base b, in this case it takes
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ d = \log_2 ( N 2^N ) + 1= \log_2 2^N + \log_2 N + 1 = N + \log_2 N + 1 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
digits to express this index in&amp;nbsp;binary.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And there&amp;#8217;s the rub.  Instead of sending you N bits of information contained in the file, all my genius compression algorithm has manged to do is replace N bits of information in the file, with a number that takes ( ~ N + \log_2 N ) bits to express.  I&amp;#8217;ve actually managed to make the files larger not&amp;nbsp;smaller!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You may have noticed above, that even for the simple case of &amp;#8220;alemi&amp;#8221;, all I managed to do was swap the binary&amp;nbsp;message&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;alemi -&amp;gt; 0000101100001010110101001
with the index 3149096356 -&amp;gt; 10111011101100110110010110100100&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;which is longer in&amp;nbsp;binary!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As an aside, you may have felt uncomfortable with my estimation for how long we have to wait to see our message, and you would be right.  Just because all N digits I draw at a time don&amp;#8217;t match up doesn&amp;#8217;t mean that the second half isn&amp;#8217;t useful.  For instance if I was looking for 010, lets say some of the digits are 101,010.  While both of those sequences didn&amp;#8217;t match, if I was looking at every digit at a time, I would have found a match.  And you&amp;#8217;d be right.  &lt;a href="http://www.cs.elte.hu/~mori/cikkek/Expectation.pdf"&gt;Smarter people than I&lt;/a&gt; have computed just how long you should have to wait, and end up with the better estimation
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{wait time} \sim 2^N N \log 2 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
which is pretty darn close to our silly&amp;nbsp;estimate. &lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pi day"></category><category term="fun"></category><category term="probability"></category><category term="storage"></category></entry><entry><title>A Clarification</title><link href="/posts/a-clarification.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T12:20:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Yariv</name></author><id>tag:,2012-03-14:posts/a-clarification.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;As there seems to be some &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Date_format#Date_format"&gt;confusion&lt;/a&gt; among my fellow Virtuosi, I wanted to point out that Pi day occurs on July 22nd or, in the year 4159, on January&amp;nbsp;3rd.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today is in fact &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Waring%27s_problem"&gt;Seventh Power Day&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Eurocentrism"></category><category term="pi day"></category><category term="day-month-year"></category></entry><entry><title>Pi-rithmetic</title><link href="/posts/pi-rithmetic.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T11:52:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:,2012-03-14:posts/pi-rithmetic.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-7rfL9Iby34A/T2C3LhSj_6I/AAAAAAAAAa0/rXTR30c77bk/s1600/IMAG0200.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="188" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-7rfL9Iby34A/T2C3LhSj_6I/AAAAAAAAAa0/rXTR30c77bk/s320/IMAG0200.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Fun fact:  pi squared is very close to 10.  How close?  Well, &lt;a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=%2810+-pi%5E2+%29%2Fpi%5E2"&gt;Wolfram Alpha&lt;/a&gt; tells me that it is only about 1%&amp;nbsp;off.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I first realized this fact when looking at my slide rule, pictured to the left (click to embiggen), just another reason why slide rules are&amp;nbsp;awesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It turns out I use this fact all of the time.  How&amp;#8217;s that you ask?  Well, I use this fast to enable me to do very quick mental arithmetic. 
&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It goes like this.  For every number you come across in a calculation, drop all of the information save two parts, first, what&amp;#8217;s its order of magnitude, that is, how many digits does it have, and second, is it closest to 1, pi, or&amp;nbsp;10?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first part amounts to thinking of every number you come across as it looks in scientific notation, so a number like 2342 turns into 2.342 x 10^3, so that I&amp;#8217;ve captured its magnitude in a power of 10.  As for the next part, the rules I usually use&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;If the remaining bit is between 1 and 2, make it&amp;nbsp;1&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;If its between 2 and 6.5 make it&amp;nbsp;pi&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;if its bigger than 6.5, make it another&amp;nbsp;10&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Another way to think of this is to estimate every number to be a power of ten, and then either 1, a few, or 10.  The reason I choose pi is because if I use pi, I know how the rest of the arithmetic should work, namely, I only need to know a few rules, plus when I use this to estimate answers of physics formulae, making a bunch of pis show up tends to help me cancel other natural pis that are in the formulae.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;$$ \pi \times \pi \sim10 \qquad \frac{1}{\pi} \sim \frac{\pi}{10} \qquad \sqrt{10} \sim \pi $$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Which you might notice is just the same approximation written in 3 different ways.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s work an example&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;   $$  \begin{align*}  23 \times 78 / 13 \times 2133  &amp;amp;= ? \ \pi \times 10 \times 100 / 10 \times \pi \times 10^3 &amp;amp;= ? \ \pi^2 \times 10^5 &amp;amp;\sim 10^6 \ \end{align*}$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;of course the &lt;a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=23+*+78%2F13+*+2133"&gt;real answer&lt;/a&gt; is 294,354, so you&amp;#8217;ll notice I got the answer wrong, but I only got it wrong by a factor of 3, which is pretty good for mental arithmetic, and in particular mental arithmetic that takes no time flat.&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;In fact, the average error I introduce by using this approximation is just 30% or so for each number, which I&amp;#8217;ve shown below [the script that produced this plot for those interested is &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/2037431"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-uwGlV6y_pps/T2C90lPhmQI/AAAAAAAAAbA/k_Hl8H-y2ys/s1600/pierr.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="231" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-uwGlV6y_pps/T2C90lPhmQI/AAAAAAAAAbA/k_Hl8H-y2ys/s320/pierr.png" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;So, there you go, now you can impress all of your friends with a simple mental arithmetic that gets you within a factor of 3 or so on average.&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="order of magnitude"></category><category term="pi day"></category><category term="approximation"></category><category term="pi-rithmetic"></category></entry><entry><title>Moving Pi-ctures</title><link href="/posts/moving-pi-ctures.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T08:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:,2012-03-14:posts/moving-pi-ctures.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-YJBJw29pxZk/T1ribOQLS-I/AAAAAAAAAVA/xsJ-KAOJt5w/s1600/tv_pi.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="213" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-YJBJw29pxZk/T1ribOQLS-I/AAAAAAAAAVA/xsJ-KAOJt5w/s320/tv_pi.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;My &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; celebrates without me.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Today, as I&amp;#8217;m sure you&amp;#8217;re aware, is Pi Day - a day for the festive consumption of pies and quiet self-reflection.  In the spirit of the holiday, I&amp;#8217;d like to present a point for&amp;nbsp;discussion:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;i&gt;Everyone has a great talent for at least one&amp;nbsp;thing.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That this is true for at least &lt;i&gt;some&lt;/i&gt; people is seen through even a cursory glance at a history book:  George Washington was really good at leading revolutions, Michelangelo was an outstanding ceiling painter &lt;a href="#note1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id="back1"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, and Batman was the best at solving complex riddles (especially in English, pero &lt;i&gt;especialmente&lt;/i&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RY1U_pXUxUo&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;en español&lt;/a&gt;). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But I&amp;#8217;m certain that this holds for everyone.  What&amp;#8217;s your talent? Mine, as those of you who read this blog should know very well by now, is certainly &lt;i&gt;not&lt;/i&gt; doing physics.  Nope, my talent is watching &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt;.  Seriously guys, I watch &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; like a boss &lt;a href="#note2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id="back2"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  In light of this talent, I thought I would describe a few instances in which I have seen pi represented (for better or for worse) in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; and&amp;nbsp;movies.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Over the last few months, I have been re-watching a lot of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; show &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psych"&gt;Psych&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/i&gt; with my good friend and fellow Virtuosi contributor, Matt &amp;#8220;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TT&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; Showbiz &lt;a href="#note3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id="back3"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.  For the uninitiated, &lt;i&gt;Psych&lt;/i&gt; is a detective show where the main characters (Shawn and Gus) run a (fake) psychic detective agency, which allows them to solve mysteries, engage in various shenanigans, and make an inordinate number of references to &lt;i&gt;Tears for Fears&lt;/i&gt; frontman Curt Smith &lt;a href="#note4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id="back4"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In one of the episodes, Shawn and Gus enter a room where a long train of digits is written across the top of the wall.  It soon becomes evident that these are the digits of pi and the camera is sure to zoom in on the famous first few digits to reassure&amp;nbsp;us. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But there are hundreds of digits written out and I have very little faith in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; prop people when it comes to background mathematical expressions.  So I decided to check it&amp;nbsp;out. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sIqwUS9wlog/T17KQ7mU7nI/AAAAAAAAAV4/1hiiMuN-yxA/s1600/pi_psych1.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="222" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sIqwUS9wlog/T17KQ7mU7nI/AAAAAAAAAV4/1hiiMuN-yxA/s400/pi_psych1.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Pi on the Wall (click to enhance for texture)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Using a neat little pi &lt;a href="http://www.angio.net/pi/piquery"&gt;searcher&lt;/a&gt;, I checked to see if (and where) this sequence appeared in pi.  Turns out it&amp;#8217;s legit and (almost!) correct.  The first 105 digits of pi (counting after the three) are:
&lt;blockquote class="tr_bq"&gt;&lt;div id="showstring"&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: white;"&gt;3.14159265358979323846264338327950288419716939937510582097494459230781640628620899862803482534211706&lt;b&gt;&lt;u&gt;798&lt;/u&gt;&lt;/b&gt;2148&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div id="querytime" style="font-size: 13px; font-style: italic; margin-right: 5px; text-align: right;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: white;"&gt;where I have underlined the 99th, 100th, and 101st digits.  Looking back at the writing on the wall, we see that the 100th digit has been duplicated.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="background-color: white;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;table align="center" cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6vQ2gmfNULw/T17Nb29jAvI/AAAAAAAAAWA/2hMW9vdU3S0/s1600/pi_psych.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="222" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6vQ2gmfNULw/T17Nb29jAvI/AAAAAAAAAWA/2hMW9vdU3S0/s400/pi_psych.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Very Almost Pi&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: white;"&gt;So close!  Oh well, nobody is perfect.  Even though there is an error here, I very much appreciate that whoever was doing the set design decided to use the &lt;i&gt;actual&lt;/i&gt; digits of pi.  All too often I see nonsensical equations in the background of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; shows and movies when it would take &lt;i&gt;exactly the same&lt;/i&gt; amount of work to put real equations there.  So congratulations to you, O nameless prop-making intern!, for giving an accurate (well, to a part in 10^100) value of pi.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="background-color: white;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
Neat, so are there any other &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; shows or movies that have pi in them?  Well, there&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jo18VIoR2xU" style="font-style: italic;"&gt;Pi&lt;/a&gt;.  &lt;i&gt;Pi&lt;/i&gt; is film by Darren Aronofsky (&lt;i&gt;Requiem for a Dream&lt;/i&gt;, etc) about a mathematician looking for patterns in the stock market.  It&amp;#8217;s a pretty good movie with a really cool &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Cq_QO_4Cx4&amp;amp;feature=player_embedded"&gt;soundtrack&lt;/a&gt; by Clint Mansell.  It also appears to display the digits of pi in the opening credits.  But does it?  To the&amp;nbsp;Youtube-mobile!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can watch the opening credits &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L61x5mbE-jc"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if you like and here is a still image of the relevant&amp;nbsp;section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pEbkgRx-PFw/T17UHYdfhwI/AAAAAAAAAWI/vsyzWd139pg/s1600/sad_pi.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="210" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pEbkgRx-PFw/T17UHYdfhwI/AAAAAAAAAWI/vsyzWd139pg/s400/sad_pi.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Pi?&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: white;"&gt;Looks pretty cool, huh?  But once we get past the slick aesthetics, we see that something doesn&amp;#8217;t seem right.  This number they are showing appears at first glance to be our good friend pi, but after the 8th digit the cover is blown and we see that this is actually some impostor number!  &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="background-color: white;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-5afmhwZOhWk/T17U-d1okrI/AAAAAAAAAWQ/KB7NHwwOvQg/s1600/verysadpi.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="210" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-5afmhwZOhWk/T17U-d1okrI/AAAAAAAAAWQ/KB7NHwwOvQg/s400/verysadpi.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;More like Darren Aron-wrong-sky.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;Now, I fully understand that this has no bearing whatsoever on the film and, in the grand scheme of things, is not a Big Deal.  But it would have been just as easy to put the &lt;i&gt;real&lt;/i&gt; digits of pi here instead of just random&amp;nbsp;filler. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The only way that this could possibly be better than the real deal would be if it is actually a secret code.  I have not yet ruled this out, as the movie is entirely about looking for meaning in seemingly random numbers.  Unfortunately, the difficulty in transcribing the numbers from the screen greatly outweighs the very small chance that this isn&amp;#8217;t just gibberish.  Four hundred Quatloos to anyone who can tell me if this is a code or&amp;nbsp;not!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="note1"&gt;[1] And an above average Ninja Turtle to boot. &lt;a href="#back1"&gt;&amp;nbsp;[back] &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;p id="note2"&gt;[2] Yes, I am putting my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; watching skills on par with the talents of George Washington.  In fact, the stoic way in which I persevered through the entirety of &lt;i&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terminator:_The_Sarah_Connor_Chronicles"&gt;The Sarah Connor Chronicles&lt;/a&gt; &lt;/i&gt;in under two weeks was described by historian David McCullough as &amp;#8220;Washingtonian.&amp;#8221;  These are simply facts. &lt;a href="#back2"&gt;&amp;nbsp;[back] &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt; &lt;p id="note3"&gt;[3] The extra &amp;#8220;T&amp;#8221; is for extra talent. &lt;a href="#back3"&gt;&amp;nbsp;[back] &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;  &lt;p id="note4"&gt;[4] A duo can &lt;i&gt;absolutely&lt;/i&gt; have a frontman.  For evidence, feel free to ask the not-George-Michael-guy from &lt;i&gt;Wham!&lt;/i&gt; or the not-Paul-Simon-guy from &lt;i&gt;Simon &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Garfunkel&lt;/i&gt;. &lt;a href="#back4"&gt;&amp;nbsp;[back] &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pineapple"></category><category term="pi day"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>A Very Small Slice of Pi</title><link href="/posts/a-very-small-slice-of-pi.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T08:22:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:,2012-03-14:posts/a-very-small-slice-of-pi.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q37nqPUh_t0/T2AJgUmFLKI/AAAAAAAAAWY/0rvkqKzmDBs/s1600/rhubarb.JPG" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="240" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q37nqPUh_t0/T2AJgUmFLKI/AAAAAAAAAWY/0rvkqKzmDBs/s320/rhubarb.JPG" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Rhubarb pie (Source: Wikipedia)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people know a &lt;i&gt;suspiciously&lt;/i&gt; large number of the digits of pi.  Perhaps you have met one of these people.  They can typically be found hiding behind bushes and under the counters at pastry shops, just&amp;#8230; &lt;i&gt;waiting&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the slightest hint of a mention of pi, they will jump out and start reciting the digits like there&amp;#8217;s a prize at the end.  After rattling off numbers for a few minutes they abruptly come to an end, grin like an idiot, and walk away.  It is an unpleasant&amp;nbsp;encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheer uselessness of this kind of thing has always bothered me, so I&amp;#8217;d like to set a preliminary upper bound on the number of digits of pi that could ever possibly potentially kind of be useful (maybe).  For those following along at home, now would be a good time to put on your numerology&amp;nbsp;hats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Alright, so I hear this thing pi is fairly useful when dealing with circles.  Let&amp;#8217;s say we want to make a really big circle and have its diameter only deviate by a very small amount from the correct value.  To do this successfully, we will have to know pi fairly&amp;nbsp;well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s take this to extremes now.  Suppose I want to put a circle around the &lt;i&gt;entire visible universe&lt;/i&gt; such that the uncertainty in the diameter is the size of a &lt;i&gt;single proton&lt;/i&gt;.  What would be the fractional uncertainty in the circumference in this&amp;nbsp;case?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we know pi exactly, then we have&amp;nbsp;that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\delta C = \frac{\partial C}{\partial d} \delta d = \pi \delta d = C \frac{\delta d}{d}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where d is the diameter and C is the circumference.  In other words, the fractional uncertainty in the circumference is&amp;nbsp;just&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta C}{C} = \frac{\delta d}{d}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a femtometer for the size of a proton and 90 billion light years for the size of the Universe &lt;a href="#note"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id="back"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we&amp;nbsp;get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta C}{C} = \frac{\delta d}{d} = \frac{10^{-15}\mbox{m}}{(90\times10^9)(3\times10^7\mbox{s})(3\times10^8\mbox{m s}^{-1})} \sim\frac{10^{-15}}{10^{27}}\sim10^{-42}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so how well do we need to know pi to get a similar fractional uncertainty?  Well, we have&amp;nbsp;that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta \pi}{\pi} = \frac{\delta C}{C} = 10^{-42}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so we can afford an uncertainty in pi&amp;nbsp;of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \delta \pi = \pi \times 10^{-42}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and thus we&amp;#8217;ll need to know pi to about 42 digits.  How&amp;#8217;s that for an &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phrases_from_The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy#Answer_to_the_Ultimate_Question_of_Life.2C_the_Universe.2C_and_Everything_.2842.29"&gt;answer&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we have a giant circle the size of the &lt;i&gt;entire visible universe&lt;/i&gt;, we can find its diameter to within the size of a &lt;i&gt;single proton&lt;/i&gt; using pi to 42 digits.  Therefore, I adopt this as the maximal number of digits that could ever prove useful in a physical sense (albeit under a somewhat bizzarre set of&amp;nbsp;circumstances). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If reciting hundreds of digits is what makes you happy, go for it.  But 42 digits is more than enough pi for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="note"&gt;[1] &amp;#8220;But I thought the Universe was only 13.7 billion years!  What voodoo is this!?&amp;#8221;  Yeah, I know.  See &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/startswithabang/2011/01/q_a_how_is_the_universe_so_big.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for a nice explanation.&lt;a href="#back"&gt;&amp;nbsp;[back] &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pi day"></category><category term="42"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Primes in Pi</title><link href="/posts/primes-in-pi.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T03:14:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:,2012-03-14:posts/primes-in-pi.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-zr3Ex0CiRk4/T2DBK9RBX-I/AAAAAAAAAbQ/7SA_87njptE/s1600/repunit.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="155" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-zr3Ex0CiRk4/T2DBK9RBX-I/AAAAAAAAAbQ/7SA_87njptE/s320/repunit.png" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Recently, I&amp;#8217;ve been concerned with the fact that I don&amp;#8217;t know many large primes.  Why?  I don&amp;#8217;t know.  This has led to a search for easy to remember prime numbers.  I&amp;#8217;ve found a few goods ones,&amp;nbsp;namely&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt;867-5309  - &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/867-5309/Jenny"&gt;Jenny&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;number&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; the digit 1 - 1031 times, in the style of the picture to above, and the largest known &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Repunit_prime#Repunit_primes"&gt;repunit&amp;nbsp;prime&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt;1987 (my birth year), 2011 (last year), 1999 (&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/1999_(song)"&gt;the party year&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;&lt;div&gt;But then I remembered that I already know 50 digits of pi, memorized one boring day in grade school, so this got me wondering whether there were any primes among the digits of pi&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Lo an behold, I wrote a &lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/2033970"&gt;little script&lt;/a&gt;, and found a few:&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;&lt;span style="background-color: white; font-family: monospace, sans-serif; font-size: 15px; line-height: 15px; text-align: left; white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;Found one, with 1 digits, is: 3 Found one, with 2 digits, is: 31 Found one, with 6 digits, is: 314159 Found a rounded one with 12 digits, is: 314159265359 Found one, with 38 digits, is: 31415926535897932384626433832795028841&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="background-color: white; font-family: monospace, sans-serif; font-size: 15px; line-height: 15px; text-align: left; white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;div style="text-align: -webkit-auto;"&gt;I think it&amp;#8217;s usual for most science geeks to know pi to at least 3.14159, if you&amp;#8217;re one of those people, now you know a 6 digit prime! for free!&lt;span style="font-family: monospace, sans-serif;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 15px; line-height: 15px; white-space: pre-wrap;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;</summary><category term="pi day"></category><category term="primes"></category></entry></feed>