<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/tag.green-power.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2011-03-24T17:46:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Blown Away</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/blown-away.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-03-24T17:46:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-03-24:posts/blown-away.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-NFVShpYzscc/TYutYtPSIVI/AAAAAAAAAEM/vRA8KbFV6tc/s1600/wind-turbine-2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-NFVShpYzscc/TYutYtPSIVI/AAAAAAAAAEM/vRA8KbFV6tc/s200/wind-turbine-2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I was reading a discussion on green energy recently, in particular wind
power, where the following claim was&amp;nbsp;made&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;enough wind turbines to power the world would cover the surface of
the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, this was quickly decried by supporters of wind power, but the claim
has stuck with me. The question on my mind today is: How much of the
earth&amp;#8217;s surface would have to be covered to power the earth with wind
turbines? We can&amp;#8217;t hope to put an exact number on this, the best we&amp;#8217;ll
be able to do is an order of magnitude. I also don&amp;#8217;t know much about
wind turbines, so I&amp;#8217;ll be making liberal use of
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Wind_turbine"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt; as I go. Let&amp;#8217;s
start with the size of the wind turbine. According to wikipedia the
largest wind turbine has a rotor sweep diameter of 128 m. To an order of
magnitude, we&amp;#8217;ll say that our average wind turbine has a diameter of 100
m. Next we need to know how much power this puts out. The maximum power
of this turbine is \~8 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MW&lt;/span&gt;. However, it certainly wouldn&amp;#8217;t be producing
that at all times. Current wind farms produce around 20-30% maximum
capacity. However, these turbines are careful placed in areas of high
wind. We&amp;#8217;re not going to get that lucky with our wind dose when we place
our turbines haphazardly, so we&amp;#8217;ll assume they produce at 1% maximum
capacity. According to
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/World_energy_resources_and_consumption"&gt;wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;,
the world energy consumption in 2008 was 474 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EJ&lt;/span&gt; (exajoules), or an
average power use in 2008 of 15 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TW&lt;/span&gt;. To an order of magnitude then, the
area we&amp;#8217;d have to occupy with wind turbines to power the world would be:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\left( \frac{(100\text{ m})^2}{1\text{
turbine}}\right)\left(\frac{1\text{ turbine}}{.01*8 \text{
MW}}\right)15 \text{TW} = 2\cdot 10^{12}\text{ m}^2$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; That&amp;#8217;s
2&lt;em&gt;10^6 km^2, or, in english, 2 million square kilometers. For
comparison, the land area of the united states is roughly 10 millon
square kilometers. So we&amp;#8217;d only have to cover 1/5th of the united states
with wind turbines to power the entire world (in 2008, no doubt power
use has risen since then)! While that is a lot of space taken up, it is
nowhere near the entire surface of the world. There are, of course,
&lt;a href="http://xkcd.com/556/"&gt;other concerns&lt;/a&gt; about wind power. &lt;/em&gt;Note: maybe
the wind turbines are less efficient overall. Also, I assumed that the
footprint was just the square area of the turbine diameter. I know this
is the size of the face of the turbine, but to an order of magnitude I
imagine it is correct for the space occupied on the&amp;nbsp;ground.*&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="order of magnitude"></category><category term="wind"></category><category term="green power"></category></entry></feed>