<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.problem-of-the-week.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2010 02:01:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Problem of the Week #3: Solution</title><link>/posts/problem-of-the-week-3-solution.html</link><description>&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TPnT0ucqSUI/AAAAAAAAAHk/kOFxbYCSx1g/s1600/koala.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="183" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TPnT0ucqSUI/AAAAAAAAAHk/kOFxbYCSx1g/s200/koala.jpg" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Cold-Blooded Killer&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Hello all and welcome to to another roundup of Problem of the Week.  If the time intervals don&amp;#8217;t seem to be adding up, just remember that &amp;#8220;week&amp;#8221; is an illusion here at Virtuosi headquarters.  &amp;#8220;Problem of the Week,&amp;#8221; doubly so.  But enough with the excuses, let&amp;#8217;s see if Mr. Bond lives to Die Another&amp;nbsp;Day. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The situation presented in the problem was one of a glass of water filled all the way to the top with a single ice cube in it.  The goal is to see if any water falls to the floor as the ice cube&amp;nbsp;melts.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The simplest analysis would be to just consider the displacement of water by the ice cube.  By Archimedes&amp;#8217; principle we know that the buoyant force on the ice cube is equal to the weight of the water displaced by the ice cube.  But since the ice cube is floating, we know that the buoyant force is equal to the weight of the ice cube.  Therefore, the ice cube just displaces it&amp;#8217;s own weight in water.  So as the ice cube melts, the water level stays the same and no water is spilled&amp;nbsp;over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Stated a bit more explicitly, we have that the buoyant force is the weight of the displaced&amp;nbsp;water:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F_b = m_{water}g = {\rho}_{water}V_{water}g $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where we have just expressed the mass of the water as the density of water times the volume of the water displaced.  Likewise, the weight of the ice cube&amp;nbsp;is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ W_{ice} = m_{ice}g = {\rho}_{ice}V_{ice}g $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But since the ice cube is floating, the buoyant force is equal to the weight.  Setting the above equations equal to each other and rearranging a bit, we can solve for the volume of the water displaced by the ice&amp;nbsp;cube:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ V_{water} = \frac{{\rho}_{ice}V_{ice}}{{\rho}_{water}} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great, now we have the volume of water that the ice cube displaced, so now we just need to see what volume of water the ice cube will add once it melts.  Since we know that the mass of ice cube better be the same as the mass of the water left after it melts, we can&amp;nbsp;write&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ {\rho}_{ice}V_{ice} = {\rho}_{water}V_{water} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which gives that the total volume of the water  is&amp;nbsp;just&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div style="margin-bottom: 0px; margin-left: 0px; margin-right: 0px; margin-top: 0px;"&gt;$$ V_{water} = \frac{{\rho}_{ice}V_{ice}}{{\rho}_{water}} $$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;which is exactly the same volume we found before.  Therefore, when the ice cube melts it fills up exactly the same amount of volume as the water displaced to hold up the ice cube, so the water level remains the same and James Bond lives!&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Or does he?  Well, he sure does if the system is entirely described by the analysis above.  But we need to be exact here since a single drop would set off the Koala death trap.  We have considered the biggest contributions to the change of volume of the water (and easiest to calculate!), but we have ignored a large number of much much smaller effects on the volume.  Typically these effects would be swept aside and callously labeled &amp;#8220;negligible,&amp;#8221; but since even the smallest change of volume could mean life or death for our hero, they must be accounted for to give a final &amp;#8220;exact&amp;#8221; answer.  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Unfortunately, &amp;#8220;exact&amp;#8221; isn&amp;#8217;t something science can do very well.  We can only do as good as the measurements we make allow.  And since I gave you practically no information, this was very tough.  However, one could consider the magnitude of the effects given typical values and see which side wins out.  But if two competing effects give similar values under reasonable conditions, it becomes very difficult to give an answer.  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;The last two &amp;#8220;Problems of the Week&amp;#8221; were well posed math problems, each with a clear-cut &amp;#8220;correct&amp;#8221; answer.  This one was a physics problem and physics is a lot messier than math.  That may initially seem less satisfying, but it means that there is a whole lot of interesting &amp;#8220;mess&amp;#8221; to sort out!  I really enjoyed reading the &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/11/problem-of-week-3.html#more"&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt; detailing all the neat small effects to the change of volume that I ignored in my solution.  Density variations as a function of temperature, surface tension effects, evaporation and thermal expansion all play some role in determining the final answer.   There&amp;#8217;s a whole lot of interesting physics going on!  &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Without knowing the exact conditions a bit more and doing a whole lot more work, it seems as though I will not be able to provide a final physics solution.  But, having seen just about every Bond movie, I can give an answer with a certainty not afforded to me by science:  Mr. Bond lives.  How do I know this?  Well, it is common knowledge that James Bond has tiny smoke grenades in the soles of his shoes that release a potent koala knock-out potion specifically created by Q.  So Bond releases these into the koala death pit, rendering the vicious beasts harmless.  Then he uses his watch laser to cut any bindings Dr. Cherrycoke may have placed him in, falling into the death pit.  The fall leaves Mr. Bond uninjured, as a cuddly mass of sleeping koalas break his fall.  By stacking the koalas into a rudimentary series of steps, Mr. Bond ascends out of the death pit and free to save the world&amp;#8217;s ice supply from the evil Dr. Cherrycoke.       &lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div&gt;Obviously.&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Corky</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Dec 2010 02:01:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-12-15:posts/problem-of-the-week-3-solution.html</guid><category>koalas</category><category>problem of the week</category><category>scott bakula</category></item><item><title>Problem of the Week #2: Solution</title><link>/posts/problem-of-the-week-2-solution.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Thanks to all who sent in solutions! We are very happy with the vast number of responses, and we will put up a leader board&amp;nbsp;shortly!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Solution&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; be the fraction of the rubber band that the ant has&amp;nbsp;traversed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$A\left(t\right)=\frac{x\left(t\right)}{L+vt}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The  ant&amp;#8217;s velocity relative to any point along the rubber band is equal to  the length of the rubber band times the first time derivative of &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$u=\left(L+vt\right)\frac{dA}{dt}=\left(L+vt\right)\left[\frac{\dot{x}}{L+vt}-\frac{vx}{\left(L+vt\right)^{2}}\right]=\dot{x}-\frac{vx}{L+vt}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This gives us an inseparable, first-order differential equation for &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;). The general differential equation of this&amp;nbsp;type,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\dot{x}+p\left(t\right)x=q\left(t\right),$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;has the general&amp;nbsp;solution&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$x\left(t\right)=e^{-\int_{0}^{t} p\left(t\right)dt}\int_{0}^{t} q\left(t\right)e^{\int_{0}^{t} p\left(t\right)dt}dt.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our&amp;nbsp;case,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$p\left(t\right)=-\frac{v}{L+vt},\quad q\left(t\right)=u.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Therefore,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$x\left(t\right)&amp;amp;amp;=&amp;amp;amp;e^{\int\frac{v}{L+vt}dt}\int ue^{-\int\frac{v}{L+vt}dt}dt=\frac{u}{v}\left(L+vt\right)\ln\left(1+\frac{vt}{L}\right).$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When the ant has reached the other side, &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;x&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt;) = &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;L&lt;/span&gt; + &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;vt&lt;/span&gt;,&amp;nbsp;so&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$x\left(t\right)=L+vt=\frac{u}{v}\left(L+vt\right)\ln\left(1+\frac{vt}{L}\right).$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Solving for t, we&amp;nbsp;get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$t=\frac{L}{v}\left(e^{v/u}-1\right).$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So the ant always makes it to the other side (unless &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;u&lt;/span&gt; = 0)! In the limit as &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;v&lt;/span&gt; -&amp;gt; 0, we&amp;nbsp;get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$t\approx\frac{L}{u},$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is exactly what we would&amp;nbsp;expect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We  can show that the ant will reach the other side without doing any  calculations. As the ant moves across the rubber band, the velocity of  the point on the rubber band that the ant is currently walking on  increases from 0 to &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;v&lt;/span&gt;.  Therefore, the ant is accelerating. Since the other end of the rubber  band is moving at a constant velocity, the accelerating ant will always  eventually catch up to the far&amp;nbsp;end.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to see this is  that since the ant is accelerating, if it makes it halfway, it will make  it all the way to the other side; if it makes it one-quarter of the  way, it will make it halfway, and so on. We know that since the ant is  traveling at some nonzero velocity, it must make it some nonzero  fraction of the way to the other side. Therefore, it must make it twice  that far, and so on, all the way to the other side. Thanks to Frank for pointing this&amp;nbsp;out!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Holmes</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 23 Nov 2010 17:46:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-11-23:posts/problem-of-the-week-2-solution.html</guid><category>problem of the week</category></item><item><title>Problem of the Week #3</title><link>/posts/problem-of-the-week-3.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, Times, serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;We welcome you to send in solutions, or even any ideas you have about how to solve the problems to &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, Times, serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com" style="background-attachment: initial; background-clip: initial; background-color: transparent; background-image: initial; background-origin: initial; background-position: initial initial; background-repeat: initial initial; color: #2d6e89; font-weight: bold; text-decoration: none;"&gt;&lt;i&gt;the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, Times, serif; font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;&lt;i&gt; with “problem of the week” in the subject line. We will keep track of the top Virtuosi problem&amp;nbsp;solvers.&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the third installment of &lt;/span&gt;&lt;i style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;Problem of the Week&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;!  We are very pleased with the number of responses we have gotten so far and we super duper promise to put up some kind of leader board soon.  In fact, I super duper promise to relegate that assignment to Alemi.  We intend to keep this up as long as we can and give out prizes for high scores maybe&amp;#8230;? They will be lame internet&amp;nbsp;prizes&amp;#8230;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The solution to the last problem of the week will be up shortly.  Adam is the only one who knows the answer and he was busy all weekend taking a magic ring to&amp;nbsp;Mordor.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One more housekeeping note.  Since we want everyone to have a clean shot at answering the question, we would prefer the solutions to be sent by email instead of posted in the comments.  However, we certainly don&amp;#8217;t want to stop discussion on the problem, so if you don&amp;#8217;t want any hints you might want to avoid the comments!&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt;Now for the problem&amp;#8230;&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TOohHfT9CTI/AAAAAAAAAHg/kpLDQteBptA/s1600/james+bond007.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="320" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TOohHfT9CTI/AAAAAAAAAHg/kpLDQteBptA/s320/james+bond007.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;James Bond has been captured by the evil mastermind Dr. Vontavious Cherrycoke, who is trying to take over the world&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ice_Cube"&gt;ice cube&lt;/a&gt; supply.  The minions of Dr. Cherrycoke have placed Mr. Bond in an elaborate and unnecessary death contraption that, if triggered, would drop our hero into a pit of ravenous killer koalas.  In other words, certain death!          &lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;Dr. Cherrycoke has constructed a fitting trigger for his death machine / koala feeder.  A single ice cube is placed in a glass of water so that the water is completely filling the glass up to the brim.  The glass of water is then placed on a very sensitive detector.  If even a single drop of water spills out of the glass as the ice cube melts, James Bond will find himself on the wrong end of a murderous marsupial mauling.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;Vontavious exits the room with his minions, confident that his death trap will be triggered and Bond will be vanquished once and for all.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt;Does Mr. Bond survive?  If not, roughly how long does it take until he checks in to the big &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MI6&lt;/span&gt; in the sky?  Be sure to back up your answer!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: medium;"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-size: 14px; line-height: 19px;"&gt; &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; font-size: 4px; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Corky</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 22 Nov 2010 03:53:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-11-22:posts/problem-of-the-week-3.html</guid><category>koalas</category><category>problem of the week</category><category>james bond</category></item><item><title>Problem of the Week #2</title><link>/posts/problem-of-the-week-2.html</link><description>&lt;div class="MsoNormal"&gt;&lt;i&gt;As always, we welcome you to send in solutions, or even any ideas you have about how to solve the problems to &lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;&lt;i&gt;the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt; with “problem of the week” in the subject line. We will keep track of the top Virtuosi problem solvers.

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Why did the ant cross the rubber band?&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A rubber band is held fixed at one end. The other end is pulled at a velocity &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;v&lt;/span&gt;. At time &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;t&lt;/span&gt; = 0, the rubber band has a length of &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;L&lt;/span&gt;, and an ant starts crawling from one end to the other at velocity &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;u&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Does the ant reach the other side? If so, how long does it take to get there? Assume that the rubber band is able to be stretched indefinitely without&amp;nbsp;breaking.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Holmes</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 14 Nov 2010 16:30:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-11-14:posts/problem-of-the-week-2.html</guid><category>rubber bands</category><category>problem of the week</category><category>ants</category></item><item><title>Problem of the Week #1</title><link>/posts/problem-of-the-week-1.html</link><description>&lt;div class="MsoNormal"&gt;&lt;i&gt;I thought we could spice things up a bit with a more interactive post on The Virtuosi. Starting this week, a new problem of the week will be posted each week. Solutions will be posted the following week. These problems will be a collection of physics and math problems and riddles, and although hopefully challenging enough to be fun and interesting, they should mostly be solvable using concepts from introductory undergraduate physics and math classes.

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="MsoNormal"&gt;&lt;i&gt;We welcome you to ponder these problems, and send in solutions, or even any ideas you have about how to solve the problems to &lt;/i&gt;&lt;a href="mailto:the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com"&gt;&lt;i&gt;the.physics.virtuosi@gmail.com&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt; with “problem of the week” in the subject line. We will keep track of the top Virtuosi problem solvers.

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="MsoNormal"&gt;&lt;i&gt;Here it goes…

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;i&gt;

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Maximizing Gravity&lt;/span&gt;&lt;i&gt;

&lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="MsoNormal"&gt;&lt;i&gt; &lt;/i&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="MsoNormal"&gt;You are given a blob of Play-Doh (with a fixed mass and uniform density) that you can shape however you choose. How can you shape it to maximize the gravitational force at a given point &lt;i&gt;P&lt;/i&gt; on the surface of the Play-Doh?&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div class="MsoNormal"&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;!--more--&gt;

&lt;div class="MsoNormal"&gt;&lt;span style="font-weight: bold;"&gt;Solution&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;In cylindrical coordinates, where the point &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;P&lt;/span&gt; is taken to be the origin, the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;z&lt;/span&gt;-component of the gravitational field due to any point (&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;z&lt;/span&gt;) felt at the origin, is proportional to&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;$$\frac{1}{s^{2}+z^{2}}\frac{z}{\sqrt{s^{2}+z^{2}}},$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;where the second factor is necessary to take the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;z&lt;/span&gt;-component. If we have azimuthal symmetry, the magnitude of the gravitational field is given by the sum of all the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;z&lt;/span&gt;-components of the forces due to all points in the planet. For a given contour&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;$$\frac{z}{\left(s^{2}+z^{2}\right)^{3/2}}=C,$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_kdZd6FJQtZQ/TN9Jgv8f9gI/AAAAAAAAAAM/qdRknJVbCT0/s1600/maxgravity.jpg" onblur="try {parent.deselectBloggerImageGracefully();} catch(e) {}"&gt;&lt;img alt="" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5539226893663860226" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_kdZd6FJQtZQ/TN9Jgv8f9gI/AAAAAAAAAAM/qdRknJVbCT0/s320/maxgravity.jpg" style="cursor: pointer; float: right; height: 320px; margin: 0pt 0pt 10px 10px; width: 320px;" border="0" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;for some constant &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt;, each point on the interior contributes more to the total gravitational field than each point on the exterior. Thus, the gravitational field is maximized if the surface of the planet takes the shape of one of these contours. Solving for &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;s&lt;/span&gt;(&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;z&lt;/span&gt;), we get$$s\left(z\right)=\sqrt{\left(\frac{z}{C}\right)^{2/3}-z^{2}}.$$ If the length of the planet in the &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;z&lt;/span&gt;-direction is $$z_0,$$ we can replace &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;C&lt;/span&gt; in the above expression to get&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;$$s\left(z\right)=\sqrt{\left(z_{0}^{4}z^{2}\right)^{1/3}-z^{2}}.$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;As can be seen by the plot above, this shape looks a lot like a sphere, but slightly smushed toward the point of interest &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;P&lt;/span&gt;. We can rigorously compare the field of the maximal gravity solid to that of a sphere with the same volume. The volume of the maximal solid is given by&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;$$V=\pi\int_{0}^{z_{0}}s^{2}\left(z\right)dz=\pi\int_{0}^{z_{0}}\left[\left(z_{0}^{4}z^{2}\right)^{1/3}-z^{2}\right]dz=\frac{4\pi}{15}z_{0}^{3}$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;The volume of a sphere of radius &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;r&lt;/span&gt; is of course $$V=\frac{4}{3}\pi r^{3},$$ so in order for the volumes to be the same, the sphere must have a radius of $$r=z_{0}/5^{1/3}.$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;The acceleration due to the maximal solid is proportional to&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;$$a_{max}=\int dVa_{z}=2\pi G\rho\int_{0}^{z_{0}}dz\int_{0}^{s\left(z\right)}sds\frac{z}{\left(s^{2}+z^{2}\right)^{3/2}}=\frac{4\pi G\rho z_{0}}{5},$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;while the acceleration due to the sphere is just $$a_{sphere}=\frac{G\rho\frac{4}{3}\pi r^{3}}{r^{2}}=\frac{4\pi G\rho z_{0}}{3\cdot5^{1/3}}.$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;Thus, we have&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;$$\frac{F_{max}}{F_{sphere}}=\frac{4\pi G\rho z_{0}/5}{4\pi G\rho z_{0}/\left(3\cdot5^{1/3}\right)}=\frac{3}{5^{2/3}}\approx1.026.$$&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;So the solid that gives the maximum gravitational field at a point is only about 3% better than a sphere.

&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;div style="margin: 0px; text-indent: 0px;"&gt;For a more detailed discussion, see &lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/%7Eaalemi/random/planet.pdf"&gt;Alemi&amp;#8217;s solution&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/div&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Holmes</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 05 Nov 2010 19:39:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-11-05:posts/problem-of-the-week-1.html</guid><category>problem of the week</category><category>gravity</category></item></channel></rss>