<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.dvorak.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2010-09-19T23:55:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Paradigm Shifts 2: Paradigm ShiftER</title><link href="/posts/paradigm-shifts-2-paradigm-shifter.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-19T23:55:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Sam</name></author><id>tag:,2010-09-19:posts/paradigm-shifts-2-paradigm-shifter.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Last time, I presented reasons why it would be economically infeasible
for the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; to switch to the metric system. This time, I&amp;#8217;d like to talk
about a change that could relatively easily be brought about soon. A
change that would barely cost a thing, but could improve efficiency
dramatically in many jobs and in every day life for many people. A
change of this type would be very handy. Puns aside though, what I&amp;#8217;m
talking about is this: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DVORAK&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SIMPLIFIED&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KEYBOARD&lt;/span&gt; (again lots from
Wikipedia)
&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/500px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/500px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/1000px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/1000px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/thumb/2/25/KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg/1000px-KB_United_States_Dvorak.svg.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Look down at your keyboard. Chances are very good that if you bought
your keyboard in an English speaking country, you&amp;#8217;re using the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt;
keyboard layout. You&amp;#8217;ll also probably know (or else you&amp;#8217;ll learn from
me) that the letter &amp;#8220;E&amp;#8221; is the most common in the English language. You
might wonder then, why it&amp;#8217;s not in the &amp;#8220;home row&amp;#8221; (the row of keys in
the middle of the keyboard that would be right under your fingers if
you&amp;#8217;re typing in the standard way). You might also wonder why other
common letters like &amp;#8220;T&amp;#8221; were exiled to the top row while less common
letters like &amp;#8220;J&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;K&amp;#8221; sit right under your fingertips as they rest
idle. You may then think about how slow it is to type words like
&amp;#8220;December&amp;#8221; which require you to use the same finger for consecutive
letters. You may even get to thinking that a lot of words require using
the same hand for consecutive letters, but it would be much nicer to
alternate hands as you type. The reasons for the slow speed of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt;
are not entirely clear. There are stories floating around about the
inventor of the typewriter deliberately laying out the keyboard this way
to keep typing speeds down so that the mechanical keys wouldn&amp;#8217;t jam. The
authenticity of these stories are disputed, but you&amp;#8217;d be hard pressed to
argue that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt; is the most efficient layout there could be. One
competitor for the title that has stood out is called Dvorak, named
after its creator. Some statistics from Wikipedia (sources given&amp;nbsp;there):&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;the Dvorak layout uses about 63% of the finger motion required by&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;the vast majority of the Dvorak layout&amp;#8217;s key strokes (70%) are done
    in the home row&amp;#8221; whereas &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt; &amp;#8220;has only 32% of the strokes done in
    the home&amp;nbsp;row&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt; layout has more than 3,000 words that are typed on the
    left hand alone and about 300 words that are typed on the right hand
    alone&amp;#8221;, but &amp;#8220;with the Dvorak layout, only a few words can be typed
    on the left hand and not one syllable can be typed with the right
    hand alone, much less a&amp;nbsp;word.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;On &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt; keyboards, 56% of the typing strokes are done by the left
    hand. As the left hand is weaker for the majority of people, the
    Dvorak keyboard puts the more often used keys on the right hand
    side, thereby having 56% of the typing strokes done by the right&amp;nbsp;hand.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Because the Dvorak layout requires less finger motion from the
    typist compared to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt;, many users with repetitive strain
    injuries have reported that switching from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt; to Dvorak
    alleviated or even eliminated their repetitive strain&amp;nbsp;injury.&amp;#8221;&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;The fastest English language typist in the world, according to The
    Guinness Book of World Records&amp;#8221; achieved &amp;#8220;a peak speed of 212 wpm&amp;#8221;
    using&amp;nbsp;Dvorak&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Okay, so maybe by now you see that Dvorak can be more efficient. So why
hasn&amp;#8217;t it been implemented yet? Well, back in the typewriter era, it was
one layout or the other, and people picked &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt;. Look at Wikipedia for
a summary. But now, assuming you&amp;#8217;re not using a typewriter or a 386 or
something equivalently ancient, it&amp;#8217;s actually quite easy to switch back
and forth between &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt; and Dvorak. Check out your control panel if
you&amp;#8217;re on a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PC&lt;/span&gt; (or the equivalent on a mac or linux or what have you)
and I bet you&amp;#8217;ll find the setting for changing the keyboard layout
pretty easily, and I bet that Dvorak will be one of the layouts you can
choose. So it&amp;#8217;s easy enough to switch all the devices to the new system,
with pretty much no cost. The problem is of course that hardly anybody
can type with Dvorak. Everybody is used to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt;! And I&amp;#8217;m sure there
are people out there who are happy to try to learn Dvorak, but I&amp;#8217;m not
one of them. I&amp;#8217;m used to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt; and I&amp;#8217;m pretty sure if I tried to
switch, I&amp;#8217;d get confused and completely jumble the two systems. I just
can&amp;#8217;t see the slight increase in my typing speed being worth the hassle.
Maybe some can, but I&amp;#8217;m sure that many feel the same way I do,
especially those who, like me, don&amp;#8217;t do a lot of transcribing or the
like, and so rarely need to type very fast. The key? (sorry, no more
puns, I promise) Get &amp;#8216;em while they&amp;#8217;re young. That&amp;#8217;s right, all the
young typists out there can be trained on Dvorak instead of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt;. If
they never learn &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt;, they&amp;#8217;ll never be confused. And they can use the
same keyboards as everyone else. All that we&amp;#8217;d have to do is make it
easier to switch the keyboard layout (put something a little closer than
the control panel, maybe right on the keyboard), and print two sets of
characters on the keyboard when they are made (note that I&amp;#8217;ve neglected
cell phones and other devices that also have keyboards, but they can be
updated in the same way). It would be as easy as that to implement the
change. Give it maybe 5-10 years to phase in keyboards and operating
systems with the easy-switch built in (in this case, it&amp;#8217;s nice that
computers have such short life spans), then have schools start teaching
kids to use Dvorak in typing classes. In a generation, hardly anyone
will even remember &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QWERTY&lt;/span&gt; except as a weird hiccup along the way to&amp;nbsp;efficiency.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="QWERTY"></category><category term="Dvorak"></category><category term="puns"></category></entry></feed>