<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/tag.scrabble.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 22:52:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Re-evaluating the values of the tiles in Scrabble™</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.scrabbleassociation.com/tourneys/2012/nsc/build2/photo/21/PH1_8830.JPG"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://www.scrabbleassociation.com/tourneys/2012/nsc/build2/photo/21/PH1_8830.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Recently I have seen quite a few blog posts written about re-evaluating
the points values assigned to the different letter tiles in the
Scrabble™ brand Crossword Game. The premise behind these posts is that
the creator and designer of the game assigned point values to the
different tiles according to their relative frequencies of occurrence in
words in English text, supplemented by information gathered while
playtesting the game. The points assigned to different letters reflected
how difficult it was to play those letters: common letters like E, A,
and R were assigned 1 point, while rarer letters like J and Q were
assigned 8 and 10 points, respectively. These point values were based on
the English lexicon of the late 1930’s. Now, some 70 years later, that
lexicon has changed considerably, having gained many new words (e.g.:
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;EMAIL&lt;/span&gt;) and lost a few old ones. So, if one were to repeat the analysis
of the game designer in the present day, would one come to different
conclusions regarding how points should be assigned to various&amp;nbsp;letters?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I’ve decided to add my own analysis to the recent development because I
have found most of the other blog posts to be unsatisfactory for a
variety of reasons.* &lt;a href="http://deadspin.com/5975490/h-y-and-z-as-concealed-weapons-we-apply-google+inspired-math-to-scrabbles-flawed-points-system"&gt;One
article&lt;/a&gt;
calculated letters’ relative frequencies by counting the number of times
each letter appeared in each word in the Scrabble™ dictionary. But this
analysis is faulty, since it ignores the probability with which
different words actually appear in the game. One is far less likely to
draw &lt;span class="caps"&gt;QI&lt;/span&gt; than &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AE&lt;/span&gt; during a Scrabble™ game (since there’s only one Q in the
bag, but many A&amp;#8217;s and E&amp;#8217;s). Similarly, very long words like
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;ZOOGEOGRAPHICAL&lt;/span&gt; have a vanishingly small probability of appearing in the
game: the A’s in the long words and the A’s in the short words cannot be
treated equally. &lt;a href="http://blog.useost.com/2012/12/30/valett/"&gt;A second
article&lt;/a&gt; I saw calculated
letter frequencies based on their occurrence in the Scrabble™ dictionary
and did attempt to weight frequencies based on word length. The author
of this second article also claimed to have quantified the extent to
which a letter could “fit well” with the other tiles given to a player.
Unfortunately, some of the steps in the analysis of this second article
were only vaguely explained, so it isn’t clear how one could replicate
the article’s conclusions. In addition, as far as I can tell, neither of
these articles explicitly included the distribution of letters (how many
A’s, how many B’s, etc) included in a Scrabble™ game. Also, neither of
these articles accounted for the fact that there are blank tiles (that
act as wild cards and can stand in for any letter) that appear in the&amp;nbsp;game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what does one need to do to improve upon the analyses already
performed? We’re given the Scrabble™ dictionary and bag of &lt;a href="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/b/b8/Scrabble_tiles_en.jpg"&gt;100
tiles&lt;/a&gt;
with a set distribution, and we’re going to try to determine what a good
pointing system would be for each letter in the alphabet. We’re also
armed with the knowledge that each player is given 7 letters at a time
in the game, making words longer than 8 letters very rare indeed. Let’s
say for the sake of simplicity that words 9 letters long or shorter
account for the vast majority of words that are possible to play in a
normal&amp;nbsp;game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Based on these constraints, how can one best decide what points to
assign the different tiles? As stated above, the game is designed to
reward players for playing words that include letters that are more
difficult to use. So, what makes an easy letter easy, and what makes a
difficult letter difficult? Sure, the number of times the letter appears
in the
&lt;a href="http://scrabblehelper2.googlecode.com/svn-history/r3/trunk/src/scrabble/dictionary.txt"&gt;dictionary&lt;/a&gt;
is important, but this does not account for whether or not, on a given
rack of tiles (a rack of tiles is to Scrabble™ as a hand of cards is to
poker), that letter actually can be used. The letter needs to combine
with other tiles available either on the rack or on the board in order
to form words. The letter Q is difficult to play not only because it is
used relatively few times in the dictionary, but also because the
majority of Q-words require the player to use the letter U in
conjunction with&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, what criterion can one use to say how useful a particular tile is?
Let’s say that letters that are useful have more potential to be used in
the game: they provide more options for the players who draw them. Given
a rack of tiles, one can generate a list of all of the words that are
possible for the player to play. Then, one can count the number of times
that each letter appears in that list. Useful letters, by this
criterion, will combine more readily with other letters to form words
and so appear more often in the list than un-useful&amp;nbsp;letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;(I would also like to take a moment to preempt &lt;a href="http://scrabbleplayers.org/w/Valett"&gt;criticism from the
competitive Scrabble™ community&lt;/a&gt; by
saying that strategic decisions made by the players need not be brought
into consideration here. The point values of tiles are an engineering
constraint of the game. Strategic decisions are made by the players,
given the engineering constraints of the game. Words that are “available
to be played” are different from “words that actually do get played.”
The potential usefulness of individual letter tiles should reflect
whether or not it is even possible to play them, not whether or not a
player decides that using a particular group of tiles constitutes an
optimal&amp;nbsp;move.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To give an example, suppose I draw the rack &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BEHIWXY&lt;/span&gt;. I can generate**
the full list of words available to be played given this rack: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BE&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BEY&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BI&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BY&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BYE&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EH&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EX&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HE&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HEW&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HEX&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HEY&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HI&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HIE&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IBEX&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WE&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WEB&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WHEY&lt;/span&gt;,
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;WHY&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;WYE&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;XI&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YE&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YEH&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;YEW&lt;/span&gt;. Counting the number of occurrences of each
letter, I see that the letter E appears 18 times, while the letter W
only appears 7 times. This example tells me that the letter E is
probably much more potentially useful than the letter&amp;nbsp;W.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The example above is only one of the many, many possible racks that one
can see in a game of Scrabble™. I can use a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monte_Carlo_method"&gt;Monte
Carlo&lt;/a&gt;-type simulation
to estimate the average usefulness of the different letters by drawing
many example racks. Monte Carlo is a technique used to estimate
numerical properties of complicated things without explicit calculation.
For example, suppose I want to know the probability of drawing a
straight flush in poker.*** I can calculate that probability
explicitly by using combinatorics, or I can use a Monte Carlo method to
deal a large number of hypothetical possible poker hands and count the
number of straight flushes that appear. If I deal a large enough number
of hands, the fraction of hands that are straight flushes will converge
upon the correct analytic value. Similarly here, instead of explicitly
calculating the usefulness of each letter, I use Monte Carlo to draw a
large number of hypothetical racks and use them to count the number of
times each letter can be used. Comparing the number of times that each
tile is used over many, many possible racks will give a good
approximation of how relatively useful each tile is on average. Note
that this process accounts for the words acceptable in the Scrabble™
dictionary, the number of available tiles in the bag, as well as the
probability of any given word&amp;nbsp;appearing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my simulation, I draw 10,000,000 racks, each with 9 tiles
(representing the 7 letters the player actually draws plus two tiles
available to be played through to form longer words). I perform the
calculation two different ways: once with a 98-tile pool with no blanks,
and once with a 100-tile pool that does include blanks. In the latter
case, I make sure to not count the blanks used to stand in for different
letters as instances of those letters appearing in the game. The results
are summarized in the table&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-FXxaPgNpk7Y/UPyeMh8pe6I/AAAAAAAAAHo/x3m0XvORWGw/s1600/scrabble+tiles+table+small+3.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-FXxaPgNpk7Y/UPyeMh8pe6I/AAAAAAAAAHo/x3m0XvORWGw/s400/scrabble+tiles+table+small+3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are two key observations to be made here. First, it does not seem
to matter whether or not there are blanks in the bag! The results are
very similar in both cases. Second, it would be completely reasonable to
keep the tile point values as they are. Only the Z, H, and U appear out
of order. It’s only if one looks very carefully at the differences
between the usefulness of these different tiles that one might
reasonably justify re-pointing the different&amp;nbsp;letters.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For fun, I have included in the table my own suggestions for what these
tiles’ values might be changed to based on the simulation results.
(&lt;strong&gt;Note&lt;/strong&gt;: here&amp;#8217;s where any pretensions of scientific rigor go out the
window.) I have kept the scale of points between 1 and 10, as in the
current pointing system. I have assigned groups of letters the same
number of points based on whether they have a similar usefulness score.
Here are the significant changes: L and U, which are significantly less
useful than the other 1-point tiles may be bumped up to 2 points,
comparable to the D and G. The letter V is clearly less useful than any
of the other three 4-point tiles (W, Y, and F, all of which may be used
to form 2-letter words while the V forms no 2-letter words), and so is
undervalued. The H is comparable to the 3-point tiles, and so is
currently overvalued. Similarly, the Z is overvalued when one considers
how close to the J it is. Unlike in the previous two articles that I
mentioned, I don&amp;#8217;t find any strong reason to change the value of the
letter X compared to the other 8 point tiles. I suppose one could lower
its value from 8 points to 7, but I have (somewhat arbitrarily) chosen
not to do&amp;nbsp;so.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One may also ask the question whether or not the fact that a letter
forms 2- or 3-letter words is unfairly biasing that letter. In
particular, is the low usefulness of the C and V compared to
comparably-pointed tiles due to the fact that they form no 2-letter
words? Performing the simulation again without 2-letter words, I found
no changes in the results in any of the letters except for C, which
increased in usefulness above the B and the H. The letter V&amp;#8217;s ranking,
however, did not change at all, indicating that unlike the C the V is
difficult to use even when combining with letters to make longer words.
Repeating the simulation yet again without 2- or 3-letter words yielded
the same&amp;nbsp;results.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a final note, I would like to respond directly to to Stefan Fatsis&amp;#8217;s
&lt;a href="http://www.slate.com/articles/sports/gaming/2013/01/scrabble_tile_values_why_it_s_a_mistake_to_change_the_point_value_of_the.single.html"&gt;excellent
article&lt;/a&gt;
about the so-called controversy surrounding re-calculating tile values
and say that I am fully aware that this is indeed a &amp;#8220;statistical
exercise,&amp;#8221; motivated mostly by my desire to do the calculation made by
others in a way that made sense in the context of the game of Scrabble.
Similarly, I realize that these recommendations are unlikely to actually
change anything. Given that the original points values of the tiles are
still justifiably appropriate by my analysis, it&amp;#8217;s not like anybody at
Hasbro is going to jump to &amp;#8220;fix&amp;#8221; the game. Lastly, my calculations have
nothing to do with the strategy of the game whatsoever, and cannot be
used to learn how to play the game any better. (If anything, I&amp;#8217;ve only
confirmed some things that many experienced Scrabble players already
know about the game, such as that the V is a tricky tile, or that the H,
X, and Z tiles, in spite of their high point values, are quite&amp;nbsp;flexible.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;To state my own credentials, I have played Scrabble™competitively for
4 years, and am quite familiar with the mechanics of the game, as well
as contemporary&amp;nbsp;strategy.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;** Credit where credit is due: Alemi provided the code used to
generate the list of available words given any set of tiles. Thanks&amp;nbsp;Alemi!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*&lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt; Monte Carlo has a long history of being used to estimate the
properties of games. As recounted by George Dyson in &lt;/em&gt;Turing’s
Cathedral&lt;/em&gt;, in 1948 while at Los Alamos the mathematician Stanislaw Ulam
suffered a severe bout of encephalitis that resulted in an emergency
trepanation. While recovering in the hospital, he played many games of
solitaire and was intrigued by the question of how to calculate the
probability that a given deal could result in a winnable game. The
combinatorics required to answer this question proved staggeringly
complex, so Ulam proposed the idea of generating many possible solitaire
deals and merely counting how many of them resulted in victory. This
proved to be much simpler than an explicit calculation, and the rest is
history: Monte Carlo is used today in a wide variety of&amp;nbsp;applications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Additional&amp;nbsp;References:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The photo at top of a Scrabble™ board was taken during the 2012 National
Scrabble™ Championship. Check out the 9-letter double-blank&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BINOCULAR&lt;/span&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For anyone interested in learning more about the fascinating world of
competitive Scrabble™, check out &lt;em&gt;Word Freak&lt;/em&gt;, also by Stefan Fatsis.
This book has become more or less the definitive documentation upon this
subculture. If you don&amp;#8217;t have enough time to read, check out &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Word_Wars"&gt;Word
Wars&lt;/a&gt;, a documentary that
follows many of the same people as Fatsis&amp;#8217;s book. (It still may be
available streaming on Netflix if you&amp;nbsp;hurry.)&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">DTC</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 20 Jan 2013 22:52:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2013-01-20:posts/re-evaluating-the-values-of-the-tiles-in-scrabble.html</guid><category>Scrabble</category><category>fun</category><category>monte carlo</category></item></channel></rss>