<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.end%20of%20the%20earth.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2011-04-22T13:11:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>End of the Earth VI: Nanobot destruction</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/end-of-the-earth-vi-nanobot-destruction.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-22T13:11:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-04-22:posts/end-of-the-earth-vi-nanobot-destruction.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-hGkMD-tB1RY/TbGfhRvcA6I/AAAAAAAAAQ4/eCaG-z1Zarc/s1600/612px-C60a.png" imageanchor="1" style="clear:left; float:left;margin-right:1em; margin-bottom:1em"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="314" width="320" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-hGkMD-tB1RY/TbGfhRvcA6I/AAAAAAAAAQ4/eCaG-z1Zarc/s320/612px-C60a.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s destroy the earth with&amp;nbsp;technology.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A while ago, I read the novel &lt;i&gt;Postsingular&lt;/i&gt; by Rudy Rucker, and in the first chapter the Earth gets destroyed, and then undestroyed, and then the novel unfolds and the Earth&amp;#8217;s likelihood is threatened again, and it looks like the Earth will be destroyed, but it&amp;nbsp;isn&amp;#8217;t. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How does all of this craziness happen you might ask: nanobots!  The story revolves around little self-replicating robots.  The story explores what it would be like to live in a world where every surface on Earth was coated in little computers, all of which were networked together.  It&amp;#8217;s certainly a neat idea, but whenever you have self-replicating things, you need to worry a bit about what might happen if they get out of control.
&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, let&amp;#8217;s assume we, evil scientists that we are, have managed to create a little self-replicating nanobot.  This little guy can scurry around, running off something ubiquitous, probably some combination of solar, and some kind of infrared photovoltaics.  This little guy, call him Bob, his only mission in life is to create a friend.  He scurries around collecting the various ingredients necessary, and using his little robot arms, he slices and dices up the pieces and welds them together to create another copy of himself, Rob.  Not satisfied with his work; Bob found Rob quite the bore, and honestly Rob didn&amp;#8217;t too much like Bob either, both of them part ways and try to fashion a new&amp;nbsp;friend.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How long until Bob and Rob and their cohorts manage to chew through all of the material on&amp;nbsp;Earth?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we have here is the setup to a problem in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Exponential_growth"&gt;Exponential Growth&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Exponential&amp;nbsp;Growth&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s simplify things a bit and assume that the nanobots always take a fixed amount to time to make a new copy of themselves, call that time T.  We&amp;#8217;ll start with one guy, so we know that at t =0, we have 1 bot
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N(t =0 ) = 1 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
And we know that after T seconds we should have 2
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N(T) = 2 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
and after 2T seconds, we&amp;#8217;ve managed to double twice and get 4
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N(2T) = 4 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
after 3T seconds we&amp;#8217;ll double again to 8, etc.  In fact, after nT seconds, so m repetitions we should have doubled m times
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N(nT) = 2^n $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we want to describe all times, we need only ask how many doublings can fit into t seconds
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = n T $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
which gives us
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N(t) = 2^{t/T} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point you might object, as this formula doesn&amp;#8217;t always give an integer, so we could ask things like how many bots are there after 0.5T seconds?  We know the true answer is still 1, Bob hasn&amp;#8217;t finished Rob yet, but our formula tells us the answer is&amp;nbsp;1.414&amp;#8230;  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What we&amp;#8217;ve done is made a continuous approximation to a discrete function.  Certainly, we&amp;#8217;ve paid a price, in that our new formula doesn&amp;#8217;t get answers right in fractions of T, but its a small price to pay for the mathematical simplicity afforded by the nice continuous function, and as long as we don&amp;#8217;t really care about time scales smaller than T in the long run, we haven&amp;#8217;t done any real&amp;nbsp;harm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These kinds of approximations show up all over the place in physics, and going both ways too.  Sometimes it is advantageous to treat some discrete quantity as continuous, and sometimes it might be beneficial to treat some continuous quantity as discrete.  These kinds of approximations are more than adequate, provided you don&amp;#8217;t really take the answers they give you in the cases where your approximation starts to break too&amp;nbsp;seriously.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this case, as long as we don&amp;#8217;t try to seriously predict the number of nanobots to an exact count in time scales less than a fraction of their doubling time, we will have a nice prediction of the number of bots running&amp;nbsp;around.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Earth&amp;nbsp;Destruction&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;As promised, we wanted to calculate the time it would take the nanobots to devour the earth.  For this we need a little bit more to our model.  How will the nanobots eat the earth, I reckon it will be through using up its mass.  Assuming the bots are made out of elements that are rich enough, something like iron, they ought to have a field day on Earth, seeing as it&amp;#8217;s composed of about 5% iron on the surface, and with an interior that is probably about 32% iron overall &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abundance_of_the_chemical_elements#Abundance_of_elements_in_the_Earth"&gt;[ref]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, we need to estimate the mass of a single nanobot.  Let&amp;#8217;s say the nanobot is roughly a 1 micron sized cube, made out of iron.  This gives us a nanobot mass of 
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ m = (\text{ density of iron }) * (\text{ 1 micron} )^3 = \rho_{\text{Fe}} L^3 \sim 8 \text{ picograms} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From here we can estimate the time it would take to chew through the earth, as the time for the nanobots to be as massive as the&amp;nbsp;earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{M_{\oplus}}{\rho_{\text{Fe}} L^3 } = N(t) = 2^{t/T} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Solving for t we obtain
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = T \log_2 \frac{ M_{\oplus}}{ \rho_{\text{Fe}} L^3 }  $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Solution&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s say it takes Bob one month to make Rob, which I don&amp;#8217;t think is a completely unrealistic time for nanobot replication, assuming Bob and Rob and all of their cohorts are 1 micron in size,  I calculate that in 10 years time they would chew through the&amp;nbsp;Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The power of exponential growth!  Even with a 1 month gestation, if left unabashed, the self-replicating robots would eat the entire earth in 10 years time.  They could eat through Mars in about 2.  In fact in &lt;i&gt;Postsingular&lt;/i&gt; this is what the humans planned.  They wanted a Dyson sphere, so they sent some self-replicating robots to Mars, let them chew through it a couple years, and they had 10^37 little robots to do their bidding.  That is of course until the nants set their sites on Earth as their next&amp;nbsp;target&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In order to let you play around with the doubling time and bot size, I&amp;#8217;ve created a Wolfram Alpha widget that solves the above equation, feel free to play around with the parameters and see how long Earth would&amp;nbsp;survive.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;script type="text/javascript" id="WolframAlphaScript6a645314f9be6be7b902d4cc1f776d00" src="http://www.wolframalpha.com/widget/widget.jsp?id=6a645314f9be6be7b902d4cc1f776d00"&gt;&lt;/script&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The widget should be right above this text.  If it isn&amp;#8217;t working for some reason, here&amp;#8217;s a &lt;a href="http://developer.wolframalpha.com/widgets/gallery/view.jsp?id=6a645314f9be6be7b902d4cc1f776d00"&gt;link&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="fun"></category><category term="nanobots"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category><category term="earth day"></category></entry><entry><title>End of the Earth V: There Goes the Sun</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/end-of-the-earth-v-there-goes-the-sun.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-22T09:42:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-04-22:posts/end-of-the-earth-v-there-goes-the-sun.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-LtXsyHxxSi0/TbDfL6l4tnI/AAAAAAAAAMg/l_12lafg6LQ/s1600/creepy_sun.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="224" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-LtXsyHxxSi0/TbDfL6l4tnI/AAAAAAAAAMg/l_12lafg6LQ/s320/creepy_sun.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;The Sun [photo courtesy of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People that know me well know that I have a lot in common with Robert Frost.  We both were born in March and we both employ rural New England settings to explore complex social and philosophical themes in our poetry.  We also like the same rap&amp;nbsp;groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In honor of my literary doppelganger, I will now, having already had the world end in &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-physics-i.html"&gt;fire&lt;/a&gt;, try my hand at&amp;nbsp;ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s try to answer the question:  &amp;#8220;If the sun blinks out of existence this instant, what is the temperature of the Earth as a function of&amp;nbsp;time?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Sun, in addition to being the &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=haAhdtDmsOw"&gt;King of Planets&lt;/a&gt;, is also what keeps us all warm and toasty and alive.  What happens if we turn that off?  Well, the Earth will cool by radiating its heat away into space.  To see how long this would take, let&amp;#8217;s make some&amp;nbsp;assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s model the surface of the Earth as an ocean 1 km deep and let&amp;#8217;s pretend that all the heat is stored in this ocean.  Let&amp;#8217;s take the ocean to be liquid water at T = 0 degrees Celsius.  How long will it take this ocean to freeze into ice at 0 degrees&amp;nbsp;Celsius?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the amount of energy released from the oceans as the water freezes is given&amp;nbsp;by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q = L_{w} M_{ocean} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where L is the &amp;#8220;latent heat of fusion&amp;#8221; and M is the mass of the water.  The &amp;#8220;latent heat of fusion&amp;#8221; is a fancy way of saying &amp;#8220;the amount of energy released per unit mass as water turns to ice at constant temperature.&amp;#8221;  For water, we have&amp;nbsp;that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ L_{w} = 3.3 \times 10^5 \mbox{J/kg} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for the mass of the ocean, it will be convenient later to write it&amp;nbsp;as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ M_{ocean} = 4\pi {R_{\oplus}}^2 \Delta R \rho $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so now we&amp;#8217;ve got enough to say how much heat energy we have, so how fast do we lose it?  We can take the Earth to be a blackbody radiator, so the power lost in such a case&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P =4\pi \sigma R_{\oplus}^2 T^4 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Power is just Energy per unit Time, we now have all we need to get the time for total freezing of all the oceans.  We&amp;nbsp;have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = \frac{Q}{P} = \frac{4\pi {R_{\oplus}}^2 \Delta R \rho L_{w}}{4\pi \sigma R_{\oplus}^2 T^4} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simplifying the above expression a bit, we&amp;nbsp;get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t =\frac{\Delta R \rho L_{w}}{\sigma T^4} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can plug in some&amp;nbsp;numbers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t =\frac{\left(10^3 \mbox{ m}\right) \times \left(10^3 \frac{kg}{m^3}\right) \times \left(3.3 \times 10^5 \mbox{J/kg}\right)}{\left( 5.67 \times 10^{-8} J s^{-1} m^{-2} K^{-4}\right) \times \left( 273 K\right)^4} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where we have made sure to put our temperatures in Kelvin.  Crunching the numbers with the calculator we &amp;#8220;borrowed&amp;#8221; from Nic three months ago&amp;nbsp;gives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = 10^9 \mbox{ s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remembering that a year is very&amp;nbsp;nearly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1 \mbox{ year} = \pi \times 10^7 \mbox{ s}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we find that the time for the oceans to freeze after the sun disappears is about 30 years.&amp;nbsp;Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this model was very simple.  First of all, I assumed that the ocean temperatures were already at 0 degrees, but they are a bit warmer.  If the oceans are about 300 K (ie 80 degrees in not-Yariv units), then we get another 30 years to cool down to freezing temperatures.  Secondly, I have completely neglected the heat stored in the Earth.  Will this change my answer by an embarrassingly large factor?  Lastly, I have ignored all internal heating mechanisms (ie, radioactive decay) that will also heat up the Earth.  But ignoring all&amp;nbsp;that&amp;#8230;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is there a way for anyone to survive this?  Well, for the most part it will mean the end of life on Earth.  There could potentially be a few exceptions, like by geothermal vents and such.  But for the most part, it&amp;#8217;s one quick cold spiral down to eternal nothingness.  But what about a few people, could they survive for a bit even if the human race is&amp;nbsp;doomed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m glad you asked!  You see, I have this plan involving mine shafts.  Hunkering down underground with a nuclear power plant and all the canned food food we can stomach should allow us to at least ride the rest of our lives.  Details can be found &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iesXUFOlWC0&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sun"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category></entry><entry><title>End of the Earth IV - Shocking Destruction</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/end-of-the-earth-iv-shocking-destruction.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-22T07:54:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-04-22:posts/end-of-the-earth-iv-shocking-destruction.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-aa4EF60W7m0/TbCwQ8Vc3WI/AAAAAAAAAEU/03HiJiGJ6hc/s1600/exploding-earth11.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="200" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-aa4EF60W7m0/TbCwQ8Vc3WI/AAAAAAAAAEU/03HiJiGJ6hc/s200/exploding-earth11.jpg" width="200" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Earth day is upon us once more.  So many other namby-pamby bloggers out there (don&amp;#8217;t hurt me!) are writing about how wonderful the earth is and how great earth day is.  We here at The Virtuosi take a more hardline approach.  Today I&amp;#8217;m going to tell you how to destroy the earth.  Completely and totally.  Unlike &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-physics-i.html"&gt;last&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory.html"&gt;year&amp;#8217;s&lt;/a&gt; &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-physics-iii-asteroids.html"&gt;methods&lt;/a&gt;, this one should&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;In fact, this method is so simple that I can tell you what to do right now.  Just tweak the charge on the electron so it is a bit out of balance with the charge on the proton.  Just a little bit.  How little a bit, you might ask?  A very little bit.  Really, this doesn&amp;#8217;t sound hard.  I mean, sure, you have to do it for all of the electrons in the earth, but we&amp;#8217;re talking about a very very small percentage change.  Not convinced?  Let me show you just how small a change we&amp;#8217;re&amp;nbsp;talking.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there is a charge imbalance in the electron and the proton, this will give the earth a net charge, throughout it&amp;#8217;s volume.  I&amp;#8217;ve got to make a few assumptions about the earth here, so hold on.  I&amp;#8217;m going to assume that the earth is a uniform density everywhere, and I&amp;#8217;m going to assume that the earth is made entirely of iron.&lt;em&gt;  Now, the net charge of any iron atom will be
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ (q_e-q_p)Z=(q_e-q_p)26$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where Z is the atomic number of iron, the number of protons (and electrons) the atom has.  The net charge of the earth, Q, is the number of iron atoms, N, times this charge,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$Q=(q_e-q_p)ZN$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
I&amp;#8217;ve &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory.html"&gt;previously estimated&lt;/a&gt; that N is about 3&lt;/em&gt;10^50 atoms.  Now, the electric potential energy of a sphere of radius r with charge q uniformly distributed throughout it&amp;#8217;s volume is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$U_e=\frac{3kq^2}{5r}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where k is the coulomb&amp;nbsp;constant.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Dissolution of the earth will occur when the electrostatic energy of the earth equals the gravitational potential energy of the earth.  The gravitational bound energy of the earth is given by
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$U_g=\frac{3GM^2}{5R}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Where M is the mass of the earth, G is Newton&amp;#8217;s gravitational constant, and R is the radius of the earth.  Setting this equal to the electrostatic energy of the earth,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{3GM^2}{5R}=\frac{3kQ^2}{5R}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$Q^2=\frac{G}{k}M^2$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
so
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$(q_e-q_p)ZN=\left(\frac{G}{k}\right)^{1/2}M$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Now, N is given, in our approximations, by
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$N=\frac{M_{earth}}{m_{iron}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
so
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$q_e-q_p=\left(\frac{G}{k}\right)^{1/2}\frac{m_{iron}}{Z_{iron}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can plug in some numbers.  G=6.7&lt;em&gt;10^-11 m^3&lt;/em&gt;kg^-1&lt;em&gt;s^-2, k= 9&lt;/em&gt;10^9 m^3&lt;em&gt;kg&lt;/em&gt;s^-2&lt;em&gt;C^-2, m_iron=9&lt;/em&gt;10^-26 kg, Z=26.&amp;nbsp;Thus,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$q_e-q_p=3*10^{-37} C$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To put this in perspective, the charge on the electron is 1.6&lt;em&gt;10^-19 C, so this is roughly 10^18 times less than that charge.  Put another way, if the charge on the electron was imbalanced from that of the proton by roughly 1 part in 10^18, the earth would cease to exist due to electrostatic repulsion.&lt;/em&gt;*&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As I told you at the beginning, you only have to change the charge by a very small amount!  So get working.  There are only about 1000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000000 electrons you need to&amp;nbsp;modify!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*According to the internet, the density of the earth, on average, is roughly 5.5 g/cm^3.  The density of iron is 7.9 g/cm^3 at room temperature, and the density of water is 1 g/cm^3 at room temperature.  So, while the earth is not entirely iron (of course), it is a better approximation to assume the earth is iron than the earth is water.  And those, of course, were really our only two&amp;nbsp;choices.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;** It turns out that this is a good argument for the charge balance of the electron and the&amp;nbsp;proton.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="charge"></category><category term="proton"></category><category term="electron"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category></entry><entry><title>Why Black Holes from the Large Hadron Collider Won’t Destroy the World</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/why-black-holes-from-the-large-hadron-collider-won-t-destroy-the-world.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-05-16T19:53:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Nic Eggert</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-16:posts/why-black-holes-from-the-large-hadron-collider-won-t-destroy-the-world.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Hi everyone. As this is my first post, I thought I&amp;#8217;d introduce myself. Like the rest of the Virtuosi, I&amp;#8217;m a graduate student in physics at Cornell University. I work in experimental particle physics, in particular on the Compact Muon Solenoid, one of the detectors at the Large Hadron Collider. I&amp;#8217;ll post more on what I actually do at some point in the future, but I thought I&amp;#8217;d start with a post in the spirit of some of the other fun calculations that we&amp;#8217;ve done. My goal is to convince you that black holes created by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt; cannot possibly destroy the world.&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;To start with, the main reason no one working on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt; is too concerned about black holes is because of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hawking_radiation"&gt;Hawking radiation&lt;/a&gt;. While we usually think of black holes as objects that nothing can escape from, Stephen Hawking predicted that black holes actually do emit some light, losing energy (and mass) in the process. In the case of the little bitty black holes that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt; could produce, they should just evaporate in a shower of Hawking radiation.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;That&amp;#8217;s great you say, but Hawking radiation has never actually been observed. What if Hawking is wrong and the black holes won&amp;#8217;t evaporate? Well, the usual next argument is that &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cosmic_ray"&gt;cosmic rays&lt;/a&gt; from space bombard the earth all the time, producing collisions many times more energetic than what we&amp;#8217;ll be able to produce at the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt;. To me, this is a fairly convincing argument. However, let&amp;#8217;s pretend we don&amp;#8217;t know about these cosmic rays and that there&amp;#8217;s no Hawking radiation. We can calculate what effect black holes produced by the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt; would have on the earth if they do stick around.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;div&gt;To start out with, the most massive black hole the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt; could produce would be around 10 Tera-electron-volts, or TeV. We&amp;#8217;re probably overestimating here. The eventual goal is for the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt; collisions to be 14 TeV, but producing a particle with the entire collision energy is incredibly unlikely (see &lt;a href="http://www.scientificblogging.com/quantum_diaries_survivor/fascinating_new_higgs_boson_search_dzero_experiment"&gt;Tomasso Dorigo&amp;#8217;s post&lt;/a&gt; for more details on why, along with more details than you probably wanted to know about hadron colliders). However, we want to think about the worst case scenario here, and we&amp;#8217;re just going to do an order of magnitude calculation, so 10 TeV is a good number. Note that I&amp;#8217;m using a particle physics convention here of giving masses in terms of energies using E=mc^2. For reference, 10 TeV is about 1000 times smaller than a small virus.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now from the mass of our black hole, we can get its size by calculating something called the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwarzschild_radius"&gt;Schwarzschild radius&lt;/a&gt;. The Schwarzchild radius for a black hole of mass m is given by&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$r = \frac{2Gm}{c^2}\text{.}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Here G is Newton&amp;#8217;s gravitational constant and c is the speed of light. Plugging our mass in gives us &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$r = 10^{-50} \text{meters.}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;This is incredibly small! In fact as I was writing this, I realized that it&amp;#8217;s actually smaller than the Planck length, which means our equation for the Schwarzschild radius may be somewhat suspect. Nonetheless, let&amp;#8217;s hope that if we ever figure out quantum gravity, it gives us a correction of order one and proceed with our calculation, which is just an order-of-magnitude affair anyway.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now, anything that enters the Schwarzschild radius of the black hole is absorbed by it. The lightest thing that we could imagine the black hole swallowing is an electron. Let&amp;#8217;s figure out how long on average a black hole would have to travel through material with the density of the earth before it absorbs an electron. In the spirit of considering the worst case scenario, we&amp;#8217;ll have the black hole travel at the speed of light, and consider the earth to be the density of lead.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;We could do a complicated cross-section calculation to find the rate at which the black hole accumulates mass, but we can also get it right up to factors of pi through unit analysis. We know that the answer should involve the area of the black hole, the density of the earth, and the speed of the black hole. We want our answer to have units of mass per time to represent the mass accumulation rate of the black hole. The only combination that gives the right units is&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$a=\frac{\text{mass}}{\text{time}} = \rho c r^2=\frac{10,000\text{kg}}{\text{m}^3}\frac{3\times 10^8 \text{m}}{\text{s}}(10^{-50}\text{m})^2} = 10^{-88}\text{kg/s}\text{.}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Alright, now that we know how fast our black hole accumulates mass, let&amp;#8217;s figure out how long it takes it to accumulate an electron. The electron mass is &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$m_e = 10^{-30}\text{kg,}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;so the time to accumulate an electron is&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$t = \frac{m_e}{a} = 10^{50}\text{s.}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now, the current age of the universe is 10^17 seconds. The time it takes our black hole to accumulate an electron is longer than the age of the universe by many orders of magnitude! So, if the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt; produces black holes, and if Hawking is wrong, the black holes will just fly straight through the earth without interacting with anything. Even if we take the size of the black hole to be the Planck length, our black hole accumulates an electron in 10^25 seconds, which is still much longer than the age of the universe.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So the moral of the story is that you should be excited about the new discoveries that the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt; might produce, and you don&amp;#8217;t need to worry about black holes.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="LHC"></category><category term="physics"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category></entry><entry><title>End of the Earth II - Blaze of Glory</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/end-of-the-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-22T14:26:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-22:posts/end-of-the-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S9CFFAkGooI/AAAAAAAAABM/2SpaTtw4ivI/s1600/Marvin_the_Martian.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; float: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="100" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S9CFFAkGooI/AAAAAAAAABM/2SpaTtw4ivI/s200/Marvin_the_Martian.jpg" width="73" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In honor of earth day today, many bloggers are posting things about how to save the earth, or retrospectives on earth days past.  We here at The Virtuosi decided, what better way to celebrate the earth than to figure out how to destroy it?  So that is exactly what we intend to do.  This post will focus on the destruction of the earth by a laser beam.  This is a familiar concept.  Whether it is Marvin the Martian or the Death Star, destroying planets with lasers (or threatening to) is a common&amp;nbsp;theme.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;object height="200" width="249"&gt;&lt;param name="movie" value="http://www.youtube.com/v/djZFHTa6TfA&amp;hl=en_US&amp;fs=1&amp;"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowFullScreen" value="true"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;param name="allowscriptaccess" value="always"&gt;&lt;/param&gt;&lt;embed src="http://www.youtube.com/v/djZFHTa6TfA&amp;hl=en_US&amp;fs=1&amp;" type="application/x-shockwave-flash" allowscriptaccess="always" allowfullscreen="true" width="480" height="385"&gt;&lt;/embed&gt;&lt;/object&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We will be considering two questions today.  The first is fairly obvious:  how much power would the death star need to destroy the earth?  The second relates to a topic of continuing interest of mine: how much would the death star recoil upon&amp;nbsp;firing?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;First, the power we would need.  Most estimates of the death star&amp;#8217;s power seem to rely on simply overcoming the gravitational binding energy of the earth.  We&amp;#8217;re going to assume the earth is a uniform density.  We can easily calculate the gravitational binding energy to be
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$U_G=\frac{3GM_{earth}^2}{5R_{earth}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$U=2.3\cdot 10^{32} J$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
However, looking at the video of the death star blast, it looks like the earth was more than just gravitationally unbound.  It looks like we&amp;#8217;ve actually managed to atomize some of the constituent molecules.  Let us assume that about half of the earth gets atomized.  We&amp;#8217;re also going to assume that the earth is made entirely of iron (not &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; bad an assumption).  In a lattice, iron will have ~6 bonds, and the energy of each bond will be on the order of ~2 eV.  We can calculate the number of iron atoms, N, needed to give the mass of the earth by:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$N=\frac{M_{earth}}{m_{iron}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$N=3\cdot 10^{50} atoms$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We assume half of these have all of their bonds broken, this gives an energy required to break the bonds of
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$E \approx 3N(2eV)=2.88\cdot 10^{32} J$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
This gives us a total destruction energy of
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$E_{tot}=5.2\cdot 10^{32} J$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Analyzing the video of the firing of the first death star tells us that the laser fired for about 4s, so this is a power of 1.3*10^32 W!  As an aside, that much energy is about the total energy output of the sun over a&amp;nbsp;day.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That means the impulse this laser delivered (momentum per second, or force) to the death star must be the power over c, the speed of light (see my &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/today-id-like-to-approach-question-near.html"&gt;earlier post&lt;/a&gt; for a discussion of laser gun recoil).  This is a force of 4.3*10^23 N.  We now need to estimate the death star mass.  According to &lt;a href="http://starwars.wikia.com/wiki/Death_Star"&gt;confidential sources&lt;/a&gt; the death star had a diameter of 150 km.  The death star is made of metal, but it also has a lot of empty space inside of it.  We&amp;#8217;ll go ahead and assume it has the density of water.  This gives is a mass of
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$M_{ds}=\tfrac{4}{3}\pi r^3\rho=2.4\cdot 10^{13} kg$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
A quick glance at our numbers reveals that we&amp;#8217;re going to need special relativity here!  Otherwise we&amp;#8217;d be accelerating this thing well past the speed of&amp;nbsp;light.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We have a total momentum change of 1.7&lt;em&gt;10^{24}kg&lt;/em&gt;m/s.  This is a relativistic momentum, which we can solve for v.  The algebra is a tiny bit ugly, but it turns out that velocity in terms of relativistic momentum is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$v=\sqrt{\frac{p^2}{m^2+p^2/c^2}} \approx c $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
It turns out that the death star would be moving so close to speed of light as to not matter.  That&amp;#8217;s fast!  I think we can safely say that this laser recoil would be&amp;nbsp;noticed!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="star wars"></category><category term="recoil"></category><category term="marvin the martian"></category><category term="lasers"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category></entry><entry><title>The End of Earth Physics I</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/the-end-of-earth-physics-i.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-17T16:25:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-17:posts/the-end-of-earth-physics-i.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was reading the Wikipedia page for the Hitchhiker&amp;#8217;s Guide books the other day and found that it started as a series of radio shows called &amp;#8220;The Ends of Earth.&amp;#8221;  At the end of each episode, the Earth would be destroyed.  Since I feel like this is the best way to end any &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; show/movie/book/news broadcast/Mayan calendar, I will shamelessly steal the idea.  &lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Since this is the first End of the Earth post, we will start small and just consider the boiling off of all the world&amp;#8217;s oceans.  To be precise, we will consider how much energy it would take to turn all the world&amp;#8217;s water at 0 degrees Celsius to water vapor at 100 degrees Celsius.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;First we need to estimate the mass of all the water on earth.  I will make the assumptions that all water is fresh water and that the oceans account for all water on earth.  These are obviously not exactly true, but will give the proper order of magnitude.  The volume of a spherical shell is given by&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{V} =  4 \pi R^{2} \Delta R $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Taking the radius of the earth to be 6000 km, the ocean depth to be 1 km, and the fraction of earth covered by water to be 7/10 , we see that&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ V_\text{water} =  4 \pi  {R_{\text{earth}}^{2} \times \text{height} \times \text{fraction}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ V_\text{water} =  4 \pi  (6 \times 10^{6} \text{m})^{2} \times 10^{3} \text{m} \times (\frac{7}{10})  = 3 \times 10^{17} \text{m}^{3}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now we have the volume of the ocean.  Now, since &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{Density} =  \frac{Mass}{Volume}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;we can calculate the mass of the oceans using the density of water to be 1000 kg / m^3.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{Mass} =  (\rho_\text{water})(V_\text{water}) = (1000 \frac{\text{kg}}{\text{m}^{3}})(3 \times 10^{17} \text{m}^{3}) = 3 \times 10^{20} \text{kg}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FACT&lt;/span&gt;: The mass of all the water on earth is about 2% the mass of that celestial punching bag known as Pluto.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Alright, now that we have the mass of the earth, we can start calculating how much energy it would take to heat it up and boil it away.  The amount of heat Q required to raise the temperature of a given material is &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_\text{heat} = \text{mc}\Delta\text{T} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;where m is the mass of the thing we are heating, c is the specific heat ( the amount of energy required to heat our material up 1 degree Celcius) and delta T is our change in temperature.  This equation only holds when there are no phase transitions, so we can use it to calculate how much energy is needed to heat up the oceans from 0 degrees to 100 degrees:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_\text{heat} = (3 \times 10^{20} \text{kg}) \times (4000 \frac{\text{J}}{\text{kg C}}) \times (100 \text{deg C}) = 10^{26} \text{J} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;where we have used the fact that the specific heat of water is about 4000 J/kg deg C.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So now we know how much energy it takes to bring water to its boiling point, but this is not the same as boiling it off.  To find that, we need to calculate how much energy we have to add to liquid water at a constant 100 degrees to turn it into water vapor.  This is given by&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_{\text{boil}} = \text{mL} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;where m is the mass again and L is the &amp;#8220;latent heat of vaporization.&amp;#8221;  It tells us how much energy we need to add to turn a kilogram of liquid water at 100 degrees to a kilogram of water vapor at 100 degrees.  For water, L is about 2*10^6 J/kg, so&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_{\text{boil}} = ( 3 \times 10^{20} \text{kg} ) \times (2 \times 10^{6} \frac{\text{J}}{\text{kg}}) = 6 \times 10^{26} \text{J} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Comparing this to the energy calculated before, we see that amount of energy needed to vaporize water at 100 degrees is about six times larger than the amount of energy needed to heat up the water by  100 degrees!&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now we can calculate the total amount of energy to boil way the oceans:&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_{\text{total}} = Q_{\text{heat}} + Q_{\text{boil}} = 7 \times 10^{26} \text{J} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;So how much energy is that really?  Well the total power of the sun is &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ L_{\text{sun}} = 4 \times 10^{26} \frac{\text{J}}{\text{s}} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Thus, it would take the entire energy output of the sun for about 2 seconds to boil away all the earth&amp;#8217;s oceans.  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Now thats a lot of energy.  To put this into the conventional unit of destruction, this is equivalent to 10^11 Megatons of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TNT&lt;/span&gt;.  Typical hydrogen bombs are 10 Megatons.   So if you want to boil away the oceans with H-bombs, you&amp;#8217;d need about ten billion hydrogen bombs.  &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;Luckily,  short of constructing a reflecting Dyson sphere with a hole that directs all the sun&amp;#8217;s radiation at the earth, these energies are unobtainable.  So don&amp;#8217;t panic.&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category></entry></feed>