<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.42.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 08:22:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>A Very Small Slice of Pi</title><link>/posts/a-very-small-slice-of-pi.html</link><description>&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q37nqPUh_t0/T2AJgUmFLKI/AAAAAAAAAWY/0rvkqKzmDBs/s1600/rhubarb.JPG" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="240" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q37nqPUh_t0/T2AJgUmFLKI/AAAAAAAAAWY/0rvkqKzmDBs/s320/rhubarb.JPG" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Rhubarb pie (Source: Wikipedia)&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Some people know a &lt;i&gt;suspiciously&lt;/i&gt; large number of the digits of pi.  Perhaps you have met one of these people.  They can typically be found hiding behind bushes and under the counters at pastry shops, just&amp;#8230; &lt;i&gt;waiting&lt;/i&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At the slightest hint of a mention of pi, they will jump out and start reciting the digits like there&amp;#8217;s a prize at the end.  After rattling off numbers for a few minutes they abruptly come to an end, grin like an idiot, and walk away.  It is an unpleasant&amp;nbsp;encounter.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The sheer uselessness of this kind of thing has always bothered me, so I&amp;#8217;d like to set a preliminary upper bound on the number of digits of pi that could ever possibly potentially kind of be useful (maybe).  For those following along at home, now would be a good time to put on your numerology&amp;nbsp;hats.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Alright, so I hear this thing pi is fairly useful when dealing with circles.  Let&amp;#8217;s say we want to make a really big circle and have its diameter only deviate by a very small amount from the correct value.  To do this successfully, we will have to know pi fairly&amp;nbsp;well. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s take this to extremes now.  Suppose I want to put a circle around the &lt;i&gt;entire visible universe&lt;/i&gt; such that the uncertainty in the diameter is the size of a &lt;i&gt;single proton&lt;/i&gt;.  What would be the fractional uncertainty in the circumference in this&amp;nbsp;case?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If we know pi exactly, then we have&amp;nbsp;that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\delta C = \frac{\partial C}{\partial d} \delta d = \pi \delta d = C \frac{\delta d}{d}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where d is the diameter and C is the circumference.  In other words, the fractional uncertainty in the circumference is&amp;nbsp;just&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta C}{C} = \frac{\delta d}{d}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a femtometer for the size of a proton and 90 billion light years for the size of the Universe &lt;a href="#note"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a id="back"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;, we&amp;nbsp;get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta C}{C} = \frac{\delta d}{d} = \frac{10^{-15}\mbox{m}}{(90\times10^9)(3\times10^7\mbox{s})(3\times10^8\mbox{m s}^{-1})} \sim\frac{10^{-15}}{10^{27}}\sim10^{-42}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so how well do we need to know pi to get a similar fractional uncertainty?  Well, we have&amp;nbsp;that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta \pi}{\pi} = \frac{\delta C}{C} = 10^{-42}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;so we can afford an uncertainty in pi&amp;nbsp;of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \delta \pi = \pi \times 10^{-42}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;and thus we&amp;#8217;ll need to know pi to about 42 digits.  How&amp;#8217;s that for an &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phrases_from_The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy#Answer_to_the_Ultimate_Question_of_Life.2C_the_Universe.2C_and_Everything_.2842.29"&gt;answer&lt;/a&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So if we have a giant circle the size of the &lt;i&gt;entire visible universe&lt;/i&gt;, we can find its diameter to within the size of a &lt;i&gt;single proton&lt;/i&gt; using pi to 42 digits.  Therefore, I adopt this as the maximal number of digits that could ever prove useful in a physical sense (albeit under a somewhat bizzarre set of&amp;nbsp;circumstances). &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If reciting hundreds of digits is what makes you happy, go for it.  But 42 digits is more than enough pi for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p id="note"&gt;[1] &amp;#8220;But I thought the Universe was only 13.7 billion years!  What voodoo is this!?&amp;#8221;  Yeah, I know.  See &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/startswithabang/2011/01/q_a_how_is_the_universe_so_big.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; for a nice explanation.&lt;a href="#back"&gt;&amp;nbsp;[back] &lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Corky</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 08:22:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2012-03-14:posts/a-very-small-slice-of-pi.html</guid><category>pi day</category><category>42</category><category>scott bakula</category></item></channel></rss>