<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.experiment.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Thu, 05 May 2011 21:06:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Anatomy of an Experiment I - The Question</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/anatomy-of-an-experiment-i-the-question.html</link><description>&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-V-68a5ev1W0/TcNG1UXmaBI/AAAAAAAAAEY/0f-Uq2EjMJY/s1600/installation_of_world_largest_silicon_tracking_detector.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="204" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-V-68a5ev1W0/TcNG1UXmaBI/AAAAAAAAAEY/0f-Uq2EjMJY/s320/installation_of_world_largest_silicon_tracking_detector.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Warning: picture has little or no relation to this post.&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I realized the other day that I've seen a lot of people talk about research results, but it is much more rare that I see someone talk about how we do research.  I think that may be because, to us as scientists, the process is second nature.  We've been doing it for years.  Other folks may be less familiar with the process though.  With this in mind, I'm going to do a short series of posts focused on how we do an experiment.  Not the results, not so much the physics, but the process that we go through to create, setup, and carry out an experiment.  As my example I'll use a short little experiment that I built from the ground up in the last few weeks, that I'm currently in the process of (hopefully) wrapping up.  Today I'll talk about the driving force behind almost any experiment: The Question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;It might be argued that there are two types of experiments.  There are those that set out to answer a specific question, and those that set out to explore what happens under certain conditions (explore some part of phase space).  An example of the first type that comes immediately to mind is the recently announced results from &lt;a href="http://science.nasa.gov/science-news/science-at-nasa/2011/04may_epic/"&gt;Gravity Probe B&lt;/a&gt; (GP-B).  This was an experiment designed with one goal in mind, to test the validity of einstein's theory of general relativity, specifically geodesic precession and frame dragging.  They asked the question, built the apparatus, and then got results.  Here's a spoiler from the article: Einstein was right, to remarkable precision.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'm going to mostly ignore the second type of experiment.  While very important, I argue that those exploratory experiments are (almost?) always done on experimental apparatus that was built for another experiment.  You don't spend the time, money, and energy to build an experimental apparatus without having good evidence that it's worth doing, that is, without expecting to see something.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This brings me to The Question.  The name might be misleading, the motivation for an experiment might not be a question (though it can usually be phrased as one).  One common motivation is to test theoretical predictions, as was the case with GP-B.  Theory without experimental verification is empty.  It may sound nice, but we can't trust it unless we've tested it against what nature actually does.  Sometimes theory develops because of experimental results, for example the knowledge of the quantization of light came out of anomalous experimental effects of the photoelectric effect and blackbody radiation (among others).  Other times, experiment develops to test theory, the GP-B and the Large Hadron Collider for example.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another common motivation is a question based on a physical observation, for example: &lt;a href="http://physicsbuzz.physicscentral.com/2011/04/small-insects-paddle-through-air.html"&gt;how does a fly fly&lt;/a&gt;?  That question is, as these things go, very simply stated.  For an idea of how complicated they can get, just take a look at any recent collection of articles from any physics journal, wherein we find things like the form and source of 'itinerant magnetism in FeAs' (grabbed from a recent Phys. Rev. B article).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I classify a third type of question, one that is more process based: "How can we do X?".  This third category is where the question that motivates (at least in the broad sense) the experiment I'm going to describe comes from.  I can phrase it as: "How can we successfully cryopreserve biological samples?"  For those unfamiliar with biological cryopreservation, this is something I discussed &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/05/cryopreservation.html"&gt;almost a year ago&lt;/a&gt;.  From there, we get into smaller questions, most of those are type two, based on physical observations.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This particular small experiment has grown out of my work on cryopreservation, and has more to do with the structure of water on freezing.  Over the past year, one of the projects I've been working on has been to measure the so called critical warming rate of aqueous solutions.  This is the rate at which you have to warm vitreous aqueous solutions (see my earlier cryopreservation post for more details) to prevent ice formation on warming.  The question that has grown out of this work is: how does the cooling history of my vitreous sample affect the critical warming rate?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Having arrived at the question, we'll next discuss the apparatus.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 05 May 2011 21:06:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-05-05:posts/anatomy-of-an-experiment-i-the-question.html</guid><category>question</category><category>cryopreservation</category><category>physics</category><category>experiment</category></item><item><title>Steak Dinner</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/steak-dinner.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Sorry about the blog hiatus.  During the summer, without teaching classes, inspiration is harder to come by.  But, tonight I cooked a steak.  I recently got a new digital meat thermometer.  My plan was to slowly cook the steak until the internal temperature got to be about 140 degrees Fahrenheit with the oven at 200 degrees, take it out, wrap in tin foil, crank the oven to 500 degrees, stick it back in, and give it a nice exterior, reaching an internal temperature of about 150 degrees which would put it at about medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After I put the steak into the oven though, I started to watch the temperature go up on my digital thermometer and thought, why not take data.  And so I did.  Here are the results.
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/TFi924poROI/AAAAAAAAAMg/VSSuNTCh30g/s1600/steakdinner.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="186" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/TFi924poROI/AAAAAAAAAMg/VSSuNTCh30g/s400/steakdinner.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
Above you see the internal temperature of the steak as a function of time.  First some comments about the graph.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt; The steak started at 37 degrees, the temperature of my refrigerator.
&lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; I didn't start taking data until about 20 minutes in. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; The red dashed lines mark where I turned up the temperature of the oven.  It started at 200 degrees, then 250, then 300, and in the final stretch, 500 with the broiler. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; The green dotted lines mark where I got impatient and opened the door to the over to check on the food. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; The yellow background denotes where the steak was outside of the oven resting in tinfoil. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now some comments on the data
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt; You can clearly see a change in the data when I changed the oven temperature. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; Opening the oven door really seems to slow down the cooking process &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; The temperature of the center of the steak continues to rise after you take it out of the oven. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; In fact, curiously enough, the temperature of the center of the steak seems to have risen the quickest after it was taken out of the oven. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
Next I decided to look at the heating rate, computed by taking the finite differences of my data points and propagating the errors.
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/TFi97yIEe9I/AAAAAAAAAMo/EzZ_kvRdb7U/s1600/heatrate.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="223" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/TFi97yIEe9I/AAAAAAAAAMo/EzZ_kvRdb7U/s400/heatrate.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
As you'll see, I really didn't have enough data points or a precise enough thermometer to really see the changes in the heating rate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally some comments about the food.
&lt;ul&gt;&lt;li&gt; The steak was good.  You'll notice I shot past 150, ended up with a temperature of about 160, and a steak that was nearly medium well. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; Cooking the steak slowly like this yielded as pretty soft texture, akin to a roast.  Heck, I essentially roasted the steak. &lt;/li&gt;&lt;li&gt; The steak was served with asparagus and baked potatoes. As an interesting aside, the baked potatoes were in the oven along with the steak the whole time, but did not cook all the way through.  I normally bake potatoes at 350 for about an hour, and here they were in a hot oven for over an hour and a half, half an hour of which was above 300, but they didn't cook through.&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ul&gt;
I clearly have too much time on my hands.  I have one more steak, and I think I'll try a different cooking method.  Maybe I'll have the patience to take data again, we'll see.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Alemi</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 03 Aug 2010 21:20:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-08-03:posts/steak-dinner.html</guid><category>data</category><category>steak</category><category>fun</category><category>graph</category><category>experiment</category></item><item><title>Life as an Experimenter - Reflections</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/life-as-an-experimenter-reflections.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I've been doing experimental physics for about three years.  I started during my sophomore year in college, went straight to graduate school, and continued here (albeit not quite immediately).  There are people out there who have been doing this for a lot longer than I have, but I've gained a few insights, by working with said people, and through my own experiences in the lab.  I thought I'd try to share a few of these, to help illuminate the past few days I blogged about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;b&gt;Something Always Goes Wrong&lt;/b&gt;
It's the nature of experimental science.  Something always goes wrong.  It might be your equipment, it might be your sample, hell, it might be something personal.  But something will go wrong.  Wednesday was a prime example.  Not only did I get soaked by rain and temporarily lose my bike lock, but it took us 9 hours to really start taking data due to equipment problems.  I think this is endemic in what we're doing.  We're trying to investigate something that no one has ever done (at least not quite exactly what we're doing).  This means that we're usually pushing the bounds of our equipment and setup.  Not just that, but most of the equipment is exceedingly complex, giving it many more places it can break down.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;It's An Emotional Roller Coaster&lt;/b&gt;
Sometimes nothing works.  At all.  You try and try and you just can't make it work.  Then sometimes everything is going well.  You're getting data, and not just that, but the data looks good.  Whether it's confirming or destroying your expectations, you're finding out something new about the world.  It's exciting.  You find something interesting and start chasing it.  However, you have to be careful.  Often the result is not what you think you're seeing.  It's a false signal from your equipment, or attributable to the background material doing something strange.  Or you've destroyed the sample, and that's why it's  not doing what you expect.  You go up and down quite a bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;It's Exhausting&lt;/b&gt;
Part of it is the long hours.  But really, 16 hour days are not &lt;em&gt;that&lt;/em&gt; bad.  Sleeping 6.5-7 hours.  I can usually do that, no problem.  So what's different when it's research?  You have to be thinking all the time.  For 16 hours.  In general, you can't just push the button and wait.  You need to look at the data while it comes in, to determine what data to take next.  Combine that with the emotional up and down . . . even though you're not necessarily physically exhausted, you're mentally worn out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;You Get More Questions Than Answers&lt;/b&gt;
My undergraduate advisor would always say that when you're doing research you generate three questions for every question you answer.  That's more or less true.  It is very rare to go out and answer all the questions you have.  It is even more rare to not get more questions.    There's always more to learn.  In many ways, that's great, though a little frustrating.  If we ran out of questions, we'd probably run out of a job.  But there's always another twist that you didn't expect nature to have, something else surprising you.  That's why we do it.  There's no finality in research.  We can't get all the answers, ever.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A lot of our time isn't data taking, but making/setting up our equipment, analyzing data, and such things.  Still, I hope that this series of posts has given you a taste of what we scientists may do when we're taking data.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Sat, 19 Jun 2010 15:50:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-06-19:posts/life-as-an-experimenter-reflections.html</guid><category>reflection</category><category>CHESS</category><category>experiment</category></item><item><title>Life as an Experimenter - Day Three</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/life-as-an-experimenter-day-three.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Today marks the third and final day in our beam time at CHESS.  I think the circles under all of our eyes may take away from the glamor a bit, but the right makeup specialist could fix that.  If they ever make a movie about us, which they should, I want to be played by some really awesome british actor.  I think that would be about right.  Someone with a strong jaw.  In case it's not obvious, lack of sleep is getting to me a little bit.  Read on for the final few hours of our experiment.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Friday 6/18&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;9:07am&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - Not sure if I didn't turn on my alarm, or turned it off without noticing.  But somehow I manage to jerk awake not too much later than planned.  Dragging a little bit.  Get some food.  No time for shower, do that in a few hours.  Only have to get through to noon.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;9:41&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - Leave house.  Hop in car.  Realize as I drive through that there's a stop sign at a corner that I didn't see last night, mostly hidden by trees.  Very glad there wasn't any traffic.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;9:54&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - Arrive back at CHESS.  Set up laptop to stream the US game.  Get a report from Matt and Ryan.  Looks like the data that was exciting last night is actually repeatable, and though it is a small effect, probably real.  This is a very nice bonus for our experiment, we were mostly expecting null results from that phase of things.  Plan is to test that more, run some experiments to make sure we're not seeing other, more mundane, effects that would look the same with our collection methods.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;10:25&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - I take over crystal mounting.  Matt is busy with data, and Ryan is not having luck with crystals this morning.  That's how it goes.  US is down a goal.  Morale low for that reason.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;10:45&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - Data taking going okay.  Still seeing the effect, though small.  US down 2 goals.  Not good at all.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;11:00&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - US down 1 goal!  Oh yes.  Some experiment.  We're almost done, not paying too much attention any more.  Everyone is slowing down.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;11:20&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - CHESS staff members keep on wandering into our area and staying to watch the game.  Kind of fun.  One got us an ethernet cable to eliminate some of the pauses we were getting in the streaming  using the wireless.  Set up a final run, determine if the effect is from what we suspect (hope?) or from mundane causes.  Need to pack up and be out in 40 minutes.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;11:45&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - Experiment finishes.  US is robbed!  Should have been a victory.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;11:50&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - Mad scramble to pack up equipment.  Crystals, mounts, computers, etc.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;11:58&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; - Off the beam.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;12:05pm &lt;/span&gt;&lt;/b&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;- Parking permit returned.  On my way home.  Taking the rest of the day off.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt; &lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;I hope that you, dear reader, have enjoyed this brief taste of how experiments go.  I tried to let the emotions reflect what I actually was feeling at the time, but often for the most harrowing/exciting parts there was no time to write, so much of this has been upon reflection.  Tomorrow I hope to offer a few insights into how experiments usually seem to go.  A lot of people have never done experimental science, and experimentation in movies is &lt;/span&gt;&lt;a href="http://xkcd.com/683/"&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;very different&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt; from what we actually do.  Now it's time to sleep.  And maybe watch the England/Algeria game.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2010 13:49:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-06-18:posts/life-as-an-experimenter-day-three.html</guid><category>CHESS</category><category>experiment</category></item><item><title>Life as an Experimenter - Day Two</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/life-as-an-experimenter-day-two.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today I'm continuing my series on the life of an experimenter.  Today is the longest day, since we have beam time for all 24 hours.  And after the setbacks of yesterday, we feel compelled to use it to the utmost bit.  Read on for more tantalizing glimpses of the grit behind the glamor of the rock-star-like lifestyle of an experimental physicist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;Today had a very different feel.  Things were working, and that meant a lot of down time waiting for data to collect.  Despite the excitement of data coming in, I was a little bored at points.  Lots of internet use.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Thursday 6/17
&lt;b&gt;7:15am&lt;/b&gt; - Alarm goes off.  6.5 hours of sleep?  Up quickly, and eat and shower.  Run into a couple of my housemates that I normally don't.  I don't feel to tired.  Which is good, because I don't usually do caffeine, if I had to now, it might well mess me up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;7:50&lt;/b&gt; - Out of the house.  Taking my car, since my bike isn't working.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;8:05&lt;/b&gt; - At the F1 station.  Matt is there, awake, looking not too much worse for ware.  Ryan comes in right behind me.  I have to get a parking permit, which CHESS kindly provides for visiting researchers.  Since my car isn't registered on campus, I qualify as a visiting researcher.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;8:10&lt;/b&gt; - Matt briefs us on the progress of the night.  Some good data was taken, and we've switched from the helium to a liquid nitrogen (LN) cooling.  He lays out the set of experiments we should try to run today.  Obvious that he needs sleep.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;8:45 &lt;/b&gt;- Matt goes home.  Ryan and myself are on our own.  Start a data run.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;9-10&lt;/b&gt; - All the staff are checking in on us.  After the problems of yesterday, they want to make sure everything is running smoothly.  Which it is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10:30&lt;/b&gt; - Data running smoothly.  When everything goes well, for this particularly type of data set, there's not much to be done while it's coming in.  Put on the Greece vs. Nigeria world cup game, streaming on my laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:30&lt;/b&gt; - Data run finished.  Load up a new crystal smooth as can be.  Start another data set.  Everything working like a charm.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;12:30pm&lt;/b&gt; - Lunch break.  Much more relaxed today.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:00&lt;/b&gt; - Data run done.  Switching to a different type of data run&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:15&lt;/b&gt; - New run starts.  Smooth sailing so far.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:30&lt;/b&gt; - Put on Mexico vs. France world cup game.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;3:30&lt;/b&gt; - Attempting to start a new run.  Took us three or four tries to find a new crystal that was good.  Run good to go.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4:15&lt;/b&gt; - We're trying to run at 80K, but we're having problems with temperature stability. We talk to Ulrich, and he thinks that we've got a partial ice plug in the LN line, reducing the LN we can draw through.  We can either waste two hours having it replaced, or run with it as it is.  No guarantee that it won't get worse.  We decide to run with it, we've lost too much beam time already.  Our lowest temperature seems to be ~90K.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;5:15&lt;/b&gt; - Data run finishes.  New crystal mounted.  New data run started.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;6:30 &lt;/b&gt;- Data run finishes.  Two attempts before we get a good crystal.  Data flowing smoothly.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;7:10&lt;/b&gt; - Matt returns.  There is much rejoicing.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;8:00 &lt;/b&gt;- Trying room temperature data taking.  Matt wants us to learn all the tricks this run, it seems.  Having trouble getting good crystals.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10:00 &lt;/b&gt;- Room temperature data giving us a few interesting results.  Trying a full run, but we're going to kill the crystal long before that.  X rays will kill proteins (that's why we avoid them, ourselves).  Faster at room temperature than at 100K.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10:45&lt;/b&gt; - Dinner from the stuff I packed this morning.  I do love microwaved leftovers.  No rush, though.  All three of us are in the lab, and Ryan and Matt can handle whatever comes.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:25&lt;/b&gt; - Lots of trouble getting good crystals (4 or 5 attempts?).  220K is a hard temperature.  Finally gave up and went to 240K.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:55&lt;/b&gt; - Ryan goes home.  He'll be back around 6 tomorrow.  I'm sticking it out for a while.  Interesting data coming in around 240K.  If we're skilled and lucky, we'll get something around 220K also.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Friday 6/18
&lt;b&gt;12:20am&lt;/b&gt; - Potentially exciting results!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;12:45&lt;/b&gt; - Reproducible potentially exciting results!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;1:15&lt;/b&gt; - My brain can't do simple calculations right now, but we're changing temperatures and trying out another look for our result at 240K.  I hope it's there!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;1:20&lt;/b&gt; - Morale lower.  Possibly the effect is from a perfectly reasonable explainable thing.  What a great hour though!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;1:45&lt;/b&gt; - Data inconclusive but leaning towards no.  Heading home.  Leave Matt all by his lonesome.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;1:55&lt;/b&gt; - Home.  Sleep time.  Alarm set for 9.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 18 Jun 2010 01:57:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-06-18:posts/life-as-an-experimenter-day-two.html</guid><category>long</category><category>CHESS</category><category>experiment</category></item><item><title>Life as an Experimenter - Day One</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/life-as-an-experimenter-day-one.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;I'm an experimental physicist.  If you think this sounds like a job second in glamour only to rock star you would be right.  Just like being a rock star, you have to deal with the people, the shows, the lights, the groupies . . . okay, maybe I'm lying about the groupies.  Unless you're &lt;a href="http://groups.myspace.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=groups.groupprofile&amp;amp;groupID=103575126"&gt;Brian Greene&lt;/a&gt;.  Also similar to a rock star, no one really knows what it is we do behind the scenes (when we're not touring the nation or publishing papers).  I'd like to pull back that curtain a little bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A bit of background.  For this data run we're looking at the structure of protein crystals.  The basic idea is that if you have a bunch of proteins, you can create a crystal out of them using various synthesis techniques.  If they're formed right, they look similar to the crystals you are more familiar with, quartz, diamond, emerald, etc.  We're interested in how the proteins are held in the crystal, that is, what kind of structure the protein crystal has.  I'll talk more about this at some other point.  Our method for examining this is using x rays.  Similar to a medical x-ray, we shoot x-rays at our sample, and look at the transmitted images.  Of course, instead of something like this:
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TBpWZFChfhI/AAAAAAAAABs/Cp-4Rf5ca5Y/s1600/X-ray-hands.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="228" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TBpWZFChfhI/AAAAAAAAABs/Cp-4Rf5ca5Y/s320/X-ray-hands.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;we see something like this:
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TBpWqG2OqLI/AAAAAAAAAB0/SncRJvsz1Uk/s1600/20071104200851!X-ray_diffraction_pattern_3clpro.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TBpWqG2OqLI/AAAAAAAAAB0/SncRJvsz1Uk/s320/20071104200851!X-ray_diffraction_pattern_3clpro.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;which is a little bit harder to interpret.  Nevertheless, we've got some pretty nifty software that will do the job for us.  The unfortunate part about using x-rays is that to produce research grade x-rays takes really big expensive facilities, so we have a limited amount of time we get to use them for.  Right now, we've got 48 hours of beam time, so we want to take data for as many of those 48 hours as possible.  For those interested, we're using CHESS at Cornell, station F1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wednesday, 6/16
&lt;b&gt;9:30am &lt;/b&gt;- Get up.  I was warned by the postdoc in my group to sleep in as much as I could.  Our data run starts at noon, and goes for 48 hours.  Who knows how much sleep we'll get in those 48 hours.  Our beam time starts at noon today.  I eat breakfast, and realize that I've left my lab notebook in the lab.  I need to swing by there and pick it up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10:52&lt;/b&gt; - Out of the house.  My goal is to be at CHESS by 11.  As this is my first time using the facility,  I need to get a safety tour before I can use the beam line.  I hope on my bike and speed towards to the physics building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10:54&lt;/b&gt; - Downpour.  I get soaked.  I'm wearing a rain jacket, but my jeans and shoes are soaked through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10:55 &lt;/b&gt;- A pocket on my backpack comes unzipped, dumping my water bottle (and, as I find out later, my bike lock) into the road.  I stop and retrieve the water bottle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:02&lt;/b&gt; - Arrive at physics building.  Hasten to the lab, dripping water.  Grab notebook.  Receive call from Ryan, another graduate student in the lab, saying he's at CHESS, and ready to take the safety tour when I am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:12 &lt;/b&gt; - Arrive at CHESS.  Realize I don't have my bike lock anymore.  Call Ryan and tell him to take the tour without me, I'll get to it later.  Hop on bike, ride route in reverse.  Find lock right where water bottle fell out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:25&lt;/b&gt; - Back at CHESS.  Check in.  Get given safety tour, radiation badge.  Meet up with Ryan.  Good times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:59&lt;/b&gt; - Matt, the postdoc in my lab, with experience at CHESS and the samples and equipment, arrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;12:00pm&lt;/b&gt; - Beam time starts.  We're not ready.  For this run, we're using liquid helium to cool our sample.  We have to get that set up first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;1:45&lt;/b&gt; - With the aid of Ulrich, one of the Research Associates at CHESS, we have the liquid helium stream set up to cool our sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:00 &lt;/b&gt;- Matt trains Ryan and myself how to mount samples for the beam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:15&lt;/b&gt; - Matt mounts a sample, and trains Ryan and myself how to operate beam controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:30 &lt;/b&gt;- Start taking data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:45 &lt;/b&gt;- Crystal turns out to be not very crystalline.  Rinse and repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4:00&lt;/b&gt; - After 7 increasingly frustrating attempts with bad crystals, the 8th turns out to give us a good signal.  Looks like we're back in business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4:15&lt;/b&gt; - Getting anomalous signals from our sample.  Every 5th image has about have the intensity of the others.  Also getting some weird tiling in the image.  No one knows what's going on.  We call in Ulrich and the beam operator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4:30 &lt;/b&gt;- In the midst of trying to resolve the anomalous signals, the computer we're running the experimental control software on goes down.  Requires calling in more tech support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4:50 &lt;/b&gt;- I take a break to eat.  First food since breakfast.  Two sandwiches and a half-frozen banana (kept it near the back of the fridge in the CHESS lounge.  I learned my lesson).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;5:10&lt;/b&gt; - Food eaten.  Computer back up.  Data taking ready.  Still no resolution for the anomalous signal.  While the experts continue to trouble shoot, Matt attempts to figure out if we can run any of our experiments with the data as bad as it currently is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;5:45&lt;/b&gt; - Still no solution.  Matt has determined that none of our planned experiments will work with the data as bad as it is.  Suspicion of a bad detector (a million dollar piece of equipment).  Morale is low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;8:00&lt;/b&gt; - After continued trouble shooting, Ulrich is convinced that the problem is a bad shutter for the x ray beam (just like a camera, you achieve a certain image exposure by letting the beam hit the sample/detector for a certain amount of time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;8:30&lt;/b&gt; - Technician arrives to swap shutters.  Operation successful!  Data looks good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;9:00&lt;/b&gt; - After some test runs, we start taking real data.  Morale is high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:15&lt;/b&gt; - Data coming in with no sign of stopping.  Ryan and I head home.  Matt has the night shift, we're to relieve him at 8 the next morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:20 &lt;/b&gt;- Discover that my bike has somehow broken while sitting on the bike rack.  The collar that keeps the handlebars in the frame is loose, and the handlebars no longer connect with the front wheel.  Bike is unrideable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:25&lt;/b&gt; - Decide bike is unfixable with current tools.  I have to walk it home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:40&lt;/b&gt; - Home.  Attempt to fix bike. Discover none of my wrenches are quite large enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:45 &lt;/b&gt;- Food.  Microwave leftovers.  Discover one of my housemates has left fresh chocolate chip cookies on the counter for the rest of the house.  Bless her a thousand times over and eat two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;
&lt;/b&gt;
Thursday 6/17
&lt;b&gt;12:15am&lt;/b&gt; - Set alarm for 7:15am, and hop into bed.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 17 Jun 2010 13:53:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-06-17:posts/life-as-an-experimenter-day-one.html</guid><category>CHESS</category><category>long day</category><category>experiment</category></item><item><title>Letting Air Out of Tires II</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/letting-air-out-of-tires-ii.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;In a &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/05/letting-air-out-of-tires.html"&gt;recent post&lt;/a&gt; I calculated how cold air coming out of bike tires should feel.  However, at the end of the post, I did note that there are competing explanations for why the air cools.  There's the approach I took, which is adiabatic cooling, but there's also something called the Joule-Thomson effect.  The Joule-Thomson effect has the interesting property that helium being let out of a bike tire would actually be warmer, which suggests an immediate way to test which effect is dominant.  We pressurize a bike tire with helium, and see if the valve gets cold or hot.  This is exactly what I did.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;With the help of Mark and Vince, our local equipment gurus, I was able to pressurize a bike tire to 26 psi with helium.  Using one of those little thermal measurers you can buy at radio shack, we measured the initial temperature of the valve as 80 F.  We then released the helium, and measured the temperature of the valve as 73 F.  The adiabatic approach is the winner!  Our experiment confirms that the dominant effect of the cooling is the adiabatic cooling I talked about yesterday.  The Joule-Thomson effect may be at play, but if so it takes a secondary role to the adiabatic cooling.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, some of you may be saying: wait a second, you predicted the air would be -100 F!  It doesn't feel that cold!  Nor did your valve cool down to -100 F!  To which I reply: Yes, I did predict very cold air.  But you have to remember that it is mixing with a lot of room temperature air, so it won't feel as cold as I predicted.  Nor will it transfer much heat to the valve (recall, we predicted this would be an adiabatic process, with absolutely no heat transfer, something that is obviously false).  Also, I didn't have 60 psi of pressure.  If we do the calculation, 26 psi only gives a temperature of 250K = - 10 F.  Hopefully that answers your question.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now, dear reader, as I've wanted to say for a while: Myth Busted!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 04 May 2010 14:52:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-04:posts/letting-air-out-of-tires-ii.html</guid><category>bike</category><category>tire</category><category>thermodynamics</category><category>gas</category><category>cold</category><category>experiment</category><category>busted</category></item><item><title>Letting Air Out of Tires</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/letting-air-out-of-tires.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Have you ever noticed how when you let air out of a bike tire (or, I suppose, a car tire) it feels rather cold?  Today we're going to explore why that is, and just how cold it is.  Many people consider the air escaping from a tire as a classic example of an adiabatic process.  What is an adiabatic process?  It is a process that happens so quickly there is no time for heat flow to occur.  For our air in the bike tire this means we're letting it out of the tire so quickly that no energy can move into it from the surrounding air.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;This may not be exactly true, there may be a little energy flow, but there is little enough that we can ignore it.  Given that, how do we talk about temperature change?  Let's give a physical motivation first.  Imagine a gas as a collection of hard spheres, like baseballs.  Envision this bunch of baseballs in a box.  Suppose you make the volume of the box smaller, you move the walls in.  The baseballs will start to bounce around faster.  Having trouble thinking of this?  Think of a single baseball in a box.  Imagine it hits a wall moving towards it.  What happens?  That's just like what happens when a baseball hits a baseball bat moving towards it, it goes flying.  That is, it starts moving faster.  The speed with which these gas particles are moving is what we measure as temperature.  So shrinking our box increases the temperature.  Likewise, expanding our box will decrease the temperature.  The same principle holds here.  Our gas is expanding from a small volume (the bike tire) into a larger volume (the surrounding world).  Thus we expect the temperature to decrease.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Got all that?  Good.  Now for some math.  It turns out that using the ideal gas law, we can derive that for an (reversible) adiabatic process&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$PV^\gamma=constant$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;where P is the pressure of the gas, V is the volume of the gas, and gamma is (for our purposes) just a number.  The ideal gas law states that&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$PV=NkT$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Where N is the number of gas molecules we have, T is the temperature of the gas, and k is a constant.  Since N doesn't change in the process we're considering, we can use this to rewrite the above equation, by substituting for V.  This gives&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$P^{1-\gamma}T^{\gamma}=constant$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Where the constant is not the same as above.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Because this is equal to a constant, we can say that our initial pressure and temperature are related to our final pressure and temperature by&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$P_i^{1-\gamma}T_i^{\gamma}=P_f^{1-\gamma}T_f^{\gamma}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;We can solve this for the final temperature giving&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$T_f=T_i\left(\frac{P_i}{P_f}\right)^{\tfrac{1-\gamma}{\gamma}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Finally, we can plug in some numbers.  Gamma is 7/5 for diatomic gases (which is most of air).  If we assume the air is about room temperature, 20 C, and the tire is at 60 psi, this gives (1 atmosphere of pressure is 15 psi):&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$T_f=293K\left(\frac{60 psi}{15 psi}\right)^{\tfrac{1-7/5}{7/5}}=197K$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Converting back from Kelvin to C, this is -76 C or -105 F.  That's cold!&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;&lt;b&gt;For the Expert:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;There is actually a debate as to whether or not adiabatic cooling is responsible for the chill of air upon being let out of a tire.  The argument for it is fairly straightforward.  The released air does work on the surrounding atmosphere as it leaves, lowering the energy of the gas.  If this is the primary effect, then the change in temperature is given above.  However, it is possible that we can consider this a free adiabatic expansion.  In a free adiabatic expansion (like a gas expanding into a vacuum), there is no work done, because gas is not acting 'against' anything.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;The other possibility is the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Joule%E2%80%93Thomson_effect"&gt;Joule-Thomson effect&lt;/a&gt;.  I don't claim to understand this effect very thoroughly, but it is another mechanism for cooling when air is let out of a well insulated valve.  I've seen claims both ways as to which process is actually responsible for cooling.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;div&gt;&lt;span class="Apple-style-span" style="font-family: Georgia, 'Times New Roman', serif;"&gt;Fortunately, a simple experiment suggests itself.  Helium heats up through the Joule-Thomson effect (when it starts abot ~50K).  It will cool down through the above described adiabatic cooling.  So, fill a bike tire with Helium gas, and let it out.  See if the valve/gas feels hot or cold.  This will determine the dominant effect.  As an experimentalist, this &lt;a href="http://www.brightlywound.com/?comic=42"&gt;appeals greatly to me&lt;/a&gt;.  But if any theorists out there have ideas, please speak up.&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/div&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 03 May 2010 23:21:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-03:posts/letting-air-out-of-tires.html</guid><category>bike</category><category>tire</category><category>thermodynamics</category><category>gas</category><category>cold</category><category>experiment</category></item></channel></rss>