<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/tag.daylight-savings-time.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2012-03-12T00:57:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>F-91 Revisited</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/f-91-revisited.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-12T00:57:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-03-12:posts/f-91-revisited.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-05FSvjIalzs/T11JuY0apyI/AAAAAAAAAVI/hHndDNPO5CE/s1600/dst_sam.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-05FSvjIalzs/T11JuY0apyI/AAAAAAAAAVI/hHndDNPO5CE/s400/dst_sam.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Farmer Uncle Sam&amp;#8230;with a rifle. (Image Credit:&amp;nbsp;Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was a sunny exception to the grey overcast rule of weather in
Ithaca. I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be overjoyed by this anomaly, spending the day
outside flying a kite or playing frisbee with a border collie in a
bandanna. Unfortunately, today was also the beginning of Daylight
Savings Time (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DST&lt;/span&gt;) - my least favorite day of the year. For my
colleagues unfamiliar with this temporal travesty (I&amp;#8217;m looking at you
Arizona), let me briefly explain &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DST&lt;/span&gt;. Once a year, the time lords steal
a single hour from us and place it in an escrow account for future
disbursement, presumably in some elaborate scheme to gain the favor of
hat-throwing farmer-clock hybrids (see image left). The details are a
bit murky, but the net result is that today I had one less hour to do my
very favorite thing in the whole wide world - sleep. It also means that
I have to set my watch, so I figured I&amp;#8217;d check in and see how well my
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2012/02/time-keeps-on-slippin.html"&gt;previous
model&lt;/a&gt;
for time-loss in my watch has held up. About a month ago, I looked at
how my watch slowly deviated from the &lt;a href="http://nist.time.gov/timezone.cgi?Eastern/d/-5/java"&gt;official
time&lt;/a&gt; (the original
post can be found
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2012/02/time-keeps-on-slippin.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
and a helpful clarification by Tom can be found
&lt;a href="http://blogs.scienceforums.net/swansont/archives/11014"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Based
on a little over 50 days worth of data, I found that my watch lost about
0.35 seconds per day against the official time. About 50 days have
passed since my last measurement and today when I set the watch, so I
thought it would be interesting to see how well my model fit the new
data. The old data are presented in Figure 1 in blue, the old best fit
line is in red, and the new data point (taken this morning) is in green.
As always, click through the plot for a larger&amp;nbsp;version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HqpuhvxXl8M/T1115Tz6lnI/AAAAAAAAAVQ/I1AUjQLXres/s1600/dst_update_long.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HqpuhvxXl8M/T1115Tz6lnI/AAAAAAAAAVQ/I1AUjQLXres/s400/dst_update_long.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new data point appears to be in fair agreement with the old best-fit
model, but it&amp;#8217;s a little hard to see here. Zooming in a bit, though, we
see that the model lies outside the error bar of the new data&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1euutOYSIrs/T1125Hi_XNI/AAAAAAAAAVY/tnWZ6N3mJJs/s1600/dst_update_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1euutOYSIrs/T1125Hi_XNI/AAAAAAAAAVY/tnWZ6N3mJJs/s400/dst_update_short.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is this a big deal? Not really. But if it will help you sleep at
night, we can redo the fitting with the new data point included to see
how much things change. The the plots with the updated model to include
all data points are provided below with the old data in blue and the new
point in&amp;nbsp;green.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-oIeLFmzJgKI/T115TGf3laI/AAAAAAAAAVg/RHPJuP9UrKk/s1600/dst_newfit_long.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-oIeLFmzJgKI/T115TGf3laI/AAAAAAAAAVg/RHPJuP9UrKk/s400/dst_newfit_long.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new model looks a whole lot like the old one, except the best fit
line now appears to go through the new data point. Zooming in a little,
we see that it does indeed fall within the error bars of our new&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-EUf50O2-jjQ/T11514CpS_I/AAAAAAAAAVo/Ryt2v1LOeVk/s1600/dst_newfit_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-EUf50O2-jjQ/T11514CpS_I/AAAAAAAAAVo/Ryt2v1LOeVk/s400/dst_newfit_short.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so the new model fits with our new point, but how much did the
model have to change? Well, the fit to just the old data gave an offset
of 0.36 seconds and a loss rate of 0.35 seconds per day. The new model
has an offset of 0.40 seconds and a loss rate of 0.348 seconds per day.
Overall, not a significant change.
It looks as though I may continue to not worry about the accuracy of my
watch. I have set it to match the official time and have no intention of
fiddling with it until I have to set it again at the end of Daylight
Savings Time - my favorite day of the&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="daylight savings time"></category><category term="casio"></category></entry></feed>