<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.long-day.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2010-06-17T13:53:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Life as an Experimenter - Day One</title><link href="/posts/life-as-an-experimenter-day-one.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-06-17T13:53:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:,2010-06-17:posts/life-as-an-experimenter-day-one.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m an experimental physicist.  If you think this sounds like a job second in glamour only to rock star you would be right.  Just like being a rock star, you have to deal with the people, the shows, the lights, the groupies &amp;#8230; okay, maybe I&amp;#8217;m lying about the groupies.  Unless you&amp;#8217;re &lt;a href="http://groups.myspace.com/index.cfm?fuseaction=groups.groupprofile&amp;amp;groupID=103575126"&gt;Brian Greene&lt;/a&gt;.  Also similar to a rock star, no one really knows what it is we do behind the scenes (when we&amp;#8217;re not touring the nation or publishing papers).  I&amp;#8217;d like to pull back that curtain a little&amp;nbsp;bit.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;A bit of background.  For this data run we&amp;#8217;re looking at the structure of protein crystals.  The basic idea is that if you have a bunch of proteins, you can create a crystal out of them using various synthesis techniques.  If they&amp;#8217;re formed right, they look similar to the crystals you are more familiar with, quartz, diamond, emerald, etc.  We&amp;#8217;re interested in how the proteins are held in the crystal, that is, what kind of structure the protein crystal has.  I&amp;#8217;ll talk more about this at some other point.  Our method for examining this is using x rays.  Similar to a medical x-ray, we shoot x-rays at our sample, and look at the transmitted images.  Of course, instead of something like this:
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TBpWZFChfhI/AAAAAAAAABs/Cp-4Rf5ca5Y/s1600/X-ray-hands.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="228" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TBpWZFChfhI/AAAAAAAAABs/Cp-4Rf5ca5Y/s320/X-ray-hands.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;we see something like this:
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TBpWqG2OqLI/AAAAAAAAAB0/SncRJvsz1Uk/s1600/20071104200851!X-ray_diffraction_pattern_3clpro.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TBpWqG2OqLI/AAAAAAAAAB0/SncRJvsz1Uk/s320/20071104200851!X-ray_diffraction_pattern_3clpro.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;which is a little bit harder to interpret.  Nevertheless, we&amp;#8217;ve got some pretty nifty software that will do the job for us.  The unfortunate part about using x-rays is that to produce research grade x-rays takes really big expensive facilities, so we have a limited amount of time we get to use them for.  Right now, we&amp;#8217;ve got 48 hours of beam time, so we want to take data for as many of those 48 hours as possible.  For those interested, we&amp;#8217;re using &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHESS&lt;/span&gt; at Cornell, station&amp;nbsp;F1.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Wednesday, 6/16
&lt;b&gt;9:30am &lt;/b&gt;- Get up.  I was warned by the postdoc in my group to sleep in as much as I could.  Our data run starts at noon, and goes for 48 hours.  Who knows how much sleep we&amp;#8217;ll get in those 48 hours.  Our beam time starts at noon today.  I eat breakfast, and realize that I&amp;#8217;ve left my lab notebook in the lab.  I need to swing by there and pick it&amp;nbsp;up.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10:52&lt;/b&gt; - Out of the house.  My goal is to be at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHESS&lt;/span&gt; by 11.  As this is my first time using the facility,  I need to get a safety tour before I can use the beam line.  I hope on my bike and speed towards to the physics&amp;nbsp;building.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10:54&lt;/b&gt; - Downpour.  I get soaked.  I&amp;#8217;m wearing a rain jacket, but my jeans and shoes are soaked&amp;nbsp;through.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;10:55 &lt;/b&gt;- A pocket on my backpack comes unzipped, dumping my water bottle (and, as I find out later, my bike lock) into the road.  I stop and retrieve the water&amp;nbsp;bottle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:02&lt;/b&gt; - Arrive at physics building.  Hasten to the lab, dripping water.  Grab notebook.  Receive call from Ryan, another graduate student in the lab, saying he&amp;#8217;s at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHESS&lt;/span&gt;, and ready to take the safety tour when I&amp;nbsp;am.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:12 &lt;/b&gt; - Arrive at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHESS&lt;/span&gt;.  Realize I don&amp;#8217;t have my bike lock anymore.  Call Ryan and tell him to take the tour without me, I&amp;#8217;ll get to it later.  Hop on bike, ride route in reverse.  Find lock right where water bottle fell&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:25&lt;/b&gt; - Back at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHESS&lt;/span&gt;.  Check in.  Get given safety tour, radiation badge.  Meet up with Ryan.  Good&amp;nbsp;times.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:59&lt;/b&gt; - Matt, the postdoc in my lab, with experience at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHESS&lt;/span&gt; and the samples and equipment,&amp;nbsp;arrives.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;12:00pm&lt;/b&gt; - Beam time starts.  We&amp;#8217;re not ready.  For this run, we&amp;#8217;re using liquid helium to cool our sample.  We have to get that set up&amp;nbsp;first.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;1:45&lt;/b&gt; - With the aid of Ulrich, one of the Research Associates at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHESS&lt;/span&gt;, we have the liquid helium stream set up to cool our&amp;nbsp;sample.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:00 &lt;/b&gt;- Matt trains Ryan and myself how to mount samples for the&amp;nbsp;beam.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:15&lt;/b&gt; - Matt mounts a sample, and trains Ryan and myself how to operate beam&amp;nbsp;controls.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:30 &lt;/b&gt;- Start taking&amp;nbsp;data.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;2:45 &lt;/b&gt;- Crystal turns out to be not very crystalline.  Rinse and&amp;nbsp;repeat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4:00&lt;/b&gt; - After 7 increasingly frustrating attempts with bad crystals, the 8th turns out to give us a good signal.  Looks like we&amp;#8217;re back in&amp;nbsp;business.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4:15&lt;/b&gt; - Getting anomalous signals from our sample.  Every 5th image has about have the intensity of the others.  Also getting some weird tiling in the image.  No one knows what&amp;#8217;s going on.  We call in Ulrich and the beam&amp;nbsp;operator.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4:30 &lt;/b&gt;- In the midst of trying to resolve the anomalous signals, the computer we&amp;#8217;re running the experimental control software on goes down.  Requires calling in more tech&amp;nbsp;support.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;4:50 &lt;/b&gt;- I take a break to eat.  First food since breakfast.  Two sandwiches and a half-frozen banana (kept it near the back of the fridge in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CHESS&lt;/span&gt; lounge.  I learned my&amp;nbsp;lesson).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;5:10&lt;/b&gt; - Food eaten.  Computer back up.  Data taking ready.  Still no resolution for the anomalous signal.  While the experts continue to trouble shoot, Matt attempts to figure out if we can run any of our experiments with the data as bad as it currently&amp;nbsp;is.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;5:45&lt;/b&gt; - Still no solution.  Matt has determined that none of our planned experiments will work with the data as bad as it is.  Suspicion of a bad detector (a million dollar piece of equipment).  Morale is&amp;nbsp;low.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;8:00&lt;/b&gt; - After continued trouble shooting, Ulrich is convinced that the problem is a bad shutter for the x ray beam (just like a camera, you achieve a certain image exposure by letting the beam hit the sample/detector for a certain amount of&amp;nbsp;time).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;8:30&lt;/b&gt; - Technician arrives to swap shutters.  Operation successful!  Data looks&amp;nbsp;good.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;9:00&lt;/b&gt; - After some test runs, we start taking real data.  Morale is&amp;nbsp;high.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:15&lt;/b&gt; - Data coming in with no sign of stopping.  Ryan and I head home.  Matt has the night shift, we&amp;#8217;re to relieve him at 8 the next&amp;nbsp;morning.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:20 &lt;/b&gt;- Discover that my bike has somehow broken while sitting on the bike rack.  The collar that keeps the handlebars in the frame is loose, and the handlebars no longer connect with the front wheel.  Bike is&amp;nbsp;unrideable.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:25&lt;/b&gt; - Decide bike is unfixable with current tools.  I have to walk it&amp;nbsp;home.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:40&lt;/b&gt; - Home.  Attempt to fix bike. Discover none of my wrenches are quite large&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;11:45 &lt;/b&gt;- Food.  Microwave leftovers.  Discover one of my housemates has left fresh chocolate chip cookies on the counter for the rest of the house.  Bless her a thousand times over and eat&amp;nbsp;two.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;
&lt;/b&gt;
Thursday 6/17
&lt;b&gt;12:15am&lt;/b&gt; - Set alarm for 7:15am, and hop into&amp;nbsp;bed.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="CHESS"></category><category term="long day"></category><category term="experiment"></category></entry></feed>