<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.recoil.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2010-04-22T14:26:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>End of the Earth II - Blaze of Glory</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/end-of-the-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-22T14:26:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-22:posts/end-of-the-earth-ii-blaze-of-glory.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S9CFFAkGooI/AAAAAAAAABM/2SpaTtw4ivI/s1600/Marvin_the_Martian.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S9CFFAkGooI/AAAAAAAAABM/2SpaTtw4ivI/s200/Marvin_the_Martian.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In honor of earth day today, many bloggers are posting things about how
to save the earth, or retrospectives on earth days past. We here at The
Virtuosi decided, what better way to celebrate the earth than to figure
out how to destroy it? So that is exactly what we intend to do. This
post will focus on the destruction of the earth by a laser beam. This is
a familiar concept. Whether it is Marvin the Martian or the Death Star,
destroying planets with lasers (or threatening to) is a common theme. We
will be considering two questions today. The first is fairly obvious:
how much power would the death star need to destroy the earth? The
second relates to a topic of continuing interest of mine: how much would
the death star recoil upon firing? First, the power we would need. Most
estimates of the death star&amp;#8217;s power seem to rely on simply overcoming
the gravitational binding energy of the earth. We&amp;#8217;re going to assume the
earth is a uniform density. We can easily calculate the gravitational
binding energy to be &lt;mathjax&gt;$$U_G=\frac{3GM_{earth}^2}{5R_{earth}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$U=2.3\cdot 10^{32} J$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; However, looking at the video of the death
star blast, it looks like the earth was more than just gravitationally
unbound. It looks like we&amp;#8217;ve actually managed to atomize some of the
constituent molecules. Let us assume that about half of the earth gets
atomized. We&amp;#8217;re also going to assume that the earth is made entirely of
iron (not &lt;em&gt;too&lt;/em&gt; bad an assumption). In a lattice, iron will have \~6
bonds, and the energy of each bond will be on the order of \~2 eV. We
can calculate the number of iron atoms, N, needed to give the mass of
the earth by: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$N=\frac{M_{earth}}{m_{iron}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$N=3\cdot 10^{50}
atoms$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; We assume half of these have all of their bonds broken, this
gives an energy required to break the bonds of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$E \approx
3N(2eV)=2.88\cdot 10^{32} J$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; This gives us a total destruction energy
of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$E_{tot}=5.2\cdot 10^{32} J$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Analyzing the video of the firing
of the first death star tells us that the laser fired for about 4s, so
this is a power of 1.3&lt;em&gt;10^32 W! As an aside, that much energy is about
the total energy output of the sun over a day. That means the impulse
this laser delivered (momentum per second, or force) to the death star
must be the power over c, the speed of light (see my &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/today-id-like-to-approach-question-near.html"&gt;earlier
post&lt;/a&gt;
for a discussion of laser gun recoil). This is a force of 4.3&lt;/em&gt;10^23 N.
We now need to estimate the death star mass. According to &lt;a href="http://starwars.wikia.com/wiki/Death_Star"&gt;confidential
sources&lt;/a&gt; the death star had a
diameter of 150 km. The death star is made of metal, but it also has a
lot of empty space inside of it. We&amp;#8217;ll go ahead and assume it has the
density of water. This gives is a mass of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$M_{ds}=\tfrac{4}{3}\pi
r^3\rho=2.4\cdot 10^{13} kg$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; A quick glance at our numbers reveals
that we&amp;#8217;re going to need special relativity here! Otherwise we&amp;#8217;d be
accelerating this thing well past the speed of light. We have a total
momentum change of 1.7&lt;em&gt;10^{24}kg&lt;/em&gt;m/s. This is a relativistic
momentum, which we can solve for v. The algebra is a tiny bit ugly, but
it turns out that velocity in terms of relativistic momentum is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$v=\sqrt{\frac{p^2}{m^2+p^2/c^2}} \approx c $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; It turns out that
the death star would be moving so close to speed of light as to not
matter. That&amp;#8217;s fast! I think we can safely say that this laser recoil
would be&amp;nbsp;noticed!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="star wars"></category><category term="recoil"></category><category term="marvin the martian"></category><category term="lasers"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category></entry><entry><title>Laser Gun Recoil: Follow-up</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/laser-gun-recoil-follow-up.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-21T16:31:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-21:posts/laser-gun-recoil-follow-up.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Matt Springer over at &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/builtonfacts/"&gt;Built on
Fact&lt;/a&gt;s has a &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/builtonfacts/2010/04/laser_rifle_recoil.php"&gt;very nice
post&lt;/a&gt;
following up on my earlier analysis of &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/today-id-like-to-approach-question-near.html"&gt;whether or not a laser gun would
recoil&lt;/a&gt;.
In my analysis I came to the conclusion that the momentum delivered was
much less than that of a conventional gun, but that the impulse, and
hence the force delivered, was about the same. However, that force was
delivered over a \~30ns timescale, which left open the question of
whether or not the wielder would be able to feel that recoil. While I
had thought to possibly return to this issue at some point, Matt has
beat me to it. This is fortuitous, because I wasn&amp;#8217;t sure quite where to
start with the question, while he approaches it in a very sensible,
clear manner. The gist of his post is that he compares our response to
short time scale forces to our ability to sense sound. I won&amp;#8217;t go
through his calculations, you can check those out for yourself, but he
concludes that it is very unlikely that we could feel the recoil of our
laser gun. Case closed. Though, like any good scientist, we may choose
to reopen it later if more evidence comes to&amp;nbsp;light.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="recoil"></category><category term="laser"></category><category term="sound"></category><category term="momentum"></category><category term="gun"></category></entry><entry><title>Would a laser gun recoil?</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/would-a-laser-gun-recoil-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-08T23:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Jesse</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-08:posts/would-a-laser-gun-recoil-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#8217;d like to approach a question near and dear to many a geek
heart: do laser guns have recoil?
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S76cWh0vVrI/AAAAAAAAAA8/3AVsx5suF0A/s1600/19990814dogfight.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S76cWh0vVrI/AAAAAAAAAA8/3AVsx5suF0A/s200/19990814dogfight.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Let&amp;#8217;s motivate our question a little bit. I&amp;#8217;ve wondered about this
question since I saw star wars. Though I&amp;#8217;m no firearms expert, the
recoil in guns must come from conservation of momentum principles.
Momentum is conserved in a system. The gun starts with zero momentum. We
fire, give the bullet momentum, and so to keep the system at zero
momentum, the gun must gain equal and opposite momentum. That is, the
gun will move backwards. All of that was for conventional guns. Light
carries momentum, so if we fire a pulse of light, we expect our laser
gun to recoil. So yes, they do have recoil. Satisfied, dear readers?
Neither am I. The question we really mean to ask is, does a laser gun
have noticeable recoil? We need to make a few reasonable assumptions.
Let&amp;#8217;s assume that the laser gun fires a pulse with as much energy as a
bullet has kinetic energy, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KE&lt;/span&gt;. The energy, E, of light is related to its
momentum, p, by E=pc, where c is the speed of light. This gives a
momentum of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E=KE=pc $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ p=\frac{KE}{c}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; What is the kinetic
energy of a bullet? A little searching reveals that a .22 bullet is
\~2.5g and fires with a muzzle velocity of \~330m/s. Kinetic energy is
given by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KE&lt;/span&gt;=1/2mv^2, where m is mass and v velocity. So, the momentum
of a laser pulse with equal energy would be &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ p=\frac{mv^2}{2c} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
p=\frac{.0025kg*(330m/s)^2}{2*3\cdot 10^8m/s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
p=4.5\cdot10^{-7}kg \cdot m/s $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; For comparison, the momentum (p=mv)
of a .22 bullet is .83 kg&lt;em&gt;m/s. The momentum of a laser gun is 2 million
times less than the momentum of a .22. But is momentum all we should
consider? I suspect the &amp;#8216;kick&amp;#8217; we feel on the recoil is directly related
to the force that the gun exerts on the holder. This means that instead
of momentum we need to consider impulse, momentum per time. We estimate
the time it takes to fire a .22 is \~.1s, so the force delivered 8.3 N.
Let&amp;#8217;s estimate the time it takes a laser gun to fire. Unfortunately, not
having a laser gun to fire (feel free to send me one, dear readers),
we&amp;#8217;re more or less going to have to guess at the firing time. Most
movies with laser guns show pulses of light (which, incidentally would
move so fast we wouldn&amp;#8217;t see them) on the order of a meter or two long.
Given the speed of light, this would give a firing time of \~30
nanoseconds. This would give a force delivered of 15 N. This is close to
what we estimated or a .22. So, if movies are to be believed (and
really, why wouldn&amp;#8217;t we believe them?), it seems like laser guns may
well have recoil. &lt;/em&gt;Note: It is worth questioning if we need the same
energy for a laser as for a bullet. That could certainly change our
estimate. Maybe we&amp;#8217;ll return to this question&amp;nbsp;again.*&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="recoil"></category><category term="laser"></category><category term="momentum"></category></entry></feed>