<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.pineapple.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2012-03-14T08:35:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Moving Pi-ctures</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/moving-pi-ctures.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T08:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-03-14:posts/moving-pi-ctures.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-YJBJw29pxZk/T1ribOQLS-I/AAAAAAAAAVA/xsJ-KAOJt5w/s1600/tv_pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-YJBJw29pxZk/T1ribOQLS-I/AAAAAAAAAVA/xsJ-KAOJt5w/s320/tv_pi.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  My &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; celebrates without&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, as I&amp;#8217;m sure you&amp;#8217;re aware, is Pi Day - a day for the festive
consumption of pies and quiet self-reflection. In the spirit of the
holiday, I&amp;#8217;d like to present a point for discussion: &lt;em&gt;Everyone has a
great talent for at least one thing.&lt;/em&gt; That this is true for at least
&lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; people is seen through even a cursory glance at a history book:
George Washington was really good at leading revolutions, Michelangelo
was an outstanding ceiling painter &lt;a href="#note1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, and Batman was the
best at solving complex riddles (especially in English, pero
&lt;em&gt;especialmente&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RY1U_pXUxUo&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;en
español&lt;/a&gt;).
But I&amp;#8217;m certain that this holds for everyone. What&amp;#8217;s your talent? Mine,
as those of you who read this blog should know very well by now, is
certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; doing physics. Nope, my talent is watching &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt;. Seriously
guys, I watch &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; like a boss &lt;a href="#note2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. In light of this talent, I
thought I would describe a few instances in which I have seen pi
represented (for better or for worse) in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; and movies. Over the last
few months, I have been re-watching a lot of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; show
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psych"&gt;Psych&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; with my good friend and
fellow Virtuosi contributor, Matt &amp;#8220;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TT&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; Showbiz &lt;a href="#note3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. For the
uninitiated, &lt;em&gt;Psych&lt;/em&gt; is a detective show where the main characters
(Shawn and Gus) run a (fake) psychic detective agency, which allows them
to solve mysteries, engage in various shenanigans, and make an
inordinate number of references to &lt;em&gt;Tears for Fears&lt;/em&gt; frontman Curt Smith
&lt;a href="#note4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. In one of the episodes, Shawn and Gus enter a room where
a long train of digits is written across the top of the wall. It soon
becomes evident that these are the digits of pi and the camera is sure
to zoom in on the famous first few digits to reassure us. But there are
hundreds of digits written out and I have very little faith in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; prop
people when it comes to background mathematical expressions. So I
decided to check it&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sIqwUS9wlog/T17KQ7mU7nI/AAAAAAAAAV4/1hiiMuN-yxA/s1600/pi_psych1.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sIqwUS9wlog/T17KQ7mU7nI/AAAAAAAAAV4/1hiiMuN-yxA/s400/pi_psych1.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Pi on the Wall (click to enhance for&amp;nbsp;texture)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a neat little pi &lt;a href="http://www.angio.net/pi/piquery"&gt;searcher&lt;/a&gt;, I
checked to see if (and where) this sequence appeared in pi. Turns out
it&amp;#8217;s legit and (almost!) correct. The first 105 digits of pi (counting
after the three)&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.14159265358979323846264338327950288419716939937510582097494459230781640628620899862803482534211706&lt;strong&gt;798&lt;/strong&gt;2148&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where I have underlined the 99th, 100th, and 101st digits. Looking back
at the writing on the wall, we see that the 100th digit has been&amp;nbsp;duplicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6vQ2gmfNULw/T17Nb29jAvI/AAAAAAAAAWA/2hMW9vdU3S0/s1600/pi_psych.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6vQ2gmfNULw/T17Nb29jAvI/AAAAAAAAAWA/2hMW9vdU3S0/s400/pi_psych.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Very Almost&amp;nbsp;Pi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So close! Oh well, nobody is perfect. Even though there is an error
here, I very much appreciate that whoever was doing the set design
decided to use the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; digits of pi. All too often I see
nonsensical equations in the background of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; shows and movies when it
would take &lt;em&gt;exactly the same&lt;/em&gt; amount of work to put real equations
there. So congratulations to you, O nameless prop-making intern!, for
giving an accurate (well, to a part in 10^100) value of pi. Neat, so
are there any other &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; shows or movies that have pi in them? Well,
there&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jo18VIoR2xU"&gt;Pi&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt; is film
by Darren Aronofsky (&lt;em&gt;Requiem for a Dream&lt;/em&gt;, etc) about a mathematician
looking for patterns in the stock market. It&amp;#8217;s a pretty good movie with
a really cool
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Cq_QO_4Cx4&amp;amp;feature=player_embedded"&gt;soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;
by Clint Mansell. It also appears to display the digits of pi in the
opening credits. But does it? To the Youtube-mobile! You can watch the
opening credits &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L61x5mbE-jc"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if
you like and here is a still image of the relevant&amp;nbsp;section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pEbkgRx-PFw/T17UHYdfhwI/AAAAAAAAAWI/vsyzWd139pg/s1600/sad_pi.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pEbkgRx-PFw/T17UHYdfhwI/AAAAAAAAAWI/vsyzWd139pg/s400/sad_pi.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;Pi?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks pretty cool, huh? But once we get past the slick aesthetics, we
see that something doesn&amp;#8217;t seem right. This number they are showing
appears at first glance to be our good friend pi, but after the 8th
digit the cover is blown and we see that this is actually some impostor&amp;nbsp;number!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-5afmhwZOhWk/T17U-d1okrI/AAAAAAAAAWQ/KB7NHwwOvQg/s1600/verysadpi.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-5afmhwZOhWk/T17U-d1okrI/AAAAAAAAAWQ/KB7NHwwOvQg/s400/verysadpi.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  More like Darren&amp;nbsp;Aron-wrong-sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I fully understand that this has no bearing whatsoever on the film
and, in the grand scheme of things, is not a Big Deal. But it would have
been just as easy to put the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; digits of pi here instead of just
random filler. The only way that this could possibly be better than the
real deal would be if it is actually a secret code. I have not yet ruled
this out, as the movie is entirely about looking for meaning in
seemingly random numbers. Unfortunately, the difficulty in transcribing
the numbers from the screen greatly outweighs the very small chance that
this isn&amp;#8217;t just gibberish. Four hundred Quatloos to anyone who can tell
me if this is a code or&amp;nbsp;not!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] And an above average Ninja Turtle to boot. &lt;a href="#back1"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Yes, I am putting my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; watching skills on par with the talents of
George Washington. In fact, the stoic way in which I persevered through
the entirety of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terminator:_The_Sarah_Connor_Chronicles"&gt;The Sarah Connor
Chronicles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;in
under two weeks was described by historian David McCullough as
&amp;#8220;Washingtonian.&amp;#8221; These are simply facts. &lt;a href="#back2"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] The extra &amp;#8220;T&amp;#8221; is for extra talent. &lt;a href="#back3"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] A duo can &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; have a frontman. For evidence, feel free to
ask the not-George-Michael-guy from &lt;em&gt;Wham!&lt;/em&gt; or the not-Paul-Simon-guy
from &lt;em&gt;Simon &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Garfunkel&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href="#back4"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pineapple"></category><category term="pi day"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry></feed>