<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.free-data-sets.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 16:44:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Free data set of the month: Imaging Spectroscopy</title><link>/posts/free-data-set-of-the-month-imaging-spectroscopy.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s a lot of free data sets floating around the internet, and while
things like funny cat videos and the &lt;a href="http://blog.xkcd.com/2010/05/03/color-survey-results/"&gt;results of color-naming
surveys&lt;/a&gt; get a
lot of play, many others don&amp;#8217;t get used for much. Recently I&amp;#8217;ve been
playing around with one such data set: images from the &lt;a href="http://aviris.jpl.nasa.gov/"&gt;Airborne
Visible/Infrared Imaging Spectrometer
(&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AVIRIS&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ve always found it interesting that the way we perceive color is very
different from how light actually works. Most of us have three different
types of cones in our eyes and we perceive different colors as different
combinations of stimuli to these three types of cones. In a very rough
sense, when we look at a color, our brain gets three different numbers
to figure out what it is. Light, on the other hand, is a bunch of
photons with some distribution of wavelengths. To fully describe the
light coming from an object you need a function that shows how many
photons are at any given wavelength, which is way more complicated than
just the three numbers we&amp;nbsp;get.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what about all that information that gets thrown away on the way to
our brain? Are we missing out on a magical world of super-duper colors
and wonder? Not really, but skip past the break anyways to find out&amp;nbsp;more.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There are a few things our eyes have a hard time distinguishing. For
example, take a look at this picture of a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sodium-vapor_lamp#Low_pressure_sodium"&gt;low-pressure sodium
lamp&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:LPS_Lamp_35W_running.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx02kW16bI/AAAAAAAABI0/vonaPzNiAag/s320/LPS_Lamp_35W_running.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you&amp;#8217;ve ever been in a sketchy parking lot at night or an intro
physics class you&amp;#8217;ve probably seen one of these in real life. It looks
just like the picture right? It does to us, but the light coming from
the picture and the light from the real lamp are totally different. All
the photons from the real lamp have wavelengths very close to 589
nanometers, while the ones coming from the picture on your screen have a
bunch of different wavelengths ranging from 500 to 700 nanometers,
depending on what type of monitor you have. (It&amp;#8217;s easy to &lt;a href="http://www.cs.cmu.edu/%7Ezhuxj/astro/html/spectrometer.html"&gt;build your
own
spectrometer&lt;/a&gt;
and see this for&amp;nbsp;yourself.)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?gl=us&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;ll=37.432068,-122.017937&amp;amp;spn=0.196834,0.308647&amp;amp;t=h&amp;amp;z=12"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx1kWr0ZpI/AAAAAAAABI8/K7RQ-Qzxa50/s400/Moffett%2BField%2BCrop.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;This
is an extreme example since there are few objects that emit purely
monochromatic light. What do normal objects look like spectroscopically?
I wanted to find out, but unfortunately there&amp;#8217;s not too many
freely-available spectroscopic images of everyday objects floating
around the internet, and my attempts to make my own were stymied by the
fact that no one wanted to let me borrow $20,000 worth of optical
bandpass filters. However, there are a several orbital satellites and
planes which take spectroscopic images of the earth, and one of them,
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AVIRIS&lt;/span&gt;, has a few sample data sets for people to play around with. I
recently wrote some code to help me look at one data set in particular –
a spectroscopic image of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Moffett_Federal_Airfield"&gt;Moffett Federal
Airfield&lt;/a&gt; in
California, shown here in a normal picture from Google&amp;nbsp;Earth.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AVIRIS&lt;/span&gt; acts much like a normal camera, but instead of three wide-band
filters for distinguishing color it uses 225 narrow bands ranging from
366 nanometers (near &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UV&lt;/span&gt;) to 2500 nanometers (near &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IR&lt;/span&gt;). Any of these
bands can be thought of as a single monochromatic image. Here I have
plotted two bands side by side for comparison. The right image is at 463
nanometers (a nice blue color) and the other is at 2268 nanometers, well
into the infrared. (Both images are false-colored to enhance the&amp;nbsp;contrast).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx2M29FDwI/AAAAAAAABJE/lSUTxxI4ZFw/s1600/Img10and200withInsets.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx2M29FDwI/AAAAAAAABJE/lSUTxxI4ZFw/s400/Img10and200withInsets.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The scene looks a lot different at the two different wavelengths. In the
first image there&amp;#8217;s one area that&amp;#8217;s particularly bright – it is one of
several settling ponds belonging to a Morton Salt factory, although I
have no idea what is special about this one that makes it reflect blue
light so strongly. The second image highlights different features and
clearly shows the difference between the moving water in the creeks and
the standing water in the&amp;nbsp;bay.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;These are just two of the bands, but you can see all of them fly by in
the movie below. (Note that the color scale is set for each band
individually, which is why there sometimes seems to be a large change
between adjacent&amp;nbsp;bands).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you agree with me that the embedded video looks super-crappy you can
&lt;a href="http://gotfork.net/virtuosi/VariableGain.avi"&gt;download the original
here&lt;/a&gt; (6.4&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MB&lt;/span&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One of the things that struck me about this video is that it seems like
much of the image doesn&amp;#8217;t change too much through the whole visual
range. Not surprisingly, it&amp;#8217;s a lot easier for us to distinguish between
the slight differences in color in a normal image than it is for us to
distinguish between the slight changes of intensity&amp;nbsp;here.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So what do the spectra of individual points in the image look like?
Let&amp;#8217;s focus on a few easily-identifiable objects. (I&amp;#8217;ll talk about how I
made the roughly-true color image below in a later&amp;nbsp;post).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx7dCumIAI/AAAAAAAABJk/9b8gXeMkqg4/s1600/FiveLocMapCombo.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_f2jEPVoC9C4/TUx7dCumIAI/AAAAAAAABJk/9b8gXeMkqg4/s400/FiveLocMapCombo.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing that stands out is that there&amp;#8217;s a lot of features that
are common to all of the locations, such as the big gap near 1750
nanometers. While the sun sends photons with a distribution of
wavelengths roughly described by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Planck%27s_law"&gt;Planck&amp;#8217;s
Law&lt;/a&gt;, certain wavelengths
are strongly absorbed by gasses in the atmosphere as shown&amp;nbsp;below:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://commons.wikimedia.org/wiki/File:Solar_Spectrum.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://upload.wikimedia.org/wikipedia/commons/4/4c/Solar_Spectrum.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looking at the different spectra we can see that &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Electromagnetic_absorption_by_water"&gt;liquid water absorbs
strongly in the
infrared&lt;/a&gt;,
and the green grass on the golf course reflects strongly in the
near-infrared (no clue why). There is also a clear difference in
intensities for each of the locations in the visual range, but the five
locations otherwise look quite similar, even though they are very
different colors in real&amp;nbsp;life.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;ll look at a few more interesting things in this data set and talk a
bit about about how our eyes and brains process color in a later&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Alex</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 04 Feb 2011 16:44:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-02-04:posts/free-data-set-of-the-month-imaging-spectroscopy.html</guid><category>reflection</category><category>optics</category><category>how do i get free stuff?</category><category>free data sets</category><category>blackbody</category><category>spectra</category></item></channel></rss>