<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.analysis.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2010-08-11T14:04:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Teminal Velocity</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/teminal-velocity.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-08-11T14:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Yariv</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-08-11:posts/teminal-velocity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The impetus for this post lies with three facts. First, I like to bike to work. Second, Cornell sits on a &lt;a href="http://www.cornell.edu/search/index.cfm?tab=facts&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;id=272"&gt;hill&lt;/a&gt;. And finally, I&amp;#8217;m not very&amp;nbsp;brave.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result of all of these, along with Ithaca&amp;#8217;s less-than-optimal road maintenance, my semi-daily rides home tend to produce a lot of wear on my brakes as I cruise downhill at what appears to me to be very high speeds. I began to ponder just how high this speed really is, and if I could reduce my use of the brakes or if I&amp;#8217;m going to end up using them anyway at the bottom of the&amp;nbsp;hill.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;img alt="" border="0" id="BLOGGER_PHOTO_ID_5504225823691657218" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGLwOVisUAI/AAAAAAAACD4/V9TvWzmEv9k/s200/200px-Free_body.svg.png" style="cursor: pointer; display: block; height: 136px; margin: 0px auto 10px; text-align: center; width: 200px;" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;center&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 85%;"&gt;Figure 1: An inclined plane&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/center&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I asked myself, what do I remember about bikes going down the hill? Well, I remember the good old inclined plane (figure 1), and I remember that air resistance is proportional to velocity, so that the equation of motion is given by
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ma = mg\sin\theta - \alpha v. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I had no idea what &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;α&lt;/span&gt; was, though. My first stop in considering it was naturally Wikipedia. A quick &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terminal_velocity"&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; came up with the formula
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$m a = mg\sin\theta -  \frac{1}{2}\rho A C_d  v^2$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;ρ&lt;/span&gt; is the density of air, &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; the projected area of the body and &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;C&lt;sub&gt;d&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 100%;"&gt;&lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/span&gt; the drag&amp;nbsp;coefficient&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first thing to notice here is that I was wrong - drag in a fluid acts like the velocity squared, and not the velocity. Second, we can easily determine terminal velocity out of this formula - it&amp;#8217;s the speed at which the sum of the forces equals to zero, or
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$v_t = \sqrt{\frac{2mg\sin\theta}{\rho A C_d}}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can throw in some numbers into that. &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;ρ&lt;/span&gt; = 1.2 kg/m&lt;sup&gt;3&lt;/sup&gt; for air; Wikipedia estimates &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;C&lt;sub&gt;d&lt;/sub&gt;&lt;/span&gt; =  0.9 for a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drag_coefficient"&gt;cyclist&lt;/a&gt;. For the mass, we need to add up mine (~75 kg), the bike&amp;#8217;s (15-20 kg) and my bag&amp;#8217;s (let&amp;#8217;s say 5 kg). We come to about 100 kg, give or take 5%. &lt;span style="font-style: italic;"&gt;A&lt;/span&gt; is a little harder to estimate, but height times width gives me an initial guess of 0.62 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt;, which I&amp;#8217;ll revise to 0.7 m&lt;sup&gt;2&lt;/sup&gt; to account for the bike, flailing arms and fashionable helmet, up to about 10%&amp;nbsp;accuracy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re left with sinθ, which varies by road, but in general we expect the terminal velocity to look like
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$v_t \approx \left(50 \pm 3  \rm{m/s}\right) \sqrt{\sin\theta}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This appears not-unreasonable. For an 8% grade like we have down University avenue  this yields about 50  km/h and for a 13% grade like we have down Buffalo street this will bring us up to a respectable 65 &lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/post-edit.g?blogID=8807287158334608095&amp;amp;postID=6743488546064317383#miles" title="That's - sigh - about 30 mph and 40 mph, respectively, in crazy units"&gt;km/h&lt;/a&gt;. Both, incidentally, are faster than I&amp;#8217;m willing to go down a badly maintained, not entire straight&amp;nbsp;road.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we have some numbers, and I begin to feel justified about pressing those breaks often, but all of this is really an introduction for the next post, in which I go against all my theorist instincts and take some data in the field. Stay tuned.
&lt;span style="font-size: 78%;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="font-size: 78%;"&gt;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span style="font-size: 78%;"&gt;&lt;ol&gt;&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/post-edit.g?blogID=8807287158334608095&amp;amp;postID=6743488546064317383" name="miles"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;That&amp;#8217;s - sigh - about 30 mph and 40 mph, respectively, in crazy&amp;nbsp;units&lt;/li&gt;&lt;/ol&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span style="font-size: 78%;"&gt;
&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="analysis"></category><category term="guestimation"></category><category term="bike"></category><category term="wiki"></category><category term="equations"></category></entry><entry><title>Locating the Sun Photo</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/locating-the-sun-photo.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-14T02:21:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-14:posts/locating-the-sun-photo.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;This photo has been making the rounds on the internet lately:
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VQNEo7GUI/AAAAAAAAAJA/mHcIfKfPleM/s1600/pinholecamerajd09.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="342" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VQNEo7GUI/AAAAAAAAAJA/mHcIfKfPleM/s400/pinholecamerajd09.jpg" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Originally from &lt;a href="http://helpmyphysics.co.uk/wordpress/?p=276"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its a time lapse photo of the sun taken from a pinhole camera from June until December.  The real question is:  Where was this photo taken?
&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wandering&amp;nbsp;Sun&lt;/h3&gt;Well, first lets think a second about why the sun would wander in the sky.  As you may already know, the earth&amp;#8217;s pole is not aligned with our solar system&amp;#8217;s axis.  The earth&amp;#8217;s axis has what is called a 23.5 degree &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earth's_Axis"&gt;axial tilt&lt;/a&gt;, or&amp;nbsp;obliquity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, if you sit at a fixed latitude on the earth, then as the earth revolves around the sun and the year goes by, the angle the sun makes with the horizon&amp;nbsp;changes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to estimate how much the sun&amp;#8217;s angle in the sky changes.  Consider the following diagram
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VVHRzTrXI/AAAAAAAAAJI/zxe2OAcYSSw/s1600/diagram.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="87" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VVHRzTrXI/AAAAAAAAAJI/zxe2OAcYSSw/s400/diagram.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
You&amp;#8217;ll notice that the angle that the dashed line towards the sun makes with respect to the dotted horizon line, changes when the earth is on either side of the sun.  But how much does it&amp;nbsp;change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can estimate it by realizing that the angle of that triangle centered at the sun is very small.  Very small indeed.  We could estimate its size by:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \arctan \frac{R_{\text{Earth}}}{D_{\text{Earth-Sun}}} \approx 0.002^{\circ} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Very small.  So, knowing that the one angle is very tiny, and remembering that the sum of all of the angles in a triangle must add up to 180 degrees, we can calculate how much that angle in the sky&amp;nbsp;changes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that the angle between the line pointing to our latitude of interest and the equator has a known angle, namely the angle there is our latitude +/- 23.5 degrees.   So if that is the angle our observation point makes with the horizontal, by the reasoning above, the angle that the sun makes with respect to our observation point ought to be 180 - our latitude +/- 23.5 degrees. So on either side of the sun, the difference in this angle from summer to winter is just twice 23.5 degrees of 47&amp;nbsp;degrees. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, regardless of where you are on the earth, between when the sun is highest in the sky, and when it is lowest in the sky, there ought to be a 47 degree difference.  (Assuming of course you can see the sun year round, which you can&amp;#8217;t if you live too far&amp;nbsp;north).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great.  So we know that the difference between the height of the traces in the picture and the bottom needs to be 47 degrees.  But that still doesn&amp;#8217;t help us calculate the latitude the picture was taken&amp;nbsp;at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finding Latitude in&amp;nbsp;theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at our diagram again, we notice that when the sun is lowest in the sky, we can calculate directly what angle the sun should make with respect to the horizon (psi) (We already obtained the upper angle in our triangle, the last part is realizing that the angle to the horizon from the radial line is just 90 degrees).  We obtain
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \psi = \theta - 90^\circ  + 23.5^\circ = \theta + 66.5^\circ $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So, turning it on its head, we can calculate the latitude (theta) we are at if we know the lowest angle the sun makes in the sky
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \theta = 66.5^\circ - \psi $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finding Latitude in&amp;nbsp;Practice &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now I know two things.  The total angle difference between the upper most the sun gets and the lowest point in the sky is 47 degrees.  And I also know that if I know the angle between the horizon and the lowest point the sun gets in the sky, I can calculate the latitude.  So how am I going to do this, well, I just took the picture and opened it up in Gimp, and used the measure tool to get the difference between the highest and lowest points in the sky in pixels, and the distance to the horizon in pixels.  Here&amp;#8217;s one example of my guesses:
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VZsHEcTMI/AAAAAAAAAJQ/fOqIQq1776I/s1600/pinholecamerajdwithlines.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VZsHEcTMI/AAAAAAAAAJQ/fOqIQq1776I/s320/pinholecamerajdwithlines.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Getting the differences in height for the sun was relatively straight forward.  In order to get the distance to the horizon, I had to guess a little bit.  I just lined it up by eye to where I thought the horizon should be in the picture since its not&amp;nbsp;visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does this do me any good?  Well assuming the picture doesn&amp;#8217;t have too much distortion, since I know the one angle is 47 degrees, I can make a comparison between the pixel lengths.  Lets say in the picture above I call the length of the green line B, and the length of the yellow line S, then I can estimate
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{\psi}{S} = \frac{47^\circ}{B} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
which gives me a measure on psi.  Since I was doing this by eye, I repeated the measurement ten times independently for each, obtaining in the end
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ B = 356 \pm 2 \qquad S = 66 \pm 6 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I have a complete formula for my estimation of the latitude
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \theta = 66.5^\circ - 47^\circ \frac{S}{B} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allowed me to estimate the latitude at 58 +/- 1 degree latitude.  Naturally, I can&amp;#8217;t tell the difference between 58 degrees north or 58 degrees south.  To get a better idea of what this guess looks like, here I&amp;#8217;ve overlayed the possible locations in green
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VcAVzG7jI/AAAAAAAAAJY/3csC2nzT8OM/s1600/world1.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="356" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VcAVzG7jI/AAAAAAAAAJY/3csC2nzT8OM/s400/world1.jpg" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll notice that there isn&amp;#8217;t much life down at 58 degrees south of the equator.  So, I reckon the picture was taken in the northern&amp;nbsp;hemisphere.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surfing around on the webpage where the picture was found, you&amp;#8217;ll first notice that its taken from a co.uk site (Great Britain), and if you go to the homepage, Mr. Mallon has a weather widget which says Bellshill.  &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;gl=us&amp;amp;g=Bellshill&amp;amp;q=Bellshill,+UK+lattitude+longitude&amp;amp;btnG=Search+Maps"&gt;Google Maps&lt;/a&gt; tells me that Bellshill, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; is at about 56 degrees North.  I&amp;#8217;ve tried to put a green dot on the map above near where Bellshill actually is (its hard to&amp;nbsp;see).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not bad for a night&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="analysis"></category><category term="sun"></category><category term="fun"></category><category term="picture"></category><category term="lattitude"></category></entry></feed>