<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.batman.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2012 11:10:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Batman, Helicopters, and Center of Mass</title><link>/posts/batman-helicopters-and-center-of-mass.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://cdn.medialib.computerandvideogames.com/screens/screenshot_263713.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://cdn.medialib.computerandvideogames.com/screens/screenshot_263713.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
A couple weeks ago, I came home after a long day at work looking for a
break. I thought to myself, “What’s more fun than physics? Batman*.” I
sat down to play the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Arkham_City"&gt;latest Batman
videogame&lt;/a&gt;, in which Batman’s
current objective was to use his grappling hook to jump onto an enemy
helicopter to steal an electronic MacGuffin. As awesome as this was, it
occurred to me that something was very wrong about the way the
helicopter moved while Batman zipped through the air. &lt;a href="http://youtu.be/81qN-PHucqM?t=3m12s"&gt;See if you can
spot it too&lt;/a&gt;. (Watch for about 5
seconds after the video starts. Ignore the commentary. Note: The
grunting noises are the sounds that Batman makes if you shoot him with
bullets.) What occurred to me was this: If the helicopter’s rotors
provided enough lift to balance the force of gravity, wouldn’t Batman’s
sudden additional weight cause the helicopter to fall out of the sky?
Also, to get lifted up into the air, the helicopter must be pulling up
on Batman: shouldn’t Batman also be pulling down on the helicopter? By
how much should we expect to see the helicopter’s altitude change? To
address the first question, let&amp;#8217;s go to Newton&amp;#8217;s second law: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \\sum
\\vec{F} = m\\vec{a} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Let’s assume that the helicopter is hovering
stationary, minding its own business, when Batman jumps onto it. Let&amp;#8217;s
also assume the helicopter pilots are totally oblivious to Batman and
make no flight corrections after Batman jumps onto it. In order to
hover, the lift from the helicopter&amp;#8217;s rotors exactly matched the pull of
gravity. &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \\sum \\vec{F} = \\vec{F}\_{rotors} - \\vec{F}\_{gravity} =
0 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Batman&amp;#8217;s sudden additional weight would cause the helicopter to
start falling, as the forces would no longer balance: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \\sum \\vec{F}
= \\vec{F}\_{rotors} - \\vec{F}\_{gravity} - \\vec{F}\_{Batman} &amp;lt; 0 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So the helicopter does accelerate (and move) when Batman jumps onto it.
How much does it move? Let’s assume there are no crazy winds or other
external forces acting on the helicopter or Batman while Batman grapples
onto the helicopter. “No external forces” means that momentum of
helicopter + Batman does not change during Batman&amp;#8217;s flight. Let&amp;#8217;s make
things a little simpler and assume that neither Batman nor the
helicopter had any vertical momentum before Batman used his grappling
hook. (I can choose to approach this problem from a reference frame
where the center of mass is stationary. Choosing a frame where the
center of mass moves won&amp;#8217;t change the results, it will just make the
calculation more complicated.) Because the momentum of helicopter +
Batman does not change, then the center of mass does not move while
Batman zips through the air: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \\frac{d}{dt} y\_{COM} = \\frac{d}{dt}
\\frac{m\_{Bat} y\_{Bat} + m\_{Copter} y\_{Copter}}{m\_{Bat} +
m\_{Copter}} = \\frac{p}{m\_{Bat} + m\_{Copter}} = 0 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
The center of mass must remain stationary, so we can find how much the
helicopter&amp;#8217;s height changes by if Batman starts on the ground (y = 0)
and both end up at the same height with Batman hanging from the
helicopter: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ y\_{COM} = \\frac{m\_{Copter} y\_{Copter} + m\_{Bat}
(0)}{m\_{Bat} + m\_{Copter}} = \\frac{m\_{Copter} y\_{final} + m\_{Bat}
y\_{final}}{m\_{Bat} + m\_{Copter}} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \\Delta y = y\_{Copter} -
y\_{final} = \\frac{m\_{Bat}}{m\_{Bat} + m\_{Copter}} y\_{Copter}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Now, some numbers: The police helicopters in the game are pretty small,
probably about &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bell_206"&gt;1500 kg&lt;/a&gt;. Batman
is a big guy who works out and probably weighs around 100 kg (220 lb).
Plus, he’s wearing body armor (hence surviving when bullets hit him) and
a utility belt and all of those other Bat-gadgets, which probably adds
about 30 kg (\~30 lb for the gadgets, &lt;a href="http://www.nationaldefensemagazine.org/archive/2011/February/Pages/ManufacturersAnswerMilitary%E2%80%99sCalltoReduceBodyArmorWeight.aspx"&gt;\~30 lb for the
armor&lt;/a&gt;).
If Batman has to grapple onto a helicopter 30 meters above him, then the
helicopter should drop out of the air by about 2.4 m. This is greater
than the height of Batman himself, and would be noticeable if the
helicopter physics in the game were perfect. Of course, if the
helicopters appearing in the game were the giant army helicopters (they
do carry rockets, after all), their mass would be much larger
(\~5000-10000 kg) so the effect of Batman’s additional weight would be
much smaller. None of these considerations detracted from the fun I had
playing the game, but it did seem odd that the helicopters appeared to
be nailed to the sky instead of moving freely through the air. I’ll be
writing the game developers a strongly-worded letter directly. * The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DC&lt;/span&gt;
superhero, not the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Batman,_Turkey"&gt;city&lt;/a&gt;
or the
&lt;a href="http://www.newcritters.com/2007/01/23/the-batman-fish-otocinclus-batmani/"&gt;fish&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">DTC</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 26 Jun 2012 11:10:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2012-06-26:posts/batman-helicopters-and-center-of-mass.html</guid><category>Center of Mass</category><category>Batman</category></item><item><title>Lessons in Prohibition: One</title><link>/posts/lessons-in-prohibition-one.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;Holy lack of self control, Batman!&amp;#8221;
Cornell University Department of Physics-A P6510 Auxiliary Report
&lt;strong&gt;Introduction:&lt;/strong&gt;
I feel terrible. Batman made me feel terrible. Batman also cost me 20
bucks.
&lt;strong&gt;Theoretical Background:&lt;/strong&gt;
You see, it&amp;#8217;s pretty natural for humans to place the mind and body
within hypothetical constraints. &amp;#8220;What would it be like to be
deaf/blind? What if you didn&amp;#8217;t have an arm? What if you were forced to
watch reruns of Quantum Leap for 24 hours straight?&amp;#8221;. I guess this is in
some way a thinking-man&amp;#8217;s survival instinct. It&amp;#8217;s always prudent to be
prepared, even if just emotionally, and Scott Bakula can be kinda pushy.
We here at the Virtuosi believe in preparation. That&amp;#8217;s why we&amp;#8217;ve decided
to convert one of our own (me) into a guinea pig. It is our goal to
apply some actual constraints to a real mind (mine) and to observe the
results, thereby gleaning valuable insights into how humans (me) respond
to adverse conditions (psychological torture).
&lt;strong&gt;Experimental Procedure:&lt;/strong&gt;
This week we started small. My task was the simple omission of a single
word from my written and spoken vocabulary. The word should be innocuous
enough that I wouldn&amp;#8217;t usually say it, but common enough not to be
obscure. The word chosen was &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BATMAN&lt;/span&gt;. I was to expressly abstain from the
use of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BATMAN&lt;/span&gt;, else risk a monetary penalty (20 bucks), and if I were
successful after 1 week, I would gain a monetary reward (20 bucks). This
experiment (bet) began two days ago. I have obviously failed.
&lt;strong&gt;Data Tables:&lt;/strong&gt;
Data in this case, and always, will be presented with the utmost
objectivity (stream of consciousness).
&lt;strong&gt;Day one:&lt;/strong&gt;
Ha This is really easy Everybody keeps mentioning Shatfan** though I
don&amp;#8217;t even know what we&amp;#8217;re testing I do kinda wanna say it though 20
bucks Shatfan feels kinda dirty Whatever this is dumb I have homework
maybe I should just stop thinking about Shatfan Nah This is kinda fun I
don&amp;#8217;t wanna lose 20 bucks I liked Val Kilmer as Shatfan, I can&amp;#8217;t believe
Nic disagrees Catban Batmatt &lt;span class="caps"&gt;HA&lt;/span&gt; thought I lost it there &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOWP&lt;/span&gt; there are
so many alternatives Shut the hell up Corky [possessor of said $20] Oh
man everybody knows about this bet I might lose What if someone asks me
about fratcan in class?
&lt;strong&gt;Day two:&lt;/strong&gt;
I actually feel kinda gross thinking about Shatfan he&amp;#8217;s like in my mouth
please get him out this is all people talk about when I&amp;#8217;m around oh yeah
thanks for that this week will at least be comical hey this might offset
the 500 bucks I owe corky maybe I could just say it and not tell anybody
ah but no that&amp;#8217;s not science and this is very obviously science&lt;em&gt;manbat
tabnam batfarm man of bats shatbat&lt;/em&gt; oh hey dad whats up yea we&amp;#8217;re doing
this thing where I cant say &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BATMAN&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8230;
Dad: oops! uh&amp;#8230;.
Me: crap. I have phone calls to make. I&amp;#8217;ll talk to you later dad.
*click*
&lt;strong&gt;Post Failure Data:&lt;/strong&gt;
Batman is dirty. I don&amp;#8217;t even want to say it&amp;nbsp;now.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**Shatfan is the preferred euphemism for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BATMAN&lt;/span&gt;.
&lt;strong&gt;Analysis:&lt;/strong&gt;
We therefore conclude it is impossible (for me) not to say &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BATMAN&lt;/span&gt; for
longer than approximately two days. It was assumed by observers that the
continual substitution of Shatfan and derivatives (highlighted above)
for &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BATMAN&lt;/span&gt; was purely cavalier. This is false. While a bit of joviality
was included in the experiment, a vast majority of euphemisms used were
to assuage psychological tension. This was accompanied by laughter to
maximize psychological relief. Obviously experimental procedures must be
altered. We propose now an alternate method of success, via locking the
subject in his office for a week.
&lt;strong&gt;Conclusions:&lt;/strong&gt;
In this report we find that I am a weakling, and that the experiment was
kind of lame. However, as a test run for future Prohibitive Tests (PTs)
we find the concept promising, in that when Scott Bakula comes around,
I&amp;#8217;ll be the only one ready to take him on.
Current developments in PTs include subject which are not fit for print,
and thus the authors invite suggestions in which a mundane aspect of my
life will be removed for the greater good of mankind.
&lt;strong&gt;Acknowledgements:&lt;/strong&gt;
The authors would like to acknowledge that Corky is a shatfan. Stay
tuned for more.&amp;nbsp;-Jared&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jared</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 07 Apr 2010 20:56:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-04-07:posts/lessons-in-prohibition-one.html</guid><category>cognitive dissonance</category><category>Batman</category></item></channel></rss>