<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.approximation.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2012-03-14T11:52:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Pi-rithmetic</title><link href="/posts/pi-rithmetic.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T11:52:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:,2012-03-14:posts/pi-rithmetic.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-7rfL9Iby34A/T2C3LhSj_6I/AAAAAAAAAa0/rXTR30c77bk/s1600/IMAG0200.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-7rfL9Iby34A/T2C3LhSj_6I/AAAAAAAAAa0/rXTR30c77bk/s320/IMAG0200.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fun fact: pi squared is very close to 10. How close? Well, &lt;a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=%2810+-pi%5E2+%29%2Fpi%5E2"&gt;Wolfram
Alpha&lt;/a&gt;
tells me that it is only about 1% off. I first realized this fact when
looking at my slide rule, pictured to the left (click to embiggen), just
another reason why slide rules are awesome. It turns out I use this fact
all of the time. How&amp;#8217;s that you ask? Well, I use this fast to enable me
to do very quick mental arithmetic. It goes like this. For every number
you come across in a calculation, drop all of the information save two
parts, first, what&amp;#8217;s its order of magnitude, that is, how many digits
does it have, and second, is it closest to 1, pi, or 10? The first part
amounts to thinking of every number you come across as it looks in
scientific notation, so a number like 2342 turns into 2.342 x 10\^3, so
that I&amp;#8217;ve captured its magnitude in a power of 10. As for the next part,
the rules I usually use&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If the remaining bit is between 1 and 2, make it&amp;nbsp;1&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;If its between 2 and 6.5 make it&amp;nbsp;pi&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;if its bigger than 6.5, make it another&amp;nbsp;10&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Another way to think of this is to estimate every number to be a power
of ten, and then either 1, a few, or 10. The reason I choose pi is
because if I use pi, I know how the rest of the arithmetic should work,
namely, I only need to know a few rules, plus when I use this to
estimate answers of physics formulae, making a bunch of pis show up
tends to help me cancel other natural pis that are in the&amp;nbsp;formulae.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \\pi \\times \\pi \\sim10 \\qquad \\frac{1}{\\pi} \\sim
\\frac{\\pi}{10} \\qquad \\sqrt{10} \\sim \\pi $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Which you might notice is just the same approximation written in 3
different&amp;nbsp;ways.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s work an&amp;nbsp;example&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \\begin{align\*} 23 \\times 78 / 13 \\times 2133 &amp;amp;= ? \\\\ \\pi
\\times 10 \\times 100 / 10 \\times \\pi \\times 10\^3 &amp;amp;= ? \\\\ \\pi\^2
\\times 10\^5 &amp;amp;\\sim 10\^6 \\\\ \\end{align\*}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;of course the &lt;a href="http://www.wolframalpha.com/input/?i=23+*+78%2F13+*+2133"&gt;real
answer&lt;/a&gt; is
294,354, so you&amp;#8217;ll notice I got the answer wrong, but I only got it
wrong by a factor of 3, which is pretty good for mental arithmetic, and
in particular mental arithmetic that takes no time&amp;nbsp;flat.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, the average error I introduce by using this approximation is
just 30% or so for each number, which I&amp;#8217;ve shown below [the script that
produced this plot for those interested is
&lt;a href="https://gist.github.com/2037431"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;].&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-uwGlV6y_pps/T2C90lPhmQI/AAAAAAAAAbA/k_Hl8H-y2ys/s1600/pierr.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-uwGlV6y_pps/T2C90lPhmQI/AAAAAAAAAbA/k_Hl8H-y2ys/s320/pierr.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, there you go, now you can impress all of your friends with a simple
mental arithmetic that gets you within a factor of 3 or so on&amp;nbsp;average.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="order of magnitude"></category><category term="pi day"></category><category term="approximation"></category><category term="pi-rithmetic"></category></entry></feed>