<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/tag.hooray.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2011 22:30:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Physics Challenge Update</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-update.html</link><description>&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mQtqC-5MmYk/Tq9MkU56O9I/AAAAAAAAAPE/iaFRwtMKwJ0/s1600/mary_mcwatch.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="320" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-mQtqC-5MmYk/Tq9MkU56O9I/AAAAAAAAAPE/iaFRwtMKwJ0/s320/mary_mcwatch.jpg" width="221" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;Marty McFly realizes he is running out
of time to submit his solution&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Did you know that our &lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachine.php"&gt;Physics Challenge&lt;/a&gt; problem contest thingy is still up and going?  It is!  The contest will be open until the end of the day this &lt;b&gt;Friday, November 4th&lt;/b&gt;.  And, unlike last time, the winning solution will be chosen and posted by the end of the weekend.  So even if you don&amp;#8217;t submit your own solution (though you &lt;i&gt;totally&lt;/i&gt; should), check back here Monday morning for the winning&amp;nbsp;entry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why should you submit a solution to our problem?  Lots of reasons!  The top ten reasons as decided by a random sample of me are given below the&amp;nbsp;break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;b&gt;Top Ten Reasons to Submit a&amp;nbsp;Solution:&lt;/b&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;1)  You will win super-awesome prizes!  What kinds of prizes?  Well how does a greeting card with kittens on the front and a collection of encouraging haikus from the entire Virtuosi staff written inside sound?  It sounds awesome, awesome to the&amp;nbsp;max.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;2)  You get to show off your totally rad physics&amp;nbsp;skills!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3)  You can put it on your resume/cv!  The semi-annual Virtuosi Physics Challenge problem winners are held to the same esteem as Fields Medalists and Nobel Prize&amp;nbsp;winners!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;4)  You will earn the respect and admiration of your peers!  Winners of this contest develop an aura that all other people can see, fear, and&amp;nbsp;respect.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;5)  You will become stronger, faster, and more productive than ever before!  This is a scientifically proven fact&amp;nbsp;perhaps.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;6)  You may gain the ability to talk to animals!  Have you ever wanted to discuss espionage-related topics with a platypus (perhaps this &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ONgjXrOShlc"&gt;platypus&lt;/a&gt;)?  Of course you have!  Winners&amp;nbsp;can!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;7)  You will be in Presidential company!  Did you know William Henry Harrison won the very first Virtuosi physics challenge contest shortly before becoming the ninth President of the United States?  Yep!  Tippecanoe and so can&amp;nbsp;you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;8)  Alemi will salute in your general direction.  No questions&amp;nbsp;asked.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;9)  You will give me work to do on the weekend!  This will give my dull and uninteresting life a small glimmer of meaning!&amp;nbsp;Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;10) There&amp;#8217;s like a 50% chance that you will get three wishes from a magical genie named David Bowie (no relation).  Seriously.  Like&amp;nbsp;50%.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That should get you properly motivated!  So check out the Challenge Problem &lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/challenge/timemachine.php"&gt;website&lt;/a&gt; and when you have a solution, send it to our email address (given up in the&amp;nbsp;sidebar).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good&amp;nbsp;luck!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Corky</dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 31 Oct 2011 22:30:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-10-31:posts/physics-challenge-update.html</guid><category>desperate plea</category><category>physics challenge</category><category>hooray</category></item></channel></rss>