<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.wiki.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2010-08-11T14:04:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Teminal Velocity</title><link href="/posts/teminal-velocity.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-08-11T14:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Yariv</name></author><id>tag:,2010-08-11:posts/teminal-velocity.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The impetus for this post lies with three facts. First, I like to bike
to work. Second, Cornell sits on a
&lt;a href="http://www.cornell.edu/search/index.cfm?tab=facts&amp;amp;q=&amp;amp;id=272"&gt;hill&lt;/a&gt;. And
finally, I&amp;#8217;m not very brave. As a result of all of these, along with
Ithaca&amp;#8217;s less-than-optimal road maintenance, my semi-daily rides home
tend to produce a lot of wear on my brakes as I cruise downhill at what
appears to me to be very high speeds. I began to ponder just how high
this speed really is, and if I could reduce my use of the brakes or if
I&amp;#8217;m going to end up using them anyway at the bottom of the hill.
&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_JIGLe2C6VxI/TGLwOVisUAI/AAAAAAAACD4/V9TvWzmEv9k/s200/200px-Free_body.svg.png" /&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Figure 1: An inclined&amp;nbsp;plane&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, I asked myself, what do I remember about bikes going down the hill?
Well, I remember the good old inclined plane (figure 1), and I remember
that air resistance is proportional to velocity, so that the equation of
motion is given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ma = mg\\sin\\theta - \\alpha v. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; I had no idea
what α was, though. My first stop in considering it was naturally
Wikipedia. A quick
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terminal_velocity"&gt;search&lt;/a&gt; came up with
the formula &lt;mathjax&gt;$$m a = mg\\sin\\theta - \\frac{1}{2}\\rho A C\_d v\^2$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where ρ is the density of air, A the projected area of the body and C~d~
the drag coefficient The first thing to notice here is that I was wrong
- drag in a fluid acts like the velocity squared, and not the velocity.
Second, we can easily determine terminal velocity out of this formula -
it&amp;#8217;s the speed at which the sum of the forces equals to zero, or &lt;mathjax&gt;$$v\_t
= \\sqrt{\\frac{2mg\\sin\\theta}{\\rho A C\_d}}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; We can throw in some
numbers into that. ρ = 1.2 kg/m^3^ for air; Wikipedia estimates C~d~ =
0.9 for a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Drag_coefficient"&gt;cyclist&lt;/a&gt;. For
the mass, we need to add up mine (\~75 kg), the bike&amp;#8217;s (15-20 kg) and my
bag&amp;#8217;s (let&amp;#8217;s say 5 kg). We come to about 100 kg, give or take 5%. A is a
little harder to estimate, but height times width gives me an initial
guess of 0.62 m^2^, which I&amp;#8217;ll revise to 0.7 m^2^ to account for the
bike, flailing arms and fashionable helmet, up to about 10% accuracy.
We&amp;#8217;re left with sinθ, which varies by road, but in general we expect the
terminal velocity to look like &lt;mathjax&gt;$$v\_t \\approx \\left(50 \\pm 3
\\rm{m/s}\\right) \\sqrt{\\sin\\theta}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; This appears not-unreasonable.
For an 8% grade like we have down University avenue this yields about 50
km/h and for a 13% grade like we have down Buffalo street this will
bring us up to a respectable 65
&lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/post-edit.g?blogID=8807287158334608095&amp;amp;postID=6743488546064317383#miles" title="That's - sigh - about 30 mph and 40 mph, respectively, in crazy units"&gt;km/h&lt;/a&gt;.
Both, incidentally, are faster than I&amp;#8217;m willing to go down a badly
maintained, not entire straight road. So we have some numbers, and I
begin to feel justified about pressing those breaks often, but all of
this is really an introduction for the next post, in which I go against
all my theorist instincts and take some data in the field. Stay&amp;nbsp;tuned.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.blogger.com/post-edit.g?blogID=8807287158334608095&amp;amp;postID=6743488546064317383"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;That&amp;#8217;s&lt;ul&gt;
&lt;li&gt;sigh - about 30 mph and 40 mph, respectively, in crazy&amp;nbsp;units&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ul&gt;
&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;</summary><category term="analysis"></category><category term="guestimation"></category><category term="bike"></category><category term="wiki"></category><category term="equations"></category></entry></feed>