<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.esoteric.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 09:04:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Flying back</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/flying-back.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Those of us originating on the right side of the &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;geocode=&amp;amp;q=Atlantic+Ocean&amp;amp;sll=39.368279,-9.316406&amp;amp;sspn=57.758311,144.316406&amp;amp;dirflg=w&amp;amp;ie=UTF8&amp;amp;hq=&amp;amp;hnear=Atlantic+Ocean&amp;amp;ll=37.857507,-22.675781&amp;amp;spn=62.051619,144.316406&amp;amp;z=3"&gt;atlantic
ocean&lt;/a&gt;
are familiar with a little quirk of international flights: the flights
home are shorter. Specifically, going from Tel Aviv to New York takes
about one hour longer than going the other way around. This is an
oddity, and the very first explanation that comes to mind the rotation
of the Earth. After all, our naive image of a plane going up in the air
might be something a little like a rock being thrown up from a moving
cart, and we would imagine the plane to pick up some relative speed by
not rotating as fast as the Earth. Is this a factor in the plane&amp;#8217;s
movement? This gives us a perfect chance to use the Earth Units we
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/earth-day-earth-units.html"&gt;introduced&lt;/a&gt;
a few weeks ago. Specifically I&amp;#8217;ll use the Earth meter (equal to the
radius of the Earth, which I&amp;#8217;ll dub e-m) and Earth second (one day,
e-s). First we want to figure out velocity of the airplane compared to
the ground. When it is grounded, the plane and the Earth&amp;#8217;s surface both
have an angular velocity of 2π 1/e-s; they do one revolution per day.
This means the plane&amp;#8217;s linear velocity is 2π e-m/e-s, and its angular
velocity once it&amp;#8217;s airborne is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$2 \pi \cdot \frac{(1\;
\rm{m_\oplus})}{(1\; \rm{m_\oplus}+A)}
\;\rm{s_\oplus^{-1}},$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where A is the altitude. That&amp;#8217;s the one
number I&amp;#8217;m going to pull out of thin air here; that being the thin air
of the cabin where they always announce that we have attained a cruising
altitude of 30,000 feet. In real people units, that&amp;#8217;s about 9,000
meters, or 9 kilometers - round it up to 10. Going back to the Earth day
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/earth-day-earth-units.html"&gt;post&lt;/a&gt;
1 e-m is about 6380 km, so that the angular velocity of the airplane is
about 0.9984 (2π) 1/e-s, and relative to the ground it is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$0.0016
\cdot 2 \pi \;\rm{s_\oplus^{-1}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So, over a journey of length
of about 0.5 e-s, the overall distance traveled due to this effect would
come to about &lt;mathjax&gt;$$0.0008 \cdot 2\pi \;\rm{m_\oplus}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Tel Aviv and
New York are both in the mid-northern hemisphere and seven time zones
apart, so a first-order estimate of the distance between them would be
about &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{7}{24}\cdot 2\pi \;\rm{m_\oplus} \approx
0.29\cdot 2\pi \;\rm{m_\oplus}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Overall, it looks like this
effect is negligible. Indeed, anyone who gives the matter a second
thought would notice that the planes should go faster when traveling
westwards, as the Earth spins eastwards toward the rising sun. Anyone
who looks even further into the matter finds that eastbound and
westbound planes simply take different routes across the Atlantic,
leaving us with a rather more mundane and less exciting explanation.
Still, I won&amp;#8217;t complain if it makes my flight any shorter. Now, if
you&amp;#8217;ll excuse me, I have some beaches to catch up&amp;nbsp;with.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Yariv</dc:creator><pubDate>Tue, 25 May 2010 09:04:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-25:posts/flying-back.html</guid><category>units</category><category>flying</category><category>esoteric</category></item><item><title>Esoteric Physics I - The Hall Effect</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/esoteric-physics-i-the-hall-effect.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;What we usually do here at the The Virtuosi is take an interesting
problem, and work out the physical principles behind what we&amp;#8217;re seeing.
Or pose a question and try to answer it. Now, I&amp;#8217;m a big fan of this kind
of thing, which is why I&amp;#8217;ve done so much of it. But I worry that it
might give a slightly skewed view of physics. Sure, physics explains
things. That&amp;#8217;s why we do it. But not everything in physics is &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/laser-gun-recoil-follow-up.html"&gt;laser
guns&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/05/solar-sails-i.html"&gt;solar
sails&lt;/a&gt;.
There are a lot of interesting physics phenomena that the general public
will never hear about, because they&amp;#8217;re just too, well, esoteric. What
I&amp;#8217;m going to do is occasionally talk about such effects, and, for some
of them, give you applications for these strange effects you might see
on a day-to-day basis. Today I&amp;#8217;m going to examine the Hall effect. The
Hall effect is simple, as these things go, once we understand the
pieces. The first piece is that magnetic fields deflect moving
electrically charged particles. I don&amp;#8217;t think I can give you a good
simple reason for this, you&amp;#8217;re just going to have to trust me (for those
interested, I&amp;#8217;d argue that the relativistic transformation of a magnetic
field is an electric field, and that will certainly deflect an
electrically charged particle). This is a piece of the Lorentz force.
The next piece that we need to know is that opposite electrically
charged particles attract. So a positively charged particle attracts a
negatively charged particle. Knowing those two things we can detail the
Hall effect.
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S_nxJSw3bQI/AAAAAAAAABU/Mi2_jDtskus/s1600/Hall+effect+pos.JPG"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S_nxJSw3bQI/AAAAAAAAABU/Mi2_jDtskus/s320/Hall+effect+pos.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Take the slab pictured above. We run an electric current through it.
Conventionally we take current as moving positively charged particles.
There is a magnetic field into the screen. This deflects the positive
charges up the screen, as shown, with some upward force. Over some time,
we will accumulate positive charges at the top. Because there is no net
charge in our slab, this must leave a region of negative charge at the
bottom. These regions of charge will attract, and cancel out the force
from the magnetic field. This charge separation results in a voltage
differential between the two sides of the slab, which is what we
actually measure. The Hall effect has some nifty consequences
physically. I mentioned that conventionally we take current to be
positive particles moving. A microscopic picture of our conductors will
tell us that, in general, electrons are what we consider to be flowing
in an electric current. Now, it turns out that our magnetic field will
deflect electrons moving opposite our current direction (negative
current moving backwards is the same as positive current moving
forwards) to the same side as our hypothetical positive particles got
deflected to. This generates a charge differential with negative and
positive charges on the opposite sides of the slab (shown below), which
means the voltage is negative what we would have measured above! This
means we expect to get a certain sign of the measured Hall voltage,
which we can predict. This sign would correspond to negative particles
(electrons) being the moving charge carriers in substances. It turns out
that there are some substances (some semiconductors) where the sign of
the Hall voltage is opposite what we expect from electrons. This means
that in those substances the current is being carried by positive
particles! I won&amp;#8217;t explain what that means here (I may address that in a
later post), but I hope you can see why that would be fascinating. We
expected to have electrons moving, and it turns out that something else
is really doing the moving. The Hall effect is an experimental result
that helped suggest a whole new way of thinking about conduction in
materials.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S_nxRTxhhoI/AAAAAAAAABc/AJGpkjd-iWU/s1600/Hall+effect+neg.JPG"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S_nxRTxhhoI/AAAAAAAAABc/AJGpkjd-iWU/s320/Hall+effect+neg.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Beyond being very interesting physics, there are some applications to
this effect. It is an easy way to create a magnetic field sensor. Take a
slab of material, run a current through it, and measure the voltage on
the sides. Where do we use magnetic field sensors? Well, they sometimes
show up as a way to tell if something is open or closed. Put a magnet in
your lid, and a Hall effect sensor in the lip the lid rests on. When it
is closed, you&amp;#8217;ll measure a voltage, and when it is open you won&amp;#8217;t. Now
you can tell if it is open or closed. A little imagination, and you can
see how this would be useful for all kinds of switches. Hit the switch,
move your magnet, and change your voltage. According to Wikipedia, Hall
effect switches are used in things as diverse as paintball guns and
go-cart speed controls. They could also be used as a speed or
acceleration measurement in a rotating system. Attach a magnet to the
rotating object, put a sensor at a fixed location, and measure how the
voltage in your sensor changes as the object sweeps past it. There are
many more applications, but this is just to give you a taste of how this
seemingly esoteric physics concept may show up in your everyday life.
It&amp;#8217;s not just the interesting problems we often work on this blog,
physics is everywhere. In many different&amp;nbsp;guises&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 23 May 2010 23:31:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-23:posts/esoteric-physics-i-the-hall-effect.html</guid><category>magnetism</category><category>hall effect</category><category>current</category><category>esoteric</category></item></channel></rss>