<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.advice.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2010-04-25T20:29:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>Some of the Best Advice You’ll Ever Receive</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/some-of-the-best-advice-you-ll-ever-receive.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-25T20:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Alemi</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-25:posts/some-of-the-best-advice-you-ll-ever-receive.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I came across what might be the best advice any student (nay any human
being) could possibly ever receive reading a book&amp;nbsp;today&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now there are two ways in which you can increase your understanding of
these issues. One way is to remember the general ideas and then go
home and try to figure out what commands you need and make sure you
don&amp;#8217;t leave one out. Make the set shorter or longer for convidence and
try to understand the tradeoffs by trying to do problems with your
choice. This is the way I would do it because I have that kind of
personality! It&amp;#8217;s the way I study &amp;#8212; to understand somethingby trying
to work it out or, in other words, to understand something by creating
it. Not creating it one hundred percent, of course; but taking a hint
as to which direction to go but not remembering the details. These you
work out for yourself. The other way, which is also valuable, is to
read carefully how someone else did it. I find the first method best
for me, once I have understood the basic idea. If I get stuck I look
at a book that tells me how someone else did it. I turn the pages and
then I say &amp;#8220;Oh, I forgot that bit&amp;#8221;, then close the book and carry on.
Finally, after you&amp;#8217;ve figured out how to do it you read how they did
it and find out how dum your solution is and how much more clever and
efficient theirs is! But this way you can understand the cleverness of
their ideas and have a framework in which to think about the problem.
When I start straight off to read someone else&amp;#8217;s solution I find it
boring and uninteresting, with no way of putting the whole picture
together. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AT&lt;/span&gt; least, thats the way it works for me! Throughout the
book, I will suggest some problems for you to play with. You might
feel tempted to skip them. If they&amp;#8217;re too hard, fine. Some of them are
pretty difficult! But you might skip them thinking that, well, they&amp;#8217;ve
probably been done by somebody else; so what&amp;#8217;s the point? Well, of
&lt;em&gt;course&lt;/em&gt; they&amp;#8217;ve been done! But so what? Do them for the &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; of it.
That&amp;#8217;s how to learn the knack of doing things when you have to do
them. Let me give you an example. Suppose I wanted to add up a series
of numbers, 1 + 2 + 3 + 4 + 5 + 6 + 7 &amp;#8230; up to say, 62. No doubt you
know how to do it; but when you play with this sort of problem as a
kid, and you haven&amp;#8217;t been shown the answer &amp;#8230; it&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;fun&lt;/em&gt; trying to
figure out how to do it. Then, as you go into adulthood, you develop a
certain confidence that you can discover things&amp;#8217; but if they&amp;#8217;ve
already been discovered, that shouldn&amp;#8217;t bother you at all. &lt;strong&gt;What one
fool can do, so can another, and the fact that some other fool beat
you to it shouldn&amp;#8217;t disturb you: you should get a kick out of having
discovered something.&lt;/strong&gt; Most of the problems I give you in this book
have been worked over many times, and many ingenious solutions have
been devised for them. But if you keep proving stuff that other s have
done, getting confidence, increasing the complexities of your solution
for the fun of it &amp;#8212; then one day you&amp;#8217;ll turn around and discover that
&lt;em&gt;nobody actually did that one!&lt;/em&gt; And that&amp;#8217;s the way to become a&amp;nbsp;scientist.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The quote is from none other than &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Richard_feynman"&gt;Richard
Feynman&lt;/a&gt; in his &lt;a href="http://books.google.com/books?id=-olQAAAAMAAJ&amp;amp;q=feynman+lectures+on+computation&amp;amp;dq=feynman+lectures+on+computation&amp;amp;ei=4dLUS4HBC43aygSIqaXoCQ&amp;amp;cd=1"&gt;Lectures
on
Computation&lt;/a&gt;
(a great read by the way). [reproduced without permission] Honestly I
think that&amp;#8217;s one of the biggest problems with science and math education
in this country. They have taken something which is fun and challenging,
a path of discovery, and reduced it to memorizing a list of dogmatic
equations handed down from high. Students are all but taught that the
men and women that discovered these laws are somehow above the rest of
us. One of the best kept secrets of science is that scientists are in
fact mere mortals. They have their faults, and deficiencies just like
the rest of us. You don&amp;#8217;t need anything special to do science, all you
need is a sense of curiosity and wonder, and the resolve to spend some
time working at it. The more time you work at it, the better you get.
Science is not a list of facts. It is not plugging numbers into
equations. It is neither history nor accounting. It is, in its purest
form, the recognition that as human beings we are each endowed with the
power to come to understand the world around us. I firmly believe that
anyone of a sane mind is capable of becoming a physicist. I&amp;#8217;m not saying
that everyone should be; people should follow their passions, but I
worry that too many students are turned away thinking they aren&amp;#8217;t cut
out to be scientists, and that&amp;#8217;s rubbish. And that&amp;#8217;s my two&amp;nbsp;cents.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="education"></category><category term="feynman"></category><category term="advice"></category></entry></feed>