<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.scott-bakula.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</id><updated>2012-08-04T04:56:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>A Curious Footprint</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/a-curious-footprint.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-08-04T04:56:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-08-04:posts/a-curious-footprint.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-nW-i5yFeM6Y/UByrmMDEVbI/AAAAAAAAAZM/rBD78ulDQj0/s1600/msl_laser.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-nW-i5yFeM6Y/UByrmMDEVbI/AAAAAAAAAZM/rBD78ulDQj0/s320/msl_laser.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Lasers! &lt;em&gt;Credit:&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JPL&lt;/span&gt;/Caltech&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In less than two days, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s Mars Science Laboratory (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MSL&lt;/span&gt;) /
&lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt; rover will begin its harrowing descent to the Martian
surface. If everything goes according to the
kind-of-crazy-what-the-heck-is-a-sky-crane plan, this process will be
referred to as &amp;#8220;landing&amp;#8221; (otherwise, more crashy/explodey gerunds will
no doubt be used). The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MSL&lt;/span&gt; mission is run through &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s Jet Propulsion
Laboratory where, by coincidence, I happen to be at the moment. Now, I&amp;#8217;m
not working on this project, so I don&amp;#8217;t have a lot to add that
&lt;a href="http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/msl/index.cfm"&gt;isn&amp;#8217;t&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://blogs.discovermagazine.com/badastronomy/2012/08/02/curiositys-chem-lab-on-mars/"&gt;available&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/startswithabang/2012/07/20/43-years-later-were-seven-minutes-away-from-a-second-great-step-forward/"&gt;elsewhere&lt;/a&gt;.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BUT&lt;/span&gt; I do feel an authority-by-proximity kind of fallacy kicking in, so
how about a post why&amp;nbsp;not?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Preliminaries&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we get started, I feel obligated to link to &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=Ki_Af_o9Q9s"&gt;Seven
Minutes of Terror&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;video. If
you haven&amp;#8217;t seen it yet, I highly recommend watching it right now (my
favorite part is the subtitles). It has over a million views on YouTube
and seems to have done a pretty good job at generating interest in the
mission. Although, it&amp;#8217;s a shame they had to interview the first guy in
what appears to be a police interrogation room. Oh&amp;nbsp;well.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;About the&amp;nbsp;Rover&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This thing is &lt;em&gt;big&lt;/em&gt;. It&amp;#8217;s the size of a car and is jam-packed with
&lt;a href="http://mars.jpl.nasa.gov/msl/mission/instruments/"&gt;scientific
equipment&lt;/a&gt;. There&amp;#8217;s a
couple different spectrometers, a bunch of cameras, a drill for
collecting rock samples, and radiation detectors. Probably the coolest
instrument onboard &lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt; is called the ChemCam. The ChemCam uses a
laser to vaporize small regions of rock, which allows it to study the
composition of things about 20 feet&amp;nbsp;away.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In addition to the scientific payload, &lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt; also needs some way
to generate power. Previous rovers had been powered by solar panels, but
there don&amp;#8217;t appear to be any here. Instead, &lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt; is
&lt;a href="http://www.ne.doe.gov/pdfFiles/MMRTG_Jan2008.pdf"&gt;powered&lt;/a&gt; by the heat
released from the radioactive decay of about 10 pounds of plutonium
dioxide. This source will power the rover for ~~about a Martian year~~
well beyond the currently planned mission duration of one Martian year
(about 687 Earth days) &lt;em&gt;[Thanks to Nathan in the comments for pointing
this out!]&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To summarize, the rover is a nuclear-powered lab-on-wheels that &lt;em&gt;shoots
lasers out of its head&lt;/em&gt;. This is pretty&amp;nbsp;cool.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-jLOpoGLY6Yk/UBzbYgwRMKI/AAAAAAAAAZg/lViBtW_vQgM/s1600/msl2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-jLOpoGLY6Yk/UBzbYgwRMKI/AAAAAAAAAZg/lViBtW_vQgM/s400/msl2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  In non-&lt;span class="caps"&gt;SI&lt;/span&gt; units, the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MSL&lt;/span&gt; is roughly one handsome man (1 hm)&amp;nbsp;tall&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;A Curious&amp;nbsp;Footprint&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;There&amp;#8217;s been a lot of preparation at &lt;span class="caps"&gt;JPL&lt;/span&gt; this week for the upcoming
landing. All the shiny rover models have been taken out of the visitor&amp;#8217;s
center and put in a tent outside, presumably so there will be a pretty
backdrop for press reports and the&amp;nbsp;like.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Anyway, I was out taking pictures of the rovers at the end of the day
today when someone pointed out something cool about the tires on
&lt;em&gt;Curiosity&lt;/em&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here&amp;#8217;s a&amp;nbsp;close-up:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ZAritHZ1usE/UBzfOUrM_oI/AAAAAAAAAZ0/meA5wgE6HCM/s1600/MSL_tire.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-ZAritHZ1usE/UBzfOUrM_oI/AAAAAAAAAZ0/meA5wgE6HCM/s400/MSL_tire.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Hole-y&amp;nbsp;Tires&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Each tire on the rover is has &amp;#8220;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;JPL&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; punched out in &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:International_Morse_Code.svg"&gt;Morse
code&lt;/a&gt;!
Makes sense, though. If you&amp;#8217;re going to spend $2.5 billion on something,
you might as well put your name on&amp;nbsp;it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Watch the&amp;nbsp;Landing&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to watch the landing, check out the &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/multimedia/nasatv/index.html"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt;
stream&lt;/a&gt;. The landing
is scheduled for Sunday night at 10:31 pm &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PDT&lt;/span&gt; (1:31 am &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EDT&lt;/span&gt;). Until then,
it looks like they are showing a lot of interviews and other cool
behind-the-scenes kind of&amp;nbsp;stuff.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="mars"></category><category term="curiosity"></category><category term="MSL"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Tales from the Transit of Venus</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/tales-from-the-transit-of-venus.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-06-05T00:50:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-06-05:posts/tales-from-the-transit-of-venus.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-JNVfkJwnAyY/T81XzasS8iI/AAAAAAAAAYU/eCerOIwvHxA/s1600/sad_transit.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-JNVfkJwnAyY/T81XzasS8iI/AAAAAAAAAYU/eCerOIwvHxA/s200/sad_transit.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Sad Old&amp;nbsp;Sun&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today is the transit of Venus, which, aside from being a totally rad
astronomical event, is also the perfect excuse to tell my favorite story
of an unlucky Frenchman (I have many). This is by no means new and, if
you&amp;#8217;ve ever taken an astronomy course, you&amp;#8217;ve probably already heard it.
It is perhaps the closest thing Astronomy has to a ghost story, told
though the glow of a flashlight on moonless nights to scare the
children. This is the story of Guillaume Le Gentil, a dude that just
couldn&amp;#8217;t catch a&amp;nbsp;break.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Guillaume Joseph Hyacinthe Jean-Baptiste Le Gentil de la Galaisière was
a Frenchman with an incredibly long name. He was also an astronomer,
though he hadn&amp;#8217;t started out that way. Monsieur Le Gentil (as his
friends called him and so, then, shall we) had originally intended to
enter the priesthood. However, he soon began sneaking away to hear
astronomy lectures and quickly switched from studies of Heaven to those
heavens more readily observed in a telescope. Le Gentil happened to get
into the astronomy game at a very exciting time. The next pair of Venus
transits was imminent and astronomers were giddy with anticipation.
Though the previous transit of 1639 had been predicted, it was met with
little fanfare and only a few measurements. But the transits of 1761 and
1769 would be different. People would be ready. And the stakes were
higher this time, too. Soon after the 1639 transit, Edmund Halley (he of
the-only-comet-people-can-name fame) calculated that with enough
simultaneous measurements, the distance from the Earth to the Sun (the
so-called astronomical unit, or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AU&lt;/span&gt;) could be measured fairly accurately.
Since almost all other astronomical distances were known in terms of the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AU&lt;/span&gt;, knowing its precise value would essentially set the scale for the
cosmos. Brand new telescopes in hand, the astronomers of Europe set sail
for locations all over the&amp;nbsp;world.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Gentil had been assigned to observe the transit from Pondicherry, a
French holding on the eastern side of India. On March 26th, 1760, he
began his long sea voyage around the Cape of Good Hope towards&amp;nbsp;India.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The voyage from France to India was a bit too long for the ship Le
Gentil hitched a ride on and he only made it as far as Mauritius (a
small island off Madagascar). Dropped off with all his equipment, Le
Gentil was left waiting for any ship at all to take him to&amp;nbsp;Pondicherry.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Perhaps it was the Curse of the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Dodo"&gt;Dodo&lt;/a&gt; or perhaps it was just bad
luck, but while he was waiting, Le Gentil learned that
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Seven_Years'_War"&gt;war&lt;/a&gt; had broken out
between the French and the British, making a trip to British India very
difficult for a&amp;nbsp;Frenchman.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then the monsoon season started, meaning that even if he could find a
ship, it would have to take a much longer route to India than initially
planned and that it would be very difficult to make the journey before
the transit&amp;nbsp;occurred.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, he caught dysentery for the first&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, after months of waiting, Le Gentil (barely recovered from his
illness) left Mauritius for India in February of 1761. Though time
appeared to be running out, the captain of the ship he was on promised
he would be there to observe the transit in June. About halfway to
India, the winds switched directions and the ship was forced to turn
back to&amp;nbsp;Mauritius.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Le Gentil dutifully observed the transit of Venus in 1761 from a rocky
ship in the middle of the Indian Ocean. The data were useless and he
never attempted any&amp;nbsp;analysis.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Although he missed the first transit, these things come in pairs
separated by eight years. There was still another chance. And with all
this time to prepare, there was no way he was going to miss the second&amp;nbsp;one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, there was a bit &lt;em&gt;too much&lt;/em&gt; time. But as a world-traveling 18th
century man of science, Le Gentil had plenty of other interests to fill
his days. He was particularly interested in surveying the region around&amp;nbsp;Madagascar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So he made a really nice map of Madagascar. And then he ate some bad
kind of some kind of animal and came down with a terrible sickness. He
describes this illness and its &amp;#8220;cure&amp;#8221; in his&amp;nbsp;journals:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;This sickness was a sort of violent stroke, of which several very
copious blood-lettings made immediately on my arm and my foot, and
emetic administered twelve hours afterwards, rid me of it quite
quickly. But there remained for seven or eight days in my optic nerve
a singular impression from this sickness; it was to see two objects in
the place of one, beside each other; this illusion disappeared little
by little as I regained my&amp;nbsp;strength&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After recovering from both his sickness and the treatment, Le Gentil
decided to begin his preparations for the 1769 transit of Venus. He
calculated that either Manila or the Mariana Islands would be the ideal
spot to observe. The Sun would be relatively high in the sky at both
places when Venus passed by, meaning that the view would be through less
atmosphere with a reduced chance of clouds passing through the line of
sight. Le Gentil packed up his stuff and headed off to Manila, where he
could catch another ship to get to the Mariana Islands. Arriving in
Manila in 1766, the astronomer found himself exhausted from months of
sickness and sea-voyage. So, when he was offered passage on a ship
heading to the Mariana Islands, he quickly declined. That he chose not
to depart Manila at that time was perhaps his one stroke of good luck in
the entire journey. The ship sunk. Writing in his journal, Le Gentil
appears to have developed that particular sense of humor that generally
accompanies constant&amp;nbsp;disappointment:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;It is true that only three or four people were drowned, those who
were the most eager to save themselves, which is what almost always
happens in shipwrecks. I cannot answer that I would not have
increased the number of persons eager to save&amp;nbsp;themselves.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, Le Gentil was in Manila with plenty of time to prepare for
the next transit. Unfortunately, the astronomer may have over-prepared.
Having arrived three years before the event, he now had three years to
worry and second-guess his decision. It didn&amp;#8217;t help that the Spanish
governor of Manila was kind of a crazy person. Not wanting to miss the
observation of a lifetime owing to the whims of mildly insane strong
man, Le Gentil packed up his stuff and headed to Pondicherry. Finally in
Pondicherry, Le Gentil worked tirelessly to construct his observatory
and make plenty of astronomical observations in preparation for the
event. He had state of the art equipment and had fully calibrated and
double checked everything. It was now nine years since his journey began
and only a few days until the transit was scheduled to occur at sunrise
on June 4th. The entire month of May was beautiful weather and pristine
observing conditions, as were the first few days of June. Le Gentil
likely went to bed on the 3rd of June fully confident that the next
morning would be no different. He woke up early in the morning to begin
preparations for his sunrise observations only to find clouds on the
horizon. The clouds remained, obscuring the sun, all through the
duration of the transit. A few hours after the end of the transit, the
sun broke through the clouds and remained visible for the rest of the
day. Le Gentil had missed his second transit in Pondicherry. He sums it
up in his&amp;nbsp;journal:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;That is the fate which often awaits astronomers. I had gone more
than ten thousand leagues; it seemed that I had crossed such a great
expanse of seas, exiling myself from my native land, only to be the
spectator of a fatal cloud which came to place itself before the sun
at the precise moment of my observation, to carry off from me the
fruits of my pains and of my&amp;nbsp;fatigues&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In Manila, the Sun rose in perfectly clear skies. Distraught, Le Gentil
remained in bed for some weeks afterward. He soon caught a fever and
missed the ship that was supposed to take him home. He recovered, but
then came down with dysentery again. Barely recovered from his various
illnesses, he managed to get a ride back to Mauritius. He caught a ship
leaving the island in November of 1770. The ship was struck by a
hurricane and almost completely destroyed. It managed to limp back to
Mauritius. The second attempt proved more successful and Le Gentil
finally &amp;#8220;set foot on France at nine o&amp;#8217;clock in the morning, after eleven
years, six months and thirteen days of absence.&amp;#8221; Though he had finally
made it home, he was not out of the woods quite yet. In his absence, Le
Gentil&amp;#8217;s heirs had tried to declare him dead to gain their inheritance,
his accountant had mishandled (and lost) a large chunk of his holdings,
and the Academy of Sciences, which had sent him on his 11 year mission,
had given his seat to someone else. It was not quite the welcome home he
had hoped for. Despite his seemingly never-ending misfortune, things did
turn around for Le Gentil. He married, had a daughter, and was
reinstated into the Academy of Sciences. Presumably, he lived out the
rest of his days in relative happiness. Le Gentil died in 1792. Keeping
true to his style, this man who missed two of the most important
astronomical events of his time fortunately managed to also miss the
most important (and violent) &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Reign_of_Terror"&gt;political
event&lt;/a&gt; of his&amp;nbsp;time.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;References:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have mainly used a very nice series of historical papers of Le
Gentil&amp;#8217;s misadventures with the transit of Venus written by Helen Sawyer
Hogg. The papers were originally published in the &lt;em&gt;Journal of the Royal
Astronomical Society of Canada&lt;/em&gt; and can be accessed through &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8217;s &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ADS&lt;/span&gt; (
&lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1951JRASC..45...37S"&gt;Part 1&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1951JRASC..45...89S"&gt;Part
2&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1951JRASC..45..127S"&gt;Part
3&lt;/a&gt;, &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1951JRASC..45..173S"&gt;Part
4&lt;/a&gt;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;More Transit of&amp;nbsp;Venus:&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you want to see the Transit of Venus without having to go on an
eleven year voyage (or even leaving your room), check out the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="http://sunearthday.nasa.gov/transitofvenus/"&gt;live-feed&lt;/a&gt; from Mauna&amp;nbsp;Kea.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="transit of venus"></category><category term="bummer"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Money for (almost) Nothing</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/money-for-almost-nothing.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-29T01:27:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-03-29:posts/money-for-almost-nothing.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-j1vgDeAaElw/T3O5K09X6XI/AAAAAAAAAW0/b3uIqmdtPl4/s1600/mega_millions.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-j1vgDeAaElw/T3O5K09X6XI/AAAAAAAAAW0/b3uIqmdtPl4/s320/mega_millions.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Five Hundred Mega Dollars, to be precise. (Image from&amp;nbsp;Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I am not typically interested in lotteries. They seem silly and I am
seriously beginning to question their usefulness in bringing about a
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Lottery"&gt;good harvest&lt;/a&gt;. But this
morning I read in the news that the Mega Millions lottery currently has
a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mega_Millions#Record_jackpots_.28listed_by_cash_value.29"&gt;world
record&lt;/a&gt;
jackpot up for grabs. In fact, the jackpot is so&amp;nbsp;big&amp;#8230;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Tonight Show Audience: &lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HOW&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BIG&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IS&lt;/span&gt;&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;IT&lt;/span&gt;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;**&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is &lt;em&gt;so big&lt;/em&gt; that I decided to do a little bit of analysis on the
expected returns.&amp;nbsp;Zing!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Some&amp;nbsp;Background&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, a little background. The Mega Millions lottery is an aptly named
lottery in which numbered ping pong balls are pulled from a giant
rotating tub of randomization. Five of these are drawn from one tub of
56 balls, with no replacement. The sixth ball (the so-called &amp;#8220;Mega
Ball&amp;#8221;) is drawn from a &lt;em&gt;separate&lt;/em&gt;tub of 46 balls. To play, one picks 5
different numbers (1-56) for the regular draws and one number (1-46) for
the Mega Ball. The first five can match in any order, but the last ball
has to match with the Mega Ball. Prizes are given out based on how many
numbers you match. Stolen from the Mega Millions website, the prizes and
odds are given in the table below. The current jackpot is listed at &lt;mathjax&gt;$500
million (if taken in annuity) or $&lt;/mathjax&gt;359 million if taken in an up-front
lump sum. It costs $1 dollar to&amp;nbsp;play.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Zi3rSfNqtuI/T3PHTEaXmvI/AAAAAAAAAXE/y9Hs7fqWrgs/s1600/crummy_table.gif"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-Zi3rSfNqtuI/T3PHTEaXmvI/AAAAAAAAAXE/y9Hs7fqWrgs/s320/crummy_table.gif" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Don&amp;#8217;t worry about the asterisk. It just says &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CA&lt;/span&gt; is lame. (Source: &lt;a href="http://www.megamillions.com/howto/"&gt;Mega Millions&lt;/a&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hot diggity daffodil, we&amp;#8217;re ready to get&amp;nbsp;going!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Expected&amp;nbsp;Winnings&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so it costs &lt;mathjax&gt;$1 to play and we could potentially win $&lt;/mathjax&gt;500
million. It sure &lt;em&gt;feels&lt;/em&gt; like it is worth it to play (what&amp;#8217;s the harm?).
But we can do better than feelings, we have&amp;#8230;&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;MATH&lt;/span&gt;!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since we have an exhaustive list of outcomes and their probabilities
(which is just the inverse of the big number in the &amp;#8220;chances&amp;#8221; column),
we can calculate the expectation value for our winnings. The expectation
value is just the sum over all the possible prize values times the
probability of winning that prize. In other&amp;nbsp;words,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\langle W \rangle = \sum_i W_i \times p_i, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where we denote our expected winnings in angled&amp;nbsp;brackets.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In essence, this value represents the average prize you would win if you
played this lottery over and over and over again (or played all the
combinations of&amp;nbsp;numbers).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Setting the jackpot to $500 million, we can now compute the expected
winnings&amp;nbsp;as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \langle W \rangle = \frac{\$ 500,000,000}{175,711,536} +
\frac{\$ 250,000}{3,904,701} +\frac{\$ 10,000}{689,065} + \frac{\$
150}{15,313} + \frac{\$ 150}{13,781} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$+ \frac{\$ 10}{844} + \frac{\$ 7}{306} + \frac{\$ 3}{141} +
\frac{\$ 2}{75}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few flicks of the abacus later, we find that the expectation value of
our prize&amp;nbsp;is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\langle W \rangle = \$ 3.02,$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which means that after we subtract the dollar we paid for the ticket,
our expected return is&amp;nbsp;$2.02.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But what if we had chosen to take our winnings as a lump sum of &lt;mathjax&gt;$359
million instead of the $&lt;/mathjax&gt;500 million paid out over a span of 26 years? In
that case we&amp;nbsp;find&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\langle W \rangle = \$ 2.22,$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which results in a $1.22 gain when we subtract the dollar we paid for
the&amp;nbsp;ticket.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At least in a statistical sense for this particular jackpot, one is
better off playing than not playing. But are we forgetting&amp;nbsp;anything?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;The&amp;nbsp;Taxman&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you win a &lt;mathjax&gt;$500 million jackpot, do you *really* get a $&lt;/mathjax&gt;500 million
jackpot? Well, no. For winnings in a lottery over &lt;mathjax&gt;$5000, the IRS
[withholds](http://www.irs.gov/instructions/iw2g/ar02.html#d0e401) 25%
in federal income taxes. Additionally, the winnings are subject to state
taxes as well. For example, if I were to win, the great state of New
York would be entitled to about 6.8% (apparently also just for winnings
above $&lt;/mathjax&gt;5000).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After applying federal and state taxes to the prizes above $5000, we now
have an expected winnings&amp;nbsp;of&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \langle W \rangle = \left[1-(0.25 +
0.068)\right]\times\left(\frac{\mbox{Jackpot}}{175,711,536} +
\frac{\$ 250,000}{3,904,701} +\frac{\$ 10,000}{689,065}\right) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$+ \frac{\$ 150}{15,313} + \frac{\$ 150}{13,781}+ \frac{\$
10}{844} + \frac{\$ 7}{306} + \frac{\$ 3}{141} + \frac{\$
2}{75},$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which gives an expected net win (minus the &lt;mathjax&gt;$1 for the ticket) of $&lt;/mathjax&gt;1.10
for the &lt;mathjax&gt;$500 million annuity prize and $&lt;/mathjax&gt;0.55 for the $359 million
up-front lump&amp;nbsp;sum.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;re still in the black, but it&amp;#8217;s slowly slipping away. Is there
anything else we need to factor in? Well, yes. For one thing, winning
the jackpot qualifies us for the top tax bracket, so most of the
winnings would be taxed at the top marginal tax rate of 35%. Welcome to
the 1%, kids! &lt;a href="#note"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Changing the federal tax rate on the jackpot from 25% to 35% and
recalculating, we find net expected winnings of &lt;mathjax&gt;$0.81 for the $&lt;/mathjax&gt;500
million annuity and &lt;mathjax&gt;$0.34 for the $&lt;/mathjax&gt;359 million lump sum. Surprisingly,
it is still worth it in a statistical&amp;nbsp;sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Is it always like&amp;nbsp;this?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;One thing to keep in mind as we make these estimates is that this is a
&lt;em&gt;historically large&lt;/em&gt; jackpot. So even though it may be favorable to play
this time, this will not always be the case. In fact, we can find the
minimum jackpot value for which this is the&amp;nbsp;case.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The condition in which our expected return is a gain (rather than a
loss)&amp;nbsp;is&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \langle W \rangle - \$1.00 \&amp;gt; 0. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For simplicity, let&amp;#8217;s ignore the top marginal tax rate and just factor
in the 25% withholding and the 6.8% state tax. Solving for the minimum
jackpot using the expression for we found in the last section, we see&amp;nbsp;that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \mbox{Jackpot}_{min} = \$217\~\mbox{million}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Technically, this would have to be the amount actually awarded by the
payment method of your choice. The &lt;em&gt;stated&lt;/em&gt; jackpot is always the
annuity method (because it looks higher). The lump sum offering is &lt;em&gt;at
most&lt;/em&gt; about 70% of the stated jackpot. So if you want to take the lump
sum offering the &lt;em&gt;stated&lt;/em&gt; jackpot will need to&amp;nbsp;be&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \mbox{Jackpot}_{min} = \$217\~\mbox{million} / 0.7 =
\$310\~\mbox{million}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In fact, these values are likely a bit low, since we have not included
the increase to the marginal tax rate, nor have we included other
effects like having to split a prize (which seems to happen a lot) or
inflation effects if you take the prize in yearly&amp;nbsp;installments.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In any case, a quick look through the &lt;a href="http://www.megamillions.com/winners/jackpothistory.asp"&gt;jackpot
history&lt;/a&gt; shows
that these threshold values are only met occasionally. An eyeball
estimate puts about one jackpot per year that exceeds the (absolute)
minimum $217 million&amp;nbsp;threshold.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;So am I going to&amp;nbsp;win?&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;No. No, you will not. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BUT&lt;/span&gt; if you played record setting lotteries
hundreds of millions of times, you might see decent (\~10%) returns.
Although, it may just be easiest to, you know, &lt;em&gt;invest&lt;/em&gt; that&amp;nbsp;money.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h4&gt;Only One Useless&amp;nbsp;Footnote&lt;/h4&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] Although, to be fair, the top marginal tax rate is currently at
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/File:MarginalIncomeTax.svg"&gt;historical
lows&lt;/a&gt;. It could
always be worse&amp;#8230; &lt;a href="#back"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="MEGABUCKS"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="lottery"></category></entry><entry><title>Moving Pi-ctures</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/moving-pi-ctures.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T08:35:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-03-14:posts/moving-pi-ctures.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-YJBJw29pxZk/T1ribOQLS-I/AAAAAAAAAVA/xsJ-KAOJt5w/s1600/tv_pi.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-YJBJw29pxZk/T1ribOQLS-I/AAAAAAAAAVA/xsJ-KAOJt5w/s320/tv_pi.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  My &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; celebrates without&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today, as I&amp;#8217;m sure you&amp;#8217;re aware, is Pi Day - a day for the festive
consumption of pies and quiet self-reflection. In the spirit of the
holiday, I&amp;#8217;d like to present a point for discussion: &lt;em&gt;Everyone has a
great talent for at least one thing.&lt;/em&gt; That this is true for at least
&lt;em&gt;some&lt;/em&gt; people is seen through even a cursory glance at a history book:
George Washington was really good at leading revolutions, Michelangelo
was an outstanding ceiling painter &lt;a href="#note1"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, and Batman was the
best at solving complex riddles (especially in English, pero
&lt;em&gt;especialmente&lt;/em&gt; &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=RY1U_pXUxUo&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;en
español&lt;/a&gt;).
But I&amp;#8217;m certain that this holds for everyone. What&amp;#8217;s your talent? Mine,
as those of you who read this blog should know very well by now, is
certainly &lt;em&gt;not&lt;/em&gt; doing physics. Nope, my talent is watching &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt;. Seriously
guys, I watch &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; like a boss &lt;a href="#note2"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;. In light of this talent, I
thought I would describe a few instances in which I have seen pi
represented (for better or for worse) in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; and movies. Over the last
few months, I have been re-watching a lot of the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; show
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Psych"&gt;Psych&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; with my good friend and
fellow Virtuosi contributor, Matt &amp;#8220;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TT&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; Showbiz &lt;a href="#note3"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;. For the
uninitiated, &lt;em&gt;Psych&lt;/em&gt; is a detective show where the main characters
(Shawn and Gus) run a (fake) psychic detective agency, which allows them
to solve mysteries, engage in various shenanigans, and make an
inordinate number of references to &lt;em&gt;Tears for Fears&lt;/em&gt; frontman Curt Smith
&lt;a href="#note4"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;. In one of the episodes, Shawn and Gus enter a room where
a long train of digits is written across the top of the wall. It soon
becomes evident that these are the digits of pi and the camera is sure
to zoom in on the famous first few digits to reassure us. But there are
hundreds of digits written out and I have very little faith in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; prop
people when it comes to background mathematical expressions. So I
decided to check it&amp;nbsp;out.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sIqwUS9wlog/T17KQ7mU7nI/AAAAAAAAAV4/1hiiMuN-yxA/s1600/pi_psych1.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sIqwUS9wlog/T17KQ7mU7nI/AAAAAAAAAV4/1hiiMuN-yxA/s400/pi_psych1.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Pi on the Wall (click to enhance for&amp;nbsp;texture)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Using a neat little pi &lt;a href="http://www.angio.net/pi/piquery"&gt;searcher&lt;/a&gt;, I
checked to see if (and where) this sequence appeared in pi. Turns out
it&amp;#8217;s legit and (almost!) correct. The first 105 digits of pi (counting
after the three)&amp;nbsp;are:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;3.14159265358979323846264338327950288419716939937510582097494459230781640628620899862803482534211706&lt;strong&gt;798&lt;/strong&gt;2148&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where I have underlined the 99th, 100th, and 101st digits. Looking back
at the writing on the wall, we see that the 100th digit has been&amp;nbsp;duplicated.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6vQ2gmfNULw/T17Nb29jAvI/AAAAAAAAAWA/2hMW9vdU3S0/s1600/pi_psych.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6vQ2gmfNULw/T17Nb29jAvI/AAAAAAAAAWA/2hMW9vdU3S0/s400/pi_psych.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Very Almost&amp;nbsp;Pi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So close! Oh well, nobody is perfect. Even though there is an error
here, I very much appreciate that whoever was doing the set design
decided to use the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; digits of pi. All too often I see
nonsensical equations in the background of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; shows and movies when it
would take &lt;em&gt;exactly the same&lt;/em&gt; amount of work to put real equations
there. So congratulations to you, O nameless prop-making intern!, for
giving an accurate (well, to a part in 10^100) value of pi. Neat, so
are there any other &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; shows or movies that have pi in them? Well,
there&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=jo18VIoR2xU"&gt;Pi&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Pi&lt;/em&gt; is film
by Darren Aronofsky (&lt;em&gt;Requiem for a Dream&lt;/em&gt;, etc) about a mathematician
looking for patterns in the stock market. It&amp;#8217;s a pretty good movie with
a really cool
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9Cq_QO_4Cx4&amp;amp;feature=player_embedded"&gt;soundtrack&lt;/a&gt;
by Clint Mansell. It also appears to display the digits of pi in the
opening credits. But does it? To the Youtube-mobile! You can watch the
opening credits &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=L61x5mbE-jc"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; if
you like and here is a still image of the relevant&amp;nbsp;section.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pEbkgRx-PFw/T17UHYdfhwI/AAAAAAAAAWI/vsyzWd139pg/s1600/sad_pi.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-pEbkgRx-PFw/T17UHYdfhwI/AAAAAAAAAWI/vsyzWd139pg/s400/sad_pi.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;nbsp;Pi?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Looks pretty cool, huh? But once we get past the slick aesthetics, we
see that something doesn&amp;#8217;t seem right. This number they are showing
appears at first glance to be our good friend pi, but after the 8th
digit the cover is blown and we see that this is actually some impostor&amp;nbsp;number!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-5afmhwZOhWk/T17U-d1okrI/AAAAAAAAAWQ/KB7NHwwOvQg/s1600/verysadpi.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-5afmhwZOhWk/T17U-d1okrI/AAAAAAAAAWQ/KB7NHwwOvQg/s400/verysadpi.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  More like Darren&amp;nbsp;Aron-wrong-sky.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now, I fully understand that this has no bearing whatsoever on the film
and, in the grand scheme of things, is not a Big Deal. But it would have
been just as easy to put the &lt;em&gt;real&lt;/em&gt; digits of pi here instead of just
random filler. The only way that this could possibly be better than the
real deal would be if it is actually a secret code. I have not yet ruled
this out, as the movie is entirely about looking for meaning in
seemingly random numbers. Unfortunately, the difficulty in transcribing
the numbers from the screen greatly outweighs the very small chance that
this isn&amp;#8217;t just gibberish. Four hundred Quatloos to anyone who can tell
me if this is a code or&amp;nbsp;not!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] And an above average Ninja Turtle to boot. &lt;a href="#back1"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] Yes, I am putting my &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; watching skills on par with the talents of
George Washington. In fact, the stoic way in which I persevered through
the entirety of &lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Terminator:_The_Sarah_Connor_Chronicles"&gt;The Sarah Connor
Chronicles&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;in
under two weeks was described by historian David McCullough as
&amp;#8220;Washingtonian.&amp;#8221; These are simply facts. &lt;a href="#back2"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] The extra &amp;#8220;T&amp;#8221; is for extra talent. &lt;a href="#back3"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] A duo can &lt;em&gt;absolutely&lt;/em&gt; have a frontman. For evidence, feel free to
ask the not-George-Michael-guy from &lt;em&gt;Wham!&lt;/em&gt; or the not-Paul-Simon-guy
from &lt;em&gt;Simon &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; Garfunkel&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;a href="#back4"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pineapple"></category><category term="pi day"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>A Very Small Slice of Pi</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/a-very-small-slice-of-pi.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-14T08:22:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-03-14:posts/a-very-small-slice-of-pi.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q37nqPUh_t0/T2AJgUmFLKI/AAAAAAAAAWY/0rvkqKzmDBs/s1600/rhubarb.JPG"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-q37nqPUh_t0/T2AJgUmFLKI/AAAAAAAAAWY/0rvkqKzmDBs/s320/rhubarb.JPG" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Rhubarb pie (Source:&amp;nbsp;Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Some people know a &lt;em&gt;suspiciously&lt;/em&gt; large number of the digits of pi.
Perhaps you have met one of these people. They can typically be found
hiding behind bushes and under the counters at pastry shops, just&amp;#8230;
&lt;em&gt;waiting&lt;/em&gt;. At the slightest hint of a mention of pi, they will jump out
and start reciting the digits like there&amp;#8217;s a prize at the end. After
rattling off numbers for a few minutes they abruptly come to an end,
grin like an idiot, and walk away. It is an unpleasant encounter. The
sheer uselessness of this kind of thing has always bothered me, so I&amp;#8217;d
like to set a preliminary upper bound on the number of digits of pi that
could ever possibly potentially kind of be useful (maybe). For those
following along at home, now would be a good time to put on your
numerology hats. Alright, so I hear this thing pi is fairly useful when
dealing with circles. Let&amp;#8217;s say we want to make a really big circle and
have its diameter only deviate by a very small amount from the correct
value. To do this successfully, we will have to know pi fairly well.
Let&amp;#8217;s take this to extremes now. Suppose I want to put a circle around
the &lt;em&gt;entire visible universe&lt;/em&gt; such that the uncertainty in the diameter
is the size of a &lt;em&gt;single proton&lt;/em&gt;. What would be the fractional
uncertainty in the circumference in this case? If we know pi exactly,
then we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\delta C = \frac{\partial C}{\partial d} \delta
d = \pi \delta d = C \frac{\delta d}{d}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where d is the diameter
and C is the circumference. In other words, the fractional uncertainty
in the circumference is just &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta C}{C} = \frac{\delta
d}{d}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Using a femtometer for the size of a proton and 90 billion
light years for the size of the Universe &lt;a href="#note"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;, we get
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta C}{C} = \frac{\delta d}{d} =
\frac{10^{-15}\mbox{m}}{(90\times10^9)(3\times10^7\mbox{s})(3\times10^8\mbox{m
s}^{-1})} \sim\frac{10^{-15}}{10^{27}}\sim10^{-42}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Alright, so
how well do we need to know pi to get a similar fractional uncertainty?
Well, we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta \pi}{\pi} = \frac{\delta C}{C} =
10^{-42}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so we can afford an uncertainty in pi of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \delta \pi =
\pi \times 10^{-42}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and thus we&amp;#8217;ll need to know pi to about 42
digits. How&amp;#8217;s that for an
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Phrases_from_The_Hitchhiker%27s_Guide_to_the_Galaxy#Answer_to_the_Ultimate_Question_of_Life.2C_the_Universe.2C_and_Everything_.2842.29"&gt;answer&lt;/a&gt;?
So if we have a giant circle the size of the &lt;em&gt;entire visible universe&lt;/em&gt;,
we can find its diameter to within the size of a &lt;em&gt;single proton&lt;/em&gt; using
pi to 42 digits. Therefore, I adopt this as the maximal number of digits
that could ever prove useful in a physical sense (albeit under a
somewhat bizzarre set of circumstances). If reciting hundreds of digits
is what makes you happy, go for it. But 42 digits is more than enough pi
for&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] &amp;#8220;But I thought the Universe was only 13.7 billion years! What voodoo
is this!?&amp;#8221; Yeah, I know. See
&lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/startswithabang/2011/01/q_a_how_is_the_universe_so_big.php"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
for a nice explanation.&lt;a href="#back"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pi day"></category><category term="42"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>F-91 Revisited</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/f-91-revisited.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-12T00:57:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-03-12:posts/f-91-revisited.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-05FSvjIalzs/T11JuY0apyI/AAAAAAAAAVI/hHndDNPO5CE/s1600/dst_sam.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-05FSvjIalzs/T11JuY0apyI/AAAAAAAAAVI/hHndDNPO5CE/s400/dst_sam.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Farmer Uncle Sam&amp;#8230;with a rifle. (Image Credit:&amp;nbsp;Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was a sunny exception to the grey overcast rule of weather in
Ithaca. I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be overjoyed by this anomaly, spending the day
outside flying a kite or playing frisbee with a border collie in a
bandanna. Unfortunately, today was also the beginning of Daylight
Savings Time (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DST&lt;/span&gt;) - my least favorite day of the year. For my
colleagues unfamiliar with this temporal travesty (I&amp;#8217;m looking at you
Arizona), let me briefly explain &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DST&lt;/span&gt;. Once a year, the time lords steal
a single hour from us and place it in an escrow account for future
disbursement, presumably in some elaborate scheme to gain the favor of
hat-throwing farmer-clock hybrids (see image left). The details are a
bit murky, but the net result is that today I had one less hour to do my
very favorite thing in the whole wide world - sleep. It also means that
I have to set my watch, so I figured I&amp;#8217;d check in and see how well my
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2012/02/time-keeps-on-slippin.html"&gt;previous
model&lt;/a&gt;
for time-loss in my watch has held up. About a month ago, I looked at
how my watch slowly deviated from the &lt;a href="http://nist.time.gov/timezone.cgi?Eastern/d/-5/java"&gt;official
time&lt;/a&gt; (the original
post can be found
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2012/02/time-keeps-on-slippin.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
and a helpful clarification by Tom can be found
&lt;a href="http://blogs.scienceforums.net/swansont/archives/11014"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Based
on a little over 50 days worth of data, I found that my watch lost about
0.35 seconds per day against the official time. About 50 days have
passed since my last measurement and today when I set the watch, so I
thought it would be interesting to see how well my model fit the new
data. The old data are presented in Figure 1 in blue, the old best fit
line is in red, and the new data point (taken this morning) is in green.
As always, click through the plot for a larger&amp;nbsp;version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HqpuhvxXl8M/T1115Tz6lnI/AAAAAAAAAVQ/I1AUjQLXres/s1600/dst_update_long.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HqpuhvxXl8M/T1115Tz6lnI/AAAAAAAAAVQ/I1AUjQLXres/s400/dst_update_long.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new data point appears to be in fair agreement with the old best-fit
model, but it&amp;#8217;s a little hard to see here. Zooming in a bit, though, we
see that the model lies outside the error bar of the new data&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1euutOYSIrs/T1125Hi_XNI/AAAAAAAAAVY/tnWZ6N3mJJs/s1600/dst_update_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1euutOYSIrs/T1125Hi_XNI/AAAAAAAAAVY/tnWZ6N3mJJs/s400/dst_update_short.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is this a big deal? Not really. But if it will help you sleep at
night, we can redo the fitting with the new data point included to see
how much things change. The the plots with the updated model to include
all data points are provided below with the old data in blue and the new
point in&amp;nbsp;green.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-oIeLFmzJgKI/T115TGf3laI/AAAAAAAAAVg/RHPJuP9UrKk/s1600/dst_newfit_long.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-oIeLFmzJgKI/T115TGf3laI/AAAAAAAAAVg/RHPJuP9UrKk/s400/dst_newfit_long.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new model looks a whole lot like the old one, except the best fit
line now appears to go through the new data point. Zooming in a little,
we see that it does indeed fall within the error bars of our new&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-EUf50O2-jjQ/T11514CpS_I/AAAAAAAAAVo/Ryt2v1LOeVk/s1600/dst_newfit_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-EUf50O2-jjQ/T11514CpS_I/AAAAAAAAAVo/Ryt2v1LOeVk/s400/dst_newfit_short.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so the new model fits with our new point, but how much did the
model have to change? Well, the fit to just the old data gave an offset
of 0.36 seconds and a loss rate of 0.35 seconds per day. The new model
has an offset of 0.40 seconds and a loss rate of 0.348 seconds per day.
Overall, not a significant change.
It looks as though I may continue to not worry about the accuracy of my
watch. I have set it to match the official time and have no intention of
fiddling with it until I have to set it again at the end of Daylight
Savings Time - my favorite day of the&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="daylight savings time"></category><category term="casio"></category></entry><entry><title>Time Keeps On Slippin’</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/time-keeps-on-slippin-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-02-12T22:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-02-12:posts/time-keeps-on-slippin-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-rtzREUF0wYM/TyX0orGHkpI/AAAAAAAAASk/hsRZAwtg7H4/s1600/casi_f91w.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-rtzREUF0wYM/TyX0orGHkpI/AAAAAAAAASk/hsRZAwtg7H4/s320/casi_f91w.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  This is picture of a watch. (Source:&amp;nbsp;Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, the Virtuosi Action Team (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;VAT&lt;/span&gt;) assembled for
lunch and the discussion quickly and unexpectedly turned to watches. As
Nic and Alemi argued over the finer parts of fancy-dancy watch
ownership, I looked down at my watch: the lowly &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casio_F91W"&gt;Casio
F-91W&lt;/a&gt;. Though it certainly
isn&amp;#8217;t fancy, it is inexpensive, durable, and could potentially win me an
all-expense paid trip to the
&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/apr/25/guantanamo-files-casio-wristwatch-alqaida"&gt;Caribbean&lt;/a&gt;.
But how &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; of a watch is it? To find out, I decided to time it
against the official &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; time for a couple of months. Incidentally,
about half-way in I found out that Chad over at &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/principles/"&gt;Uncertain
Principles&lt;/a&gt; had done essentially
the same thing
&lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/principles/2011/05/the_testing_of_time_measuring.php"&gt;already&lt;/a&gt;.
No matter, science is still fun even if you aren&amp;#8217;t the first person to
do it. So here&amp;#8217;s my &amp;#8220;new-to-me&amp;#8221; analysis. Alright, so how do we go about
quantifying how &amp;#8220;good&amp;#8221; a watch is? Well, there seem to be two main
things we can test. The first of these is accuracy. That is, how close
does this watch come to the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; time (according to some time
system)? If the official time is 3:00 pm and my watch claims it is 5:00
am, then it is not very accurate. The second measure of &amp;#8220;good-ness&amp;#8221; is
precision or, in watch parlance, stability. This is essentially a
measure of the consistency of the watch. If I have a watch that is
consistently off by 5 minutes from the official time, then it is not
accurate but it is still stable. In essence, a very consistent watch
would be just as good as an accurate one, because we can always just
subtract off the known offset. To test any of the above measures of how
&amp;#8220;good&amp;#8221; my cheap watch is, we will need to know the actual time. We will
adopt the official &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; time as provided on the &lt;a href="http://nist.time.gov/timezone.cgi?Eastern/d/-5/java"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt;
website&lt;/a&gt;. This time
is determined and maintained by a collection of really impressive atomic
clocks. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NIST-F1"&gt;One of these&lt;/a&gt; is in
Colorado and the other is secretly guarded by an ever-vigilant Time Lord
(see Figure&amp;nbsp;1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EXMf5o9a4GI/TzCRcaMjjVI/AAAAAAAAASs/FlqyjHbJS9Q/s1600/flavor_flav.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EXMf5o9a4GI/TzCRcaMjjVI/AAAAAAAAASs/FlqyjHbJS9Q/s320/flavor_flav.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 1: Flavor Flav, Keeper of the&amp;nbsp;Time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 9:00:00 am &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EST&lt;/span&gt; on November 30th, I synchronized my watch with the
time displayed on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt; website. For the next 54 days, I kept track
of the difference between my watch an the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt; time. On the 55th day, I
forgot to check the time and the experiment promptly ended. The results
are plotted below in Figure 2 (and, as with all plots, click through for
a larger&amp;nbsp;version).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hscjUIehrHQ/TzCYqNhcsYI/AAAAAAAAATE/eAz3O5KlAcY/s1600/time_fit_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hscjUIehrHQ/TzCYqNhcsYI/AAAAAAAAATE/eAz3O5KlAcY/s400/time_fit_short.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 2: Best-fit to time&amp;nbsp;difference&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from Figure 2, the amount of time the watch lost over the
timing period appears to be fairly linear. There does appear to be a
jagged-ness to the data, though. This is mainly caused by the fact that
both the watch and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt; website only report times to the nearest
second. As a result, the finest time resolution I was willing to report
was about half a second. Adopting an uncertainty of half a second, I did
a least-squares fit of a straight line to the data and found that the
watch loses about 0.35 seconds per day. As far as accuracy goes, that&amp;#8217;s
not bad! No matter what, I&amp;#8217;ll have to set my watch at least twice a year
to appease the Daylight Savings Gods. The longest stretch between
resetting is about 8 months. If I synchronize my watch with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt;
time to &amp;#8220;spring forward&amp;#8221; in March, it will only lose about &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t_{loss}
= 8\~\mbox{months} \times 30\frac{\mbox{days}}{\mbox{month}}
\times 0.35 \frac{\mbox{sec}}{\mbox{day}} = 84\~\mbox{sec} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
before I have to re-synchronize to &amp;#8220;fall back&amp;#8221; in November. Assuming the
loss rate is constant, I&amp;#8217;ll never be more than about a minute and a half
off the &amp;#8220;actual&amp;#8221; time. That&amp;#8217;s good enough for me. Furthermore, if the
watch is &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt; losing 0.35 seconds per day and I know how long
ago I last synchronized, I can always correct for the offset. In this
case, I can always know the official time to within a second (assuming I
can add). But &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the watch consistent? That&amp;#8217;s a good question. The
simplest means of finding the stability of the watch would be to look at
the timing residuals between the data and the model. That is, we will
consider how &amp;#8220;off&amp;#8221; each point is from our constant rate-loss model. A
plot of the results is shown below in Figure&amp;nbsp;3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-13ULtvOlXuU/TzCpp6LGvfI/AAAAAAAAATM/8rybD1lxZOo/s1600/residuals.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-13ULtvOlXuU/TzCpp6LGvfI/AAAAAAAAATM/8rybD1lxZOo/s400/residuals.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 3: Timing&amp;nbsp;residuals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Figure 3, we see that the data fit the model pretty well. There&amp;#8217;s a
little bit of a wiggle going on there and we see some strong short-term
correlations (the latter is an artifact of the fact that I could only
get times to the nearest second). To get some sense of the timing
stability from the residuals, we can calculate the standard deviation,
which will give us a figure for how &amp;#8220;off&amp;#8221; the data typically are from
the model. The standard deviation of the residuals is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \sigma_{res}
= 0.19\~\mbox{sec}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; A good guess at the fractional stability of the
watch would then just be the standard deviation divided by the sampling
interval, &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{\sigma_{res}}{T} = 0.19\~\mbox{sec} \times
\frac{1}{1\~\mbox{day}} \times
\frac{1\~\mbox{day}}{24\times3600\~\mbox{sec}} \approx
2\times10^{-6}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; In words, this means that each &amp;#8220;tick&amp;#8221; of the watch
is consistent with the average &amp;#8220;tick&amp;#8221; value to about 2 parts in a
million. That&amp;#8217;s nice&amp;#8230;but isn&amp;#8217;t there something &lt;em&gt;fancier&lt;/em&gt; we could be
doing? Well, I have been wanting to learn about &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_variance"&gt;Allan
variance&lt;/a&gt; for some time
now, so let&amp;#8217;s try that. The Allan variance (refs: &lt;a href="http://www.ino.it/~azavatta/References/Allan.pdf"&gt;original
paper&lt;/a&gt; and a
&lt;a href="http://tf.boulder.nist.gov/general/pdf/118.pdf"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;) can be used to
find the fractional frequency stability of an oscillator over a wide
range of time scales. Roughly speaking, the Allan variance tells us how
averaging our residuals over different chunks of time affects the
stability of our data. The square root of the Allan variance,
essentially the &amp;#8220;Allan standard deviation,&amp;#8221; is plotted against various
averaging times for our data below in Figure&amp;nbsp;4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-_zhCroHDoNE/TzC7XYkDZ1I/AAAAAAAAATU/mCaspxYhlxA/s1600/allan_variance.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-_zhCroHDoNE/TzC7XYkDZ1I/AAAAAAAAATU/mCaspxYhlxA/s400/allan_variance.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 4: Allan variance of our&amp;nbsp;residuals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Figure 4, we see that as we increase the averaging time from one
day to ten days, the Allan deviation decreases. That is, the averaging
reduces the amount of variation in the frequency of the data, making it
more stable. However, at around 10 days of averaging time it seems as
though we hit a floor in how low we can go. Since the error bars get
really big here, this may not be a real effect. If it is real, though,
this would be indicative of some low-frequency noise in our oscillator.
For those who prefer colors, this would be
&amp;#8220;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colors_of_noise"&gt;red&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; noise. Since the
Allan deviation gives the fractional frequency stability of the
oscillator, we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\sigma_A = \frac{\delta f}{f} =
\frac{\delta(1/t)}{1/t} = \frac{\delta t}{t}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Looking at the
plot, we see that with an averaging time of one day, the fractional time
stability of the watch is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta t}{t} \approx
2\times10^{-6}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which corresponds nicely to our previously
calculated value. If we average over chunks that are ten days long
instead, we get a fractional stability of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{\delta t}{t}
\approx 10^{-7}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which would correspond to a deviation from our
model of about 0.008 seconds. Not bad. The initial question that started
this whole ordeal was &amp;#8220;How good is my watch?&amp;#8221; and I think we can safely
answer that with &amp;#8220;as good as I&amp;#8217;ll ever need it to be.&amp;#8221; Hooray for cheap
and effective&amp;nbsp;electronics!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="allan variance"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="casio"></category></entry><entry><title>How Long Will a Bootprint Last on the Moon?</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-01-01T20:46:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-01-01:posts/how-long-will-a-bootprint-last-on-the-moon-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-gEyp9bylwcQ/Tv5v7PlugjI/AAAAAAAAARU/OnVdFTPRGkI/s1600/bootprint_buzz.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-gEyp9bylwcQ/Tv5v7PlugjI/AAAAAAAAARU/OnVdFTPRGkI/s320/bootprint_buzz.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Buzz Aldrin&amp;#8217;s bootprint (source:&amp;nbsp;Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, I stumbled across a bunch of
&lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/mission_pages/apollo/revisited/index.html"&gt;pictures&lt;/a&gt;
of Apollo landing sites taken by one of the cameras onboard the Lunar
Reconnaissance Orbiter. The images have a resolution high enough that
you can resolve features on the surface down to about a meter. Looking
at the Apollo 17 &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/images/content/584392main_M168000580LR_ap17_area.jpg"&gt;landing
site&lt;/a&gt;,
you can see the trails of both astronauts and a moon buggy. It&amp;#8217;s pretty
cool. It also got me thinking about how long the landing sites would be
preserved. More specifically, I want to know how long Buzz Aldrin&amp;#8217;s
right bootprint (shown, incidentally, to the left) will last on the
Moon. Since the Moon has no atmosphere, the wind and rain that would
weather away a similar bootprint here on Earth are not present and it
seems as though the print would last a really long time. But how long?
Let&amp;#8217;s try to quantify it &lt;a href="#footnote-yariv"&gt;[1]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Pick Your Poison
Before we get going, we need to figure out what physical process would
be most important in erasing a bootprint from the Moon. Although the
Moon lacks the conventional &amp;#8220;weathering&amp;#8221; we experience on Earth (due to
wind, rain, etc), it does experience something called &amp;#8220;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Space_weathering"&gt;space
weathering&lt;/a&gt;.&amp;#8221; Space
weathering is the changing of the lunar surface due to cosmic rays,
micrometeorite collisions, regular meteorite collisions, and the solar
wind &lt;a href="#footnote-wind"&gt;[2]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Of these phenomena, the most apparent
and well-studied would be the meteorites which have covered the Moon in
craters. We adopt the meteorite impact as our primary means of wiping
out a bootprint and restate our question as follows: &amp;#8220;How long would it
take for a meteorite to hit the Moon such that the resulting crater
wipes out Aldrin&amp;#8217;s right bootprint?&amp;#8221; Background As it is currently
stated, we can answer our question if we knew the rate of formation and
size distribution of the craters on the Moon. We could count up all the
craters on the Moon (or a particular region of interest) and tabulate
their sizes. This would give us the size distribution. It would also
give us a headache and potentially drive us to lunacy
&lt;a href="#footnote-forced"&gt;[3]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Luckily, someone has beat us to it. &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1966MNRAS.134..245C"&gt;Cross
(1966)&lt;/a&gt; used images
from the Ranger 7 and 8 missions to count craters and determine the size
distribution of craters in three regions of the Moon. The data for the
crater distribution in the Sea of Tranquility (where Apollo 11 landed)
are given in the figure below. Cross found that in the Sea of
Tranquility, the number of craters with diameters greater than X meters
(per million square kilometers) is given by: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N(d\&amp;gt;X) =
10^{10}\left(\frac{X}{1\~\mbox{m}}\right)^{-2}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which holds for
craters with diameters between 1 meter and 10 kilometers (see figure&amp;nbsp;below).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-kHxcn_PTd5o/TwDg3XGAcqI/AAAAAAAAARg/jl-kb22JD-Y/s1600/fig2.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-kHxcn_PTd5o/TwDg3XGAcqI/AAAAAAAAARg/jl-kb22JD-Y/s400/fig2.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 2 from Cross&amp;nbsp;(1966)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can also estimate the rate at which craters are formed from this
data. If we assume that the craters formed at a constant rate over the
age of the Moon (about 4 billion years), then we get about 2.5 craters
with diameters above 1 meter formed in a million square kilometer area
every year. This is a &amp;#8220;crater flux&amp;#8221; for the Moon. Written another way,
the crater flux in the Sea of Tranquility is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$F \approx
1\~{\mbox{km}}^{-2} \frac{1}{4\times10^5\~\mbox{yr}}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so we get
that roughly one crater with diameter greater than 1 meter is formed on
a square kilometer of the Moon once every 400,000 years or so. We now
have enough information to do some simulations. Simulation I wrote up a
code that simulates craters being formed on a 1 square kilometer patch
of the Moon. A crater is randomly placed in the 1 square kilometer
region with a diameter pulled from the above distribution. The bootprint
is placed at the center of the grid and craters are formed until we get
a &amp;#8220;hit.&amp;#8221; At that point, the time is recorded and the run stops. As a
sanity check, I thought it would be fun to just let the simulation run
without caring if the boot was hit or not. By simulating the craters in
this way for 4 billion years, I should get something that looks like the
Moon at the present day. Here&amp;#8217;s a 200 m square from my simulation:
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DoFPG23CGwg/TwDqo-7GoQI/AAAAAAAAARs/QJW3RxeXFWI/s1600/mymoon_wticks.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-DoFPG23CGwg/TwDqo-7GoQI/AAAAAAAAARs/QJW3RxeXFWI/s400/mymoon_wticks.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
and here&amp;#8217;s a picture of the same-sized region on the surface of the&amp;nbsp;Moon:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-qWW5dU-aEN8/TwDrDLPy93I/AAAAAAAAAR4/XGOywC79NFU/s1600/200metersquare.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-qWW5dU-aEN8/TwDrDLPy93I/AAAAAAAAAR4/XGOywC79NFU/s320/200metersquare.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Cropped from &lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/images/content/584398main_M168353795RE_25cm_AP12_area.jpg"&gt;this image&lt;/a&gt; (Source:&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;LRO&lt;/span&gt;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Just eyeballing it, things look pretty good. Now it&amp;#8217;s time for the
actual simulation. I ran the simulation 10,000 times and tabulated the
amount of time needed before the bootprint was hit. The figure below
gives the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Cumulative_distribution_function"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;CDF&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt; for
the hit times in the simulation. That is, for each time T, we find the
fraction of simulations in which the bootprint got hit in a time less
than or equal to T. The dashed lines in the plot indicate the amount of
time needed to pass for half of the simulations to have recorded a hit.
This time turns out to be about 24 billion&amp;nbsp;years.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-L2WLnCepUiw/TwDs7X_njkI/AAAAAAAAASE/jS_-I0Eem4k/s1600/hit_cdf.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-L2WLnCepUiw/TwDs7X_njkI/AAAAAAAAASE/jS_-I0Eem4k/s400/hit_cdf.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  (Click for larger, actually readable&amp;nbsp;version)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Conclusions and Caveats Based on the simulations, the bootprint on the
Moon would have about even odds of lasting at least 20 billion years
&lt;em&gt;if&lt;/em&gt; the primary means of destruction is through the formation of a
crater from a meteorite. However, there are a few caveats that should be
addressed. These deal with either the details of the simulation or the
assumptions we have made. In the simulation, we just took at 1 km square
patch of the moon and scaled back the &amp;#8220;crater flux&amp;#8221; accordingly.
However, this does not fully account for all possible craters that can
form. For example, our simulation would miss an event that hit 50 km
away from the target, but had a diameter of 100 km. Obviously this would
hit the target, but we are only seeding craters in the 1 square km
region. This would mean that the actual lifetime of the bootprint would
be less than our 24 billion year figure. Re-running with a 10km by 10km
square region, we find a lifetime of 18 billion years. Thus, an increase
in area by a factor of 100 only reduces the age by 25%. Considering
areas much larger than this makes the simulation prohibitively slow, but
the order unity effect does not seem too significant. Additionally, we
have made a number of assumptions. The big one is that we have assumed
that the craters currently seen on the Moon were formed uniformly in
time. In fact, a large fraction of the craters may have been formed when
the Moon was still very young (see &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Late_Heavy_Bombardment"&gt;Late Heavy
Bombardment&lt;/a&gt;). If
this were the case, we would have greatly overestimated the rate of
crater formation and thus underestimated the time needed to hit the
bootprint. In spite of these caveats, let&amp;#8217;s take our value of 20 billion
years to be accurate. What else can we say? Well, if we are right then
we are wrong because the Moon may not last that long (and it&amp;#8217;s hard to
have bootprints on the Moon without a Moon). Current
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Sun#Life_cycle"&gt;estimates&lt;/a&gt; have that the
Sun will expand into a red giant and (potentially) destroy the Earth
(and the Moon) in about 5 billion years. So a record of the Apollo
astronauts&amp;#8217; boot sizes could potentially last as long as the Moon
&lt;a href="#footnote-nixon"&gt;[4]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href=""&gt;&lt;/a&gt;. Not bad. Footnotes and Such
[1] Now with linked footnotes so Yariv doesn&amp;#8217;t have to scroll!
&lt;a href="#back-yariv"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;
[2] There was a fairly recent press release about Coronal Mass Ejections
from the Sun &amp;#8220;sandblasting&amp;#8221; the lunar surface. For more info, check
&lt;a href="http://www.nasa.gov/topics/solarsystem/features/dream-cme.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
and note the acronymic acrobatics needed to make them the &amp;#8220;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DREAM&lt;/span&gt; team.&amp;#8221;
But it&amp;#8217;s totally worth it. &lt;a href="#back-wind"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;
[3] A horribly forced pun. But it&amp;#8217;s totally worth it.
&lt;a href="#back-forced"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;
[4] Also, &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Lunar_plaque"&gt;Nixon&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="#back-nixon"&gt;[back]&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="footprint"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="moon"></category></entry><entry><title>Betelgeuse, Betelgeuse, Betelgeuse!</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/betelgeuse-betelgeuse-betelgeuse-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-11-05T01:25:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-11-05:posts/betelgeuse-betelgeuse-betelgeuse-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-6s6rSrItOdk/TrS6st3tdVI/AAAAAAAAAPk/GpGfjY5KZ3Y/s1600/betelgeuse.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-6s6rSrItOdk/TrS6st3tdVI/AAAAAAAAAPk/GpGfjY5KZ3Y/s320/betelgeuse.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  A very cold person points out&amp;nbsp;Betelgeuse&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Betelgeuse is a massive star at the very end of its life and could
explode any second now!&lt;/em&gt; Every time I hear that I get really &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
excited. Like a kid in a candy store that&amp;#8217;s about to see a star blow up
like nobody&amp;#8217;s business. This giddiness will last for a solid minute
before I realize that &amp;#8220;any second now&amp;#8221; is taken on astronomical
timescales and roughly translates to &amp;#8220;sometime in the next million years
maybe possibly.&amp;#8221; Then I feel sad. But you know what always cheers me up?
Calculating things! Hooray! So let&amp;#8217;s take a look at the ways Betelgeuse
could end its life (even if it&amp;#8217;s not going to happen tomorrow) and how
these would affect Earth. First, a little background. Betelgeuse is the
bright orangey-red star that sits at the head/armpit of Orion. It is one
of the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/List_of_brightest_stars"&gt;brightest&lt;/a&gt;
stars in the night sky. Its distance has been measured by the
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Hipparcos"&gt;Hipparcos&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt;satellite to be
about 200 parsecs [1] from Earth (about 600 light years). Betelgeuse is
at least 10 times as massive as our Sun and has a diameter that would
easily accomodate the orbit of Mars. In fact, the star is big enough and
close enough that it can actually be spatially resolved by the Hubble
Space Telescope! Being so big and bright, Betelgeuse is destined to die
young, going out with a bang as a
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Supernova#Core_collapse"&gt;core-collapse&lt;/a&gt;
supernova. This massive explosion ejects a good deal of &amp;#8220;star stuff&amp;#8221;
into interstellar space [2] and leaves behind either a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Neutron_star"&gt;neutron
star&lt;/a&gt; or a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Black_hole"&gt;black
hole&lt;/a&gt;. Alright, now that we&amp;#8217;re
all caught up, let&amp;#8217;s turn our focus on this &amp;#8220;massive explosion&amp;#8221; bit.
What kind of energy scale are we talking about if Betelgeuse blows up?
Well, a pretty good upper bound would be if all of the star&amp;#8217;s mass (10
solar masses worth!) were converted directly to energy, so &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E_{max} =
mc^2 =
10M_{\odot}\times\left(\frac{2\times10^{30}\~\mbox{kg}}{1\~M_{\odot}}\right)\times
\left(3\times10^8\~\mbox{m/s}\right)^2 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which is about &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
E_{max} \sim 10^{48}\~\mbox{J} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and that&amp;#8217;s nothing to shake a
stick at. But remember, this is if the &lt;em&gt;entire star&lt;/em&gt; were converted
directly to energy, and that would be hard to do. Typical fusion
efficiencies are about \~1% [3], so let&amp;#8217;s say a reasonable estimate for
the total nuclear energy available is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E_{nuc} \sim \eta_{f}
\times E_{max} \sim 10^{-2} \times 10^{48}\~\mbox{J} \sim
10^{46}\~\mbox{J}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; This is the total energy released by a typical
supernova. As it turns out though, 99% of this energy is carried away in
the form of neutrinos and only about 1% is carried away in photons.
Since we are mainly concerned with how this explosion will affect Earth,
and the neutrinos will just pass on by, we will only consider the 1% of
energy released in photons that would reasonably interact with Earth.
That gives us &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E_{ph} \sim 0.01 \times E_{nuc} \sim
10^{44}\~\mbox{J}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Neato, so that&amp;#8217;s the total amount of energy
released in a supernova in the form of photons. How much of this energy
would be deposited at the Earth if Betelgeuse exploded? Well, if the
energy is deposited isotropically (that is, the same in all directions),
then the fluence (or time integrated energy flux) is given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F_{ph}
= \frac{E_{ph}}{4\pi d^2}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; All this is saying is that the total
energy release by the supernova spreads out uniformly over a sphere of
radius d, so the fluence will give us the amount of energy deposited in
each square meter of that sphere (the units of fluence here are J/m^2).
The total energy deposited on Earth is then &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E_{\oplus} = F_{ph}
\times \pi R^2_{\oplus}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Hot dog! Let&amp;#8217;s plug in some numbers,
already. The total energy deposited on the Earth by a symmetrically
exploding Betelgeuse at a distance of d = 200 pc (where 1 pc = 3 &lt;em&gt;
10^16 m) is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$E_{\oplus}=\frac{E_{ph}}{4\pi d^2}\times\pi
R^2_{\oplus}\sim
10^{19}\~\mbox{J}\left(\frac{E_{ph}}{10^{44}\~\mbox{J}}\right)\left(\frac{d}{200\~\mbox{pc}}\right)^{-2}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Well, 10^19 J certainly &lt;/em&gt;seems* like a lot of energy. In fact, it is
roughly the amount of energy contained in the entire nuclear arsenal of
the United States [4]. But it is spread over the entire atmosphere. Is
there a way to gauge how this would affect life on Earth? We could see
how much it would heat up the atmosphere using specific heats: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E =
m_{atm}c_{air}\Delta T $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where c is the specific heat of air
(\~10^3 J per kg per K). Oops, looks like we need to know the mass of
the atmosphere. But we can figure this out, the answer is pushing right
down on our heads! We know the pressure at the surface of the Earth (1
atm = 101 kPa) and that pressure is just the result of the weight of the
atmosphere pushing down on us. Since pressure is just force / area, we
have &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P = F/A = m_{atm}g / A_{\oplus} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ m_{atm} =
\frac{P\times4\pi
R^2_{\oplus}}{g}=\frac{10^5\~\mbox{Pa}\times4\pi
(6\times10^6\~\mbox{m})^2}{9.8\~\mbox{m/s}^2}\approx4\times10^{18}\~\mbox{kg}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Neato, gang. So we could see a temperature rise of about &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \Delta T =
\frac{E_{ph}}{m_{atm}c_{air}}=\frac{10^{19}\~\mbox{J}}{4\times10^{18}\~\mbox{kg}\times10^3\~\mbox{J/
kg K}}\approx0.003\~\mbox{K}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; or three one-thousandths of a degree.
Remember, too, that this will be an upper bound since we are assuming
that all this energy is deposited into the atmosphere before it has a
chance to cool. In fact, if the energy is deposited over the course of
hours or days, this value will be much less. So it looks like we&amp;#8217;ve
wrapped this thing up: Betelgeuse exploding will most certainly not put
the Earth in any danger. Or did we? We have considered the case of a
symmetric supernova, but there&amp;#8217;s more than one way to blow up a star.
Massive stars can also end their lives in a fantastic explosion called a
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Gamma-ray_burst"&gt;gamma-ray burst&lt;/a&gt; (GRBs to
the hep cats that study them, some fun facts relegated to [5]). GRBs are
still an intense area of current study, but the current picture (for one
type of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GRB&lt;/span&gt;, at least) is that they are the result of a star blowing up
with the energy of the explosion focussed into two narrow beams (see
picture below). Since the flux isn&amp;#8217;t distributed over the whole sphere,
GRBs can be seen at much greater distances than a typical&amp;nbsp;supernova.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-siXXiFnQWHY/TrITJA8z_sI/AAAAAAAAAPU/qStD4_9qLBI/s1600/grb.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-siXXiFnQWHY/TrITJA8z_sI/AAAAAAAAAPU/qStD4_9qLBI/s320/grb.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Example of a gamma-ray burst, with the explosion in two&amp;nbsp;beams.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So how will this change our answer? Well, it&amp;#8217;s going to change the
fluence we calculated above. Instead of spreading the energy out over
the whole sphere, it&amp;#8217;s only going to go to some fraction of the 4pi
steradians. So we get &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F_{ph} = \frac{E_{ph}}{4\pi f_{\Omega}
d^2}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where f_{omega} is called the &amp;#8220;beaming fraction&amp;#8221; and tells us
what fraction of the sphere the energy goes through. Typical &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GRB&lt;/span&gt; beams
range from 1 to 10 degrees in radius. Converting this to radians, we can
find the beaming fraction as &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ f_{\Omega} = \frac{2 \times \pi
\theta^2}{4\pi} \approx
10^{-4}\left(\frac{\theta}{1^\circ}\right)^2,$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so the beaming
fraction is 10^-4 and 10^-2 for a beam angle of 1 degree and 10
degrees, respectively. Alright, so now we can redo the calculations we
did for the supernova case, but keeping this beaming fraction around.
The total amount of energy that would hit Earth is then about
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$E_{\oplus}=\frac{E_{ph}}{4\pi f_{\Omega} d^2}\times\pi
R^2_{\oplus}\sim
10^{23}\~\mbox{J}\left(\frac{E_{ph}}{10^{44}\~\mbox{J}}\right)\left(\frac{d}{200\~\mbox{pc}}\right)^{-2}\left(\frac{\theta}{1^\circ}\right)^{-2}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Holy sixth-of-a-moley! Continuing as we did above, we find that this
could potentially heat up the atmosphere by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \Delta T =
\frac{E_{ph}}{m_{atm}c_{air}}=\frac{10^{23}\~\mbox{J}}{4\times10^{18}\~\mbox{kg}\times10^3\~\mbox{J/
kg
K}}\approx3\~\mbox{K}\left(\frac{\theta}{1^\circ}\right)^{-2},
$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which is certainly non-negligible. Now, this won&amp;#8217;t destroy the planet
[6], but it could make things really uncomfortable. This will be
especially true when you realize that a fair amount of the energy
carried away from a gamma-ray burst is in the form of (wait for it&amp;#8230;)
gamma-rays, which will wreck havoc on your &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNA&lt;/span&gt;. Remember, though, that
this is an absolute worst-case scenario since we have assumed the
smallest beaming angle. But this may still make us a little nervous, so
is there anyway to figure out if Betelgeuse could, in fact, beam a
gamma-ray burst towards Earth? Yes, yes there is. Jets and beams like
those in GRBs typically point along the rotation axis of the star [7].
If we could determine the rotational axis of Betelgeuse, then we could
say whether or not there&amp;#8217;s a chance it&amp;#8217;s pointed towards us. It just so
happens that Betelgeuse is the only star (aside from our Sun) that is
spatially resolved. If you could measure spectra along the star, you
could look for Doppler shifting of absorption lines and say something
about the velocity at the surface of the star. Luckily, this has already
been done for us (see, for example &lt;a href="http://adsabs.harvard.edu/abs/1998AJ....116.2501U"&gt;Uitenbroek et al.
1998&lt;/a&gt;). These
measurements are hard to do since the star is only a few pixels wide,
but it appears as though the rotation axis is inclined to the
line-of-sight by about 20 degrees (see figure below). That means this
would require a beam with at least a 20 degree radius to hit the Earth.
This appears to be outside the typical ranges observed. So even if
Betelgeuse were to explode in a gamma-ray burst, the beam would miss
Earth and hit some dumb other planet nobody cares&amp;nbsp;about.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-xYILwh0eLEM/TrSTBxflbxI/AAAAAAAAAPc/Amma1aQtmPU/s1600/rotation.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-xYILwh0eLEM/TrSTBxflbxI/AAAAAAAAAPc/Amma1aQtmPU/s400/rotation.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure reproduced from Uitenbroek et al.&amp;nbsp;(1998)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so the moral of the story is that Betelgeuse is completely
harmless to people on Earth. When it does explode, it will be a
brilliant supernova that would likely be visible at least a little bit
during the day. It will be the coolest thing that anyone alive (if there
are people&amp;#8230;) will ever see. Sadly, this explosion could take place at
just about any time during the next million years. Assuming a uniform
distribution over this time period and a human lifetime of order 100
years, there is something like a 1 in 10,000 chance you&amp;#8217;ll see this in
your life. Feel free to hope for a spectacular astronomical sight, but
don&amp;#8217;t lose sleep worrying about being hurt by Betelgeuse!
&lt;strong&gt;Semi-excessive Footnotes:&lt;/strong&gt; [1] This has nothing to do with the Kessel
Run. For a description of the actual distance unit see
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Parsec"&gt;Wikipedia&lt;/a&gt;. For a circuitous
retconning to correct for one throwaway line in &lt;em&gt;Star Wars&lt;/em&gt;, see
&lt;a href="http://starwars.wikia.com/wiki/Kessel_Run"&gt;Wookieepedia&lt;/a&gt;. [2] This is
how anything heavier than helium gets distributed throughout the
universe. The hydrogen and helium formed after the Big Bang gets fused
into heavier elements in stars and then dispersed out through
supernovae. In fact, most things heavier than Iron actually &lt;em&gt;require&lt;/em&gt;
supernovae to even exist. If you have any gold on you right now (I&amp;#8217;m
looking at you Mr. T), that only exists &lt;em&gt;because a star exploded!&lt;/em&gt; [3]
Let&amp;#8217;s consider the case of turning 4 protons into a Helium nucleus.
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Helium-4"&gt;Helium-4&lt;/a&gt; has a binding energy
of about 28 MeV, which means that the total energy of a bound He-4
nucleus is 28 MeV less than its free protons and neutrons (in other
words, we need to put in 28 MeV to break it up). So the process of
turning 4 protons into a Helium nucleus gives off 28 MeV worth of
energy. But we had a total of 4 times 1000 MeV worth of matter we could
have turned into energy. Thus, the process was 28 MeV/4000 MeV \~ 0.7%
efficient at turning matter into energy. [4] Sometime last year, the
United States
&lt;a href="http://www.defense.gov/npr/docs/10-05-03_Fact_Sheet_US_Nuclear_Transparency__FINAL_w_Date.pdf"&gt;disclosed&lt;/a&gt;
that its nuclear arsenal as of Sept 2009 was something like 5000
warheads. Assume these to be Megaton warheads. A Megaton is about 4 &lt;em&gt;
10^15 J, so the total energy in the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;US&lt;/span&gt; arsenal is about 5000 * 4 &lt;/em&gt;
10^15 J = 2 * 10^19 J. [5] A fun fact about GRBs: They were
discovered by a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Vela_(satellite)"&gt;military
satellite&lt;/a&gt; looking for
illegal nuclear tests, which would emit some gamma-rays. Instead of
seeing a signal on Earth, they saw bursts coming from space. I really
really hope that someone&amp;#8217;s first thought was that the Russians were
testing nukes on the Moon or something. &lt;em&gt;We must not allow a moon-nuke
gap!&lt;/em&gt; [6] We here at the Virtuosi are contractually obligated to only
destroy the Earth in our posts on Earth day. I apologize for any
inconvenience this may cause. [7] I am not exactly sure why this is the
case. It is certainly observed to be the case and I thought there was a
straightforward explanation for why this was the case, but I don&amp;#8217;t
really have a good explanation. Although, maybe there just &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Polar_jet"&gt;isn&amp;#8217;t a good
one yet.&lt;/a&gt; [8] For comparison,
there is about a 1 in 3000
&lt;a href="http://www.lightningsafety.com/nlsi_pls/probability.html"&gt;chance&lt;/a&gt;
you&amp;#8217;ll be struck by lightning in your&amp;nbsp;lifetime.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="things that probs wont kill you"></category><category term="betelgeuse"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Futurama Physics</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/futurama-physics.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-08-22T23:44:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-08-22:posts/futurama-physics.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6STZpSqRmJk/Tk1oSvdCgQI/AAAAAAAAAOc/M9wr0wJUlE8/s1600/global_warming.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6STZpSqRmJk/Tk1oSvdCgQI/AAAAAAAAAOc/M9wr0wJUlE8/s320/global_warming.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  The rotting corpses of sunbeams cause global&amp;nbsp;warming.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Good news, everyone! While rummaging through all my old stuff at home, I
found my long-lost copy of &lt;em&gt;Toto &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IV&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/em&gt;. Huzzah for me! This is entirely
unrelated to what I wanted to talk about, but I have it on good
authority that Toto&amp;#8217;s
&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=azVqekQBK8g"&gt;Africa&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/em&gt; syncs up &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt;
well with this post [1]. I&amp;#8217;ll tell you when to press play. Anyway, what
I really wanted to talk about was a fairly well-posed problem in
&lt;em&gt;Futurama.&lt;/em&gt; In the episode &amp;#8220;Crimes of the Hot,&amp;#8221; all of the Earth&amp;#8217;s
robots vent their various &amp;#8220;exhausts&amp;#8221; into the sky at the same time,
using the thrust to push the Earth into an orbit slightly further away
from the sun. As a result of this new orbit, the year is made longer by
&amp;#8220;exactly one week.&amp;#8221; Anything that quantitative is pretty much asking to
be analyzed. Let&amp;#8217;s explore this problem a bit more then, why not? [
&lt;em&gt;Those wishing to get the full aural experience of this post should
press&lt;/em&gt;play &lt;em&gt;on their cassette players &amp;#8230; now ]&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt; First, a little
background. In this episode, it is learned that all the robots
(especially Hedonism Bot) emit the greenhouse gases responsible for
Global Warming. The previous solution (detailed
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2taViFH_6_Y"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;) is no longer viable,
so it is decided that all robots must be destroyed (especially Hedonism
Bot). The disembodied head of Richard Nixon rounds up all the world&amp;#8217;s
robots on the Galapagos [2] to have a &amp;#8220;party&amp;#8221; so that they may be
destroyed by a giant space-based electromagnetic pulse cannon. In a
last-ditch effort to save the robots, Professor Farnsworth has all the
robots blast their exhausts into the sky, using the thrust to push the
Earth into an orbit further away from the sun, thus solving the problem
of global warming once and for all. As a result of changing the Earth&amp;#8217;s
orbit, the year is &amp;#8220;exactly one week longer.&amp;#8221; First Pass Through Ok, so
what can we say about the new orbit if all we know is that its orbital
period is exactly one week longer? Well, we know from our good buddy
Kepler that the square of the period of a bound orbit is proportional to
the cube of its semi-major axis [3], so &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\tau^2 \propto a^3.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; We
already know the Earth&amp;#8217;s period (1 year) and semi-major axis (1
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Astronomical_unit"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AU&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;) before the
robo-boost, so we can get rid of the proportionality by writing things
in terms of the initial values. In other words, &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
\left(\frac{\tau}{1\~\mbox{yr}}\right)^2=\left(\frac{a}{1\~\mbox{AU}}\right)^3.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Alright, so we know that our new orbital period is 1 year + 1 week, or
since there are 52 weeks in a year, 53/52 years. So our new semi-major
axis is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ a = \left(\frac{1 +
1/52\~\mbox{yr}}{1\~\mbox{yr}}\right)^{2/3}\mbox{AU}\approx1.013\~\mbox{AU},$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
or a little over 1% larger than it is currently. Fair enough. So would
this fix Global Warming for ever and ever? Let&amp;#8217;s see. The solar flux at
some distance d is given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ S = \frac{L_{\odot}}{4\pi d^2}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where L is the luminosity of the sun. So the ratio of the flux at the
new semi-major axis [4] to that before the orbit was changed is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
\frac{S}{S_0}=\left(\frac{a_0}{a}\right)^2=\left(\frac{a}{1\~\mbox{yr}}\right)^{-2}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;OK&lt;/span&gt;, so we have the flux, but how do we relate this to temperature? Well,
we know that the power radiated by a blackbody of temperature T is given
by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P = \sigma A T^4, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where sigma is the Stefan-Boltzmann
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stefan%E2%80%93Boltzmann_law"&gt;constant&lt;/a&gt;, A
is the area of the emitting region and T is the temperature. For a
blackbody in equilibrium, the power coming in is going to be equal to
the power going out. The power coming in is just the solar flux times
the cross-section area of Earth, given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P_{in} = S\times\pi
R^2_{\oplus} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and the power going out is just that radiated by the
Earth as a blackbody &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P_{out} =\sigma \times 4\pi
R^2_{\oplus}\times T^4. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Equating the power in to the power out
gives &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ T = \left( \frac{S}{4\sigma}\right)^{1/4}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Now we can
find the ratio of the new average Earth temperature to the temperature
before the orbital move. We have &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{T}{T_0} =\left(
\frac{S}{S_0}\right)^{1/4}=\left(
\frac{a_0}{a}\right)^{1/2}\approx0.994$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; If we take the initial
average Earth temperature to be something like T = 300 K, then we find a
new temperature of T = 298 K. Huzzah, a whole 2 degrees cooler! That may
not sound like a lot, but remember, that&amp;#8217;s the mean global temperature.
Apparently, it only takes a few degrees increase in global average
temperatures to make things a bit uncomfortable for people. The &lt;span class="caps"&gt;IPCC&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Global_warming"&gt;indicates&lt;/a&gt; that the
average global surface temperature on Earth in the next century is
likely to rise by about 1 to 2 degrees under optimistic scenarios or
about 3 to 6 degrees under pessimistic scenarios. So the robo-boost
option is at least in the right ballpark here. Neat! How Big Is The
Push? So how big of a push did the robots need to give the Earth to
boost it out to this new orbit? Is this possible? Let&amp;#8217;s find out! First
we need to find out how the Earth&amp;#8217;s velocity has changed. We can do this
by finding the change in energy. The total energy of a bound orbit is
given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E = -\frac{k}{2a}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where &lt;/em&gt;a&lt;/em&gt; is the semi-major axis of the
orbit and &lt;em&gt;k&lt;/em&gt;= &lt;em&gt;GMm&lt;/em&gt;. So the difference in Earth&amp;#8217;s energy before and
after the robo-boost is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E_f - E_0
=-\frac{k}{2a_f}-\left(-\frac{k}{2a_0}\right)=\frac{k}{2a_0}\left(1-\frac{a_0}{a_f}\right).$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
But we also know that Earth&amp;#8217;s energy in the orbit is given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E =
-\frac{k}{r} + \frac{1}{2}mv^2, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so the difference in energy before
and after is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E_f - E_0
=\frac{1}{2}m\left(v^2_f-v^2_0\right), $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where we have found the
energies immediately before and immediately after the boost so Earth is
pretty much at the same distance from the sun, so the potential energy
terms cancel. Combining our expressions for the change in energy and
solving for the final velocity, we find &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ v_f =
\left[\frac{GM_{\odot}}{a_0}\left(1-\frac{a_0}{a_f}\right)+v^2_0\right]^{1/2}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Taking the initial orbital velocity of the Earth to be 30 km/s, we find
that the final velocity of the Earth immediately after the robo-boost is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ v_f = 30.2\~\mbox{km/s}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So the robots just need to give a
&amp;#8220;little&amp;#8221; 200 m/s boost to the Earth, right? Well, we are adding velocity
vectors here, so it depends on which direction the robots are pushing.
The magnitude of the final velocity is given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$v_f =
\sqrt{\left({\bf v_0}+{\bf \Delta v}
\right)^2}=\sqrt{v^2_0+\Delta v^2-2v_0\Delta v
\cos{\beta}},$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where delta v is the boost in velocity caused by the
robots and beta is the angle between the initial orbital motion of the
Earth and the velocity boost from the robots. If they wanted to make it
slightly easier on themselves, the robots would have boosted the Earth
in the direction it was already moving. That would make the cosine beta
term equal to one and thus minimize the necessary boost. However, in the
show the robots appear to point their exhaust right at the sun (see
figure below). This is essentially at a 90 degree angle to the Earth&amp;#8217;s
orbital motion, so the cosine beta term goes to zero in our expression
above. Plugging it all in we find that the magnitude of the robo-boost
is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\Delta v \approx 3.5\~\mbox{km/s}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; We see that this is a fair
bit larger than the 0.2 km/s needed for a boost parallel to Earth&amp;#8217;s
initial&amp;nbsp;velocity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-w6j6RXF1QEo/TlFUG6hU8PI/AAAAAAAAAOg/lViVcBBpFSA/s1600/delta_v.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-w6j6RXF1QEo/TlFUG6hU8PI/AAAAAAAAAOg/lViVcBBpFSA/s400/delta_v.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Robots blasting from the Galapagos (which now appear to be in&amp;nbsp;China&amp;#8230;)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so how much effort would it take to give that kind of boost to
the Earth? We can quantify this effort in terms of a force or in terms
of the energy difference. Let&amp;#8217;s do both. For the force, we have &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F =
\frac{\Delta p}{\Delta t}=\frac{M_{\oplus}\Delta v}{\Delta t}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Here we are a little stuck unless we can figure out the duration of the
robo-boost. Watching the episode again, the robots are blasting up
exhaust for about a minute but then the show cuts to commercial. So we
don&amp;#8217;t really know how long they were pushing. Let&amp;#8217;s just say an hour,
but we&amp;#8217;ll leave the time in if we want to fiddle with that. Plugging in
numbers, the total force is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F =
6\times10^{24}\~\mbox{N}\left(\frac{\Delta
t}{1\~\mbox{hr}}\right)^{-1}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; If this force is spread evenly over
the billion robots present [5], then each robot would be applying a
force of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F = 6\times10^{15}\~\mbox{N},$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which is roughly
equivalent to the force it would take to lift up Mount Everest [6]. That
wasn&amp;#8217;t terribly helpful. Let&amp;#8217;s look at the work then instead. The total
work done by the robots to move the Earth is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ W =
\frac{1}{2}M_{\oplus}\left(v^2_f - v^2_0\right) \approx
4\times10^{31}\~\mbox{J}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Well, that&amp;#8217;s a large number. Could a
billion robots feasibly do that much work? If the robots are each 100
kg, then if the mass of all billion robots were directly converted to
energy, we would get &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E = mc^2 =
10^9\times10^2\~\mbox{kg}\times\left(3\times10^8\~\mbox{m/s}\right)^2
\approx 10^{28}\~\mbox{J},$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; or less than a thousandth the total
energy needed. So it looks unlikely that the robots would be able to
push the Earth, but that was to be expected. Changes to The Orbit
Let&amp;#8217;s take a look at how the robo-boost affects the entirety of the
Earth&amp;#8217;s new orbit. In our first pass through the problem, we ignored the
fact that the shape of the orbit changed and only focused on the new
semi-major axis. To see why we must also consider the changes to the
&amp;#8220;shape&amp;#8221; of the orbit, take a look at the figure below.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-3tRZVuztuF0/TlGMMLhegtI/AAAAAAAAAOo/3jzGbWvvM90/s1600/orbits.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-3tRZVuztuF0/TlGMMLhegtI/AAAAAAAAAOo/3jzGbWvvM90/s400/orbits.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
In the figure, the initial orbit is plotted (black dashed line) as well
as two new orbits that each have the appropriate semi-major axis so that
the period of revolution is one year and one week. The difference
between the two final orbits comes from the robots pushing in different
directions. In the blue orbit, the boost was made in a direction
radially outward from the Sun (that is, perpendicular to the orbital
velocity of the Earth). This is the case shown in the &lt;em&gt;Futurama&lt;/em&gt;episode.
In the red orbit, the boost was made parallel to the orbital velocity of
the Earth. In each case, the boost was applied at the point labeled with
an &amp;#8220;X.&amp;#8221; One thing that jumps out from this figure is that the Earth is
always further away from the sun on the red orbit than it was on the
initial (dashed black) orbit. But on the blue orbit, the Earth is
further away from the Sun than it was initially for only half the orbit.
On the other half, the blue orbit would actually make the Earth&amp;#8217;s
temperature &lt;em&gt;higher&lt;/em&gt; than it was on the old orbit! The temperature
calculation we made earlier should hold pretty well for the red orbit,
since it is essentially a circle. It would be a little more tricky for
the blue orbit, as one would need to get a time-averaged value of the
flux over the course of the whole orbit. A hundred Quatloos to anyone
that does the calculation. Wrap-Up So what have we found out here? Well,
it seems that there are certain scenarios in which boosting the Earth
out to a new orbit with period of 1 year + 1 week could cool the Earth
by a few degrees. Granted, we have made some simplifications (the Earth
is not a blackbody), but the general idea of the thing should still
hold. I had some fun playing around with this problem and I thought it
was neat that there was a good deal of information to get started with
from the episode. The &lt;em&gt;Futurama&lt;/em&gt; people gave an exact period and at
least a visual representation of the direction the robots apply their
push. So 600 Quatloos for the writers! Not Quite As Useless as Usual
Footnotes [1] At least I think it says so if you play this
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=uUjIA3Rt7gk"&gt;song&lt;/a&gt; backwards. [2]
According to the Wikipedia page for the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Crimes_of_the_Hot#Production"&gt;episode&lt;/a&gt;,
the location of the Galapagos for the party was chosen because the
writers felt that it would be most convenient to push the Earth near the
equator. [3] The semi-major axis of an ellipse is half of the longest
line cutting through the center of the ellipse. Likewise, the semi-minor
axis is half of the shortest line drawn through the center of the
ellipse. Check &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/Ellipse.html"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; out for
some more fun stuff on ellipses. [4] This is technically incorrect,
since the semi-major axis is measured from the center of the ellipse,
but the sun is located on one of the foci. However, this requires
information on the eccentricity of the orbit, which we are currently
glossing over right now. Our method is then approximate, but becomes
exact in the case where both orbits are circles. The effect, however, is
minor. At worst, it is semi-minor. Zing! [5] My source for this billion
robots number comes from Professor Farnsworth himself. When it looks
like the robots will all be destroyed the Professor says &amp;#8220;A billion
robot lives are about to be extinguished. Oh, the Jedis are going to
feel this one!&amp;#8221; [6] Well, sort of. The height of Everest is \~10^4 m,
so this gives a volume of \~10^12 m^3. The density of most metals is
around \~10 g/cm^3, which is \~10^4 kg/m^3. This gives a mass of
\~10^16 kg. The weight is then \~10^17 N. Each robot exerts a force of
\~10^16 N. So not quite, but hey it was the first thing I thought of
and it almost worked out so I&amp;#8217;m sticking with&amp;nbsp;it!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="orbits"></category><category term="hedonism bot"></category><category term="toto"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Coriolis Effect on a Home Run</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/coriolis-effect-on-a-home-run.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-07-03T11:52:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-07-03:posts/coriolis-effect-on-a-home-run.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-LxzlQ5iNaaI/Ta458E_AwvI/AAAAAAAAAMc/D0Z4vZS7IzA/s1600/phillies_stadium.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-LxzlQ5iNaaI/Ta458E_AwvI/AAAAAAAAAMc/D0Z4vZS7IzA/s320/phillies_stadium.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Citizen&amp;#8217;s Bank&amp;nbsp;Park&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I like baseball. Well, technically, I like ~~laying~~[3] lying on the
couch for three hours half-awake eating potato chips and mumbling
obscenities at the television. But let&amp;#8217;s not split hairs here.
Anyway, out of curiosity and in partial atonement for the sins of my
past [1] I would now like to do a quick calculation to see how much
effect the Coriolis force has on a home-run ball.
The Coriolis force is one of the artificial forces we have to put in if
we are going to pretend the Earth is not rotating. For a nice intuitive
explanation of the Coriolis force see &lt;a href="http://www.wired.com/wiredscience/2011/04/coriolis-force-in-a-wipeout-rotating-slide/"&gt;this
post&lt;/a&gt;
over at Dot Physics.
Let&amp;#8217;s now consider the following problem. Citizen&amp;#8217;s Bank Park (home to
the Philadelphia Phillies) is oriented such that the line from home
plate to the foul pole in left field runs essentially South-North.
Imagine now that Ryan Howard hits a hard shot down the third base line
(that is, he hits the ball due North). Assuming it is long enough to be
a home run, how with the Coriolis force effect the ball&amp;#8217;s trajectory?
This is a well-posed problem and we could solve it as exactly as we
wanted. But please don&amp;#8217;t &lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;amp;pid=explorer&amp;amp;chrome=true&amp;amp;srcid=0Bwd5hrDOxWsrOGZmMWZkYzQtM2M2Ny00NjlmLTgyYmMtNTQwZjI1ODU1NWI4&amp;amp;hl=en_US"&gt;make
me&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;#8217;s icky and messy and I don&amp;#8217;t feel like it. So let&amp;#8217;s do some
dimensional analysis! Hooray for that!
So what are the relevant physical quantities in this problem? Well,
we&amp;#8217;ll certainly need the angular velocity of the Earth and the speed of
the baseball. We&amp;#8217;ll also need the acceleration due to gravity. Alright,
so what do we want to get out of this? Well, ideally we&amp;#8217;d like to find
the distance the ball is displaced from its current trajectory. So is
there any way we can combine an angular velocity, linear velocity and
acceleration to get a displacement?
Let&amp;#8217;s see. We can write out the dimensions of each in terms of some
length, L, and some time, T. So:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \left[ \Omega \right] = \frac{1}{T} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \left[ v \right] = \frac{L}{T} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \left[ g \right] = \frac{L}{T^2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where we have used the notation that [some quantity] = units of that
quantity. Combining these in a general way gives: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ L = \left[
v^{\alpha} \Omega^{\beta} g^{\gamma} \right] = \left(
\frac{L}{T}\right)^{\alpha}\left(
\frac{1}{T}\right)^{\beta}\left( \frac{L}{T^2}\right)^{\gamma}
= L^{\alpha+\gamma} T^{-(\alpha+\beta+2\gamma)}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Since we want
just want a length scale here, we need: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\alpha+\gamma =
1\~\~\~\mbox{and}\~\~\~\alpha+\beta+2\gamma = 0. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
We can fiddle around with the above two equations to get two new
equations that are both functions of alpha. This gives: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\beta =
\alpha - 2\~\~\~\mbox{and}\~\~\~\gamma = 1 - \alpha. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Unfortunately, we have two equations and three unknowns, so we have an
infinite number of solutions. I&amp;#8217;ve listed a few of these in the Table&amp;nbsp;below.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-_wBdDaNzEP4/Tg_of5pylyI/AAAAAAAAANE/CU2Oe225_UI/s1600/table.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-_wBdDaNzEP4/Tg_of5pylyI/AAAAAAAAANE/CU2Oe225_UI/s320/table.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Ways of getting a&amp;nbsp;length&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At this point, we have taken Math as far as we can. We&amp;#8217;ll now have to
use some physical intuition to narrow down our infinite number of
solutions to one. Hot dog! One way we can choose from these expressions
is to see which ones have the correct dependencies on each variable. So
let&amp;#8217;s consider what we would expect to happen to the deflection of our
baseball by the Coriolis force if we changed each variable. What happens
if we were to &amp;#8220;turn up&amp;#8221; the gravity and make g larger? If we make g much
larger, then a baseball hit at a given velocity will not be in the air
as long. If the ball isn&amp;#8217;t in the air as long, then it won&amp;#8217;t have as
much time to be deflected. So we would expect the deflection to decrease
if we were to increase g. This suggests that g should be in the
denominator of our final expression. What happens if we turn up the
velocity of the baseball? If we hit the ball harder, then it will be in
the air longer and thus we would expect it to have more time to be
deflected. Since increasing the velocity would increase the deflection,
we would expect v to be in the numerator. What happens if we turn up the
rotation of the Earth? Well, if the Earth is spinning faster, it&amp;#8217;s able
to rotate more while the ball is in the air. This would result in a
greater deflection in the baseball&amp;#8217;s path. Thus, we would expect this
term to be in the numerator. So, using the above criteria, we have
eliminated everything on that table with alpha less than 3 based on
physical intuition. Unfortunately, we still have an infinite number of
solutions to choose from (i.e. all those with alpha greater than or
equal to 3). But, we &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DO&lt;/span&gt; have a candidate for the &amp;#8220;simplest&amp;#8221; solution
available, namely the case where alpha = 3. Since we have exhausted are
means of winnowing down our solutions, let&amp;#8217;s just go with the alpha = 3
case. Our dimensional analysis expression for the deflection of a
baseball is then &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \Delta x \sim \frac{v^3 \Omega}{g^2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Plugging in typical values of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ v =
50\~\mbox{m/s}\~\~\~(110\~\mbox{mi/hr}) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \Omega = 7 \times
10^{-5}\~\mbox{rad/s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ g = 9.8\~\mbox{m/s}^2 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; we get &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
\Delta x \approx 0.1\~\mbox{m} = 10\~\mbox{cm}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; That&amp;#8217;s all fine
and good, but which way does the ball get deflected? Is it fair or foul?
Well, remembering that the Coriolis force is given by: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ {\bf F} =
-2m{\bf \Omega} \times {\bf v} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and utilizing Ye Olde Right Hand
Rule, we see that a ball hit due north will be deflected to the East. In
the case of Citizen&amp;#8217;s Bank Park, that is fair territory. But how good is
our estimate? Well, I did the full calculation (which you can find
&lt;a href="https://docs.google.com/viewer?a=v&amp;amp;pid=explorer&amp;amp;chrome=true&amp;amp;srcid=0Bwd5hrDOxWsrOGZmMWZkYzQtM2M2Ny00NjlmLTgyYmMtNTQwZjI1ODU1NWI4&amp;amp;hl=en_US"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)
and found that the deflection due to the Coriolis force is given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
\Delta x =-\frac{4}{3}\frac{\Omega v^3_0}{g^2} \cos \phi
\sin^3 \alpha \left[1 -3 \tan \phi \cot \alpha \right] $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where phi is the latitude and alpha is the launch angle of the ball. We
see that this is essentially what we found by dimensional analysis up to
that factor of 4/3 and some geometrical terms. Not bad! Plugging in the
same numbers we used before, along with the appropriate latitude and a
45 degree launch angle we find that the ball is deflected by: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \Delta
x = 5\~\mbox{cm}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; For comparison, we note that the diameter of a
baseball is 7.5 cm. So in the grand scheme of things, this effect is
essentially negligible. [2] That wraps up the calculation, but I&amp;#8217;m
certain that many of you are still a little wary of this voodoo
calculating style. And you should be! Although dimensional analysis will
give you a result with the proper units and will &lt;em&gt;often&lt;/em&gt; give you
approximately the right scale, it is not perfect. But, it can be
formalized and made rigorous. The rigorous demonstration for dimensional
analysis is due to Buckingham and his famous pi-theorem. The original
paper can be found behind a pay-wall
&lt;a href="http://prola.aps.org/abstract/PR/v4/i4/p345_1"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; and a really nice
set of notes can be found
&lt;a href="http://www.math.ntnu.no/~hanche/notes/buckingham/buckingham-a4.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
It&amp;#8217;s a pretty neat idea and I highly recommend you check it out!
Unnecessary Footnotes:
[1] Once in college I argued with a meteorologist named Dr. Thunder over
the direction of the Coriolis force on a golf ball for the better half
of the front nine at Penn State&amp;#8217;s golf course. I was wrong. Moral of the
story: don&amp;#8217;t play golf with meteorologists.
[2] For a counterargument, see Fisk et al. (1975) [3] Text has been
corrected to illustrate our enlightenment by a former English major as
to the difference between &amp;#8216;lay&amp;#8217; and &amp;#8216;lie&amp;#8217; through the following story:
&amp;#8216;Once in a college psych class, a young student said &amp;#8220;It&amp;#8217;s too hot.
Let&amp;#8217;s lay down.&amp;#8221; A mature student, a journalist, asked, &amp;#8220;Who&amp;#8217;s Down?&amp;#8221;&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8217;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="baseball"></category><category term="coriolis"></category></entry><entry><title>Counting Critters</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/counting-critters.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-06-28T00:19:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-06-28:posts/counting-critters.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-H4DbCndvDRw/TgfuQZt7aJI/AAAAAAAAAM8/WLfVRd4USK8/s1600/marx_horse.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-H4DbCndvDRw/TgfuQZt7aJI/AAAAAAAAAM8/WLfVRd4USK8/s320/marx_horse.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  This picture allows us to set a lower bound on the number of &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=9IrCgCKrv8U"&gt;creatures&lt;/a&gt; that ever lived of&amp;nbsp;\~4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We recently had a big book sale [1] here in town where books were being
sold for about a quarter. Needless to say, I bought far more than I&amp;#8217;ll
probably ever need or read. One of the books I bought was called
&lt;em&gt;General Paleontology&lt;/em&gt; by A. Brouwer [2]. Anyways, I didn&amp;#8217;t really make
it too far in the book. In fact, I only made it to the first sentence of
the second paragraph of the first chapter, when I encountered this line:
&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;The number of individuals which has populated the Earth since life
began is beyond estimation.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt; Horse feathers, I say! Horse Feathers!
The number of things that ever lived may very well be &lt;/em&gt;unknowable&lt;/em&gt;, but
it&amp;#8217;s certainly not beyond estimation. So below, Alemi and I each provide
an estimate for the total number of creatures that have ever lived on
Earth. We flipped a coin and I lost, so I guess I&amp;#8217;ll go first. My
estimation will be a genuine guess-y kind of estimate that doesn&amp;#8217;t draw
too heavily on too many physical considerations. Instead, I will
formulate a series of assumptions and base my final answer on that. So
assuming my assumptions are valid, the answer should give a reasonable
estimate to the total number of creatures that have ever lived. My
assumptions are as follows: (1) The number of individuals that have ever
lived will be almost entirely dominated by the number of bacteria that
have ever lived on Earth. So to leading order, all the life that has
ever lived on Earth is bacteria (or something similar). (2) Life began
at some time, T, in the past and immediately spread to all places on
Earth. Hey, man, it&amp;#8217;s the power of geometric progression! (3) The
majority of life is found within h = 1 m from the surface of water. I
picked this number since it&amp;#8217;s roughly (order of magnitude) how far down
I can see in really clear water. Most of the life will be photosynthetic
and thus need a fair amount of sunlight. (4) The number density of
organisms in water is n \~ 10^5. I have no real justification for this.
(5) The average lifetime of an organism is t \~ 1 hr. Alright, so if
these assumptions are valid (a big if [3]), then the following
prediction should be fairly accurate. So the total volume in which these
creatures may live is just the shell of the Earth down to about a meter:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ V = 4 \pi R_{\oplus}^2 h $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where R = 6 * 10^6 m is the radius
of the Earth. Alright, so the number of creatures at any given moment
will be the volume times the number density which I will take to be n \~
10^5. That will give us the total number of creatures at any given
moment. But we want it for &lt;em&gt;all&lt;/em&gt; the moments. So I will take the total
number of &amp;#8220;generations&amp;#8221; to be the time life has been around divided by
the average lifetime of a given organism. Putting this all together
gives &lt;mathjax&gt;$$N = 4 \pi R_{\oplus}^2 h \times \frac{T}{t} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Plugging in
some numbers I get: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N \sim 10^{39}
\left(\frac{h}{1\~\mbox{m}}\right)\left(\frac{n}{10^5\~\mbox{cm}^{-3}}\right)\left(\frac{T}{3\times10^9\~\mbox{yrs}}
\right)\left(\frac{t}{1\~\mbox{hr}} \right)^{-1}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So for the
nominal values I&amp;#8217;ve plugged in, I&amp;#8217;ll get that about 10^39 creatures
have ever lived on Earth [4]. I&amp;#8217;ve left my equation in a dimensionless
form above, so if you think my individual estimates are garbage, you can
easily plug in your own estimates to see how things change. Except for
the completely arbitrary factor for the average number density of
organisms per cubic centimeter of water, I feel alright about this
estimate. And I&amp;#8217;m fairly confident that the number density will not be
off more than about 3 orders of magnitude either high or low. So my
final estimate is: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N \sim 10^{39 \pm 3} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; I promised that there
would be two estimates, so I present below in picture form, Alemi&amp;#8217;s
back-of-the-wrapper&amp;nbsp;estimate.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Eq37GVo3d8A/TggHx19J1pI/AAAAAAAAANA/Y0H3DTVb2so/s1600/jj_phys.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-Eq37GVo3d8A/TggHx19J1pI/AAAAAAAAANA/Y0H3DTVb2so/s400/jj_phys.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Click for the full Jimmy Johns&amp;nbsp;experience&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To explain these scribbles, I now cede the floor (and the mic) to Alemi.
[ &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SEAMLESS&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TRANSITION&lt;/span&gt; ] So, when Corky posed this question to me while
we ate some tasty sandwiches, another approach came to mind. Namely, I
wanted to try to estimate the number of critters that have ever lived by
putting some kind of energy bound on the number. Ultimately, all
critters come from the sun. That is, all life on Earth is only able to
exist in so much as it consumes energy, and for almost all life
[ignoring the under ocean heat vent guys], the energy they consume, one
way or another comes from the sun. So, let&amp;#8217;s estimate the number of
critters in three parts (1) We need the energy the Earth recieves from
the sun. (2) We need to estimate the energy density of life (3) These
two things, combined with a characteristic length or volume scale for a
critter would enable us to figure out the rate at which the Earth could
produce critters. (4) Assuming this rate and a time scale for how long
life has been around on the Earth would give us a total number of
critters. Let&amp;#8217;s begin (1) Energy from the sun. Corky and I happen to
know that the solar flux on the sun is roughly 1000 W/m^2. Multiplying
this by half the surface area of the earth gives us a rough total solar
flux &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ (1000 \text{ W/m}^2) ( 2\pi R_{\oplus}^2) \sim 2 \times
10^{17} \text{ W} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; (2) Energy density of critters For this we used
the bag of potato chips we had on hand, assuming that all life matter
has roughly the same energy content. The bag of chips was 150 calories
in a serving size of 28 grams. This and assuming that life forms are the
density of water gives us a life energy density &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \left( \frac{ 150
\text{ kcal} }{ 28 \text{ g}} \right)\left( \frac{ 1 \text{ g}}{
\text{ cm}^3} \right) \sim 2 \times 10^4 \text{ J/cm}^3 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; (3)
Length scale of critters We assumed that bacteria are the most abundant
life form, so we chose a length scale of 100 microns. Putting these
pieces together gives &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{ 2 \times 10^{17} \text{ W} }{
\left( 2 \times 10^4 \text{ J/cm}^3 \right) \left( 100\
\mu\text{m} \right)^3 } \sim 10^{19} \text{ 1/s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Which is our
estimated critter creation rate (4) Time scale for life generation
Finally, we estimate that life creation has been chugging along on earth
for about 3 billion years, this gives us our final estimate for the
number of critters that have every lived &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \left( 10^{19} \text{
1/s} \right) \left( 3 \times 10^9 \text{ years} \right) \sim
10^{36} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So, there we have it. If the Earth was 100% efficient at
converting solar energy into life, and that life is characteristically
the energy density of a potato chip and the size of a bacteria, we
should have had 1 billion billion billion billion critters ever. To make
us feel a little better we would like to tack on a 10% efficiency, since
we don&amp;#8217;t actually expect the Earth to be 100% efficient, and because 10%
seems to be the rule of thumb efficiency estimation used when it comes
to food chains and the like, so our final estimate, motivated purely by
physics is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \boxed{ \text{ Total number of critters ever } =
10^{35\pm 3} } $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; This number seems pretty good, and is in general
agreement with Corky&amp;#8217;s earlier method. Notice that the only parameter we
are a little worried about the is the length scale, especially because
our final answer depends on the inverse cube of this number, so, our
error is probably something around 3 orders of magnitude, as before,
since an order of magnitude goof in the size would cause 3 orders of
magnitude error in the final estimate. So there you have it. Two
not-egregiously-horrible estimates for the total number of critters that
have ever lived. All in all, I think that book was a quarter well spent!
Unnecessary footnotes: [1] This is a bit misleading. They actually sold
books of all sizes. [2] I like to read about paleontology and such just
in case I&amp;#8217;m ever sent back in time. This way, I&amp;#8217;ll know what dinosaurs
are safe to eat. [3] Here&amp;#8217;s a bigger if: if [4] &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FACT&lt;/span&gt;: The total
number of atoms in all the people on Earth is roughly 10^39. A proof of
this is left as an exercise for the&amp;nbsp;reader.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="circle of life"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="jimmy johns"></category></entry><entry><title>End of the Earth V: There Goes the Sun</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/end-of-the-earth-v-there-goes-the-sun.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-22T09:42:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-04-22:posts/end-of-the-earth-v-there-goes-the-sun.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-LtXsyHxxSi0/TbDfL6l4tnI/AAAAAAAAAMg/l_12lafg6LQ/s1600/creepy_sun.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-LtXsyHxxSi0/TbDfL6l4tnI/AAAAAAAAAMg/l_12lafg6LQ/s320/creepy_sun.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  The Sun [photo courtesy of&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;People that know me well know that I have a lot in common with Robert
Frost. We both were born in March and we both employ rural New England
settings to explore complex social and philosophical themes in our
poetry. We also like the same rap groups. In honor of my literary
doppelganger, I will now, having already had the world end in
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-physics-i.html"&gt;fire&lt;/a&gt;,
try my hand at ice. Let&amp;#8217;s try to answer the question: &amp;#8220;If the sun blinks
out of existence this instant, what is the temperature of the Earth as a
function of time?&amp;#8221; The Sun, in addition to being the &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=haAhdtDmsOw"&gt;King of
Planets&lt;/a&gt;, is also what keeps
us all warm and toasty and alive. What happens if we turn that off?
Well, the Earth will cool by radiating its heat away into space. To see
how long this would take, let&amp;#8217;s make some assumptions. Let&amp;#8217;s model the
surface of the Earth as an ocean 1 km deep and let&amp;#8217;s pretend that all
the heat is stored in this ocean. Let&amp;#8217;s take the ocean to be liquid
water at T = 0 degrees Celsius. How long will it take this ocean to
freeze into ice at 0 degrees Celsius? Well, the amount of energy
released from the oceans as the water freezes is given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q = L_{w}
M_{ocean} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where L is the &amp;#8220;latent heat of fusion&amp;#8221; and M is the mass
of the water. The &amp;#8220;latent heat of fusion&amp;#8221; is a fancy way of saying &amp;#8220;the
amount of energy released per unit mass as water turns to ice at
constant temperature.&amp;#8221; For water, we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ L_{w} = 3.3 \times
10^5 \mbox{J/kg} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; And for the mass of the ocean, it will be
convenient later to write it as &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ M_{ocean} = 4\pi {R_{\oplus}}^2
\Delta R \rho $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Alright, so now we&amp;#8217;ve got enough to say how much heat
energy we have, so how fast do we lose it? We can take the Earth to be a
blackbody radiator, so the power lost in such a case is: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P =4\pi
\sigma R_{\oplus}^2 T^4 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Since Power is just Energy per unit
Time, we now have all we need to get the time for total freezing of all
the oceans. We have: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = \frac{Q}{P} = \frac{4\pi
{R_{\oplus}}^2 \Delta R \rho L_{w}}{4\pi \sigma R_{\oplus}^2
T^4} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Simplifying the above expression a bit, we get &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t
=\frac{\Delta R \rho L_{w}}{\sigma T^4} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Now we can plug in some
numbers, &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t =\frac{\left(10^3 \mbox{ m}\right) \times
\left(10^3 \frac{kg}{m^3}\right) \times \left(3.3 \times 10^5
\mbox{J/kg}\right)}{\left( 5.67 \times 10^{-8} J s^{-1} m^{-2}
K^{-4}\right) \times \left( 273 K\right)^4} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where we have made
sure to put our temperatures in Kelvin. Crunching the numbers with the
calculator we &amp;#8220;borrowed&amp;#8221; from Nic three months ago gives: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = 10^9
\mbox{ s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Remembering that a year is very nearly &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1 \mbox{ year}
= \pi \times 10^7 \mbox{ s}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; we find that the time for the oceans
to freeze after the sun disappears is about 30 years. Hooray! Now this
model was very simple. First of all, I assumed that the ocean
temperatures were already at 0 degrees, but they are a bit warmer. If
the oceans are about 300 K (ie 80 degrees in not-Yariv units), then we
get another 30 years to cool down to freezing temperatures. Secondly, I
have completely neglected the heat stored in the Earth. Will this change
my answer by an embarrassingly large factor? Lastly, I have ignored all
internal heating mechanisms (ie, radioactive decay) that will also heat
up the Earth. But ignoring all that&amp;#8230;. So is there a way for anyone to
survive this? Well, for the most part it will mean the end of life on
Earth. There could potentially be a few exceptions, like by geothermal
vents and such. But for the most part, it&amp;#8217;s one quick cold spiral down
to eternal nothingness. But what about a few people, could they survive
for a bit even if the human race is doomed? I&amp;#8217;m glad you asked! You see,
I have this plan involving mine shafts. Hunkering down underground with
a nuclear power plant and all the canned food food we can stomach should
allow us to at least ride the rest of our lives. Details can be found
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iesXUFOlWC0&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="sun"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category></entry><entry><title>A Sense of Scale (in Dollars and Cents)</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/a-sense-of-scale-in-dollars-and-cents-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-07T21:42:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-04-07:posts/a-sense-of-scale-in-dollars-and-cents-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I hate politics, but for some reason I obsessively read about it. I
don&amp;#8217;t know why I do this, but I assume it&amp;#8217;s the same reason people slow
down for car wrecks and pay to see the geek [1]. Anyway, the big thing
in political news now is that if Congress can&amp;#8217;t pass a budget [2] by the
end of the day Friday, the government will shut down. Shutting down the
government means that 800,000 federal employees will go without pay [3],
lots of services will be put on hold and you won&amp;#8217;t be able to go to the
Smithsonian or the Grand Canyon. So it&amp;#8217;s kind of a big deal. Since the
ramifications of a government shutdown are so serious, there must be
some really important disagreements holding it up, right? Right? A quick
search (for example,
&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/apr/07/us-congress-staff-government-shutdown"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;),
shows that the big hold-up in passing the budget comes over a
disagreement on how much money should be cut from the budget.
Republicans want to cut &lt;mathjax&gt;$40 billion dollars and Democrats are willing to
cut $&lt;/mathjax&gt;34.5 billion dollars. So the hold-up is over &lt;mathjax&gt;$5.5 billion. Let's
consider how utterly and stupidly insignificant this is. We shall take
as our inspiration Alemi's
[post](http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/12/law-and-large-numbers.html)
a while back offering several ways to help visualize the large and scary
sounding numbers thrown around in government budgets. The first thing
we'd like to do is find out what fraction this $&lt;/mathjax&gt;5.5 billion discrepancy
is compared to the total budget. Alemi cites the total budget of the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; government in the 2010 fiscal year to be &lt;mathjax&gt;$3.55 trillion. Hot dog!
So we see that: $&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \frac{\mbox{Disputed Difference}}{\mbox{Total
Budget}} = \frac{\$&lt;/mathjax&gt;5.5 \times 10^9}{\$3.55 \times 10^{12}} =
0.0015 &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ So the disputed part amounts to 0.15% of the total budget or
one and half parts in a thousand. Let's compare this to some things for
which we have a better sense of scale. Let's pretend we are looking to
buy a car. We need it to get to work and, you know, get stuff done. If
our car costs $10,000 dollars then 0.15% of our total costs will be $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
\mbox{\$10,000} \times 0.0015 = \$15 &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ So the current budget
situation is like arguing for 6 months over a $15 charge on your $10,000
car. Sounds reasonable! Now let's switch gears and consider a timescale.
Let's consider a 40 hour work week. What's 0.15% of 40 hours? This comes
to $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; 40 \mbox{ hr} \times 0.0015 = 0.06 \mbox{ hr} &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ or, if you
prefer, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; 0.06 \mbox{ hr} \times \frac{60 \mbox{ min}}{1 \mbox{
hr}} = 3.6 \mbox{ minutes} &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ So the current budget problem is like
arguing for six months over about three and a half extra minutes to your
work week. Now let's consider a length scale. Consider the US $1 bill.
According to
[Wikipedia](http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/United_States_one-dollar_bill#Small_size_notes),
the dollar bill is 6.14 inches long, 2.61 inches wide and 0.0043 inches
thick. That means that the ratio of the thickness to the width of a
dollar bill is $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; \frac{\mbox{Thickness}}{\mbox{Width}} =
\frac{0.0043 \mbox{ inches}}{2.61 \mbox{ inches}} = 0.0016 $$ or
slightly &lt;em&gt;more&lt;/em&gt; than the disputed fraction of the budget. Hooray!
&amp;#8220;That&amp;#8217;s all well and nice,&amp;#8221; you say, lowering your voice and leaning
over in a way that makes me uncomfortable, &amp;#8220;but who is to &lt;em&gt;blame&lt;/em&gt;?&amp;#8221;
That&amp;#8217;s a great question! My answer will take the form of an experiment.
First, get a coin. Got it? Great. Now if you&amp;#8217;re Republican, let heads be
&amp;#8220;The Republicans&amp;#8221; and tails be &amp;#8220;The Democrats.&amp;#8221; If you&amp;#8217;re a Democrat,
let heads be &amp;#8220;The Democrats&amp;#8221; and tails be &amp;#8220;The Republicans.&amp;#8221; If you are
neither, then randomly assign a party to heads and allow the other to be
tails. Ready? The coin is to blame. [1] I use this in its original
meaning. That is, the guy whose job it was to do horribly gross things
at a carnival for money, not the guy whose main form of social
interaction is debating scenes in Star Wars on internet forums. A more
up-to-date comparison would have been to say &amp;#8220;for the same reason that
people watch &lt;em&gt;Jersey Shore&lt;/em&gt;.&amp;#8221; [2] That is, the budget for the 2011
fiscal year, which started on October 1st 2010. [3] Don&amp;#8217;t worry, all
members of Congress would be exempt from this and would still pick up&amp;nbsp;paychecks!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="large numbers"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="politics"></category></entry><entry><title>Collective Wanderings</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/collective-wanderings.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-04T22:39:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-04-04:posts/collective-wanderings.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;Update [04/04/11]: It seems Clicky got too popular for our bandwidth
limits on the physics servers. Hopefully we&amp;#8217;ll be able to fix this
sometime soon&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt; &lt;/em&gt;Update [04/02/11]: We made the code faster, so
check out the new and improved Clicky!&lt;/em&gt; Hey, kids! Would you like to be
a bit player in a grand experiment with poorly thought out objectives?
If so, then check
&lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~aalemi/clicky/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; out. It&amp;#8217;s a
little interactive &amp;#8220;game&amp;#8221; [1] that Alemi and Matt coded up. When you
click on the link, you will be redirected to a page showing something
like this:
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-FYqCFtPrbT0/TZaZF4ubmPI/AAAAAAAAAMM/5Hf-_v0wTrY/s1600/clicky1.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-FYqCFtPrbT0/TZaZF4ubmPI/AAAAAAAAAMM/5Hf-_v0wTrY/s400/clicky1.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Using the arrow keys on your keyboard or by clicking on the arrow
buttons on the screen, you can move the dot around. Sound fun yet? Well,
the interesting bit comes in with the fact that anyone who wants to can
move the same dot at the same time. The plot will update automatically,
so if you&amp;#8217;re really bored you can sit around and watch someone else move
the dot around. Heck, you could even give the dot a cute name like Mr.
Dottington and tell it how your day was. We won&amp;#8217;t judge you. [2] Anyway,
check it out if you&amp;#8217;ve got a bit of time to kill. Explore the space and
we&amp;#8217;ll get back to you with the &amp;#8220;results&amp;#8221; of this &amp;#8220;experiment&amp;#8221; sometime
in the &amp;#8220;future.&amp;#8221; [1] There are no objectives and &amp;#8220;winning&amp;#8221; is undefined
(for a contrary argument, however, see Sheen et. al (2011)) [2] But Mr.
Dottington&amp;nbsp;will.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="clicky"></category><category term="fun"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Special Virtuosi Book Announcement!</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/special-virtuosi-book-announcement-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-04-01T01:41:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-04-01:posts/special-virtuosi-book-announcement-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-R1-a_FlO6sA/TZVXVvoqvcI/AAAAAAAAALA/nNu7S12Sliw/s1600/kindle.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-R1-a_FlO6sA/TZVXVvoqvcI/AAAAAAAAALA/nNu7S12Sliw/s1600/kindle.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Coming soon to a Kindle near&amp;nbsp;you!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We&amp;#8217;ve been at this whole blogging thing for about a year now and I think
we&amp;#8217;ve amassed a large and dedicated enough fanbase to finally release a
book! The track record so far for physicist-writers has been &lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Spiral-Novel-Paul-McEuen/dp/038534211X/ref=sr_1_1?ie=UTF8&amp;amp;qid=1301633241&amp;amp;sr=8-1"&gt;quite
good&lt;/a&gt;
of late, so we figured why not us? Well, lots of reasons actually. For
one thing, it&amp;#8217;s &lt;em&gt;really hard&lt;/em&gt;. Books are, like, &lt;em&gt;hundreds&lt;/em&gt; of pages
long. I barely stay coherent and on-topic in a one page blog post. For
another thing, it takes lots of time. I hardly have enough time to do my
laundry in time scales deemed &amp;#8220;socially acceptable.&amp;#8221; How could I ever
find the time to write a book? Despite these potential setbacks, the
millions and millions of dollars that writers make still seems really
appealing. Who wouldn&amp;#8217;t want to be rich and popular forever. I mean,
just look at Oscar Wilde, Edgar Allan Poe and Herman Melville! Luckily,
a solution presented itself. I don&amp;#8217;t have time to write a book now, but
I found an old copy of my novel &lt;em&gt;Blue Dragon&lt;/em&gt; laying around the house
that I was able to sell using the immense popularity of the Virtuosi
brand. The book will be published this summer by Clark Hall Publishing.
Here are a few advance reviews: &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Audacious, bodacious, entropic,
synoptic, electric, eclectic, entertaining, hyperbraining, high-roller,
tripolar&amp;#8230; Buy&lt;/em&gt;~~Against the Day~~ Blue Dragon.&amp;#8221; &amp;#8212; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;THE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PHILADELPHIA&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;INQUIRER&lt;/span&gt; &lt;em&gt;&amp;#8220;Corky isn&amp;#8217;t easy to &amp;#8216;get&amp;#8217;. His melodies and chords I would
describe as complicated. But, behind all the disharmony and 11ths and so
forth.. it swings. This is my favorite Virtuosi book. It&amp;#8217;s an amazing
book and that&amp;#8217;s all you can say.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8212; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;J.D.&lt;/span&gt; Jackson &amp;#8220;&lt;em&gt;This is a book rich
in allegory and poignant social commentary. Also, you should call home
more&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt; &amp;#8212; Corky&amp;#8217;s Mom So these unbiased critics think it&amp;#8217;s totally rad.
Should you just take their word for it? Absolutely! But if you really
want see the book for yourself, here it is:
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-8h9NruKfpcY/TZVfkIGsNdI/AAAAAAAAALE/ksvtyGo97YE/s1600/Blue_Dragon+0.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-8h9NruKfpcY/TZVfkIGsNdI/AAAAAAAAALE/ksvtyGo97YE/s400/Blue_Dragon+0.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-GdbX2pEIgxI/TZVg5TR7AqI/AAAAAAAAALI/xGaSUfVSEZo/s1600/Blue_Dragon+1.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-GdbX2pEIgxI/TZVg5TR7AqI/AAAAAAAAALI/xGaSUfVSEZo/s400/Blue_Dragon+1.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-0-DVsda2lx8/TZVg5gkGEeI/AAAAAAAAALM/02ydunms7wU/s1600/Blue_Dragon+2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-0-DVsda2lx8/TZVg5gkGEeI/AAAAAAAAALM/02ydunms7wU/s400/Blue_Dragon+2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-22WcWYnjf6o/TZVg6YfuvgI/AAAAAAAAALQ/7sLTLvmEk7E/s1600/Blue_Dragon+3.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-22WcWYnjf6o/TZVg6YfuvgI/AAAAAAAAALQ/7sLTLvmEk7E/s400/Blue_Dragon+3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-AeCvk8c6cZ8/TZVg7dQrLYI/AAAAAAAAALU/zvyTSQVfiFM/s1600/Blue_Dragon+4.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-AeCvk8c6cZ8/TZVg7dQrLYI/AAAAAAAAALU/zvyTSQVfiFM/s400/Blue_Dragon+4.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-RgIlU2GhMwM/TZVg8OJZQRI/AAAAAAAAALY/Xyf-bzmvEVQ/s1600/Blue_Dragon+5.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-RgIlU2GhMwM/TZVg8OJZQRI/AAAAAAAAALY/Xyf-bzmvEVQ/s400/Blue_Dragon+5.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-665JCYacjvs/TZVg816ylbI/AAAAAAAAALc/bRiAV25GLrs/s1600/Blue_Dragon+6.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-665JCYacjvs/TZVg816ylbI/AAAAAAAAALc/bRiAV25GLrs/s400/Blue_Dragon+6.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-yRDUoYQICC8/TZVg9smkxTI/AAAAAAAAALg/4WQ_icWzhTo/s1600/Blue_Dragon+7.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-yRDUoYQICC8/TZVg9smkxTI/AAAAAAAAALg/4WQ_icWzhTo/s400/Blue_Dragon+7.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-JWO3R4e-CPo/TZVg-SITf_I/AAAAAAAAALk/5EEBXi0Pfqs/s1600/Blue_Dragon+8.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-JWO3R4e-CPo/TZVg-SITf_I/AAAAAAAAALk/5EEBXi0Pfqs/s400/Blue_Dragon+8.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hhApIwOKwC8/TZVg-8tBZ-I/AAAAAAAAALo/1p739Qh5M0Q/s1600/Blue_Dragon+9.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hhApIwOKwC8/TZVg-8tBZ-I/AAAAAAAAALo/1p739Qh5M0Q/s400/Blue_Dragon+9.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-QTmCNMcqOtw/TZVg_pZdr6I/AAAAAAAAALs/wvJs5V5_KH4/s1600/Blue_Dragon+10.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-QTmCNMcqOtw/TZVg_pZdr6I/AAAAAAAAALs/wvJs5V5_KH4/s400/Blue_Dragon+10.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sUgqqPFsz64/TZVhAAQls9I/AAAAAAAAALw/eZKCELD6RAw/s1600/Blue_Dragon+11.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-sUgqqPFsz64/TZVhAAQls9I/AAAAAAAAALw/eZKCELD6RAw/s400/Blue_Dragon+11.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ZngjLnMZ1sE/TZVhAvZ_9cI/AAAAAAAAAL0/nOGYrVxjudc/s1600/Blue_Dragon+12.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-ZngjLnMZ1sE/TZVhAvZ_9cI/AAAAAAAAAL0/nOGYrVxjudc/s400/Blue_Dragon+12.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6K0BqeU9h90/TZVhBYv-dSI/AAAAAAAAAL4/W3WScRdkCvQ/s1600/Blue_Dragon+13.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-6K0BqeU9h90/TZVhBYv-dSI/AAAAAAAAAL4/W3WScRdkCvQ/s400/Blue_Dragon+13.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-m6rVltXBHDU/TZVhB8dgN0I/AAAAAAAAAL8/0SJeEqunX4Y/s1600/Blue_Dragon+14.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-m6rVltXBHDU/TZVhB8dgN0I/AAAAAAAAAL8/0SJeEqunX4Y/s400/Blue_Dragon+14.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-WrewtPzlKfI/TZVhCZby49I/AAAAAAAAAMA/iRzSOigU43o/s1600/Blue_Dragon+15.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-WrewtPzlKfI/TZVhCZby49I/AAAAAAAAAMA/iRzSOigU43o/s400/Blue_Dragon+15.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="literature"></category><category term="book reviews"></category></entry><entry><title>Nickel Gnomes</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/nickel-gnomes.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-03-31T02:17:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-03-31:posts/nickel-gnomes.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-i8ltaoDuLpI/TZQPlf1wbaI/AAAAAAAAAK4/svtKmQjxBsE/s1600/underpants-gnomes.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-i8ltaoDuLpI/TZQPlf1wbaI/AAAAAAAAAK4/svtKmQjxBsE/s320/underpants-gnomes.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Perhaps Step 2 was to steal&amp;nbsp;copper?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;While flipping through a &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CRC&lt;/span&gt; Handbook whose days in the United States
are dwindling, I came across a section that described the naming
conventions of each chemical element. Most of the names made sense to
me. For example, Nobelium is named after Alfred Nobel (surprise!).
However, the Nickel entry was the following: Nickel: Named after
&lt;em&gt;Satan&lt;/em&gt;or &lt;em&gt;Old Nick&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;&lt;em&gt; This confused me greatly. What the heck is Santa
Claus doing hanging out with Satan [1]? After a bit of poking around on
the internet, I found an article from 1931 by a guy named William
Baldwin called &lt;/em&gt;The Story of Nickel, How &amp;#8220;Old Nick&amp;#8217;s&amp;#8221; Gnomes were
Outwitted&lt;/em&gt;. Needless to say, this did not allay my confusion. Here is
the relevant passage from the article: &lt;em&gt;In the early part of the
eighteenth century fresh lodes of ore were laid open in Saxony where
from times immemorial silver and copper mines had been worked. This new
ore was so glittering and full of promise as to cause the greatest
excitement, but after innumerable trials and endless labor all&lt;/em&gt; &lt;em&gt;that
could he obtained from the ore was a worthless metal. In disgust the
superstitious miners named the ore kupfer-nickel after &amp;#8220;Old Nick&amp;#8221; and
his mischievous gnomes who were charged with plaguing the miners and
bewitching the ore.&lt;/em&gt; This &amp;#8220;worthless&amp;#8221; metal is nickel. Kupfernickel is
the German name for the nickel ore (see image below) which comes from
the words &lt;em&gt;kupfer&lt;/em&gt;, meaning &amp;#8220;copper&amp;#8221; and &lt;em&gt;nickel&lt;/em&gt;, meaning&amp;nbsp;&amp;#8220;demon.&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-9psfFrm6qec/TZQZVPtLD0I/AAAAAAAAAK8/wyMrVWYT7Zo/s1600/niccolite.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-9psfFrm6qec/TZQZVPtLD0I/AAAAAAAAAK8/wyMrVWYT7Zo/s400/niccolite.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Ore that, if not for gnomes, would contain that sweet sweet&amp;nbsp;copper&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And that&amp;#8217;s the story of Nickel! Tune in next time [2] for our ongoing
118-part series, &lt;em&gt;Better Know an Element!&lt;/em&gt; [1] Turns out &amp;#8220;Old Nick&amp;#8221; is
an English name for the Devil. Go figure. But those of you named
Nicholas should not be upset, as your name comes from the Greek
Nikholaos, which literally means &amp;#8220;victory-people.&amp;#8221; So you&amp;#8217;ve got that
going for you. [2] I have no plans of ever doing this&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="gnomes"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Physics Challenge Award Show</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/physics-challenge-award-show.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-03-17T23:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-03-17:posts/physics-challenge-award-show.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pyHug0rZ0X0/TYGM0O4fznI/AAAAAAAAAK0/ZTrk9NSTYuw/s1600/macgyver.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="https://lh5.googleusercontent.com/-pyHug0rZ0X0/TYGM0O4fznI/AAAAAAAAAK0/ZTrk9NSTYuw/s320/macgyver.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  In an emergency, Richard Dean Anderson&amp;#8217;s mullet can be used as a flotation device and/or standard&amp;nbsp;kilogram.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Welcome to the First Physics Challenge Problem Award Show! We received
an integer number of solutions to our challenge problem and at long last
and after much deliberation, we have chosen our winner. We had before
indicated vaguely that there may be some sort of prizes involved in this
competition. After consultation with our financial advisors and breaking
Alemi&amp;#8217;s piggy bank, we have decided on the following prizes: First
Place: A brand new &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CRC&lt;/span&gt; Handbook! Second Place: An autographed [1]
picture of Scott Bakula! Honorable Mention: Nothing! [2] So before we
officially announce our winner, let&amp;#8217;s backtrack and build up some
suspense. The challenge was to come up with a bunch of MacGyveresque
experiments to determine as closely as possible the standard second,
meter and kilogram using only the materials handy to you on a desert [3]
island. Just about every response we got successfully answered the
question, so we had to base our final result on robustness and
uncertainties. We also tended to favor those that did not rest on
precise knowledge of one&amp;#8217;s own height, weight, etc (though there is
nothing wrong with these approaches). So without further ado, the winner
is&amp;#8230;. [pause] [unnecessarily long secondary pause] George from
Australia! George provided a list of no fewer than 11 different methods
for determining the second, meter and kilogram. The second was found by
timing (by means of a pendulum) the time it takes for the sun to move
through an a given angle measure. This measurement can be made each day
for a year to get the best results (remember, you&amp;#8217;ve got all the time in
the world!). Now we have the time it takes the sun to go through a given
angle measured in &amp;#8220;swings of a pendulum.&amp;#8221; We can calculate the transit
time of the sun into seconds and then we can find the number of seconds
per swing of the pendulum. So now we have a second. But since the period
of a pendulum is given by: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ T = 2\pi \sqrt{l/g}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; we also have the
length of the pendulum in meters. From this we can make a standard
meter. Now all that is left is to find the kilogram. This can be done by
making a water-tight enclosure of volume 1000 cm^3 and filling it with
water, giving a kilogram that can be compared to other objects to get a
longer lasting standard kilogram. Any other knowledge you may have (i.e.
known height and weight) may be used to check the above measurements. A
very close second place goes to Alireza, who provided a very strong
submission and perhaps one of the best uses of snail mucus in the entire
competition! Alireza&amp;#8217;s solution was to use one&amp;#8217;s own known height to
construct the standard meter. From this you can make a pendulum to get
the second and a box o&amp;#8217; water (sealed with tar, glue and snail mucus) to
get the kilogram. Both George and Alireza provided very detailed
responses with special attention paid toward reducing uncertainty and
checking their answers through several independent measurements. They
also both carried out parts of their experiments. Congratulations to you
both! In addition to the winning responses, we also received several
other submissions that merit honorable mention. They are&amp;#8230;. Oliver, who
provided several acoustical experiments using his &lt;span class="caps"&gt;SUPERPOWER&lt;/span&gt; of perfect
pitch. Nicole, who noted that we were not correct in giving the Titanic
the designation
&amp;#8220;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Her_Majesty%27s_Ship"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;HMS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; as this is
reserved for ships in the British Royal Navy. In fact, the Titanic was
designated &amp;#8220;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Royal_Mail_Ship"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RMS&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; since
it carried mail. Thanks, Nicole! Gary, who completely ignored the
premise, used arbitrary units and left a very amusing note on his
deathbed giving all his arbitrary units to be found and converted by the
first enterprising explorer who lands on his island. I know you had
asked for your prize in cash and while I cannot directly accomodate that
wish, do know that Richard Dean Anderson smiles can be cashed in most
banks nationwide (see [2]). So thanks to everyone who submitted a
response to this Challenge. We enjoyed reading all of the solutions and
we hope you had fun thinking about it. And next time you go on a boat,
don&amp;#8217;t forget that &lt;span class="caps"&gt;CRC&lt;/span&gt;! [1] Autograph will be signed by me on an 8.5&amp;#8221; x
11&amp;#8221; picture of Scott Bakula printed by a laser printer on regular copy
paper. [2] Well, you receive nothing of monetary value but, know deep
down in your hearts that in the picture at the top of this post, Richard
Dean Anderson is smiling at you. So you&amp;#8217;ve got that going for you, which
is nice. [3] Sadly, we did not choose a dessert island. That would have
been much more&amp;nbsp;fun.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="physics challenge"></category><category term="macguyver"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>The Magnetar Credit Card Swipe</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/the-magnetar-credit-card-swipe.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-30T17:22:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-01-30:posts/the-magnetar-credit-card-swipe.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TTumQ-3TLgI/AAAAAAAAAJE/BI366RfOTR0/s1600/nedflanderscredit.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TTumQ-3TLgI/AAAAAAAAAJE/BI366RfOTR0/s320/nedflanderscredit.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Ned Flanders&amp;#8217; credit card doesn&amp;#8217;t satisfy the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Luhn_algorithm"&gt;Luhn&lt;/a&gt; checksum, but could probably still be erased by a&amp;nbsp;magnetar.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello, Internet! Today I&amp;#8217;d like to talk about the Magnetar Credit Card
Swipe. Sounds like some sinister short on a derivatives deal, doesn&amp;#8217;t
it? Well, no need to worry, we don&amp;#8217;t deal with scary things like that
here. Instead, we are going to talk about a super-magnetized neutron
star speeding past Earth. A while ago I heard that a magnetar can erase
all the world&amp;#8217;s credit cards from half the distance to the moon. I did a
little research and it seems like this is the go-to &amp;#8220;fun fact&amp;#8221; about
magnetars. Almost every time they are brought up in a popular science
article, their credit card-erasing prowess is sure to get a mention. So
let&amp;#8217;s check it out! First things first, though. What the heck is a
magnetar [1]? Well, &amp;#8220;magnetar&amp;#8221; is just a spiffy name for a particular
flavor of neutron star. Now, neutron stars are already pretty extreme
objects. They&amp;#8217;ve got a little more than the mass of the sun squished
down to the size of a big city with a central density over 10 trillion
times greater than&amp;nbsp;lead.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TUXMdXcrmoI/AAAAAAAAAJI/K2MVmanh5g4/s1600/earthmag.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TUXMdXcrmoI/AAAAAAAAAJI/K2MVmanh5g4/s200/earthmag.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Dipolar magnetic&amp;nbsp;field&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What makes magnetars truly name-worthy (and more extreme than Doritos
and Mountain Dew at the X-Games) is the fact that they have strong
magnetic fields. And when I say strong, I mean &lt;em&gt;really&lt;/em&gt; strong. Taking
the magnetic field to be dipolar (like the Earth&amp;#8217;s, see figure), the
field at the poles of a magnetar can be as high as 10^15 gauss [2]. For
comparison, the magnetic field of the Earth is about half a gauss and
the big magnets used in MRIs are about 10^4 gauss. So we&amp;#8217;re talking
about some big fields! Looking up the specs for a typical credit card,
it looks like most take about 1000 gauss to erase. And now we can get
started. I always forget the exact form of the magnetic field of a
dipole, but Jackson doesn&amp;#8217;t. He tells me that it is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
\vec{B}\left(\vec{r}\right) =
\frac{3\vec{n}\left(\vec{n}\cdot\vec{m}\right) -
\vec{m}}{|\vec{r} |^3}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where m is the magnetic dipole moment, r is
the displacement vector to where we are measuring the field, and n is a
unit vector that points to where we are measuring. To find the magnitude
(which is what we really care about), we just take the dot product of
the vector with itself and take the square root. Working this out we get
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ B\left(\vec{r}\right) = \frac{|\vec{m}|}{r^3}{\left[
3\cos^2{\theta}+1\right]}^{1/2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where theta is the angle between
the magnetic moment vector and the direction vector n. But we are just
looking for a rough estimate here so let&amp;#8217;s just set the cosine term to
one. Now we have
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ B\left(r\right) = \frac{2|\vec{m}|}{r^3}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
We can now use the above to our advantage. Since we are assuming we know
the polar magnetic field strength, we can rearrange and solve for the
magnetic moment. At the pole of a star the distance is just going to be
the radius, so for radius R and field strength Bp, we get
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ |\vec{m}|} = \frac{1}{2}B_{p}R^3 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Plugging this back in, we get a nice little formula for the strength of
the magnetic field in terms of the stellar radius and the polar field
strength
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$B(r) = B_{p}{\left(\frac{R}{r}\right)}^3 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
And we are almost there! Rearranging now for r, we get &lt;mathjax&gt;$$r =
R{\left[\frac{B_p}{B(r)}\right]}^{1/3} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Huzzah! Now we just need
to plug in some values. Well, we&amp;#8217;ll use Bp = 10^15 gauss, B(r) = 1000
gauss (strong enough field to erase credit cards) and R = 10 km, which
gives&amp;#8230; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ r \approx 10km \times
{\left(\frac{10^{15}gauss}{10^{3}gauss}\right)}^{1/3} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ r
\approx \mbox{100,000 km} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; The moon is about 380,000 km away. So we
find that the magnetar will erase all credit cards up to a little over a
quarter the distance to the moon. Not bad! However, all this talk of
&amp;#8220;half&amp;#8221; and &amp;#8220;quarter&amp;#8221; is a bit misleading given that our best guesses
here will be order of magnitude. But, overall, we see that a magnetar at
roughly the Earth-Moon distance would have a good shot at erasing your
credit cards. Fun fact confirmed!
[1] For a really nice Scientific American article about magnetars, see
&lt;a href="http://solomon.as.utexas.edu/~duncan/sciam.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. For more
information than you could probably ever want, see
&lt;a href="http://solomon.as.utexas.edu/~duncan/magnetar.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.
[2] For those of you who prefer your magnetic field strengths given in
units named after someone played by David Bowie in a
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/The_Prestige_(film)#Cast"&gt;movie&lt;/a&gt;, you may
note the conversion: 1 gauss = 10^-4&amp;nbsp;tesla.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="magnetar"></category><category term="credit cards"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="neutron star"></category></entry><entry><title>Holiday Hidden Message Revealed</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/holiday-hidden-message-revealed.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2011-01-03T23:52:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2011-01-03:posts/holiday-hidden-message-revealed.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TSDGkyEUkPI/AAAAAAAAAIc/4rTQYB9jyNE/s1600/longfellow.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TSDGkyEUkPI/AAAAAAAAAIc/4rTQYB9jyNE/s320/longfellow.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Here we present the solution to the Holiday Code (original post
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/12/holiday-hidden-message.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;).
The content of the message is from the creepy looking gentleman to the
left, Henry Wadsworth Longfellow. He is perhaps most famous for writing
the poem, &amp;#8220;Paul Revere&amp;#8217;s Ride.&amp;#8221; I have taken another one of his popular
poems, &amp;#8220;&lt;a href="http://www.potw.org/archive/potw118.html"&gt;Christmas Bells&lt;/a&gt;,&amp;#8221;
and hidden its first verse in a huge mess of random letters. The
message: &amp;#8220;I heard the bells on Christmas Day Their old, familiar carols
play, And wild and sweet The words repeat Of peace on earth, good-will
to men!&amp;#8221; Sounds pretty pleasant at the start. But it was written at the
height of the Civil War and it gets pretty heavy towards the end.
Longfellow was an ardent abolitionist and most of his poems contain
allusions to the plight of slaves. He was also close friends with
Senator Charles Sumner, whose own fiery oratory and opposition to
slavery famously put him on the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Charles_Sumner#Antebellum_career_and_attack_by_Preston_Brooks"&gt;wrong
side&lt;/a&gt;
of a Southern cane. So how do we go about divining the message above
from the mess of the original code? Well, the message is explicitly in
there, it&amp;#8217;s just hidden by a bunch of randomly generated letters. To get
the message out, one needs to know how the junk is distributed. To do
that we use the first hint. The first hint was a list of pie fillings.
So we will need to use pi to find out how the junk is filling the
message:
ybeinhhhzcezavdqfnrkutxyvqlzdwctagqdzbhderikeazrbcgjhwentgyqjnylvonrzobvclzeskypvscejbpftuzoladngzckwuhwcvdreyxrsmlwivrauuxssotmhakglmtawuahzdslwudvouxcasjaqzeynatsvzizxlhlxzbcrsziersohkirguobghmobedlwjwunozwdgptofdatcmgspjmrmprxepckiulxwiewniqgegzlzbpauntrzqvcsuscacpndngxjxyanvrrfqthhisomgnqxlsspnrufgljlhcwcywavxyaibvndjyonnfuxstkydsqpawrhpbjbwpeixkgblwcvddcrcofaipfdkkkgdnjkdrbaswfhqdypoevwrbezwtegtwnobuhtqnsyhethvoxhwcookyhahvaqrzquyoiduusrupmeqdefeypsyneoecpvvlatexnweorsufzhsaphcenptwpoywhuxqlrfprnaeusrqaqxdqrlqzcsnejaozjohxpnfccsemuavrltvafxoujhgjebvyyofehogomooljtoshbrdpeknoxdwwvrislevhplxyrzcfiotokrvjqlvwmvkgfdfedhqdin
There are 3 junk letters before the first message letter, 1 before the
next, then 4, 1, 5, &amp;#8230; So the number of junk letters before a message
letter is given to you by pi. This
&lt;a href="http://www.eveandersson.com/pi/digits/1000000"&gt;site&lt;/a&gt; may prove&amp;nbsp;useful&amp;#8230;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="cipher"></category><category term="longfellow"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Benford’s Law</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/benford-s-law.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-12-31T14:42:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-12-31:posts/benford-s-law.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;Given a large set of data (bank accounts, river lengths, populations,
etc) what is the probability that the first non-zero digit is a one? My
first thought was that it would be 1/9. There are nine non-zero numbers
to choose from and they should be uniformly distributed, right? Turns
out that for almost all data sets naturally collected, this is not the
case. In most cases, one occurs as the first digit most frequently, then
two, then three, etc. That this seemingly paradoxical result should be
the case is the essence of Benford&amp;#8217;s Law. Benford&amp;#8217;s Law [1] states that
for most real-life lists of data, the first significant digit in the
data is distributed in a specific way, namely: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P(d) =
\mbox{log}_{10}\left(1 + \frac{1}{d}\right) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; The probabilities
for leading digits are roughly P(1) = 0.30, P(2) = 0.18, P(3) = 0.12,
P(4) = 0.10, P(5) = 0.08, P(6) = 0.07, P(7) = 0.06, P(8) = 0.05, P(9) =
0.04. So we would expect the first significant digit to be a one almost
30% of the time! But where would such a distribution come from? Well, it
turns out that it comes from a distribution that is logarithmically
uniform. We can map the interval [1,10) to the interval [0,1) by just
taking a logarithm (base ten). These logarithms are then distributed
uniformly on the interval [0,1). We can now get some grasp for why one
should occur as the first digit more often in a uniform log
distribution. In the figure below, I have plotted 1-10 on a logarithm
scale. In a uniform log distribution, a given point is equally likely to
be found anywhere on the line. So the probability of getting any
particular first digit is just its length along that line. Clearly, the
intervals get smaller as the numbers get bigger.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TR4s91iaKKI/AAAAAAAAAIU/uxYE4eqknCY/s1600/logscale.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TR4s91iaKKI/AAAAAAAAAIU/uxYE4eqknCY/s400/logscale.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
But we can quantify this, too. For a first digit on the interval [1,10),
the probability that the first digit is &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; is given by:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P(d) = \frac{\mbox{log}_{10}(d+1)
-\mbox{log}_{10}(d)}{\mbox{log}_{10}(10) -\mbox{log}_{10}(1)} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
which is just &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P(d) =\mbox{log}_{10}(d+1) -\mbox{log}_{10}(d) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
or &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P(d) = \mbox{log}_{10}\left( 1 + \frac{1}{d} \right) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which
is the distribution of Benford&amp;#8217;s Law. So how well do different data sets
follow Benford&amp;#8217;s Law? I decided to test it out on a couple easily
available data sets: pulsar periods, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; city populations, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; county
sizes and masses of plant genomes. Let&amp;#8217;s start first with pulsar
periods. I took 1875 pulsar periods from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ATNF&lt;/span&gt; Pulsar Database (found
&lt;a href="http://www.atnf.csiro.au/research/pulsar/psrcat/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). The results
are plotted below. The bars represent the fraction of numbers that start
with a given digit and the red dots are the fractions predicted by
Benford&amp;#8217;s Law.
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRpObM6LxrI/AAAAAAAAAH8/tz9WQ98H258/s1600/benford_pulsar.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRpObM6LxrI/AAAAAAAAAH8/tz9WQ98H258/s400/benford_pulsar.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
From this plot, we see that the pulsar period data shows the general
trend of Benford&amp;#8217;s Law, but not exactly. Now let&amp;#8217;s try &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; city
populations. This data was taken from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; census bureau from the
2009 census and contains population data for over 81,000 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; cities. We
see from the chart below that there is a near exact correspondence
between the observed first-digit distribution and Benford&amp;#8217;s Law.
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRpQhzrSFmI/AAAAAAAAAIA/ZP3YTbWiiM4/s1600/benford_uscities09.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRpQhzrSFmI/AAAAAAAAAIA/ZP3YTbWiiM4/s400/benford_uscities09.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Also from the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; census bureau, I got the data for the land area of
over 3000 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; counties. These data also conform fairly well to
Benford&amp;#8217;s Law.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRpSE9pHC1I/AAAAAAAAAII/dqG382dqoCw/s1600/benford_land.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRpSE9pHC1I/AAAAAAAAAII/dqG382dqoCw/s400/benford_land.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Finally, I found
&lt;a href="http://data.kew.org/cvalues/CvalServlet?querytype=1"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; neat website
that catalogs the genome masses of over 2000 different species of
plants. I&amp;#8217;m not totally sure &lt;em&gt;why&lt;/em&gt; they do this, but it provided a ton
of easy-to-access data, so why not?
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRpR82I2X1I/AAAAAAAAAIE/XdFQozbC7eY/s1600/benford_plant.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRpR82I2X1I/AAAAAAAAAIE/XdFQozbC7eY/s400/benford_plant.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Neat, so we see that wide variety of natural data follow Benford&amp;#8217;s Law
(some more examples
&lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/BenfordsLaw.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). But why should
they? Well, as far as I have gathered, there are a few reasons for this.
The first two come from a paper published by Jeff Boyle [2]. Boyle makes
(and proves) two claims about this distribution. First, he claims that
&amp;#8220;the log distribution [Benford&amp;#8217;s Law] is the limiting distribution when
random variables are repeatedly multiplied, divided, or raised to
integer powers.&amp;#8221; Second, he claims that once such a distribution is
achieved, it &amp;#8220;persists under all further multiplications, divisions and
raising to integer powers.&amp;#8221; Since most data we accumulate (scientific,
financial, gambling,&amp;#8230;) is the result of many mathematical operations,
we would expect that they would tend towards the logarithmic
distribution as described by Boyle. Another reason for why natural data
should fit Benford&amp;#8217;s Law is given by Roger Pinkham (in &lt;a href="http://www.williams.edu/go/math/sjmiller/public_html/BrownClasses/197/benford/Pinkham_FirstDigit.pdf"&gt;this
paper&lt;/a&gt;).
Pinkham proves that&lt;em&gt;&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;the only distribution for the first significant
digits which is invariant under scale change of the underlying
distribution&amp;#8221; is Benford&amp;#8217;s Law. This means that if we have some data,
say the lengths of rivers in feet, it will have some distribution in the
first digit. If we require that this distribution remain the same under
unit conversion (to meters, yards, cubits, &amp;#8230; ), the only distribution
that satisfies this distribution would be the uniform logarithmic
distribution of Benford&amp;#8217;s Law. This &amp;#8220;scale-invariant&amp;#8221; rationale for this
first digit law is probably the most important when it comes to data
that we actually measure. If we find some distribution for the first
digit, we would like it to be the same no matter what units we have
used. But this should also be really easy to test. The county size data
used above was given in square miles, so let&amp;#8217;s try some new units.
First, we can try square kilometers.
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TR09Vq1jCAI/AAAAAAAAAIM/1Yz5gp0-7CY/s1600/benford_landkm.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TR09Vq1jCAI/AAAAAAAAAIM/1Yz5gp0-7CY/s400/benford_landkm.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Slightly different than square miles, but still a very good fit. Now how
about square furlongs?
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TR093IwIt8I/AAAAAAAAAIQ/ern61I_MJQ0/s1600/benford_landfurlong.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TR093IwIt8I/AAAAAAAAAIQ/ern61I_MJQ0/s400/benford_landfurlong.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Neat! Seems like the distribution holds true regardless of the units we
have used. So it seems like a wide range of data satisfy Benford&amp;#8217;s Law.
But is this useful in any way or is it just a statistical curiosity?
Well, it&amp;#8217;s mainly just a curiosity. But people have found some pretty
neat applications. One field in which it has found use is &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Forensic_accounting"&gt;Forensic
Accounting&lt;/a&gt;, which I
can only assume is a totally rad bunch of accountants that dramatically
remove sunglasses as they go over tax returns. Since certain types of
financial data (for example, see
&lt;a href="http://www.uic.edu/classes/actg/actg593/Readings/Auditing/The-Effective-Use-Of-Benford's-Law-To-Assist-In-Detecting-Fraud-In-Accounting-Data.pdf"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;)
should follow Benford&amp;#8217;s Law, inconsistencies in financial returns can be
found if the data is faked or manipulated in any way. Moral of the
story: If you&amp;#8217;re going to cook the books, remember Benford! [1]
Benford&amp;#8217;s Law, in the great tradition of &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Stigler's_law_of_eponymy"&gt;Stigler&amp;#8217;s
Law,&lt;/a&gt; was
discovered by Simon Newcomb. [2] Paper can be found
&lt;a href="http://www.jstor.org/pss/2975136"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;. Unfortunately, this is only a
preview as the full version isn&amp;#8217;t publicly available without a library
license. The two points that I use from this paper are at least stated
in this&amp;nbsp;preview.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="statistics"></category><category term="benford"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Holiday Hidden Message</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/holiday-hidden-message.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-12-24T13:05:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-12-24:posts/holiday-hidden-message.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRTgRvmyQYI/AAAAAAAAAHw/Hg5dDp4N22I/s1600/robot-santa.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TRTgRvmyQYI/AAAAAAAAAHw/Hg5dDp4N22I/s200/robot-santa.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Evil gun-wielding code-breaking robo-santa from&amp;nbsp;Futurama&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Greetings and happy holidays! Everyone has gone home for the break, so
we will be taking a break from the grossly misnamed &amp;#8220;Problem of the
Week&amp;#8221; for a while. Instead, here&amp;#8217;s a &amp;#8220;Christmas Code&amp;#8221; I made up for a
friend. Figure it out and win the respect of strangers on the Internet!
Largely unhelpful hints after the break.
ybeinhhhzcezavdqfnrkutxyvqlzdwctagqdzbhderikeazrbcgjhwentgyqjnylvonrzobvclzeskypvscejbpftuzoladngzckwuhwcvdreyxrsmlwivrauuxssotmhakglmtawuahzdslwudvouxcasjaqzeynatsvzizxlhlxzbcrsziersohkirguobghmobedlwjwunozwdgptofdatcmgspjmrmprxepckiulxwiewniqgegzlzbpauntrzqvcsuscacpndngxjxyanvrrfqthhisomgnqxlsspnrufgljlhcwcywavxyaibvndjyonnfuxstkydsqpawrhpbjbwpeixkgblwcvddcrcofaipfdkkkgdnjkdrbaswfhqdypoevwrbezwtegtwnobuhtqnsyhethvoxhwcookyhahvaqrzquyoiduusrupmeqdefeypsyneoecpvvlatexnweorsufzhsaphcenptwpoywhuxqlrfprnaeusrqaqxdqrlqzcsnejaozjohxpnfccsemuavrltvafxoujhgjebvyyofehogomooljtoshbrdpeknoxdwwvrislevhplxyrzcfiotokrvjqlvwmvkgfdfedhqdin
Hint 1: Apple, pumpkin, pecan, &amp;#8230;
Hint 2: Paul&amp;nbsp;Revere&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="cipher"></category><category term="longfellow"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>A Buffoon’s Toothpicks</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/a-buffoon-s-toothpicks.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-12-18T17:33:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-12-18:posts/a-buffoon-s-toothpicks.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TQ0mf2YO5II/AAAAAAAAAHo/WMor9trnTnM/s1600/P1010471.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TQ0mf2YO5II/AAAAAAAAAHo/WMor9trnTnM/s320/P1010471.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 1: Two of the thousands of toothpicks on my&amp;nbsp;floor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You&amp;#8217;re sitting at a bar, bored out of your mind. You&amp;#8217;ve got an unlimited
supply of pretzel rods and a lot of time to kill. The floor is made of
thin wooden planks. How can you calculate pi? This is how the problem of
Buffon&amp;#8217;s needle was first presented to me. Stated more formally the
problem is this: given a needle of length &lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt; and a floor of parallel
lines separated by a distance &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;, what is the probability of a randomly
dropped needle crossing a line? Working this all out (see a derivation
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Buffon's_needle"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;, for example), we
find that the probability a needle crosses a line is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P =
\frac{2l}{d\pi} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So now we have a nice way of experimentally coming
up with a value for pi. Simply by tossing a bunch of needles of length
&lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt; on a striped surface with lines separated by a distance &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; and
counting the total number of times a needle crosses a line and the total
number of throws, we can approximate the probability (and thus, pi). I
say &amp;#8220;approximate&amp;#8221; because it will only be true in the limit of an
infinite number of throws. Anyway, we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{\mbox{Number
of crosses}}{\mbox{Number of throws}} \approx P = \frac{2l}{\pi d}
$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so, rearranging a bit, we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \pi \approx \left(
\frac{2l}{d} \right) \left(\frac{\mbox{Number of
throws}}{\mbox{Number of crosses}} \right) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Now we have something
that we can go about measuring. I am going to define the following value
to be the experimental quantity we aim to measure: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \tilde{\pi} =
\left( \frac{2l}{d} \right) \left(\frac{\mbox{Number of
throws}}{\mbox{Number of crosses}} \right) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So now that we know what
we are measuring, let&amp;#8217;s get to it! Since I&amp;#8217;m not allowed to use needles
in my home experiments anymore, I decided to use toothpicks. For my
striped surface, I just used the wooden floor in our house (see Figure
1). The toothpick length was almost exactly the same as the distance
between lines on the floor, so we see that that the &lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt;and &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt; terms
cancel in our expression above. To make the measurements, I threw ten
toothpicks at a time onto the floor and counted how many crossed the
lines. I chose ten because it seemed like a nice number. It was small
enough that I shouldn&amp;#8217;t expect too much clumping of the toothpicks (and
unwanted correlations in the data), but large enough that I didn&amp;#8217;t have
to drop and pick up a single toothpick a thousand times. I threw the
groups of ten toothpicks 100 times and tallied the results. Thus, I have
1000 throws of a single needle. It took the entirety the movie
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Undercover_Brother"&gt;Undercover Brother&lt;/a&gt; to
throw and pick up all those toothpicks, but when all was said and done I
found that out of 1000 thrown toothpicks, 618 crossed the line. Plugging
this back into our equation above (and remembering &lt;em&gt;l&lt;/em&gt; = &lt;em&gt;d&lt;/em&gt;), we get &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
\tilde{\pi}=\left(\frac{2l}{d}\right) \left(\frac{\mbox{Number
of throws}}{\mbox{Number of crosses}} \right)=2
\left(\frac{1000}{618}\right)=3.23$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Well that&amp;#8217;s not too far off I
guess. But it&amp;#8217;s certainly not the pi that I know and love. What went
wrong? As I mentioned before, since I am only doing a finite number of
runs here I am not finding the exact probability. So is there anyway to
gauge our uncertainty? Sure. Since we are doing a counting experiment
with a lot of events, we can approximate our error using Poisson
statistics. For a Poisson distribution, the standard deviation is just
the square root of the number of events (in this case, crosses). So we
have that our total number of crosses is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \mbox{Number of crosses} =
618 \pm \sqrt{618} = 618 \pm 24.9 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So now if we want to find the
uncertainty in our final measurement, we&amp;#8217;ll have to propagate the error
through. This gives us a final value of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \tilde{\pi} = 3.23 \pm
0.13 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and we see that the exact value of pi falls within there. We can
see that this value gets better and better if we plot our value of pi as
a function of the number of throws. Figure 2 shows the measured value of
pi (with error bars) over a wide range of throw numbers. The actual
value of pi is plotted as a green&amp;nbsp;line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TQ0rGuJSDQI/AAAAAAAAAHs/Sllf1A-h1tw/s1600/buffonpi.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TQ0rGuJSDQI/AAAAAAAAAHs/Sllf1A-h1tw/s400/buffonpi.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 2: Measured pi value in blue, actual in green, click for bigger&amp;nbsp;version&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we see that the more toothpicks we drop, the closer and closer we get
to pi. Hot dog! Certainly an evening well&amp;nbsp;spent.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="buffon's needle"></category><category term="toothpicks"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Problem of the Week #3: Solution</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/problem-of-the-week-3-solution.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-12-15T02:01:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-12-15:posts/problem-of-the-week-3-solution.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TPnT0ucqSUI/AAAAAAAAAHk/kOFxbYCSx1g/s1600/koala.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TPnT0ucqSUI/AAAAAAAAAHk/kOFxbYCSx1g/s200/koala.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Cold-Blooded&amp;nbsp;Killer&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hello all and welcome to to another roundup of Problem of the Week. If
the time intervals don&amp;#8217;t seem to be adding up, just remember that &amp;#8220;week&amp;#8221;
is an illusion here at Virtuosi headquarters. &amp;#8220;Problem of the Week,&amp;#8221;
doubly so. But enough with the excuses, let&amp;#8217;s see if Mr. Bond lives to
Die Another Day. The situation presented in the problem was one of a
glass of water filled all the way to the top with a single ice cube in
it. The goal is to see if any water falls to the floor as the ice cube
melts. The simplest analysis would be to just consider the displacement
of water by the ice cube. By Archimedes&amp;#8217; principle we know that the
buoyant force on the ice cube is equal to the weight of the water
displaced by the ice cube. But since the ice cube is floating, we know
that the buoyant force is equal to the weight of the ice cube.
Therefore, the ice cube just displaces it&amp;#8217;s own weight in water. So as
the ice cube melts, the water level stays the same and no water is
spilled over. Stated a bit more explicitly, we have that the buoyant
force is the weight of the displaced water: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F_b = m_{water}g =
{\rho}_{water}V_{water}g $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where we have just expressed the mass of
the water as the density of water times the volume of the water
displaced. Likewise, the weight of the ice cube is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ W_{ice} =
m_{ice}g = {\rho}_{ice}V_{ice}g $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; But since the ice cube is
floating, the buoyant force is equal to the weight. Setting the above
equations equal to each other and rearranging a bit, we can solve for
the volume of the water displaced by the ice cube: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ V_{water} =
\frac{{\rho}_{ice}V_{ice}}{{\rho}_{water}} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Great, now we have
the volume of water that the ice cube displaced, so now we just need to
see what volume of water the ice cube will add once it melts. Since we
know that the mass of ice cube better be the same as the mass of the
water left after it melts, we can write &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ {\rho}_{ice}V_{ice} =
{\rho}_{water}V_{water} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which gives that the total volume of the
water is just
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ V_{water} = \frac{{\rho}_{ice}V_{ice}}{{\rho}_{water}} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
which is exactly the same volume we found before. Therefore, when the
ice cube melts it fills up exactly the same amount of volume as the
water displaced to hold up the ice cube, so the water level remains the
same and James Bond lives!
Or does he? Well, he sure does if the system is entirely described by
the analysis above. But we need to be exact here since a single drop
would set off the Koala death trap. We have considered the biggest
contributions to the change of volume of the water (and easiest to
calculate!), but we have ignored a large number of much much smaller
effects on the volume. Typically these effects would be swept aside and
callously labeled &amp;#8220;negligible,&amp;#8221; but since even the smallest change of
volume could mean life or death for our hero, they must be accounted for
to give a final &amp;#8220;exact&amp;#8221; answer.
Unfortunately, &amp;#8220;exact&amp;#8221; isn&amp;#8217;t something science can do very well. We can
only do as good as the measurements we make allow. And since I gave you
practically no information, this was very tough. However, one could
consider the magnitude of the effects given typical values and see which
side wins out. But if two competing effects give similar values under
reasonable conditions, it becomes very difficult to give an answer.
The last two &amp;#8220;Problems of the Week&amp;#8221; were well posed math problems, each
with a clear-cut &amp;#8220;correct&amp;#8221; answer. This one was a physics problem and
physics is a lot messier than math. That may initially seem less
satisfying, but it means that there is a whole lot of interesting &amp;#8220;mess&amp;#8221;
to sort out! I really enjoyed reading the
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/11/problem-of-week-3.html#more"&gt;comments&lt;/a&gt;
detailing all the neat small effects to the change of volume that I
ignored in my solution. Density variations as a function of temperature,
surface tension effects, evaporation and thermal expansion all play some
role in determining the final answer. There&amp;#8217;s a whole lot of interesting
physics going on!
Without knowing the exact conditions a bit more and doing a whole lot
more work, it seems as though I will not be able to provide a final
physics solution. But, having seen just about every Bond movie, I can
give an answer with a certainty not afforded to me by science: Mr. Bond
lives. How do I know this? Well, it is common knowledge that James Bond
has tiny smoke grenades in the soles of his shoes that release a potent
koala knock-out potion specifically created by Q. So Bond releases these
into the koala death pit, rendering the vicious beasts harmless. Then he
uses his watch laser to cut any bindings Dr. Cherrycoke may have placed
him in, falling into the death pit. The fall leaves Mr. Bond uninjured,
as a cuddly mass of sleeping koalas break his fall. By stacking the
koalas into a rudimentary series of steps, Mr. Bond ascends out of the
death pit and free to save the world&amp;#8217;s ice supply from the evil Dr.
Cherrycoke.&amp;nbsp;Obviously.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="koalas"></category><category term="problem of the week"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Pet Projects</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/pet-projects.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-11-14T12:38:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-11-14:posts/pet-projects.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TOAM4LfDLkI/AAAAAAAAAHU/-bbyWAodpc0/s1600/cat+drink+straw.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TOAM4LfDLkI/AAAAAAAAAHU/-bbyWAodpc0/s320/cat+drink+straw.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  You&amp;#8217;re doing it&amp;nbsp;wrong!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Here at the Virtuosi, we have a very specific way of asking a very
specific type of question that sounds anything but specific. These are
the &amp;#8220;How come [blank]?&amp;#8221; questions [1]. These are very simple questions
that just about every four year old asks, but likely never get
sufficiently answered. To get a feel for what I mean by these questions
I provide the following translations of problems we have either
considered or will consider:
Q: How come trees?
Translation: How tall can trees be?
Q: How come plants?
Translation: Why are plants green?
These are my very favorite types of questions because they are
completely understandable by everyone and promise to have very
interesting physics working behind the scenes. So I&amp;#8217;ve been thrilled to
see two such questions considered by scientists lately that have also
had a good run in popular media. They are:
Q: How come cats?
Translation: How do cats drink? and
Q: How come dogs?
Translation: How do dogs shake?
The question of how cats drink was
&lt;a href="http://web.mit.edu/preis/www/mypapers/cats_Science_Express_Reis_Aristoff_Stocker.pdf"&gt;answered&lt;/a&gt;
recently by a few dudes from &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MIT&lt;/span&gt;, Virginia Tech and Princeton. One
morning, one of the guys was just watching his cat drink water and
realized he couldn&amp;#8217;t immediately figure out how it worked, so he decided
to do a bit more research and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BAM&lt;/span&gt;! science happens.
It turns out that the cat isn&amp;#8217;t just scooping up the water with it
tongue as one would probably have expected. Instead the cat uses its
tongue to effectively punch the water, drawing up a column of fluid.
They then bite this column and get a very itty bitty kitty mouthful of
water. Here it is in a slow motion video I stole from the Washington
Post who stole it from Reuters: (You&amp;#8217;ll probably have to sit through an
ad, apologies)
And here&amp;#8217;s a series of stills that illustrates the same thing:
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TOAVxjml42I/AAAAAAAAAHc/06dcbYUsowM/s1600/12cats_graphic-popup-v2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TOAVxjml42I/AAAAAAAAAHc/06dcbYUsowM/s400/12cats_graphic-popup-v2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Not a cat person? Well there was also a study done a month or so ago
about dog shaking. If you have a dog, you have almost certainly
experienced the elegant way in which a wet dog un-wettafies itself.
Well, a few students at Georgia Tech were also familiar with this
shaking and just happened to have a super high speed camera that could
track water droplets. I assume it only took a short period of time to
put two and two together and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BAM&lt;/span&gt;! science happens. In addition to
providing the logical extension of the &amp;#8220;spherical cow&amp;#8221; joke to &amp;#8220;dog of
radius R&amp;#8221;, the study also found some fairly surprising results. If we
are spinning a wet cylinder (i.e. dog), we would assume that the water
is held on by some &amp;#8220;sticking force.&amp;#8221; Then to shake off these droplets,
we&amp;#8217;d assume that the dog would have to shake fast enough that the
centrifugal force would overcome the sticking force. In other equations,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F_{centrifugal} = m{\omega}^2 R $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F_{sticking} = C $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So
we would then expect the shaking frequency to be the frequency that gets
those two guys to equal each other. We would thus predict
&lt;mathjax&gt;$${\omega} \sim R^{-0.5} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where the little squiggle just means that the frequency scales as the
radius to the -0.5 power, with some constant multipliers out front that
we don&amp;#8217;t know so we just ignore.
But this is not what the Ga Tech guys observed! Check out the video
below:
So there&amp;#8217;s still something else going on that wasn&amp;#8217;t in our simple
model. But this is what makes science so exciting! Even something dogs
and cats figured out long ago can have some really rich and interesting
physics. So keep on asking those questions! Notes: [1] Interestingly
enough, the first &amp;#8220;How come [blank]?&amp;#8221; questions we asked did not have
the now canonical form. Instead, it was stated as &amp;#8220;Why are cows?&amp;#8221;. After
much deliberation, we found that the solution is &amp;#8220;Because milkshakes.&amp;#8221;
Fair&amp;nbsp;enough.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="hello kitty"></category></entry><entry><title>Beards and Pulsars</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/beards-and-pulsars.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-28T02:56:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-09-28:posts/beards-and-pulsars.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TKF59ueq6-I/AAAAAAAAAHM/-dRSw4CNM3w/s1600/hulse_postcard.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TKF59ueq6-I/AAAAAAAAAHM/-dRSw4CNM3w/s200/hulse_postcard.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  The bearded half of&amp;nbsp;Hulse-Taylor&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A few weeks ago I was on a bus going through Scranton and I read a
super-awesome fun fact regarding the Hulse-Taylor binary pulsar in
&lt;em&gt;Black Holes, White Dwarfs and Neutron Stars&lt;/em&gt;. Sadly, I have since
forgotten it and left the book a few thousand miles away. So, let&amp;#8217;s just
make up our own! First, we need a little background. What the heck is a
pulsar? A pulsar is a rapidly rotating neutron star that beams
electromagnetic radiation towards us, which is how we can see them.
Typical rotation periods range from a millisecond to a few seconds. So
each time the pulsar rotates, we observe a blip when the radiation beams
towards us. Since these objects are additionally very stable rotators,
they are essentially very accurate clocks with which we may make
astronomical measurements. So what&amp;#8217;s the Hulse-Taylor binary pulsar? The
Hulse-Taylor binary is almost exactly what it sounds like: it&amp;#8217;s a pulsar
binary where one of the pulsars is pointed towards earth. It was the
first binary of it&amp;#8217;s kind discovered and offers a unique look into a
very high gravity environment. It also provided a very nice test for
General Relativity. General Relativity predicts that two orbiting
massive bodies should emit gravitational waves. This emission of
gravitational waves will then cause the orbit to decay and the two
bodies to move closer together. So does the Hulse-Taylor binary show
this? Take a look:
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TKF5SwXxsXI/AAAAAAAAAHI/wPELMEGlWW0/s1600/PSR_1913_new_large.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TKF5SwXxsXI/AAAAAAAAAHI/wPELMEGlWW0/s400/PSR_1913_new_large.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The
data fit the prediction of general relativity perfectly! For this
discovery Hulse and Taylor shared the 1993 Nobel prize in Physics. Now
that&amp;#8217;s all well and good, but I was promised some fun facts&amp;#8230;? Ah, yes!
Well, we mentioned that the Hulse-Taylor binary orbit is decaying. It
turns out that the orbit is decaying at about 3.5 meters per year.
That&amp;#8217;s pretty slow. Let&amp;#8217;s put it into a more conventional speed, like
meters per second. So &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 3.5 m/yr = 3.5 m/yr \times \frac{1 year}{3.14
\times 10^7 s} = 1.1 \times 10^{-7} m/s $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; or, in less useful units,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 3.5 m/yr = 110 nm/s $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Great, so what to compare this to? Well, all
people who are in the know know that I am a manly man who gained the
ability to grow facial hair sometime after my sophomore year of college.
And since I have to pretend to be an upstanding member of society this
week, I happen to know the last time I shaved. Thus, a few simple
measurements and I can estimate how long hair takes to grow. The last
time I shaved was three days ago and a quick eyeball measurement (sadly
I have no ruler) gives a facial hair length of about 2mm. Thus, a beard
grows at about 0.7 mm/ day. &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 0.7 mm/day = 0.7 mm/day \times
\frac{10^{-3} m}{mm} \times \frac{1 day}{86400s} = 8 nm/s $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; This is
a universal speed constant, which we shall call the speed of beard. Or,
bowing to our oppressive overload sponsors&lt;em&gt;, we shall call it &amp;#8220;Gillette
Mach 1.&amp;#8221; So doing a quick division, we find that the rate at which the
Hulse-Taylor binary&amp;#8217;s orbit is shrinking is roughly 14 times beard
speed, or in our commercial units, Gillette Mach 14 (a razor close
shave!). &amp;#8220;Well,&amp;#8221; I hear you cry (a bit disappointed&amp;#8230;?), &amp;#8220;that&amp;#8217;s &lt;/em&gt;&lt;em&gt;a
&lt;/em&gt;pretty&lt;em&gt; useless unit, but can&amp;#8217;t we be &lt;/em&gt;more&lt;em&gt; useless?&amp;#8221; Yes, dear
reader, we certainly can! We are currently at
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=2xZp-GLMMJ0"&gt;Snuggie&lt;/a&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0Ym65h1bmJ0"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;levels
of uselessness right now, but I think we can just about bump it up to
&lt;/em&gt;&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=0ONJfp95yoE"&gt;Member of Congress&lt;/a&gt;*
useless if we try. A furlong is a unit of length about 200 meters long.
A fortnight is a unit of time about 14 days long. Therefore, if we want
a speed we just&amp;#8230; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{furlong}{fortnight} = 1
\frac{furlong}{fortnight} \times \frac{200 m}{furlong} \times
\frac{1 fortnight}{14 \times 86400 s} = 1.6 \times 10^{-4}
\frac{m}{s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So the rate of decay of the Hulse-Taylor binary is:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 3.5 \frac{m}{yr} = 1.1 \times 10^{-7} m/s \times \frac{1
furlong/fortnight}{ 1.6 \times 10^{-4} m/s} = 7 \times 10^{-4}
\frac{furlong}{fortnight} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Hooray! So now we know the decay rate of
the Hulse-Taylor binary orbit in two horrible units: either 700
microfurlongs per fortnight or 14 times the speed of beard (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AKA&lt;/span&gt; Gillette
Mach 14). Please write these in your copybooks now and forever commit
them to memory. * In no way is The Virtuosi affiliated with the
wonderful Gillette Company, which makes the world&amp;#8217;s best razors. Since
we aren&amp;#8217;t affiliated with this great Gillette company, we are not
obligated to repeat their slogan that it&amp;#8217;s &amp;#8220;The Best A Man Can Get&amp;#8221;
despite its self-evident truth. Nor is the author required to say that
the silky smooth shave I get with a Mach 20 razor is the only reason I
can even must social interaction.&amp;nbsp;Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pulsar"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="furlong per fortnight"></category></entry><entry><title>Microseconds and Miles</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/microseconds-and-miles.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-09-12T23:04:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-09-12:posts/microseconds-and-miles.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The following is an unfinished manuscript found under heaps of rubble
and pizza boxes here at Virtuosi headquarters. It appears to be some
sort of screen play, though one would be hard-pressed to figure this out
solely from the script. The true giveaway was the 100 page addendum (not
published) full of potential titles and acceptance speeches. I dare not
bore you with these vanity pages in their entirety, but just for
completeness and posterity I include some samples.
For possible titles we have: &amp;#8220;Dr. Dre, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;OR&lt;/span&gt;: How I Learned to Stop
Worrying and Love the Metric,&amp;#8221; &amp;#8220;How to Teach Physics to your Dee Oh
Double G (West Coast Edition),&amp;#8221; &amp;#8220;Bring Da Ruckus: ODEs by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;ODB&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8221; and
&amp;#8220;Flavor Flav&amp;#8217;s Flavor Physics&amp;#8230;boooyeeeee!&amp;#8221; among other even worse and
less relevant titles.
Among the acceptance speeches we have one that starts: &amp;#8220;I would like to
thank the Academy, Scott Bakula and Chuck D. You know what you did.
Here&amp;#8217;s a song I wrote&amp;#8230;&amp;#8221;, etc. It is all very painful.
There is almost no value to this document whatsoever, but it does
present a nice fun fact about &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt;. The legible parts of the script are
thus presented below. The illegible parts appear to have been obscured
by some caustic mixture of Mountain Dew, pizza sauce and tears. &lt;strong&gt; &lt;em&gt;We
descend to the bottom of the abandoned mineshaft recently converted to
the headquarters of General Stanley K. Ripper. He is currently engaged
in a heated discussion with his science advisor, Dr. Vontavious Dre. We
join mid-sentence as a result of lazy writing&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: &amp;#8230;shortage of scientists! What&amp;#8217;s that? Yeah, you could
definitely call it a &amp;#8220;chronic&amp;#8221; shortage if you want. But semantics
aren&amp;#8217;t important right now. The &amp;#8220;G&amp;#8221;-sector needs more funding.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: You are my most trusted science advisor, Dr. Dre, but you
already have one staff scientist&amp;#8230;a Dr. Snoop Dogg, I believe&amp;#8230;? How
many scientists do we need doing relativity here? This is the military!
We need Moonraker lasers and nuclear hand grenades. So no more funding
unless&amp;#8230; That is, unless you figured out the&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: No sir, we still don&amp;#8217;t have a Stargate.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: Well then you are just wasting my time! I want something
useful. Either something that goes boom or something that helps
something that goes boom. What I don&amp;#8217;t need is a theoretical money
drain.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: And how did you find your way to work today, sir?&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;
&lt;/strong&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: What? You know very well I ride my horse, Neigh-braham
Lincoln. He knows how to get here.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: And how does Nifty &amp;#8216;Nabe know where to go&amp;#8230;?&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt;, of course!&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: Bingo. That&amp;#8217;s our department. Without correcting for general
relativistic effects (the specialty of the &amp;#8220;G&amp;#8221;-sector, I may add), &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt;
would be completely useless. Let me show you.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;A large blackboard drops down from the ceiling and a slow steady beat,
just barely audible, seems to come from all directions. Dre writes the
following equation on the board:&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ds^2 = -\left(1-\frac{R_s}{r} \right)c^2dt^2+ \left( 1 -
\frac{R_s}{r} \right)^{-1} dr^2 + r^2 \left( d{\theta}^2 +
{\sin\theta} {d\phi}^2 \right)$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
This equation gives the line element for a Schwarzschild metric. The
R_s in the equation is called the &amp;#8220;Schwarzschild Radius&amp;#8221; and is given
by
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ R_s = \frac{2GM}{c^2} .$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: Is that Karl Schwarzschild? I remember reading a delightful
biography of him somewhere&amp;#8230;? Anyway, what the heck is this &amp;#8220;line
element&amp;#8221; thing&amp;#8230;?
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: Good question. Essentially what we get is the differential
change in the space-time interval ( ds ) if we change all the
coordinates by a very tiny little bit. What is nice about this is that
although coordinates are a tricky thing in general relativity and can
change from one observer to another, the space-time interval is an
invariant quantity. That is, different observers will measure the same
space-time interval between events even though they may measure
different times and distances.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: So this space-time interval is just a kind of space-time
distance that different observers will agree on?
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: Right-o. And this invariance allows us to compare different
reference frames. Eventually, we will use this invariance to get the
frequencies observed by an observer on the surface of the earth and one
traveling along with a satellite in orbit. Since we will only be
considering observers at fixed radius and fixed theta = 90 degrees (ie
at the equator), we can simplify things a bit. Since we will have a
fixed radius and theta value we have that:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ dr = 0 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ d\theta = 0 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
and
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\sin\theta = 1 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Plugging these simplifications into our line element gives:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ds^2 = -\left( 1 - \frac{R_s}{r} \right)c^2 dt^2 + r^2
d\phi^2 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: Neato Toledo!
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: Right, so now we divide out the -c^2 dt^2 term on the right
hand side. So we have:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ds^2 = -c^2 dt^2 \left[ \left( 1 - \frac{R_s}{r} \right) -
\frac{r^2}{c^2} \frac{d\phi^2}{dt^2} \right] $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
But this is just &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ds^2 = -c^2 dt^2 \left[ \left( 1 -
\frac{R_s}{r} \right) - \frac{r^2}{c^2} {\left(\frac{d\phi}{dt}
\right)}^2 \right] $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
But what does that d phi / dt term look like?
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: Sure looks like an angular velocity to me. But don&amp;#8217;t we need
to be careful with these rates?
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: Yep, that is an angular velocity term. We need to be a little
careful with these rates. Essentially, in the coordinate system we have
chosen the time is something like the time measured at r = infinity and
thus the rate would also be measured from r = infinity. Plugging in
omega as our angular velocity, we now have:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ds^2 = -c^2 dt^2 \left[ \left( 1 - \frac{R_s}{r} \right)
-\left( \frac{r {\omega}}{c} \right)^2 \right] $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
But we want to figure out the times on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; satellites, so we&amp;#8217;ll need
some measure of how time ticks by as measured by the orbiting observer.
In the rest frame of the observer, we have that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ds^2 = -c^2 {d\tau}^2 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where the tau is the &amp;#8220;proper time&amp;#8221; of the observer. It tells us the time
that the observer measures on his clocks. To find the frequency (in
other words, how quickly the observer clock ticks by a second) we just
have
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ f = \frac{1}{d\tau} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
And now we have enough background to start talking about &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt;!
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: Hooray! Should I go get my horse&amp;#8230;?
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: I don&amp;#8217;t think that&amp;#8217;s necessary&amp;#8230;? Anyway, let&amp;#8217;s model our &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt;
system as a satellite in a 26,000 km orbit [1]. Meanwhile our earth
reference frame will be an observer standing on the surface of the
earth. So let&amp;#8217;s write out our line element for each reference frame.
First the satellite frame:
&lt;em&gt;As Dr. Dre works, the beat steadily gets louder.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ds^2 = -c^2 {dt}^2 \left[ \left( 1 - \frac{R_s}{R_{sat}}
\right) -{\left( \frac{\omega_{sat} R_{sat}}{c} \right)}^2
\right] $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So the frequency at which a satellite clock ticks is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ f_{sat} = \frac{1}{dt} \left[ \left( 1 - \frac{R_s}{R_{sat}}
\right) -{\left(\frac{\omega_{sat} R_{sat}}{c} \right)}^2
\right]}^{-1/2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and likewise the earth frame:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ ds^2 = -c^2 {dt}^2 \left[ \left( 1 - \frac{R_s}{R_{earth}}
\right) -{\left(\frac{\omega_{earth} R_{earth}}{c} \right)}^2
\right] $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So the frequency at which an earth clock ticks is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ f_{earth} = \frac{1}{dt} \left[ \left( 1 -
\frac{R_s}{R_{earth}} \right) -{\left( \frac{\omega_{earth}
R_{earth}}{c} \right)}^2 \right]}^{-1/2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Taking the ratio of these frequencies tells us how quickly the satellite
clocks tick relative to the earth clocks. We get:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{f_{sat}}{f_{earth}} = {\left[ \frac{\left( 1 -
\frac{R_s}{R_{earth}} \right) -{\left( \frac{\omega_{earth}
R_{earth}}{c} \right)}^2 }{\left( 1 - \frac{R_s}{R_{sat}}
\right) -{\left( \frac{\omega_{sat} R_{sat}}{c} \right)}^2 }
\right]}^{1/2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
And we&amp;#8217;re done. So what do we get? Let&amp;#8217;s plug in some numbers:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ r_{sat} = 26 \times 10^6 m $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ R_{earth} = 6.3 \times 10^6 m$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\omega_{earth} = 7.3 \times 10^{-5} rad/s $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\omega_{sat}=\sqrt{\frac{GM}{{r_{sat}}^3}}=15 \times 10^{-5}
rad/s $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ c = 3 \times 10^8 m/s $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
We can also find the Schwarzschild radius of the Earth to be
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ R_s = 8.9 mm $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Now you still have that fancy calculator, right General? Can you plug
all this stuff in there and tell me what you get?
&lt;em&gt;General Ripper works diligently on the calculator for a few minutes,
then shows the calculator to Dr. Dre.&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: &amp;#8220;01134&amp;#8221;..? No that can&amp;#8217;t be correct. Did you plug in the values
I &amp;#8230; ?
&lt;em&gt;General, with a wry smile, turns the calculator upside down and shows
Dr. Dre.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: Ah, well &amp;#8220;hello&amp;#8221; to you to sir. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: And I&amp;#8217;ve got
another! Now where&amp;#8217;s that eight key&amp;#8230;? &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: I guess I&amp;#8217;ll just do
the math in my head&amp;#8230;
&lt;em&gt;The background beat, which had just reached a crescendo immediately
drops out as Dre thinks&lt;/em&gt;. &lt;em&gt;Then comes right back in as he begins to
speak again&amp;#8230;&lt;/em&gt;
&lt;strong&gt;
Alright, I got that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\frac{f_{sat}}{f_{earth}} = 1 + 4.4 \times 10^{-10} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
From this we see that the satellite clock ticks faster (i.e. at a higher
frequency) than does the earth clock. The difference is very very small.
For every second that ticks by on earth, we see that the difference in
the earth and satellite clocks increases by 4.4 * 10^{-10} seconds.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: But we are talking about half a billionth of a second!
There&amp;#8217;s no way that can do much harm.
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: Well remember, that&amp;#8217;s per second. So over the course of a day
(86,400 s), the satellite has picked up 38 microseconds. But that
corresponds to&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ d = c \times t = ( 3 \times 10^8 m/s ) \times ( 38 \times
10^{-6} s ) = 11 km $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So without correcting for general relativity, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; systems would be off
by 11 km per day!
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GEN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RIPPER&lt;/span&gt;: I am impressed! Here&amp;#8217;s millions of dollars in funding!
Hooray!
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DR&lt;/span&gt;. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DRE&lt;/span&gt;: Hooray!
&lt;em&gt;Dr. Dre and General Ripper jump up and give each other a mid-air high
five. We freeze-frame this scene and&lt;/em&gt;&amp;#8220;Don&amp;#8217;t You Forget About Me&amp;#8221; &lt;em&gt;plays
as the credits roll.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/strong&gt;
&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;THE&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;END&lt;/span&gt; (?)&lt;/em&gt; &lt;strong&gt; &lt;/strong&gt; [1] Thanks to Tom from &lt;a href="http://blogs.scienceforums.net/swansont/"&gt;Swans on
Tea&lt;/a&gt; (one of my favorite
physics blogs) for fixing a mistake for me. I had initially done the
calculation assuming the satellite was in a geosynchronous orbit (about
42,000 km) and got a time delay of 48 microseconds. As it turns out, the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GPS&lt;/span&gt; satellites are really at an orbit of about 26,000 km, which gives a
time delay of 38 microseconds. I have made the appropriate changes and
the calculations now reflect this more accurate value.&amp;nbsp;**&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="dr. dre"></category><category term="GPS"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Ringing A Bridge</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/ringing-a-bridge.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-08-14T21:16:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-08-14:posts/ringing-a-bridge.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGc4zKuS4oI/AAAAAAAAAGw/dQHhvZBgASQ/s1600/bridgepic.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGc4zKuS4oI/AAAAAAAAAGw/dQHhvZBgASQ/s320/bridgepic.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Matt and Jared standing on our&amp;nbsp;experiment&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When you strike a bell, it rings at a given frequency. This frequency is
called the resonant frequency and is the natural frequency at which the
bell likes to ring. Just about anything that can shake, rattle, or
oscillate will have a resonant frequency. Things like quartz crystals,
wine glasses, and suspension bridges all have a resonant frequency. The
quartz crystals oscillate at frequencies high enough for accurate
timekeeping in watches, the wine glasses at audible frequencies to make
boring dinners more interesting, and bridges at low enough frequencies
that you can feel it when you walk. It is the resonant frequency of
bridges that we decided to measure.
To make our measurements, we &amp;#8220;borrowed&amp;#8221; Yariv&amp;#8217;s fancy phone. One of the
nice things about fancy new phones is that most of them have internal
accelerometers to detect motion. You can do a whole bunch of fun
experiments and take some pretty good data with these accelerometers
(see, for example, physicist and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt; star Rhett Allain&amp;#8217;s posts over at
&lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/dotphysics/iphone/"&gt;dot physics&lt;/a&gt;). Placing
Yariv&amp;#8217;s phone on the suspension footbridge on campus, Alemi, Matt and I
took data and confused passers-by for about 15 minutes. The
accelerometer in the phone measures acceleration in three coordinate
directions: x is along the width of the bridge, y is along the length of
the bridge, and z is up and down. The raw data is shown below. The z
data is shown in blue, and x and y in green and red.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNrbHEsuvI/AAAAAAAAAGA/4WyG8OuNww0/s1600/bridge_rawtime.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNrbHEsuvI/AAAAAAAAAGA/4WyG8OuNww0/s400/bridge_rawtime.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
The first thing you&amp;#8217;ll notice about this data is that the z direction
(blue) has big spikes in it around 180s, 300s, and 800s. The biggest
spikes are when Alemi and I jumped up and down to ring the bridge. The
smaller bumps in the blue data are the result of people walking or
jogging by.
With the raw acceleration data and knowledge of the sample rate of the
accelerometer ( 90 Hz ), we can Fourier transform it to get frequencies.
Doing this to the raw data for each dimension we get the following
spectrograms. Each of the spectrograms illustrates how much of each
frequency is present at each point in time.
The most relevant direction for us is the z direction. We see that at
several points there are strong signals at all frequencies followed by
longer periods where the main signal is around 1 Hz. These events
correspond to when Alemi and I jumped up and down and are analogous to
ringing a bell. The striking of the bell is just a sharp impulse
(roughly a delta function) which is composed of all frequencies. Soon
after the impulse, all of the frequencies die out except for the
resonant frequency, which keeps on ringing. Just looking at this graph,
it looks like the bridge resonant frequency is around 1 Hz.
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNvFsSzqGI/AAAAAAAAAGI/m2Tr3GwM1qM/s1600/bridge_Zspec.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNvFsSzqGI/AAAAAAAAAGI/m2Tr3GwM1qM/s400/bridge_Zspec.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
We can also make similar graphs for the x and y directions. Remember,
the x direction is the width of the bridge and the y direction is the
length of the bridge. Although there is less motion in these directions,
the spikes where we jumped and people walked by are still clearly
visible.
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNxb8WcJMI/AAAAAAAAAGY/tLPA6SbyyeE/s1600/bridge_Xspec.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNxb8WcJMI/AAAAAAAAAGY/tLPA6SbyyeE/s400/bridge_Xspec.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNxNPkNSTI/AAAAAAAAAGQ/3Xkx2WKFv6w/s1600/bridge_Yspec.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNxNPkNSTI/AAAAAAAAAGQ/3Xkx2WKFv6w/s400/bridge_Yspec.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Finally, we can find out how much of a particular frequency is in the
whole signal. To do this we take find the power spectrum density of the
entire data set (blue is z, green is x and red is y). The ringdown
frequency of about 1 Hz we saw in the spectrograms above after the jumps
is illustrated in this graph as the first blue peak. There are also some
other peaks at around 15 Hz, 25 Hz and 35 Hz. I am not sure what they
correspond to.
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNyNOZDLEI/AAAAAAAAAGg/a3eLidFVn3Y/s1600/bridge_psd.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGNyNOZDLEI/AAAAAAAAAGg/a3eLidFVn3Y/s400/bridge_psd.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
To clean up this a bit, we can just take the data without the jumps in
it. Computing a new power spectrum density with just the data from about
400s - 700s, we get the following graph, which also displays a fairly
prominent peak around 1 Hz.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGcYbMuUbTI/AAAAAAAAAGo/v2d2bMQNsoE/s1600/psd.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TGcYbMuUbTI/AAAAAAAAAGo/v2d2bMQNsoE/s400/psd.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
So it seems that there is definitely something going on around 1 Hz.
Initially, I was worried that this is just the rate at which people walk
and therefore it was just showing up because we had people walking the
whole time. However, the strong 1 Hz signal after each ringing in each z
spectrogram seems to indicate that it is intrinsic to the bridge.
Therefore, it seems as though the resonant frequency in the z direction
of the bridge is about 1 Hz. But don&amp;#8217;t take our word for it. If you want
to do your own analysis, you can find the raw data
&lt;a href="http://docs.google.com/leaf?id=0Bwd5hrDOxWsrMjZmOTZiZDYtMjBjNC00MjM5LWFiOTktMzg2N2Y3MmQ4NTM1&amp;amp;hl=en&amp;amp;authkey=CNuUt-EH"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bridges"></category><category term="phone data"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Death of Karl Schwarzschild</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/on-the-death-of-karl-schwarzschild.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-07-24T23:54:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-07-24:posts/on-the-death-of-karl-schwarzschild.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;\&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TEevPyrqW6I/AAAAAAAAAF4/nI7Q_2RQZV0/s1600/Karl+Schwarzschild.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TEevPyrqW6I/AAAAAAAAAF4/nI7Q_2RQZV0/s200/Karl+Schwarzschild.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Every once in a while, in the study of science, one comes across
biographical snippets that momentarily breathe life into names that
otherwise serve as shorthand for equations and eras. As an obvious
effect of the selection bias involved with including this superfluous
information in technical books, they are bound to be pretty interesting.
Such stories range from the hilarious antics of Feynman [1] or Fermi
[2], to the heartbreaking stories of
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Ludwig_Boltzmann#Final_years"&gt;Boltzmann&lt;/a&gt;
and
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Oppenheimer_security_hearing"&gt;Oppenheimer&lt;/a&gt;,
and even to the surprisingly scandalous life of Erwin Schrödinger. But
my all time favorite of all these historical &amp;#8220;fun facts&amp;#8221; is that of the
man who provided the first exact solution to the Einstein field
equations while fighting in the First World War: Karl Schwarzschild
(pictured left impersonating a surprised walrus&amp;nbsp;[3]).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Karl Schwarzschild was an astronomer, physicist and mathematician; an
across the board physical scientist with passions both abstract and
practical. He published his first article regarding the orbits of double
stars at the age of 16 while still in high school. He went on to work on
the mathematical treatment of orbits, constructed several useful
astronomical instruments, and put forward theoretical treatments of
comet tails and stellar atmospheres. His creativity was admired by some
of the greatest scientists of his era. Eddington, chief among them,
offered his praise in a strangely brutal simile&amp;nbsp;[4]:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;em&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;&amp;#8230; his joy was to range unrestricted over the pastures of
knowledge, and, like a guerrilla leader, his attacks fell where they
were least&amp;nbsp;expected.&amp;#8221;&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;But Schwarzschild&amp;#8217;s greatest contribution to science was finding the
first exact solution to Einstein&amp;#8217;s field equations for general
relativity in 1916. This solution, which takes the form of the
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Schwarzschild_metric"&gt;Schwarzschild
metric&lt;/a&gt;, describes
the space-time surrounding a non-rotating spherically symmetric object
(the solution for a rotating spherically symmetric object was found in
1963 by Roy Kerr). It was through this metric that I came to meet
Schwarzschild, since every time it is introduced in a class the
instructor is sure to drop the mother of all fun facts: Schwarzschild
discovered his solution while in the army during World War I, a war that
would eventually kill him (among&amp;nbsp;others).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this age of Wikipedia, I find it hard to believe that I didn&amp;#8217;t
immediately go home and check the full story behind this statement. I
may very well have, but over the years I have constructed a myth about
the death of Schwarzschild that I at least half believed until I finally
looked up the full story for this&amp;nbsp;post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I imagined Schwarzschild as the noble and peaceful scientist immediately
skeptical of the war, but eventually conscripted to fight. There he
fought on the front lines, carrying both a Mauser and a notebook. He
would spend the long lulls between suicidal assaults through
no-man&amp;#8217;s-land huddled down in the mud in the trenches scribbling away
like mad at what would eventually become the elegant solution that bears
his&amp;nbsp;name.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then (and here I will blatantly plagiarize the &lt;em&gt;All Quiet on the Western
Front&lt;/em&gt;movie) Schwarzschild began to see the solution, everything started
to fall in place. He became excited and no longer able to sit still. Now
standing, he reached out towards the beauty of nature he saw not in a
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=ShscVNkUmy0"&gt;butterfly&lt;/a&gt; or
&lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=DJcBC2Am-uU"&gt;bluebird&lt;/a&gt;, but in the
fabric of space-time. Just as he finishes his solution, Schwarzschild&amp;#8217;s
head briefly peaks above the trench and is caught by a sniper&amp;#8217;s bullet.
Both he and his notebook fall to the mud unnoticed, an overly
romanticized symbol for the futility of war or some such&amp;nbsp;nonsense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this version is obviously false (how did he get the solution to
anyone?), but it is the one that has persisted in my mind grapes. So
what really happened? When &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=YQkaD6fG8mk"&gt;war were
declared&lt;/a&gt; in 1914,
Schwarzschild volunteered for the German army and manned weather
stations and calculated missile trajectories in France, Belgium, and
Russia. It was in Russia that he discovered and published his well-known
results in relativity as well as a derivation of the Stark effect using
the &amp;#8216;old&amp;#8217; quantum mechanics. It was also in Russia that he began to
struggle with pemphigus, an autoimmune disease where the body starts
attacking its own cells. He was sent home, where he died in 1916 at the
age of&amp;nbsp;42.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The reality is much more sensible than my version, and still a good tale
in its own right: a brilliant scientist cut down in his prime, working
until the very end. So why did I unconsciously elevate a respectable
tale to one of mythical proportions? I think it has something to do with
how we view the great scientists of the past. Since they were
extraordinary at one thing (some scientific field), we assume they must
have been extraordinary in every regard. Therefore, their fates must
carry some deeper meaning or symbolism. But it turns out that the
reality, while certainly less romantic, may be more satisfying (to
some), that these men and women whose names live on tied to equations
were just regular people who happened to be very good at one thing:
being&amp;nbsp;scientists.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Or maybe it&amp;#8217;s just my inability to separate movies from real life. Who&amp;nbsp;knows?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[1] &lt;em&gt;Surely You&amp;#8217;re Joking, Mr. Feynman&lt;/em&gt; is essentially the gag reel for
20th century physics. It can be
&lt;a href="http://www.amazon.com/Surely-Feynman-Adventures-Curious-Character/dp/0393316041"&gt;purchased&lt;/a&gt;
with money if you&amp;#8217;re into the whole capitalism thing. Or for all you
pinko commies and poor grad students there are two free options. One,
assemble approximately one gaggle of undergrad physics majors or
Virtuosi bloggers and proceed to give them the shakedown, at least one
copy should pop out. Two, look into big government
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Public_library"&gt;socialism&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[2] See Virtuosi blog post,&amp;nbsp;Future.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[3] Some scholars use this picture as evidence of Schwarzschild&amp;#8217;s
involvement as the nerdiest and most forgotten Marx Brother. There is no
evidence to suggest his was, in fact, Poindexter&amp;nbsp;Marx.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[4] Quote (and most facts) lifted from
&lt;a href="http://www-groups.dcs.st-and.ac.uk/~history/Biographies/Schwarzschild.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;,
take that&amp;nbsp;Wikipedia!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[5] Apologies for the excessive and irrelevant links!&amp;nbsp;[6]&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;[6] Apologies for the excessive and unnecessary&amp;nbsp;footnotes!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Schwarzschild"></category><category term="footnotes"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>My Pepsi* Challenge</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/my-pepsi-challenge.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-06-08T01:30:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-06-08:posts/my-pepsi-challenge.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz2-SbRtAI/AAAAAAAAAFY/eaUWEFQHTDs/s1600/bottles.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz2-SbRtAI/AAAAAAAAAFY/eaUWEFQHTDs/s200/bottles.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The
basement of the Physics building has a Pepsi machine. Over the course of
two semesters Alemi and I have deposited roughly the equivalent of the
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDP&lt;/span&gt; of, say, Monaco to this very same Pepsi machine (see left, with most
of Landau and Lifshitz to scale). It just so happens that Pepsi is now
having a contest, called &amp;#8220;Caps for Caps,&amp;#8221; in which it is possible to win
a baseball hat. There are several nice things about this contest.
Firstly, I drink a lot of soda. Secondly, I like baseball hats. So far
so good. Lastly (and most important for this post), is that it is fairly
straightforward to calculate the statistics of winning (or at least
simulate them).
So how does the game work? Well, on each soda cap the name of a Major
League Baseball team is printed. All thirty teams are (supposedly)
printed with the same frequency, so the odds of getting any particular
team are 1/30. You can win a hat by collecting three caps with the same
team printed on them. So if I had five caps, the following would be a
win:
Phillies Cubs Tigers Phillies Phillies
whereas the following would not win me anything:
Yankees Rays Blue Jays Orioles Royals
and I would also lose if I had:
Mets Nationals Braves Braves Mets.
In addition, one in eight caps gets you 15% off on some &lt;mathjax&gt;$50 dollar or
more purchase to MLB.com or something like that. For simplicity, I
ignored these 15% off guys, but all they will do is push back the number
of caps you need by one for every eight purchased. It should not be too
difficult to factor these ones in, but I was lazy and I already made all
these nice graphs, so...
The first thing I tried to do was just simulate the contest. I wrote a
little Python script that randomly generates a team for each cap and
counts my wins over a given number of caps purchased. Running this about
100,000 times for all number of caps between 1 and 61 (with 61
guaranteed to win) and averaging over the number of wins, I could
determine both the expected number of wins per cap value and the
probability of winning at least once. The results are shown below.
[![image](http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAwPaC7VV-I/AAAAAAAAAEA/ei6DPQ09bmI/s400/CapsforCaps(sim1).png)](http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAwPaC7VV-I/AAAAAAAAAEA/ei6DPQ09bmI/s1600/CapsforCaps(sim1).png)
[![image](http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxwinoE0FI/AAAAAAAAAFA/VTOnToOXcmM/s400/WinsvsSodas.png)](http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxwinoE0FI/AAAAAAAAAFA/VTOnToOXcmM/s1600/WinsvsSodas.png)
But we can also exactly solve this game. This turned out to take longer
for me (I'm bad at probability) than just simulating the darn thing. I
had initially included my derivation in the post but it was long,
muddled, and none too illuminating, so I took it out. But I super-duper
promise I did it and can post if you really really want to know.
Otherwise, I have just plotted the predicted results below (as a red
curve) along with the simulated data (blue dots). Turns out they agree
pretty well!
[![image](http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxxKz3m-MI/AAAAAAAAAFI/S6YpmCcO1Fs/s400/CapsforCapsSimandPred.png)](http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxxKz3m-MI/AAAAAAAAAFI/S6YpmCcO1Fs/s1600/CapsforCapsSimandPred.png)
Just eyeballing the graph, we see that after 18 or 19 sodas the chances
of winning are about a half. Beyond about 25 or so it appears to be
almost 90% that you'll win at least once. In reality, these percentages
would occur about 2 or 3 caps later to compensate for the 15% off
thingies. So now that we have some numbers and can trust our model a
bit, let's see how worth it this contest is for us.
First, we can ask: Is this a good way to get a hat cheaper than retail
value (about $&lt;/mathjax&gt;15)? To quantify &amp;#8220;worth it&amp;#8221; I have chosen to find the
value of winnings (price of hat times expected number of wins) minus the
cost of caps (how much I spend on soda). I am fairly embarrassed to say
that the cost of each soda is &lt;mathjax&gt;$1.75. See plot below.
[![image](http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxzBhvw-4I/AAAAAAAAAFQ/RiKEfFBDqig/s400/ValueDifferential.png)](http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAxzBhvw-4I/AAAAAAAAAFQ/RiKEfFBDqig/s1600/ValueDifferential.png)
From this plot, we see that it doesn't become "worth it" (that is, value
of winnings is greater than cost of sodas) until about 40 sodas
purchased. That's a lot! In fact, we see that just when I start feeling
pretty confident I'll win something (around 20-25 sodas), I'm right in a
big valley of "totally not worth it." So if I just want a baseball hat,
I'm better off forking over the $&lt;/mathjax&gt;15 dollars.
Although, one does see from this plot that once I get above about 40 or
so sodas, it becomes much more cost effective to just keep buying sodas
and winning hats. However, Pepsi tries to stifle this a bit in the
&lt;a href="http://www.pepsiusa.com/capsforcaps/"&gt;rules&lt;/a&gt;, stating that &amp;#8220;Limit one
(1) Official &lt;span class="caps"&gt;MLB&lt;/span&gt;® baseball cap per name, address or household.&amp;#8221; Unless I
either make a lot of friends real soon or develop a creative definition
of my address, it looks like I&amp;#8217;m out of luck.
But what if I want a hat but I don&amp;#8217;t want to actually buy soda like a
chump? This contest, like many others, needs to have a &amp;#8220;No Purchase
Necessary&amp;#8221; clause for some legal reason or another (so they aren&amp;#8217;t
lotteries or gambling or something). I had assumed they (the nameless
overlords at Pepsi) would limit the number of caps possible from just
mailing in, but it doesn&amp;#8217;t seem that way. From the Official rules,
Chapter Two, verses nine to twenty-one:
&amp;#8220;Limit one (1) free game piece per request, per stamped outer envelope.&amp;#8221;
That sounds to me like you could get as many as you want, as long as you
use different envelopes. So we can redo our cost analysis with the cost
of getting one cap as the cost of a stamp. Putting the value of a cap
now at the cost of a stamp (44 cents), we get the following:
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz3jfb-KcI/AAAAAAAAAFg/erU1nZU7ZCg/s1600/mailincaps.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz3jfb-KcI/AAAAAAAAAFg/erU1nZU7ZCg/s400/mailincaps.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Zooming in:
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz3tj6kg8I/AAAAAAAAAFo/MDHgjjjS2J0/s1600/mailinZoom.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/TAz3tj6kg8I/AAAAAAAAAFo/MDHgjjjS2J0/s400/mailinZoom.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Hey, that seems worth it! And it should, since from above we saw that
the probability of winning after about 30 caps was in the high 90% &amp;#8216;s.
The cost of getting 30 caps this way is the cost of 30 stamps, which is
less than the $15 that the hat is (supposedly) worth. So if I really
wanted a hat from this contest and didn&amp;#8217;t feel like drinking all my
money away, I&amp;#8217;d just send away for the mail-in pieces.
I may try this method, since it seems to be allowed under the rules.
Although, even a strict constructionist reading of the contest rules
pretty much allows Pepsi to do whatever the heck it wants. Either way,
I&amp;#8217;ll be sure to update to see how well my model holds&amp;nbsp;up!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;*&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOTE&lt;/span&gt;: In no way is The Virtuosi blog affiliated in any way with Pepsi.
We may occasionally purchase Pepsi products (like sweet tasting Wild
Cherry Pepsi!), but we don&amp;#8217;t do it because we think it makes us look
&amp;#8220;cool&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;hip&amp;#8221; or &amp;#8220;rad&amp;#8221; (we &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KNOW&lt;/span&gt; it does). In fact, drinking too much
soda can have certain adverse health effects (like making you stronger,
faster, and in general more attractive). So if you want to have a Pepsi
product (like sweet tasting Wild Cherry Pepsi!) every now and then
(literally, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EVERY&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;INSTANT&lt;/span&gt;), go ahead. But drinking too many Pepsi
products (like sweet tasting Wild Cherry Pepsi!) could make you sick
(with&amp;nbsp;awesome-itis).&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pepsi"></category><category term="how do i get free stuff?"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="baseball"></category></entry><entry><title>Why is the Grass Green?</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/why-is-the-grass-green-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-05-25T23:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-25:posts/why-is-the-grass-green-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was outside talking with Alemi last week and we were both startled to
realize that the frozen white tundras of Ithaca had somehow transformed
into fields of green. Apparently the snow was a temporary fixture that
covered real live grass. Neato, gang! The joy at seeing green grass led
quickly to surprise, confusion and then anger. Why the heck is grass
green? Well, things look a color when they reflect back that color. So
grass is green because its pigments (chlorophyll) absorb only a certain
range of the visible spectrum, reflecting back the greenish bits. But if
I know anything about approximating the sun as a blackbody, I know that
it has a peak output of around 550 nm (i.e. green) light. So what&amp;#8217;s
going on? Why are plants blatantly rejecting the most abundant kind of
light? Since my initial confusion rested on the assumption of the sun as
a blackbody, I decided to take a closer look at the actual spectrum of
the sun. Below is a graph showing the frequency dependence of solar
radiation incident on the top of the atmosphere and at sea level. Since
plants typically don&amp;#8217;t live in space, we are most concerned with the sea
level plot.
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xmXr6HTaI/AAAAAAAAACw/weKj6XTaf4M/s1600/Solar_Spectrum.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xmXr6HTaI/AAAAAAAAACw/weKj6XTaf4M/s400/Solar_Spectrum.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
From this plot, it looks like the incident radiation from the sun is
fairly level beyond about 450nm or so. Just going on this graph alone,
it looks like plants could just absorb reddish light and do alright for
themselves. But do they? Let&amp;#8217;s take a look at the absorption spectrum of
chlorophyll. As it turns out there are a bunch of different &amp;#8220;flavors&amp;#8221; of
chlorophyll (chlorophyll a, b, c, and d). As far as I could gather, only
a and b are important (a is found in just about everything that plays
the photosynthesis game and b is found in plants and green algae). So we
need to find the absorption spectrum of chlorophyll a and b. After
looking for a while at very qualitative drawings, I found this
&lt;a href="http://omlc.ogi.edu/spectra/PhotochemCAD/html/alpha.html"&gt;neato-toledo
site&lt;/a&gt;, which
actually gives real live data. Plotting the results, we get the figure
below.
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xpZIEtjkI/AAAAAAAAAC4/B7RknYpI63w/s1600/chlorophyll.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xpZIEtjkI/AAAAAAAAAC4/B7RknYpI63w/s400/chlorophyll.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Comparing with our handy dandy wavelength-to-color converter below we
see that there is a big peak in absorption of both chlorophyll a and b
in the dark blue and lesser peaks in the red.
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xqlbrKz0I/AAAAAAAAADA/fsx_JmlD5Ks/s1600/spectrum.gif"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xqlbrKz0I/AAAAAAAAADA/fsx_JmlD5Ks/s320/spectrum.gif" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
So how do these absorption lines correspond to the incident light at sea
level given above. Well, its kind of tough to check by eye, but it looks
like chlorophyll has its biggest peaks right below the plateau in the
solar spectrum. Marking the wavelengths of the absorption peaks makes
this clear (a = blue, b = green). It seems like plants are using a
sub-optimal band of the spectrum!
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xrLFfWBXI/AAAAAAAAADI/NwShTicac9A/s1600/solarwithchlorphyll.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xrLFfWBXI/AAAAAAAAADI/NwShTicac9A/s400/solarwithchlorphyll.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
So how do we reconcile this? Well, let&amp;#8217;s first start at The Beginning.
The first photosynthetic organisms developed and spent the first billion
or so years of their existence living and evolving in the oceans. The
solar spectrum we have been using so far has been accurate only in air
at sea level. Presumably it would be favorable for the organism to be
able to survive at some finite depth in the ocean and not merely at the
surface. Thus we must consider the effects of water on our incident
solar radiation. A plot of the absorption spectrum of water is shown
below (note the log-log scale).
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xwl48ZUSI/AAAAAAAAADQ/kPVlOauL1o4/s1600/water+absorption.gif"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_xwl48ZUSI/AAAAAAAAADQ/kPVlOauL1o4/s400/water+absorption.gif" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Lo and behold, the minimum absorption of visible light in water occurs
towards the far end in the blue. And this is exactly where our biggest
absorption peak in of chlorophyll is! Comparing our two graphs we see
that the ratio of incident blue light to incident green light at see
level is at worst about a third. But we see that for each meter traveled
in water, green light is absorbed almost ten times more than blue light.
Thus, an organism that lives a few meters underwater and wants to
harness solar energy would probably do best to focus on that blue light.
[&lt;span class="caps"&gt;WARNING&lt;/span&gt;: The next bit is speculative and I haven&amp;#8217;t taken a bio class
since high school] As much as I gather about chlorophyll from Wikipedia
and other semi-reputable sites, chlorophyll a is found in just about
anything that photosynthesizes, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BUT&lt;/span&gt; chlorophyll b is only found in
plants and green algae. And apparently, land plants are largely
descended from green algae (which are aquatic, but typically around the
surface and around the shoreline). Now take a look at the chlorophyll
absorption spectra again. The chlorophyll b spectrum is sort of squished
in more towards the middle (towards 550 nm maybe?) than chlorophyll a.
In fact, on the graph where I have drawn lines on the solar spectra
graph where the chlorophyll peaks are, we see that chlorophyll b just
barely gets up to that plateau region. This suggests to me that
chlorophyll a was working just fine for the early aquatic plants, but
once they reached land and got out of all that water it became an
advantage to utilize light closer to the peak solar output. Thus, plants
that had chlorophyll b in addition to a had a slight advantage over
their b-less brethren. Or so I shall continue to shamelessly speculate
(and, apparently, alliterate). Anyway, I thought that was kind of cool,
but if I have made some horrible error or mangled some biology, please
let me&amp;nbsp;know!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="chlorophyll more like borophyll"></category></entry><entry><title>Solar Sails III (because two just isn’t enough)</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/solar-sails-iii-because-two-just-isn-t-enough-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-05-17T22:24:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-17:posts/solar-sails-iii-because-two-just-isn-t-enough-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_IKFerS7nI/AAAAAAAAACo/DPNAyMeuMaQ/s1600/leezle+pon+justice.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_IKFerS7nI/AAAAAAAAACo/DPNAyMeuMaQ/s320/leezle+pon+justice.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
One thing that I&amp;#8217;ve wanted to quantify since reading &lt;em&gt;Intelligent Life
in the Universe&lt;/em&gt;, an outstanding book by Carl Sagan and &lt;span class="caps"&gt;I.S.&lt;/span&gt; Shklovskii,
is the idea of exogenesis. Exogenesis is the hypothesis that life formed
elsewhere in the universe and was somehow transferred to earth in the
form of some small seed or spore. Now since &lt;span class="caps"&gt;E.T. E.&lt;/span&gt; coli presumably do
not have little tiny jetpacks or other means of active transport, they
would need to traverse the cosmos in some passive way. One such way
would be solar sailing.
Way back in Solar Sails I, we derived equations describing the maximum
speeds and time-of-travel for various distances for a given solar sail.
Each of these equations was a function of the surface mass density of
the sail, which is just the amount of mass per unit cross-sectional
area. All we need to know is the cross-sectional area and mass of a
given object and we can apply these equations to just about anything!
Assume we have some spherical blob with the density of water (1g/cm^3).
The effective sigma of this blob would just be the mass divided by the
cross-sectional area. In other words,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \sigma = \frac{m}{Area} = \frac{\frac{4}{3}\pi r^3 \rho}{\pi
r^2} = \frac{4}{3}\rho r .$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Rearranging to get r in terms of the other variables, we have
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ r = \frac{3\sigma}{4\rho} . $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Plugging in our density of 1g/cm^3 and a suitable sigma (10^-4
g/cm^2), we get
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ r \le 0.75 \times 10^{-4} cm = 0.75 \mu m .$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Check out
&lt;a href="http://learn.genetics.utah.edu/content/begin/cells/scale/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; fun
site to see what kind of critters can fit in this blob.
From the previous post, we saw that for a sigma of 10^-4 g/cm^2, our
sail would get to the nearest stars on a timescale of order 10,000
years. Thus if our blob has a radius of less than about a micron, it
could spread to hundreds of stars in around 10,000-100,000 years. Even
if it would take millions of years, that would be almost no time at all
on the cosmic scale. Just based on this calculation it all seems fairly
feasible.
In making these calculations I have neglected several important aspects
of the problem. First, in no way have I actually calculated any sort of
probability of this happening. Additionally, I would have to see how
likely it is for some blob to reach planetary escape velocity
(presumably just by riding that tail of the Boltzmann distribution).
Finally, and perhaps most important of all, I have not given any sort of
motivation or mechanism by which some living body could survive hundreds
of thousands of years in the vacuum of space with constant radiation
exposure. But I have heard that some forms of life are totally
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Extremophile"&gt;extreme&lt;/a&gt; (especially if they
drink &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Mountain_Dew"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt;).
Even though such a process seems possible, it certainly doesn&amp;#8217;t seem
like the easiest way to get life on earth. I prefer the much more
satisfying &amp;#8220;amino acids + lightning + magic =
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Abiogenesis"&gt;life&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; model. But it does
offer some interesting possibilities. Suppose we as people think that
people are super awesome and therefore people should be everywhere. We
do some bio magic and put whatever &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DNA&lt;/span&gt; we want into viruses, which we
then pack into as many micron spheres as we can make. We then point them
at the nearest stars and have them disperse.
What would the probabilities be that they land somewhere habitable? Are
there any ethical considerations in doing this? Is it a galactic faux&amp;nbsp;pas?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="exogenesis"></category><category term="solar sails"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="do the dew"></category></entry><entry><title>Solar Sails II</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/solar-sails-ii.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-05-17T01:15:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-17:posts/solar-sails-ii.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;[&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOTE&lt;/span&gt;: In my hurry to make up for weeks of non-posts, I managed to
almost immediately knock Nic&amp;#8217;s &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/05/why-black-holes-from-large-hadron.html"&gt;first
post&lt;/a&gt;
from the top of the page. It&amp;#8217;s got the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LHC&lt;/span&gt;, black holes, and about 3
full cups of metric awesome, so make sure you check it out (after
reading this one, of course).]
Last time we did some calculations on how fast and far our solar sails
can go, but those calculations were just for the sail itself. If you are
going to do any science with it, you&amp;#8217;re going to need a payload. Let&amp;#8217;s
take it a step further and make it an actual spaceship (with people and
everything!).
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_DXvcSsDXI/AAAAAAAAACg/jK_N-B4mOME/s1600/ssradius.png"&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Comparing it with a typical people-carrying space hotel (the
International Space Station), let&amp;#8217;s give our payload a mass of 300,000
kg. Remembering from the last post that a sigma of less that about
10^-4 g/cm^2 gave fairly nice results, we can make an effective sigma
of our payload carrying sail as
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \sigma_{eff} = \frac{m_{total}}{Area} = \frac{m_s +
m_p}{Area}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where m_s is the mass of the sail and m_p is the mass of our payload
(the ship). Assuming the sail has some surface density of sigma and the
sail is circular with some radius r, we have
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \sigma_{eff} = \frac{\pi r^2 {\sigma}_s + m_p}{\pi r^2} =
{\sigma}_s + \frac{m_p}{\pi r^2} . $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Now we can find the radius of our sail such that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \sigma_{eff} \le 10^{-4} \frac{g}{{cm}^2}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Rearranging our equation above and solving for radius, we find that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ r \ge \left[\frac{m_p}{\pi \left( 10^{-4}\frac{g}{cm^2} -
\sigma_s \right)} \right]^{1/2} cm. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Below is a plot of sail radius (in meters) against sail surface density
(g/cm^2).
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_DXvcSsDXI/AAAAAAAAACg/jK_N-B4mOME/s1600/ssradius.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_DXvcSsDXI/AAAAAAAAACg/jK_N-B4mOME/s400/ssradius.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
From this plot, we see that we will need our sail radius to be &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;LEAST&lt;/span&gt;
10 km and the surface density of our sail must be less than 10^-4
g/cm^2. Now that&amp;#8217;s a big sail, but it&amp;#8217;s not obscenely big (depending,
of course, on your definitions of obscenity). One could certainly
imagine such a sail being built, but it would be an impressive
engineering feat.
So get to work engineers! I&amp;#8217;ve already made a whole plot in Mathematica,
I can&amp;#8217;t do&amp;nbsp;everything.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="solar sails"></category><category term="Nic shout outs"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>Solar Sails I</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/solar-sails-i.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-05-16T23:29:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-16:posts/solar-sails-i.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_C9Ll986gI/AAAAAAAAACY/eTykcbU6PTE/s1600/solarsail.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_C9Ll986gI/AAAAAAAAACY/eTykcbU6PTE/s200/solarsail.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Solar sails are in the news again, and this time not just for &lt;a href="http://www.cbsnews.com/stories/2005/06/22/tech/main703405.shtml"&gt;blowing
up&lt;/a&gt;.
The Japanese space agency is
&lt;a href="http://www.space.com/businesstechnology/japan-venus-double-mission-100516.html"&gt;launching&lt;/a&gt;
what they hope to be the first successful solar sail tomorrow. In honor
of that, we will be discussing the physics of solar sails.
First of all, what the heck are solar sails? Solar sails are a means of
propulsion based on the simple observation that &amp;#8220;Hey, sails work on
boats. Therefore, they should work on interplanetary spacecraft (in
space).&amp;#8221; Boat sails work when air molecules hit into the sail and bounce
back. By conservation of momentum, this gives the boat sail an itty
bitty boost in momentum. Summing over the large number of air molecules
moving as wind, the boat gets pushed along in the water. A similar
process works with solar sails, but instead of air molecules doing the
hitting, it&amp;#8217;s photons. Since each photon of a given wavelength has some
momentum, by reflecting that photon the solar sail can gain a tiny bit
of momentum. Summing over the large number of photons coming from the
sun over a long time frame we can get a considerable boost. So let&amp;#8217;s see
how good solar sails are.
First we need to find the net force on our sail. We will certainly have
to deal with gravitational forces (which will slow us down) :
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F_{g} = \frac{-GM_{\odot}m}{r^2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where big M is the mass of the sun and little m is the mass of the sail.
Now we need to find the radiation force on the sail. Since force is just
rate of change of momentum, we can find the change of momentum of one
photon per unit time, then find how many photons are hitting our sail.
So for one elastic collision of a photon with the sail, the change in
momentum will be
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \Delta p = 2 \frac{h\nu}{c} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
and by conservation of momentum, this will also be the momentum gained
by the sail. Now we want to find the number of photons incident on a
given area in a given time. This will just be the energy flux output by
the sun ( energy/ m^2 s ) divided by the energy per photon. In other
words:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ f_n = \frac{L_{\odot}}{4\pi r^2}\frac{1}{h\nu} .$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So now we can get a force by
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{Force} = \left(\frac{\Delta p}{\text{1 photon}} \right)
\times \left(\frac{\text{number of photons}}{area \times
time}\right) \times \left( Area\right) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
which is just
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F_{rad} = 2 \frac{h\nu}{c} \times \frac{L_\odot}{4\pi r^2
h\nu} \times \pi R^2 = \frac{L_{\odot} R^2}{2cr^2} .$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So combining the radiation force with the gravitation force, we have a
net force on the sail of
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ F = \left( \frac{L_{\odot} R^2}{2c} - GM_{\odot}m \right)
\frac{1}{r^2} .$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
This can then be integrated over r to find an effective potential,
giving:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ U = \left( \frac{L_{\odot} R^2}{2c} -
GM_{\odot}m\right)\frac{1}{r} .$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
For simplicity, let&amp;#8217;s just write that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \alpha = \frac{L_{\odot} R^2}{2c} - GM_{\odot}m $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
so
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ U = \frac{\alpha}{r} .$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Now we can start saying some things about this sail. The most
straightforward quantity to find would be the maximum velocity. By
conservation of energy (and starting from some r_0 at rest), we have
that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ v_f = \left[\frac{2\alpha}{m} \left(\frac{1}{r_0} -
\frac{1}{r_f} \right) \right]^{1/2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So as r_f goes to very large values, the subtracted piece gets smaller
and smaller. In the limit that r_f goes to infinity we have that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ v_{max} = \left(\frac{2\alpha}{mr_0}\right)^{1/2} .$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Plugging back in our long term for alpha and plugging in some numbers we
get:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ v_{max} = 42,000 m/s \left( \frac{1.5 \times 10^{-4}}{\sigma} -
1\right)^{1/2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where sigma is just the surface mass density [g/cm^2] of the sail.
Below is a plot of maximum velocity ( m/s) plotted against surface mass
density (g/cm^2). For a sigma of 10^-4 g/cm^2, we get a max velocity
of about 30,000 m/s. Not bad.
&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_CjbwxG-JI/AAAAAAAAAB4/PS7tTqbmLUE/s1600/maxvel.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_CjbwxG-JI/AAAAAAAAAB4/PS7tTqbmLUE/s400/maxvel.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
From this graph we see that there must be some maximum surface density,
above which we don&amp;#8217;t get any (forward) motion at all. This makes sense
since we want our radiation forces (which scale with area) to overcome
our gravitational forces (which scale with mass). And below this maximal
surface density we see a power law behavior. Cool.
We can also find the distance traveled as a function of time. Taking the
final velocity equation above and writing v as dr/dt, we see that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{dr}{dt} = \left[ \frac{2\alpha}{m} \left( \frac{1}{r_0}
- \frac{1}{r_f} \right)\right]^{1/2} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Rearranging and integrating, we can get time (in years) as a function of
distance r (in &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AU&lt;/span&gt;):
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = \frac{0.11 \left(\sqrt{(-1+r)
r}+\text{Log}\left[1+\sqrt{\frac{-1+r}{r}}\right]+\frac{\text{Log}[r]}{2}\right)}{\sqrt{-1+\frac{1.5
\times 10^{-4}}{\sigma}}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
A plot of t vs. r is shown below for typical solar system distances and
a sigma of 10^-4 g/cm^2. We assume that we are launching from earth (1
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;AU&lt;/span&gt;). Since Pluto is at a distance of about 40 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AU&lt;/span&gt;, we see that our sail
could get there in less than 7 years. For comparison, the &lt;a href="http://pluto.jhuapl.edu/"&gt;New
Horizons&lt;/a&gt; probe will use conventional
propulsion to get to Pluto in 9.5 years (and it is the fastest
spacecraft ever made).
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_Ck6enlpVI/AAAAAAAAACI/_gjIHLCm_G8/s1600/ssplutolong.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_Ck6enlpVI/AAAAAAAAACI/_gjIHLCm_G8/s400/ssplutolong.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Zooming in to our starting point around 1 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AU&lt;/span&gt;, we see that there is a
period of acceleration and then the maximum velocity is reached after a
few months. Just eyeballing it, it looks like it takes at least a month
to reach appreciable speed. That it takes so long is a result of the
very small forces involved due to radiation pressure. But even a small
acceleration amounts to a considerable speed if applied for long enough!
&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_CopsUAIrI/AAAAAAAAACQ/_-IqCnf8xs8/s1600/sscloseup.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_CopsUAIrI/AAAAAAAAACQ/_-IqCnf8xs8/s400/sscloseup.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Now Pluto is fine I guess (it&amp;#8217;s the second largest dwarf-planet!), but
how about some interstellar flight? Well, the nearest star is Proxima
Centauri which is about a parsec away. A parsec is 3&lt;em&gt;10^16 m, or about
200,000 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;AU&lt;/span&gt;. From, the plot below (or plugging in to the equation above),
we see that such a trip would take of order 10,000 years. That&amp;#8217;s a long
time, but its not too shabby considering this craft uses no fuel of its
own.
&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_Cgqa_fqDI/AAAAAAAAABw/xxgjj5VEZww/s1600/ssTOTHESTARS.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S_Cgqa_fqDI/AAAAAAAAABw/xxgjj5VEZww/s400/ssTOTHESTARS.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
So solar sails can do some fairly impressive things simply by harnessing
the free energy of the sun. Though this only provides a very small
acceleration, it can be taken over a long enough time to be useful.
However, since the radiation pressure of the sun falls off as 1/r^2, we
start to observe diminishing returns and the sail reaches a max
velocity. But overall the numbers seem fairly impressive. All that
remains now is whether they are feasible to construct. Right now my only
data point for feasibility was that it was in &lt;a href="http://www.starwars.com/databank/starship/solarsailer/"&gt;Star
Wars&lt;/a&gt;, but as I
recall that was a &lt;/em&gt;long* time&amp;nbsp;ago.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="Geonosian solar sailer"></category><category term="solar sails"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>End of the Earth Physics III- Asteroids!</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/end-of-the-earth-physics-iii-asteroids-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-22T18:45:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-22:posts/end-of-the-earth-physics-iii-asteroids-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S9EZLq8fRRI/AAAAAAAAAAc/pg5n-zg70QE/s1600/armageddon.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S9EZLq8fRRI/AAAAAAAAAAc/pg5n-zg70QE/s200/armageddon.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;No
day of earth destroying celebration would be complete without that
apocalyptic all-time favorite: the asteroid. And to be fair, it deserves
to be the favorite. Of all the doomsday predictions out there (nuclear
holocaust for the cynics, death by snoo-snoo for the optimists) it is
the only one that is just about certain to occur at some point in the
geological near future. On top of that, it&amp;#8217;s one that we could
potentially avoid with enough time and some &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Asteroid_deflection_strategies"&gt;neat
ideas&lt;/a&gt; .
Let&amp;#8217;s model an asteroid impact on the earth. We will assume an asteroid
starting from rest at infinity and falling to the surface of the earth
due to earth&amp;#8217;s gravity only. Now obviously these assumptions are not
exactly correct. We can imagine our asteroid not starting from rest or
feeling some force due to the sun. Each of these would certainly change
our answer, but should still be within an order of magnitude of our
result. By conservation of energy, we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{KE}_{i} +
\text{PE}_{i} = \text{KE}_{f} + \text{PE}_{f} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Plugging in the
formulas for kinetic and potential energy, we have &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
\frac{1}{2}m{v_i}^{2} + \frac{-GM_{\oplus}m_a}{{r_{i}}} =
\text{KE}_f + \frac{-GM_{\oplus}m_a}{{r_{f}}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Now, plugging in
our initial conditions of starting at rest at infinity and rearranging,
we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{KE}_f =
\frac{GM_{\oplus}m_a}{{R_{\oplus}}} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Assuming that all of this
kinetic energy is deposited into the earth as heat, we have that our
total energy added to the earth is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{E} =
\frac{GM_{\oplus}m_a}{{R_{\oplus}}} = \frac{(7 \times 10^{-11}
J m kg^{-2})(6 \times 10^{24} kg)}{6 \times 10^{6} m}m_a \approx
(10^{8} J)(\frac{m_a}{1kg}) $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Now let&amp;#8217;s consider an asteroid made
out of iron. Iron is about 10 times denser that water so it has a
density of 10^4 kg/m^3. If our asteroid is a sphere, we can find its
radius given &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ m_a = \frac{4}{3} \pi {R_a}^{3} \rho $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Plugging
this into our energy equation gives energy as a function of asteroid
radius: &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{E} \approx (4 \times 10^{8} J) \times (
\frac{R_a}{1m} )^{3} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;. Now we have the energy released during an
asteroid impact in terms of either the size or the mass. So let&amp;#8217;s do
some destruction. We have heard in the last decade or so that even
relatively small changes in average global temperatures can result in
catastrophe. So let&amp;#8217;s see how big of an asteroid we would need to
deposit enough energy to raise global temperatures by 1 degree (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NOTE&lt;/span&gt;:
this is very much a toy model. For a more realistic and sadistically
addicting model, check out
&lt;a href="http://www.lpl.arizona.edu/impacteffects/"&gt;this&lt;/a&gt; site). To do this,
let&amp;#8217;s pretend increasing global temperatures is the same as increasing
ocean temperatures. Since water has a much much higher specific heat
than air, this seems like a reasonable assumption. Plus, we have already
made this calculation before. In the first End of the Earth post a bit
ago, we found that the amount of energy required to raise the
temperature of the world&amp;#8217;s oceans by 100 degrees is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E_{\text{100}}
\approx 10^{26} J $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Since the scaling is linear, we can see that the
energy to heat up the oceans by 1 degree is just one hundredth of this
value, or &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E_{\text{heat}} \approx 10^{24} J $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; So how big of an
asteroid is this? Using our equation from before, setting E = Eheat, we
have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ R_a = \frac{E_\text{heat}}{4 \times 10^{8} J m^{-1}}
= (\frac{10^{24}}{4 \times 10^8})^{1/3}m = (2.5)^{1/3}
\times{10^5}m \approx 100 km $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; For comparison, the asteroid that
killed the dinosaurs was thought to be about 30 km or so. This is a big
rock. &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FACT&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FINALE&lt;/span&gt;: We all know that an asteroid killed the
dinosaurs. But what would happen if instead of an asteroid, we dropped a
dinosaur from infinity? According to wikipedia, a brontosaurus was about
30 tons which is about 30,000 kg. Using the equation for energy as a
function of mass derived earlier, we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\text{E} = (10^{8}
J)(\frac{m_a}{1kg}) = 3 \times 10^{12} J \approx 1 \text{kiloton}
\text{TNT} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; For comparison, the Hiroshima bomb was about 15 kilotons.
So to reproduce the Hiroshima energy yield we need about 15
brotosauruses falling from&amp;nbsp;infinity.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="bruce willis"></category><category term="dinosaur"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="asteroid"></category></entry><entry><title>The End of Earth Physics I</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/the-end-of-earth-physics-i.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-17T16:25:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-17:posts/the-end-of-earth-physics-i.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;I was reading the Wikipedia page for the Hitchhiker&amp;#8217;s Guide books the
other day and found that it started as a series of radio shows called
&amp;#8220;The Ends of Earth.&amp;#8221; At the end of each episode, the Earth would be
destroyed. Since I feel like this is the best way to end any &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TV&lt;/span&gt;
show/movie/book/news broadcast/Mayan calendar, I will shamelessly steal
the idea.
Since this is the first End of the Earth post, we will start small and
just consider the boiling off of all the world&amp;#8217;s oceans. To be precise,
we will consider how much energy it would take to turn all the world&amp;#8217;s
water at 0 degrees Celsius to water vapor at 100 degrees Celsius.
First we need to estimate the mass of all the water on earth. I will
make the assumptions that all water is fresh water and that the oceans
account for all water on earth. These are obviously not exactly true,
but will give the proper order of magnitude. The volume of a spherical
shell is given by
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{V} = 4 \pi R^{2} \Delta R $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Taking the radius of the earth to be 6000 km, the ocean depth to be 1
km, and the fraction of earth covered by water to be 7/10 , we see that
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ V_\text{water} = 4 \pi {R_{\text{earth}}^{2} \times
\text{height} \times \text{fraction}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ V_\text{water} = 4 \pi (6 \times 10^{6} \text{m})^{2} \times
10^{3} \text{m} \times (\frac{7}{10}) = 3 \times 10^{17}
\text{m}^{3}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Now we have the volume of the ocean. Now, since
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{Density} = \frac{Mass}{Volume}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
we can calculate the mass of the oceans using the density of water to be
1000 kg / m^3.
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{Mass} = (\rho_\text{water})(V_\text{water}) = (1000
\frac{\text{kg}}{\text{m}^{3}})(3 \times 10^{17} \text{m}^{3}) =
3 \times 10^{20} \text{kg}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;FUN&lt;/span&gt; &lt;span class="caps"&gt;FACT&lt;/span&gt;: The mass of all the water on earth is about 2% the mass of
that celestial punching bag known as Pluto.
Alright, now that we have the mass of the earth, we can start
calculating how much energy it would take to heat it up and boil it
away. The amount of heat Q required to raise the temperature of a given
material is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_\text{heat} = \text{mc}\Delta\text{T} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where m is the mass of the thing we are heating, c is the specific heat
( the amount of energy required to heat our material up 1 degree
Celcius) and delta T is our change in temperature. This equation only
holds when there are no phase transitions, so we can use it to calculate
how much energy is needed to heat up the oceans from 0 degrees to 100
degrees:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_\text{heat} = (3 \times 10^{20} \text{kg}) \times (4000
\frac{\text{J}}{\text{kg C}}) \times (100 \text{deg C}) = 10^{26}
\text{J} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where we have used the fact that the specific heat of water is about
4000 J/kg deg C.
So now we know how much energy it takes to bring water to its boiling
point, but this is not the same as boiling it off. To find that, we need
to calculate how much energy we have to add to liquid water at a
constant 100 degrees to turn it into water vapor. This is given by
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_{\text{boil}} = \text{mL} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where m is the mass again and L is the &amp;#8220;latent heat of vaporization.&amp;#8221; It
tells us how much energy we need to add to turn a kilogram of liquid
water at 100 degrees to a kilogram of water vapor at 100 degrees. For
water, L is about 2*10^6 J/kg, so
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_{\text{boil}} = ( 3 \times 10^{20} \text{kg} ) \times (2
\times 10^{6} \frac{\text{J}}{\text{kg}}) = 6 \times 10^{26}
\text{J} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Comparing this to the energy calculated before, we see that amount of
energy needed to vaporize water at 100 degrees is about six times larger
than the amount of energy needed to heat up the water by 100 degrees!
Now we can calculate the total amount of energy to boil way the oceans:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q_{\text{total}} = Q_{\text{heat}} + Q_{\text{boil}} = 7
\times 10^{26} \text{J} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So how much energy is that really? Well the total power of the sun is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ L_{\text{sun}} = 4 \times 10^{26} \frac{\text{J}}{\text{s}} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Thus, it would take the entire energy output of the sun for about 2
seconds to boil away all the earth&amp;#8217;s oceans.
Now thats a lot of energy. To put this into the conventional unit of
destruction, this is equivalent to 10^11 Megatons of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TNT&lt;/span&gt;. Typical
hydrogen bombs are 10 Megatons. So if you want to boil away the oceans
with H-bombs, you&amp;#8217;d need about ten billion hydrogen bombs.
Luckily, short of constructing a reflecting Dyson sphere with a hole
that directs all the sun&amp;#8217;s radiation at the earth, these energies are
unobtainable. So don&amp;#8217;t&amp;nbsp;panic.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="end of the earth"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Nature of Many Penny Systems</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/on-the-nature-of-many-penny-systems.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-11T01:08:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-11:posts/on-the-nature-of-many-penny-systems.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;The other day I was on my way through ye olde internets to the Quantum
Leap episode index at Wikipedia, but stumbled over a quote by Feynman by
accident:
&amp;#8220;There are 10^11 stars in the galaxy. That used to be a huge number.
But it&amp;#8217;s only a hundred billion. It&amp;#8217;s less than the national deficit! We
used to call them astronomical numbers. Now we should call them
economical numbers&amp;#8221;
So this got me thinking. What if we decided to pay the national
debt&amp;#8230;in pennies? Seems fair enough, we don&amp;#8217;t really want to pay it and
when you don&amp;#8217;t want to pay something but you have to you pay it in
pennies. Hooray!
Last I heard this figure was somewhere around &lt;mathjax&gt;$10,000,000,000,000 (ten
trillion), that is:
$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \text{Debt} = 10^{13} \text{dollars} = 10^{15} \text{pennies} $&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$
Given that a penny is about 1.5 mm thick, how far does stacking them end
to end take us? Well:
$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \text{Length} = (10^{15} \text{pennies}) \times ( 0.15
\text{cm}) = 1.5 \times 10^{14} \text{cm} $&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$
As a bit of comparison, the mean distance from the earth to the sun is
$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \text{a} = 1.5 \times 10^{13} \text{cm,} $&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$
so our penny stack goes out to 10 AU, which just barely passes by
Saturn. Impressive!
Fine, so we've got all our pennies out now and we want to fit them in a
more economical fashion, taking advantage of all three of our
dimensions. How big is the warehouse needed to hold all these shiny
Lincolns?
Well, we know (or can guess) that one penny weighs about a gram
(technically 2.5 g). So if we were to know the density of a penny, we
would be good to go. A good guess at density for any metal is around 10
g /cm^3 , and this is true for zinc ( FUN FACT: Pennies were almost
entirely made of copper up until 1982, when they switched to 97.5% zinc,
2.5% copper). So,
$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \text{Mass} = (10^{15} \text{pennies}) \times ( 1 \frac{
\text{g}}{\text{penny}})= 10^{15} \text{g} $&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$
$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \text{Volume} = \frac{\text{mass}}{\text{density}} =
\frac{10^{15}\text{g}}{10 \frac{\text{g}}{\text{cm}^{3}}} =
10^{14} \text{cm}^{3}= 0.1 \text{km}}^{3} $&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$
That's a warehouse 1 km wide, 1km long, and a 100 m high. Pretty big. So
our next logical progression would be to ask: what are its gravitational
properties? To do this let's stack our pennies in a sphere. In that case
we have
$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \text{Volume} = \frac{4 \pi}{3} \text{R}^{3} $&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$
so
$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \text{R} = (\frac{3}{4 \pi} \text{Volume})^{1/3} = (\frac{3}{4
\pi} 10^{14} \text{cm}^{3})^{1/3} \approx 3 \times 10^4
\text{cm}=0.3 \text{km.} $&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$
To find the gravitational binding energy of a sphere of uniform density
we use
$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \text{Binding Energy} = \frac{3}{5}
\frac{\text{G}\text{M}^{2}}{R}\text{.} $&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$
So
$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$ \text{Binding Energy} = \frac{3}{5} \frac{ (7 \times 10^{-8}
\frac{cm^3}{gs^2})(10^{15} \text{g})^{2}}{3 \times 10^{4}
\text{cm}} \approx 10^{18} \text{ergs} = 10^{11} \text{Joules.} $&lt;/mathjax&gt;$
Noting that the useful measure of destruction, the kiloton of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TNT&lt;/span&gt;, is
about 10^12 J, we see that the binding energy of our spherical mass of
pennies is about 100 tons of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TNT&lt;/span&gt;. So what does this mean to us
practically? Well, the binding energy of an object essentially tells us
how much energy we need to put in to completely break up the body. So to
fully disperse our pennies off to our lendors, we need about 100 tons of
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;TNT&lt;/span&gt; worth of energy.
An alternative financial fermi problem that might be interesting is how
many trees would it take to make the money to equal the national debt or&amp;nbsp;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GDP&lt;/span&gt;?&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="pennies"></category><category term="fermi problem"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category></entry><entry><title>On the Superposition of Hip and Hop</title><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/on-the-superposition-of-hip-and-hop.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2010-04-09T17:42:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-04-09:posts/on-the-superposition-of-hip-and-hop.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S7-kbDKRebI/AAAAAAAAAAM/GU_aK1ssCyE/s1600/diracula.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_fa6AZDCsHnY/S7-kbDKRebI/AAAAAAAAAAM/GU_aK1ssCyE/s320/diracula.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
For posterity, completeness and another superfluous Scott Bakula
reference I present the following. It is an expression, through the
majesty of song (rap), of our love for all things quantum and undead (
or perhaps a superposition of dead/ not dead states&amp;#8230;?&amp;nbsp;).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We all know that the great physicist Paul Dirac, was not a vampire. What
this rap presupposes is&amp;#8230; maybe he was? If so, he would almost
certainly be named Diracula. He would be especially good at physics. But
he would especially be totally rad at&amp;nbsp;rapping.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Without further ado, the Diracula&amp;nbsp;Rapula:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="rap"&gt;Yo, its Diracula and I got something to say
Better listen close cause sometimes my teeth get in the way.

Of my rappin', but never my mathin'
Gonna work it strong, gonna make these monopoles happen.

Regardless of how you feel about me
and my strings with length semi-infinity
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="rap"&gt;Respect my proclamation
cause you find just one and you got charge conservation

So let me take you on a Quantum Leap like Scott Bakula
Rockin' you out with my spectacular vernacular
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;pre&gt;&lt;code class="rap"&gt;Amazing math wunda of the undead
Blazin' through complex formulae in my head.

Classified by Linnaeus as Mathematica Rex
I'm peacin' out
watch your equations and watch your necks.

Diracula Out
&lt;/code&gt;&lt;/pre&gt;</summary><category term="vampire"></category><category term="mad beats"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="Paul Dirac"></category><category term="revisionist history"></category></entry></feed>