<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.sun.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2011 09:42:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>End of the Earth V: There Goes the Sun</title><link>/posts/end-of-the-earth-v-there-goes-the-sun.html</link><description>&lt;table cellpadding="0" cellspacing="0" class="tr-caption-container" style="float: left; margin-right: 1em; text-align: left;"&gt;&lt;tbody&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td style="text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-LtXsyHxxSi0/TbDfL6l4tnI/AAAAAAAAAMg/l_12lafg6LQ/s1600/creepy_sun.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="clear: left; margin-bottom: 1em; margin-left: auto; margin-right: auto;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="224" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-LtXsyHxxSi0/TbDfL6l4tnI/AAAAAAAAAMg/l_12lafg6LQ/s320/creepy_sun.jpg" width="320" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;tr&gt;&lt;td class="tr-caption" style="text-align: center;"&gt;The Sun [photo courtesy of &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NASA&lt;/span&gt;]&lt;/td&gt;&lt;/tr&gt;&lt;/tbody&gt;&lt;/table&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People that know me well know that I have a lot in common with Robert Frost.  We both were born in March and we both employ rural New England settings to explore complex social and philosophical themes in our poetry.  We also like the same rap&amp;nbsp;groups.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In honor of my literary doppelganger, I will now, having already had the world end in &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/end-of-earth-physics-i.html"&gt;fire&lt;/a&gt;, try my hand at&amp;nbsp;ice.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s try to answer the question:  &amp;#8220;If the sun blinks out of existence this instant, what is the temperature of the Earth as a function of&amp;nbsp;time?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;The Sun, in addition to being the &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=haAhdtDmsOw"&gt;King of Planets&lt;/a&gt;, is also what keeps us all warm and toasty and alive.  What happens if we turn that off?  Well, the Earth will cool by radiating its heat away into space.  To see how long this would take, let&amp;#8217;s make some&amp;nbsp;assumptions.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let&amp;#8217;s model the surface of the Earth as an ocean 1 km deep and let&amp;#8217;s pretend that all the heat is stored in this ocean.  Let&amp;#8217;s take the ocean to be liquid water at T = 0 degrees Celsius.  How long will it take this ocean to freeze into ice at 0 degrees&amp;nbsp;Celsius?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Well, the amount of energy released from the oceans as the water freezes is given&amp;nbsp;by&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ Q = L_{w} M_{ocean} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where L is the &amp;#8220;latent heat of fusion&amp;#8221; and M is the mass of the water.  The &amp;#8220;latent heat of fusion&amp;#8221; is a fancy way of saying &amp;#8220;the amount of energy released per unit mass as water turns to ice at constant temperature.&amp;#8221;  For water, we have&amp;nbsp;that&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ L_{w} = 3.3 \times 10^5 \mbox{J/kg} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And for the mass of the ocean, it will be convenient later to write it&amp;nbsp;as&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ M_{ocean} = 4\pi {R_{\oplus}}^2 \Delta R \rho $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so now we&amp;#8217;ve got enough to say how much heat energy we have, so how fast do we lose it?  We can take the Earth to be a blackbody radiator, so the power lost in such a case&amp;nbsp;is:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P =4\pi \sigma R_{\oplus}^2 T^4 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Since Power is just Energy per unit Time, we now have all we need to get the time for total freezing of all the oceans.  We&amp;nbsp;have:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = \frac{Q}{P} = \frac{4\pi {R_{\oplus}}^2 \Delta R \rho L_{w}}{4\pi \sigma R_{\oplus}^2 T^4} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Simplifying the above expression a bit, we&amp;nbsp;get&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t =\frac{\Delta R \rho L_{w}}{\sigma T^4} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we can plug in some&amp;nbsp;numbers,&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t =\frac{\left(10^3 \mbox{ m}\right) \times \left(10^3 \frac{kg}{m^3}\right) \times \left(3.3 \times 10^5 \mbox{J/kg}\right)}{\left( 5.67 \times 10^{-8} J s^{-1} m^{-2} K^{-4}\right) \times \left( 273 K\right)^4} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;where we have made sure to put our temperatures in Kelvin.  Crunching the numbers with the calculator we &amp;#8220;borrowed&amp;#8221; from Nic three months ago&amp;nbsp;gives:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t = 10^9 \mbox{ s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Remembering that a year is very&amp;nbsp;nearly&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ 1 \mbox{ year} = \pi \times 10^7 \mbox{ s}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we find that the time for the oceans to freeze after the sun disappears is about 30 years.&amp;nbsp;Hooray!&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now this model was very simple.  First of all, I assumed that the ocean temperatures were already at 0 degrees, but they are a bit warmer.  If the oceans are about 300 K (ie 80 degrees in not-Yariv units), then we get another 30 years to cool down to freezing temperatures.  Secondly, I have completely neglected the heat stored in the Earth.  Will this change my answer by an embarrassingly large factor?  Lastly, I have ignored all internal heating mechanisms (ie, radioactive decay) that will also heat up the Earth.  But ignoring all&amp;nbsp;that&amp;#8230;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is there a way for anyone to survive this?  Well, for the most part it will mean the end of life on Earth.  There could potentially be a few exceptions, like by geothermal vents and such.  But for the most part, it&amp;#8217;s one quick cold spiral down to eternal nothingness.  But what about a few people, could they survive for a bit even if the human race is&amp;nbsp;doomed?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I&amp;#8217;m glad you asked!  You see, I have this plan involving mine shafts.  Hunkering down underground with a nuclear power plant and all the canned food food we can stomach should allow us to at least ride the rest of our lives.  Details can be found &lt;a href="http://www.youtube.com/watch?v=iesXUFOlWC0&amp;amp;feature=related"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Corky</dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 22 Apr 2011 09:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-04-22:posts/end-of-the-earth-v-there-goes-the-sun.html</guid><category>sun</category><category>scott bakula</category><category>end of the earth</category></item><item><title>Locating the Sun Photo</title><link>/posts/locating-the-sun-photo.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;This photo has been making the rounds on the internet lately:
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VQNEo7GUI/AAAAAAAAAJA/mHcIfKfPleM/s1600/pinholecamerajd09.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="342" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VQNEo7GUI/AAAAAAAAAJA/mHcIfKfPleM/s400/pinholecamerajd09.jpg" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Originally from &lt;a href="http://helpmyphysics.co.uk/wordpress/?p=276"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Its a time lapse photo of the sun taken from a pinhole camera from June until December.  The real question is:  Where was this photo taken?
&lt;a name='more'&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Wandering&amp;nbsp;Sun&lt;/h3&gt;Well, first lets think a second about why the sun would wander in the sky.  As you may already know, the earth&amp;#8217;s pole is not aligned with our solar system&amp;#8217;s axis.  The earth&amp;#8217;s axis has what is called a 23.5 degree &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Earth's_Axis"&gt;axial tilt&lt;/a&gt;, or&amp;nbsp;obliquity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a result, if you sit at a fixed latitude on the earth, then as the earth revolves around the sun and the year goes by, the angle the sun makes with the horizon&amp;nbsp;changes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We need to estimate how much the sun&amp;#8217;s angle in the sky changes.  Consider the following diagram
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VVHRzTrXI/AAAAAAAAAJI/zxe2OAcYSSw/s1600/diagram.png" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="87" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VVHRzTrXI/AAAAAAAAAJI/zxe2OAcYSSw/s400/diagram.png" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
You&amp;#8217;ll notice that the angle that the dashed line towards the sun makes with respect to the dotted horizon line, changes when the earth is on either side of the sun.  But how much does it&amp;nbsp;change?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We can estimate it by realizing that the angle of that triangle centered at the sun is very small.  Very small indeed.  We could estimate its size by:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \arctan \frac{R_{\text{Earth}}}{D_{\text{Earth-Sun}}} \approx 0.002^{\circ} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Very small.  So, knowing that the one angle is very tiny, and remembering that the sum of all of the angles in a triangle must add up to 180 degrees, we can calculate how much that angle in the sky&amp;nbsp;changes. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Notice that the angle between the line pointing to our latitude of interest and the equator has a known angle, namely the angle there is our latitude +/- 23.5 degrees.   So if that is the angle our observation point makes with the horizontal, by the reasoning above, the angle that the sun makes with respect to our observation point ought to be 180 - our latitude +/- 23.5 degrees. So on either side of the sun, the difference in this angle from summer to winter is just twice 23.5 degrees of 47&amp;nbsp;degrees. &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So, regardless of where you are on the earth, between when the sun is highest in the sky, and when it is lowest in the sky, there ought to be a 47 degree difference.  (Assuming of course you can see the sun year round, which you can&amp;#8217;t if you live too far&amp;nbsp;north).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great.  So we know that the difference between the height of the traces in the picture and the bottom needs to be 47 degrees.  But that still doesn&amp;#8217;t help us calculate the latitude the picture was taken&amp;nbsp;at.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finding Latitude in&amp;nbsp;theory&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Looking at our diagram again, we notice that when the sun is lowest in the sky, we can calculate directly what angle the sun should make with respect to the horizon (psi) (We already obtained the upper angle in our triangle, the last part is realizing that the angle to the horizon from the radial line is just 90 degrees).  We obtain
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \psi = \theta - 90^\circ  + 23.5^\circ = \theta + 66.5^\circ $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
So, turning it on its head, we can calculate the latitude (theta) we are at if we know the lowest angle the sun makes in the sky
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \theta = 66.5^\circ - \psi $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Great.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Finding Latitude in&amp;nbsp;Practice &lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So, now I know two things.  The total angle difference between the upper most the sun gets and the lowest point in the sky is 47 degrees.  And I also know that if I know the angle between the horizon and the lowest point the sun gets in the sky, I can calculate the latitude.  So how am I going to do this, well, I just took the picture and opened it up in Gimp, and used the measure tool to get the difference between the highest and lowest points in the sky in pixels, and the distance to the horizon in pixels.  Here&amp;#8217;s one example of my guesses:
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VZsHEcTMI/AAAAAAAAAJQ/fOqIQq1776I/s1600/pinholecamerajdwithlines.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VZsHEcTMI/AAAAAAAAAJQ/fOqIQq1776I/s320/pinholecamerajdwithlines.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;Getting the differences in height for the sun was relatively straight forward.  In order to get the distance to the horizon, I had to guess a little bit.  I just lined it up by eye to where I thought the horizon should be in the picture since its not&amp;nbsp;visible.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Why does this do me any good?  Well assuming the picture doesn&amp;#8217;t have too much distortion, since I know the one angle is 47 degrees, I can make a comparison between the pixel lengths.  Lets say in the picture above I call the length of the green line B, and the length of the yellow line S, then I can estimate
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{\psi}{S} = \frac{47^\circ}{B} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
which gives me a measure on psi.  Since I was doing this by eye, I repeated the measurement ten times independently for each, obtaining in the end
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ B = 356 \pm 2 \qquad S = 66 \pm 6 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And I have a complete formula for my estimation of the latitude
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \theta = 66.5^\circ - 47^\circ \frac{S}{B} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Results&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;This allowed me to estimate the latitude at 58 +/- 1 degree latitude.  Naturally, I can&amp;#8217;t tell the difference between 58 degrees north or 58 degrees south.  To get a better idea of what this guess looks like, here I&amp;#8217;ve overlayed the possible locations in green
&lt;div class="separator" style="clear: both; text-align: center;"&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VcAVzG7jI/AAAAAAAAAJY/3csC2nzT8OM/s1600/world1.jpg" imageanchor="1" style="margin-left: 1em; margin-right: 1em;"&gt;&lt;img border="0" height="356" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S8VcAVzG7jI/AAAAAAAAAJY/3csC2nzT8OM/s400/world1.jpg" width="400" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/div&gt;You&amp;#8217;ll notice that there isn&amp;#8217;t much life down at 58 degrees south of the equator.  So, I reckon the picture was taken in the northern&amp;nbsp;hemisphere.  &lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Surfing around on the webpage where the picture was found, you&amp;#8217;ll first notice that its taken from a co.uk site (Great Britain), and if you go to the homepage, Mr. Mallon has a weather widget which says Bellshill.  &lt;a href="http://maps.google.com/maps?f=q&amp;amp;source=s_q&amp;amp;gl=us&amp;amp;g=Bellshill&amp;amp;q=Bellshill,+UK+lattitude+longitude&amp;amp;btnG=Search+Maps"&gt;Google Maps&lt;/a&gt; tells me that Bellshill, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;UK&lt;/span&gt; is at about 56 degrees North.  I&amp;#8217;ve tried to put a green dot on the map above near where Bellshill actually is (its hard to&amp;nbsp;see).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Not bad for a night&amp;#8217;s&amp;nbsp;work.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Alemi</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 14 Apr 2010 02:21:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-04-14:posts/locating-the-sun-photo.html</guid><category>analysis</category><category>sun</category><category>fun</category><category>picture</category><category>lattitude</category></item></channel></rss>