<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link href="/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.casio.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>/</id><updated>2012-03-12T00:57:00-04:00</updated><entry><title>F-91 Revisited</title><link href="/posts/f-91-revisited.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-03-12T00:57:00-04:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:,2012-03-12:posts/f-91-revisited.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-05FSvjIalzs/T11JuY0apyI/AAAAAAAAAVI/hHndDNPO5CE/s1600/dst_sam.jpeg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-05FSvjIalzs/T11JuY0apyI/AAAAAAAAAVI/hHndDNPO5CE/s400/dst_sam.jpeg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Farmer Uncle Sam&amp;#8230;with a rifle. (Image Credit:&amp;nbsp;Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Today was a sunny exception to the grey overcast rule of weather in
Ithaca. I &lt;em&gt;should&lt;/em&gt; be overjoyed by this anomaly, spending the day
outside flying a kite or playing frisbee with a border collie in a
bandanna. Unfortunately, today was also the beginning of Daylight
Savings Time (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;DST&lt;/span&gt;) - my least favorite day of the year. For my
colleagues unfamiliar with this temporal travesty (I&amp;#8217;m looking at you
Arizona), let me briefly explain &lt;span class="caps"&gt;DST&lt;/span&gt;. Once a year, the time lords steal
a single hour from us and place it in an escrow account for future
disbursement, presumably in some elaborate scheme to gain the favor of
hat-throwing farmer-clock hybrids (see image left). The details are a
bit murky, but the net result is that today I had one less hour to do my
very favorite thing in the whole wide world - sleep. It also means that
I have to set my watch, so I figured I&amp;#8217;d check in and see how well my
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2012/02/time-keeps-on-slippin.html"&gt;previous
model&lt;/a&gt;
for time-loss in my watch has held up. About a month ago, I looked at
how my watch slowly deviated from the &lt;a href="http://nist.time.gov/timezone.cgi?Eastern/d/-5/java"&gt;official
time&lt;/a&gt; (the original
post can be found
&lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2012/02/time-keeps-on-slippin.html"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;
and a helpful clarification by Tom can be found
&lt;a href="http://blogs.scienceforums.net/swansont/archives/11014"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt;). Based
on a little over 50 days worth of data, I found that my watch lost about
0.35 seconds per day against the official time. About 50 days have
passed since my last measurement and today when I set the watch, so I
thought it would be interesting to see how well my model fit the new
data. The old data are presented in Figure 1 in blue, the old best fit
line is in red, and the new data point (taken this morning) is in green.
As always, click through the plot for a larger&amp;nbsp;version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HqpuhvxXl8M/T1115Tz6lnI/AAAAAAAAAVQ/I1AUjQLXres/s1600/dst_update_long.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-HqpuhvxXl8M/T1115Tz6lnI/AAAAAAAAAVQ/I1AUjQLXres/s400/dst_update_long.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;1&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new data point appears to be in fair agreement with the old best-fit
model, but it&amp;#8217;s a little hard to see here. Zooming in a bit, though, we
see that the model lies outside the error bar of the new data&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1euutOYSIrs/T1125Hi_XNI/AAAAAAAAAVY/tnWZ6N3mJJs/s1600/dst_update_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-1euutOYSIrs/T1125Hi_XNI/AAAAAAAAAVY/tnWZ6N3mJJs/s400/dst_update_short.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;2&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So is this a big deal? Not really. But if it will help you sleep at
night, we can redo the fitting with the new data point included to see
how much things change. The the plots with the updated model to include
all data points are provided below with the old data in blue and the new
point in&amp;nbsp;green.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-oIeLFmzJgKI/T115TGf3laI/AAAAAAAAAVg/RHPJuP9UrKk/s1600/dst_newfit_long.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-oIeLFmzJgKI/T115TGf3laI/AAAAAAAAAVg/RHPJuP9UrKk/s400/dst_newfit_long.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;3&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The new model looks a whole lot like the old one, except the best fit
line now appears to go through the new data point. Zooming in a little,
we see that it does indeed fall within the error bars of our new&amp;nbsp;point.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-EUf50O2-jjQ/T11514CpS_I/AAAAAAAAAVo/Ryt2v1LOeVk/s1600/dst_newfit_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-EUf50O2-jjQ/T11514CpS_I/AAAAAAAAAVo/Ryt2v1LOeVk/s400/dst_newfit_short.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure&amp;nbsp;4&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Alright, so the new model fits with our new point, but how much did the
model have to change? Well, the fit to just the old data gave an offset
of 0.36 seconds and a loss rate of 0.35 seconds per day. The new model
has an offset of 0.40 seconds and a loss rate of 0.348 seconds per day.
Overall, not a significant change.
It looks as though I may continue to not worry about the accuracy of my
watch. I have set it to match the official time and have no intention of
fiddling with it until I have to set it again at the end of Daylight
Savings Time - my favorite day of the&amp;nbsp;year.&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="daylight savings time"></category><category term="casio"></category></entry><entry><title>Time Keeps On Slippin’</title><link href="/posts/time-keeps-on-slippin-.html" rel="alternate"></link><updated>2012-02-12T22:00:00-05:00</updated><author><name>Corky</name></author><id>tag:,2012-02-12:posts/time-keeps-on-slippin-.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-rtzREUF0wYM/TyX0orGHkpI/AAAAAAAAASk/hsRZAwtg7H4/s1600/casi_f91w.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-rtzREUF0wYM/TyX0orGHkpI/AAAAAAAAASk/hsRZAwtg7H4/s320/casi_f91w.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  This is picture of a watch. (Source:&amp;nbsp;Wikipedia)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;A couple of months ago, the Virtuosi Action Team (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;VAT&lt;/span&gt;) assembled for
lunch and the discussion quickly and unexpectedly turned to watches. As
Nic and Alemi argued over the finer parts of fancy-dancy watch
ownership, I looked down at my watch: the lowly &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Casio_F91W"&gt;Casio
F-91W&lt;/a&gt;. Though it certainly
isn&amp;#8217;t fancy, it is inexpensive, durable, and could potentially win me an
all-expense paid trip to the
&lt;a href="http://www.guardian.co.uk/world/2011/apr/25/guantanamo-files-casio-wristwatch-alqaida"&gt;Caribbean&lt;/a&gt;.
But how &lt;em&gt;good&lt;/em&gt; of a watch is it? To find out, I decided to time it
against the official &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; time for a couple of months. Incidentally,
about half-way in I found out that Chad over at &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/principles/"&gt;Uncertain
Principles&lt;/a&gt; had done essentially
the same thing
&lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/principles/2011/05/the_testing_of_time_measuring.php"&gt;already&lt;/a&gt;.
No matter, science is still fun even if you aren&amp;#8217;t the first person to
do it. So here&amp;#8217;s my &amp;#8220;new-to-me&amp;#8221; analysis. Alright, so how do we go about
quantifying how &amp;#8220;good&amp;#8221; a watch is? Well, there seem to be two main
things we can test. The first of these is accuracy. That is, how close
does this watch come to the &lt;em&gt;actual&lt;/em&gt; time (according to some time
system)? If the official time is 3:00 pm and my watch claims it is 5:00
am, then it is not very accurate. The second measure of &amp;#8220;good-ness&amp;#8221; is
precision or, in watch parlance, stability. This is essentially a
measure of the consistency of the watch. If I have a watch that is
consistently off by 5 minutes from the official time, then it is not
accurate but it is still stable. In essence, a very consistent watch
would be just as good as an accurate one, because we can always just
subtract off the known offset. To test any of the above measures of how
&amp;#8220;good&amp;#8221; my cheap watch is, we will need to know the actual time. We will
adopt the official &lt;span class="caps"&gt;U.S.&lt;/span&gt; time as provided on the &lt;a href="http://nist.time.gov/timezone.cgi?Eastern/d/-5/java"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt;
website&lt;/a&gt;. This time
is determined and maintained by a collection of really impressive atomic
clocks. &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/NIST-F1"&gt;One of these&lt;/a&gt; is in
Colorado and the other is secretly guarded by an ever-vigilant Time Lord
(see Figure&amp;nbsp;1).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EXMf5o9a4GI/TzCRcaMjjVI/AAAAAAAAASs/FlqyjHbJS9Q/s1600/flavor_flav.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-EXMf5o9a4GI/TzCRcaMjjVI/AAAAAAAAASs/FlqyjHbJS9Q/s320/flavor_flav.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 1: Flavor Flav, Keeper of the&amp;nbsp;Time&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;At 9:00:00 am &lt;span class="caps"&gt;EST&lt;/span&gt; on November 30th, I synchronized my watch with the
time displayed on the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt; website. For the next 54 days, I kept track
of the difference between my watch an the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt; time. On the 55th day, I
forgot to check the time and the experiment promptly ended. The results
are plotted below in Figure 2 (and, as with all plots, click through for
a larger&amp;nbsp;version).&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hscjUIehrHQ/TzCYqNhcsYI/AAAAAAAAATE/eAz3O5KlAcY/s1600/time_fit_short.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/-hscjUIehrHQ/TzCYqNhcsYI/AAAAAAAAATE/eAz3O5KlAcY/s400/time_fit_short.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 2: Best-fit to time&amp;nbsp;difference&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from Figure 2, the amount of time the watch lost over the
timing period appears to be fairly linear. There does appear to be a
jagged-ness to the data, though. This is mainly caused by the fact that
both the watch and the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt; website only report times to the nearest
second. As a result, the finest time resolution I was willing to report
was about half a second. Adopting an uncertainty of half a second, I did
a least-squares fit of a straight line to the data and found that the
watch loses about 0.35 seconds per day. As far as accuracy goes, that&amp;#8217;s
not bad! No matter what, I&amp;#8217;ll have to set my watch at least twice a year
to appease the Daylight Savings Gods. The longest stretch between
resetting is about 8 months. If I synchronize my watch with the &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NIST&lt;/span&gt;
time to &amp;#8220;spring forward&amp;#8221; in March, it will only lose about &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ t\_{loss}
= 8\~\\mbox{months} \\times 30\\frac{\\mbox{days}}{\\mbox{month}}
\\times 0.35 \\frac{\\mbox{sec}}{\\mbox{day}} = 84\~\\mbox{sec} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
before I have to re-synchronize to &amp;#8220;fall back&amp;#8221; in November. Assuming the
loss rate is constant, I&amp;#8217;ll never be more than about a minute and a half
off the &amp;#8220;actual&amp;#8221; time. That&amp;#8217;s good enough for me. Furthermore, if the
watch is &lt;em&gt;consistently&lt;/em&gt; losing 0.35 seconds per day and I know how long
ago I last synchronized, I can always correct for the offset. In this
case, I can always know the official time to within a second (assuming I
can add). But &lt;em&gt;is&lt;/em&gt; the watch consistent? That&amp;#8217;s a good question. The
simplest means of finding the stability of the watch would be to look at
the timing residuals between the data and the model. That is, we will
consider how &amp;#8220;off&amp;#8221; each point is from our constant rate-loss model. A
plot of the results is shown below in Figure&amp;nbsp;3.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-13ULtvOlXuU/TzCpp6LGvfI/AAAAAAAAATM/8rybD1lxZOo/s1600/residuals.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/-13ULtvOlXuU/TzCpp6LGvfI/AAAAAAAAATM/8rybD1lxZOo/s400/residuals.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 3: Timing&amp;nbsp;residuals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Figure 3, we see that the data fit the model pretty well. There&amp;#8217;s a
little bit of a wiggle going on there and we see some strong short-term
correlations (the latter is an artifact of the fact that I could only
get times to the nearest second). To get some sense of the timing
stability from the residuals, we can calculate the standard deviation,
which will give us a figure for how &amp;#8220;off&amp;#8221; the data typically are from
the model. The standard deviation of the residuals is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \\sigma\_{res}
= 0.19\~\\mbox{sec}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; A good guess at the fractional stability of the
watch would then just be the standard deviation divided by the sampling
interval, &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \\frac{\\sigma\_{res}}{T} = 0.19\~\\mbox{sec} \\times
\\frac{1}{1\~\\mbox{day}} \\times
\\frac{1\~\\mbox{day}}{24\\times3600\~\\mbox{sec}} \\approx
2\\times10\^{-6}.$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; In words, this means that each &amp;#8220;tick&amp;#8221; of the watch
is consistent with the average &amp;#8220;tick&amp;#8221; value to about 2 parts in a
million. That&amp;#8217;s nice&amp;#8230;but isn&amp;#8217;t there something &lt;em&gt;fancier&lt;/em&gt; we could be
doing? Well, I have been wanting to learn about &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Allan_variance"&gt;Allan
variance&lt;/a&gt; for some time
now, so let&amp;#8217;s try that. The Allan variance (refs: &lt;a href="http://www.ino.it/~azavatta/References/Allan.pdf"&gt;original
paper&lt;/a&gt; and a
&lt;a href="http://tf.boulder.nist.gov/general/pdf/118.pdf"&gt;review&lt;/a&gt;) can be used to
find the fractional frequency stability of an oscillator over a wide
range of time scales. Roughly speaking, the Allan variance tells us how
averaging our residuals over different chunks of time affects the
stability of our data. The square root of the Allan variance,
essentially the &amp;#8220;Allan standard deviation,&amp;#8221; is plotted against various
averaging times for our data below in Figure&amp;nbsp;4.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-_zhCroHDoNE/TzC7XYkDZ1I/AAAAAAAAATU/mCaspxYhlxA/s1600/allan_variance.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/-_zhCroHDoNE/TzC7XYkDZ1I/AAAAAAAAATU/mCaspxYhlxA/s400/allan_variance.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  Figure 4: Allan variance of our&amp;nbsp;residuals&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From Figure 4, we see that as we increase the averaging time from one
day to ten days, the Allan deviation decreases. That is, the averaging
reduces the amount of variation in the frequency of the data, making it
more stable. However, at around 10 days of averaging time it seems as
though we hit a floor in how low we can go. Since the error bars get
really big here, this may not be a real effect. If it is real, though,
this would be indicative of some low-frequency noise in our oscillator.
For those who prefer colors, this would be
&amp;#8220;&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Colors_of_noise"&gt;red&lt;/a&gt;&amp;#8221; noise. Since the
Allan deviation gives the fractional frequency stability of the
oscillator, we have that &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\\sigma\_A = \\frac{\\delta f}{f} =
\\frac{\\delta(1/t)}{1/t} = \\frac{\\delta t}{t}. $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Looking at the
plot, we see that with an averaging time of one day, the fractional time
stability of the watch is &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\\frac{\\delta t}{t} \\approx
2\\times10\^{-6}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which corresponds nicely to our previously
calculated value. If we average over chunks that are ten days long
instead, we get a fractional stability of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\\frac{\\delta t}{t}
\\approx 10\^{-7}, $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which would correspond to a deviation from our
model of about 0.008 seconds. Not bad. The initial question that started
this whole ordeal was &amp;#8220;How good is my watch?&amp;#8221; and I think we can safely
answer that with &amp;#8220;as good as I&amp;#8217;ll ever need it to be.&amp;#8221; Hooray for cheap
and effective&amp;nbsp;electronics!&lt;/p&gt;</summary><category term="allan variance"></category><category term="scott bakula"></category><category term="casio"></category></entry></feed>