<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.ice.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2011 22:41:00 -0500</lastBuildDate><item><title>Falling Ice</title><link>/posts/falling-ice.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TUINK4AQYVI/AAAAAAAAAEA/XWqewl-lS_o/s1600/shattered_windshield.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TUINK4AQYVI/AAAAAAAAAEA/XWqewl-lS_o/s320/shattered_windshield.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
It&amp;#8217;s been a while since I posted anything, much to my shame. Hopefully
this post marks a change in that streak. Today I&amp;#8217;m going to consider a
very practical application of all this physics stuff. One of my
housemates parks his car on the side of the house, with the front of the
car facing the house. Living in Ithaca, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;NY&lt;/span&gt;, the weather has been the
usual cold and snowy, like the rest of the northeast &lt;span class="caps"&gt;USA&lt;/span&gt; this winter.
Yet, early last week, we had some unusually warm weather, in the 30s
(fahrenheit). A few days later, my housemate went out to his car, and
discovered that falling chunks of ice had broken his windshield! Now, to
be clear here, I&amp;#8217;m not talking about icicles, I&amp;#8217;m talking about large,
block-like, chunks. My best guess is that during the warm days, snow on
the roof turned into chunks of ice, and slid off the roof. The question
I&amp;#8217;m going to try to answer today is: How far from the house could these
chunks possibly land? Put another way, what I want to know is, how far
from the house would we have to park our cars to not risk broken
windshields from falling ice? &lt;strong&gt;The First Attempt&lt;/strong&gt; We&amp;#8217;ll start with the
simplest assumptions we can think of. First, we&amp;#8217;ll assume that there is
no friction on the ice block as it slides down the roof. We&amp;#8217;ll also
assume there&amp;#8217;s no air resistance slowing down the ice in the air. The
maximum range will be given by a block of ice sliding from the top of
the roof. Taking the height of the peak of the roof as h, relative to
the edge of the roof, we can write down the magnitude of the velocity of
the ice chunk when it reaches the edge of the roof. We start by setting
the change in gravitational potential energy equal to the change in
kinetic energy. Recalling the form for both of these, &lt;mathjax&gt;$$PE=mgh$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$KE=\\tfrac{1}{2}mv\^2$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; we can set these equal and solve for v, &lt;mathjax&gt;$$mgh
= \\tfrac{1}{2}mv\^2$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so &lt;mathjax&gt;$$|v|=\\sqrt{2gh}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; This should be a familiar
expression to anyone who went through introductory mechanics. Now, given
that the roof is at an angle theta, we can write down the x (horizontal)
and y (vertical) components of velocity, &lt;mathjax&gt;$$v\_x=|v|\\cos\\theta$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$v\_y=-|v|\\sin \\theta$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where I&amp;#8217;ve introduced a minus sign in the y
component of velocity to indicate that the ice chunk is falling. Now
that we have the velocity, we have to call upon some more kinematics. To
figure out how far the ice flies, we have to know how long it is in the
air. So we start by considering the vertical motion. The distance
traveled by an object with an initial velocity, v_0, and a constant
acceleration, a, is given by &lt;mathjax&gt;$$\\Delta y=\\tfrac{1}{2}at\^2+v\_0t$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; In
our case, the distance traveled is the height of the first two floors of
my house. The acceleration is that of gravity, g, and the initial
velocity is the y component of velocity we found above. We&amp;#8217;d like to
find the time it takes to travel this distance. We have to be a little
careful with our minus signs, by our convention the acceleration is in
the negative direction, and the change in position is negative. Working
all of that out, and plugging in our known values, we get
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\\tfrac{1}{2}gt\^2+|v|\\sin \\theta t - l =0$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; where l is the height
of the house. We can solve this for t, finding &lt;mathjax&gt;$$t=\\frac{-|v|\\sin
\\theta + \\sqrt{(|v|\\sin \\theta)\^2+2gl}}{g}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; The horizontal
distance traveled is simply the horizontal velocity times the time,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$x=\\frac{|v|\\cos\\theta}{g}(-|v|\\sin \\theta + \\sqrt{(|v|\\sin
\\theta)\^2+2gl})$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; a result that you may recognize as the &amp;#8216;projectile
range formula&amp;#8217; (particularly if I brought the minus on the v sine theta
term into the sine, indicating that I&amp;#8217;m firing at a negative angle, that
is, downwards). Having found that result, lets plug in our velocity, and
then some numbers. First,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$x=\\frac{\\sqrt{2gh}\\cos\\theta}{g}(\\sqrt{2gh}\\sin \\theta +
\\sqrt{(2gh\\sin\^2 \\theta+2gl})$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Now, for some estimation. I&amp;#8217;d say
that the height of the roof peak is 10 ft, the height of the first two
floors of the house is 20 ft, and the angle of the roof is 30 degrees.
Having made those estimates, now I just have to plug in all the numbers,
yielding &lt;mathjax&gt;$$x=5.2 m=17 ft$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; That&amp;#8217;s a very long range! Now, I didn&amp;#8217;t see
any chunks of ice that were more than about 7 ft from the house. So we
have to question what went wrong with the above derivation. Well, maybe
nothing went wrong. I did calculate the &lt;em&gt;maximum&lt;/em&gt; range. It&amp;#8217;s quite
possible none of these ice chunks were from the very top of the roof.
Still, I&amp;#8217;m inclined to think we may have overestimated. I&amp;#8217;d say that our
initial velocity was too high. The ice, as it comes down the roof, will
have to push a bunch of snow out of the way. Even though it may not have
much friction with the roof, all that snow will slow it down, and reduce
the velocity with which it comes off. I&amp;#8217;m just going to guess that about
half of the potential energy it had is lost to the snow and roof, as a
rough estimation. That would give a velocity &lt;mathjax&gt;$$|v| = \\sqrt{gh}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; and a
maximum distance of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$x= 4m = 13ft$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which is closer to what I observed.
&lt;strong&gt;The Second Attempt&lt;/strong&gt; I&amp;#8217;m still not completely satisfied with the
previous work, the answer doesn&amp;#8217;t match my observation. As a wise man
(Einstein) once said, &amp;#8220;make things as simple as possible, but no
simpler.&amp;#8221; I may be guilty of making the problem too simple here. So I&amp;#8217;m
going to add back in air resistance. In general, we physicists like to
avoid this because it usually means we can&amp;#8217;t get nice, analytic
expressions as answers (like the one I have above). Instead, we usually
just have to calculate the result numerically. This isn&amp;#8217;t the end of the
world, and often times it is actually a bit easier, but it&amp;#8217;s not as
pretty looking. Still, to satisfy myself, and you, gentle reader, I will
step into that realm. We start by writing down the force on our block of
ice once it is falling. We&amp;#8217;ve got gravity, and air resistance. Thus
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\\vec{F}=-mg\\hat{y}-bv\^2\\hat{v}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; I&amp;#8217;ve input a drag force that goes
as v\^2, and is in the opposite direction of v. The &amp;#8216;v direction&amp;#8217; is a
cop out, because I didn&amp;#8217;t want to do the explicit direction, so lets fix
that. We&amp;#8217;ll have x and y components, and we note that the magnitude of v
times the direction of v is the velocity vector. So,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\\vec{F}=-mg\\hat{y}-bv\\hat{v}\_x-bv\\hat{v}\_y$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; Breaking this up
into components we get &lt;mathjax&gt;$$a\_x=-\\frac{bv}{m}v\_x$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$a\_y=-g-\\frac{bv}{m}v\_y$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; This is as far as we can take this work
analytically. I&amp;#8217;ll say a little more about the coefficient b. This
depends on the exact size and shape of the object, as well as the medium
it is moving through. I&amp;#8217;m going to use &lt;mathjax&gt;$$b=.4\\rho A$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; because that&amp;#8217;s
what we used for hay bales in my classical mechanics class years ago.
Here, rho is the density of air, and A is the surface area of the
object. I would estimate that the large face of the ice chunk is roughly
one square foot, or .1 m\^2. I&amp;#8217;d estimate the mass of the ice was around
2 kg. Now, for some magic. I&amp;#8217;ve put all of this into mathematica, and
asked it to solve this numerically. First we have the plot for the full
initial velocity, &lt;mathjax&gt;$$v=\\sqrt{2gh}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TUILYLcLr3I/AAAAAAAAAD4/q_j8djBIPP0/s1600/Falling+Ice.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://1.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TUILYLcLr3I/AAAAAAAAAD4/q_j8djBIPP0/s320/Falling+Ice.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  The solid line is with air resistance, the dashed line without air resistance. The plot shows vertical vs. horizontal distance, and the units are meters. (click to&amp;nbsp;enlarge)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Next we have the plot for the half initial velocity, &lt;mathjax&gt;$$v=\\sqrt{gh}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TUIMIxdlzLI/AAAAAAAAAD8/G3P9KWUB3mw/s1600/Falling+Ice2.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TUIMIxdlzLI/AAAAAAAAAD8/G3P9KWUB3mw/s320/Falling+Ice2.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  The solid line is with air resistance, the dashed line without air resistance. The plot shows vertical vs. horizontal distance, and the units are meters. (click to&amp;nbsp;enlarge)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As you can see from the plots, in neither case does it make a large
difference, about .2 m. &lt;strong&gt;The Third Round&lt;/strong&gt; The final thought that
occurs to me is that perhaps I got the angle of the roof wrong. That
would be quite easy. Humans are notoriously bad at estimating angles.
I&amp;#8217;ll plot the results (with air resistance) for 15, 30, and 45 degree
angles and the lower&amp;nbsp;velocity.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TUI5Q4qB5DI/AAAAAAAAAEE/9ydcM8EXzxA/s1600/Falling+Ice3.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TUI5Q4qB5DI/AAAAAAAAAEE/9ydcM8EXzxA/s320/Falling+Ice3.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
  The plot shows vertical vs. horizontal distance, and the units are meters. The red line is 15 degrees, the blue line is 30 degrees, and the black line is 45 degrees. (click to&amp;nbsp;enlarge)&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;hr /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In summary, the answer is unclear. What I really need to do is measure
the angle of my roof better, because there&amp;#8217;s a significant angle
dependence. It&amp;#8217;s also quite possible that we didn&amp;#8217;t see a maximum
distance hit (thankfully!). In addition, air resistance doesn&amp;#8217;t seem to
matter much in this particular problem, probably because the distance
the thing falls is short enough that terminal velocity is not reached.
Hopefully this gave you a bit of a taste of a more practical physics
problem, and how to approach air resistance (if you want to see the
mathematica code, let me know). The lesson here seems to be either don&amp;#8217;t
park too close to roofs, or have insurance for your&amp;nbsp;windshield!&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 27 Jan 2011 22:41:00 -0500</pubDate><guid>tag:,2011-01-27:posts/falling-ice.html</guid><category>ice</category><category>air resistance</category><category>physics</category></item><item><title>Cryopreservation</title><link>/posts/cryopreservation.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TAKGwD0rgVI/AAAAAAAAABk/VqmdMGXzMCI/s1600/frozen.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/TAKGwD0rgVI/AAAAAAAAABk/VqmdMGXzMCI/s200/frozen.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
I&amp;#8217;d like to start a short series of posts on what I&amp;#8217;m doing this summer.
Like most all of the first year physics graduate students, I&amp;#8217;ve found a
&lt;a href="http://pages.physics.cornell.edu/~rthorne/"&gt;research group&lt;/a&gt; at Cornell
for the summer, and if everything goes well, I&amp;#8217;ll continue working with
them after the summer is done. This is good for three reasons. First,
I&amp;#8217;m getting paid, so I can do things like pay rent. I&amp;#8217;m not all about
the money, but having a place to live is a big deal to me. Second, I&amp;#8217;m
getting a chance to explore a new area of research, with limited
expectation of commitment on my part. Third, if everything works out,
I&amp;#8217;ve found the group I&amp;#8217;ll be working with the for the next 4-6 years.
I&amp;#8217;d like to spend a few posts here on The Virtuosi discussing first the
physics I&amp;#8217;m considering, and then what I actually do. Today I&amp;#8217;m going to
talk about the most exciting sounding piece of my work,
cryopreservation. &lt;strong&gt;What do we mean when we talk about
cryopreservation?&lt;/strong&gt; For many of us our first thought may be Han Solo
frozen in carbonite. This is the basic idea. Cryopreservation is the
freezing biological samples, and thawing them, while they retain
biological viability. At least, that&amp;#8217;s the idea. At the moment,
cryopreservation is the freezing and thawing biological samples, and
hoping that some of them remain biologically viable. Even though the
methods have been in development since the 1950s, successes are limited
even for such simple objects as spermatozoa or oocytes (sperm &lt;span class="amp"&gt;&amp;amp;&lt;/span&gt; eggs),
let alone larger and much more complicated objects like Harrison Ford.
&lt;strong&gt;Why would we want to cryopreserve something? (and did I just invent a
verb?)&lt;/strong&gt; The idea is fairly simple. If we cool down biological samples,
biological functions slow down or completely stop. The hope is that if
we get samples sufficiently cold, we can suspend biological (and all
other) functions indefinitely. This would allow indefinitely
preservation of many things. Eggs and sperm for reproductive purposes
(both human and other animals), plant seeds, blood (for transfusions),
vaccines, drugs (no more pesky shelf life for pharmaceuticals until you
unfreeze them). The perfect frozen strawberries. The list of
possibilities is huge. And according to my dictionary, cryopreserve is a
well established verb. &lt;strong&gt;Why is it so hard?&lt;/strong&gt; It&amp;#8217;s easy to stick
something in the freezer. That seems to work on my food. However, it
doesn&amp;#8217;t work well on biological samples. If we just stick them in the
freezer many of the cells are damaged irreparably. We&amp;#8217;d like to know
why. To answer this we&amp;#8217;re going to need to take a step down to the
cellular level. I&amp;#8217;m not a biologist, so I&amp;#8217;m not going to attempt to
explain cell structure to you. For our current purposes it is sufficient
to know that cells have an inside and an outside (then, doesn&amp;#8217;t most
everything?), separated by a semi-permeable membrane, and that both
inside and outside of the cells there is water. We need to take a brief
detour now into the realm of water. Water is a fantastically amazing
substance, and I&amp;#8217;m not just saying that because we (and most/all life on
earth) would all die without it. Water is fascinating from a pure
physics perspective. Now, when I refer to water, I&amp;#8217;m going to use it to
mean &lt;span class="caps"&gt;H2O&lt;/span&gt;, in any phase. Colloquially we usually mean liquid water when
we say water, we say ice we mean crystalline frozen water, and steam
when we mean vaporous water. I&amp;#8217;m going to call all of these things
&amp;#8216;water&amp;#8217; and I will specify what phase I mean by saying &amp;#8216;frozen, liquid,
vapor&amp;#8217;. I will refer to frozen &lt;em&gt;crystalline&lt;/em&gt; water as &lt;em&gt;ice&lt;/em&gt;. So what&amp;#8217;s
so fascinating about water? Well, first off, it is one of the only
substances that expands when it crystallizes (forms ice). Most objects
become more dense when they transform from a liquid to a solid. Water
doesn&amp;#8217;t. This is why ice floats. There are many other fascinating
aspects of water, for example, that liquid water is most dense at 4 C.
This is mostly responsible for why fish survive in the winter. Ice forms
on top of lakes/rivers, and the 4C water stays at the bottom of the lake
because it is the densest. But for our purposes, what we really need to
know is that water expands on forming ice. When we freeze our cells,
this expansion of water can cause massive problems. Everything in the
cell besides the water contracts on cooling. The water crystallizes and
expands (by about 9%). If you&amp;#8217;ve ever frozen something liquid in a very
full container and seeing it split the container open, the idea is very
similar. The intracellular water can crystallize and split open the cell
membrane. Once you&amp;#8217;ve split the cell membrane, there&amp;#8217;s no way (that I&amp;#8217;ve
seen) to successfully revive that cell. It turns out that ice formation
outside the cell isn&amp;#8217;t such a big deal, it usually just pushes the cells
around. The water in the cells is what is most likely to cause damage to
our biological tissues when we freeze them. &lt;a href="http://www.sciencedirect.com/science?_ob=ArticleURL&amp;amp;_udi=B6WD5-4KXF5HB-1&amp;amp;_user=10&amp;amp;_coverDate=08%2F31%2F1968&amp;amp;_rdoc=1&amp;amp;_fmt=high&amp;amp;_orig=search&amp;amp;_sort=d&amp;amp;_docanchor=&amp;amp;view=c&amp;amp;_acct=C000050221&amp;amp;_version=1&amp;amp;_urlVersion=0&amp;amp;_userid=10&amp;amp;md5=41501096aa949fd2c441dc760bc6513a"&gt;Early
studies&lt;/a&gt;
showed survival rates between 10\^-6% and \~50%. Those are not good
odds. &lt;strong&gt;How do we prevent this damage?&lt;/strong&gt; There are two methods currently
in practice to prevent damage on cooling. The first of these is slow
cooling. It was discovered that if you cool your sample at a rate of \~1
C/min very little to no intracellular ice forms, though intercellular
ice still forms. The water in and between cells is not pure water, but
contains all kinds of things (proteins, salts, etc). This means that it
starts to crystallize not at 0 C, but somewhere lower. This is the
reason we salt sidewalks in the winter (at least, in places where we get
snow). The salt lowers the freezing point of water, causing the ice/snow
to melt even if the temperature is below 0 C. Of course, if the
temperature gets low enough it will still freeze. So our intra and
intercellular water crystallizes below 0 C. It turns out that the
intercellular water starts to crystallize before the intracellular
water. This means we have ice formation outside the cell while the water
inside the cell is still liquid. Earlier I told you that we needed to
know that the membrane of a cell was semi-permiable. This is why. Some
water diffuses through the membrane. At room temperature, the liquid
water outside the cells diffuses into the cell at the same rate that the
liquid water inside the cell diffuses out of the cell. Now, if we start
crystallizing the intercellular water, there will be less liquid water
moving into the cell. But since the intracellular water is still liquid
it will still be diffusing out at the same rate. This results in a
partial dehydration of the cell, more liquid water moving out than in.
This is a basic example of osmotic pressure. With less liquid water in
the cell, when it does crystallize, the ice crystals that form are
smaller, and less likely to damage the cell membrane. This method is not
perfect, because extreme dehydration of cells will also damage them, due
to cell shrinkage and extremely high solute concentration (this
phenomena is called osmotic shock). The second method that is considered
is ultrafast cooling. Here we must take another diversion into physics
land. You may have noticed my emphasis on ice as crystalline water. It
turns out that when you freeze water, forming a crystal is not the only
option available to it (and we&amp;#8217;re not even going to discuss the variety
of crystals it can form). It can also form a glass. Now, if you&amp;#8217;re not a
physicist, you&amp;#8217;re probably not familiar with glass as a type of
substance, but rather as the thing you put in your windows and drink out
of. A glass, to a physicist, is, essentially, a solid without long range
order. The best way to think about of it would be to imagine you took
liquid water and stopped time for the water (*not* freezing it in the
conventional sense). That&amp;#8217;s a glass. It looks like liquid water, has the
same density as liquid water, but is a solid. It&amp;#8217;s a very strange
concept, and I&amp;#8217;m going to save a more thorough discussion for a later
post, because that takes me into a whole different research area I&amp;#8217;m
working on this summer. For our purposes, it is sufficient to know that
we can reach a solid state of water at cold temperatures that has the
same density as liquid water. Based on our discussion above, the
advantages should be immediately obvious. Without the expansion of ice
to worry about, the solidification of water is nowhere near as damaging
to our cells. By vitrifying (turning to a glass) our liquid water, we
should see much less damage to the cells. To achieve vitrification, you
have to cool down the cells much faster (depending on the substance
&gt;1000 C/min). How do we do this? The conventional method is to dunk the
cells directly into liquid nitrogen, or put them into a very cold stream
of gas (around liquid nitrogen temperatures). I should note that I&amp;#8217;m
skipping over a very large field of putting cryopreservants into cells
and freezing them. However, the effect of cryopreservants is to prevent
ice crystallization, and so this is just a method of vitrification. It
just makes it easier to achieve by lowering the rate you have to cool
the sample at. &lt;strong&gt;So that&amp;#8217;s it?&lt;/strong&gt; It may seem like that&amp;#8217;s the solution.
Cooling fast enough to vitrify the liquid water, and we&amp;#8217;ll get good
cryopreservation of our cells. The rest is just technology development.
Unfortunately, it&amp;#8217;s not that easy. It turns out that warming is a harder
problem to solve than cooling. When we warm up glassy water, it turns
back into supercooled liquid water (liquid water way below the freezing
point of water). I&amp;#8217;ll discuss this in more detail in my next post on my
research. So now we&amp;#8217;ve got really cold water, and it will start forming
ice, unless we warm up fast enough to prevent that, very similar to how
we had to cool down very quickly to prevent ice formation. The problem
is, experiments suggest that &amp;#8216;fast enough&amp;#8217; is at least 10-100 times
faster than cooling down. Not only that, but on cooling down, we&amp;#8217;re
really trying to get very very cold. On warming up, we don&amp;#8217;t want to get
much over room temperature, otherwise we&amp;#8217;ll fry the cells. So we have to
warm really really quickly, in an extremely well controlled manner. So
far, this has proved very challenging to do. A recent study with mouse
oocytes achieved a \~90% success rate with their freezing/thawing
cycles, and that is the best that I&amp;#8217;ve seen. 90% is pretty good, but
we&amp;#8217;d like to do better. &lt;strong&gt;So what&amp;#8217;s your research this summer?&lt;/strong&gt; It
turns out that my research isn&amp;#8217;t so much into cryopreservation. As I
will talk about next post, it is more into the physics of
crystallization and glass formation of aqueous substances, where there
is a lot of fundamental physics still to be understood. However, one of
the most exciting eventual applications is cryopreservation. We&amp;#8217;ve
already developed a fast cooling system, and we&amp;#8217;re working on a fast
warming system that will allow us to study crystallization and glass
formation, and hopefully extend the techniques we develop into the field
of cryopreservation. &lt;strong&gt;That&amp;#8217;s way cool!&lt;/strong&gt; Yes. Yes it is. Even if that
is a horrible pun. &lt;em&gt;Note: The question and answer format was inspired by
Chad over at &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/principles/"&gt;Uncertain Principles&lt;/a&gt;
and his research&amp;nbsp;blogging.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 30 May 2010 13:42:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-05-30:posts/cryopreservation.html</guid><category>ice</category><category>glass</category><category>cryopreservation</category><category>summer research</category></item></channel></rss>