<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://localhost:8000/feeds/tag.probability.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 15:13:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Pi storage</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/pi-storage.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-4x2fD-exJns/T2DAEJqroqI/AAAAAAAAAbI/8_9quiDP4p0/s1600/floppies.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://4.bp.blogspot.com/-4x2fD-exJns/T2DAEJqroqI/AAAAAAAAAbI/8_9quiDP4p0/s320/floppies.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Let me share my worst &amp;#8220;best idea ever&amp;#8221; moment. Sometime during my
undergraduate I thought I had solved all the world&amp;#8217;s problems. You see,
on this fateful day, my hard drive was full. I hate it when my hard
drive fills up, it means I have to go and get rid of some of my stuff. I
hate getting rid of my stuff. But what can someone do? And then it hit
me, I had the bright&amp;nbsp;idea:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;What if we didn&amp;#8217;t have to &lt;em&gt;store&lt;/em&gt; things, what if we could just
&lt;em&gt;compute&lt;/em&gt; files whenever we wanted them&amp;nbsp;back?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Sounds like an awesome idea, right? I know. But how could we compute our
files? Well, as you may know pi is conjectured to be a &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Normal_number"&gt;normal
number&lt;/a&gt;, meaning its digits
are probably random. We also know that it is irrational, meaning pi
never ends&amp;#8230;. Since its digits are random, and they never end, in
principle any sequence you could ever imagine should show up in pi
eventually. In fact there is a nifty website
&lt;a href="http://pi.nersc.gov/"&gt;here&lt;/a&gt; that will let you search for arbitrary
strings (using a 5-bit format) in first 4 billion digits, for example
&amp;#8220;alemi&amp;#8221; &lt;a href="http://pi.nersc.gov/cgi-bin/pi.cgi?word=alemi&amp;amp;format=char"&gt;seems to show
up&lt;/a&gt; at around
digit 3149096356. So in principle, I could send you just an index, and a
length, and you could compute the resulting file. But wait you cry,
isn&amp;#8217;t computing digits of pi hard, don&amp;#8217;t people work really hard to
compute pi farther and farther? Hold on I claim, first of all, I&amp;#8217;m
imagining a future where computation is cheap. Secondly, there is a
really neat algorithm, the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bailey%E2%80%93Borwein%E2%80%93Plouffe_formula"&gt;&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BBP&lt;/span&gt;
algorithm&lt;/a&gt;,
that enables you to compute the kth binary digit of pi without knowing
any of the preceding digits. In other words, in principle if you wanted
to know the 4 billionth digit of pi, you can compute it without having
to first compute the first 4 billion other digits. Cool, this is
beginning to sound like a really good idea. What&amp;#8217;s the catch? Perhaps
you&amp;#8217;ve already gotten a taste of it. Let&amp;#8217;s try to estimate just how far
along in pi we would have to look before our message of interest shows
up. Let&amp;#8217;s assume we have written our file in binary, and are computing
pi in binary&amp;nbsp;e.g.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;ol&gt;
&lt;li&gt;00100100 00111111 01101010 10001000 10000101 10100011 00001000&amp;nbsp;11010011&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;etc. So, if the sequence is random, there is a 1/2 chance that at any
point we get the right starting bit of our file, and then a 1/2 chance
we get the next one, etc. So the chance that we would create our file if
we were randomly flipping coins would be &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ P = \left( \frac{1}{2}
\right)^N = 2^{-N} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; if our file was N bits long. So where do we
expect this sequence to first show up in the digits of pi? Well, this
turns out to be a &lt;a href="http://mathworld.wolfram.com/CoinTossing.html"&gt;subtle
problem&lt;/a&gt;, but we can get
a feel for it by assuming that we compute N digits of pi at a time and
see if its right or not. If its not, we move on to the next group of N
digits, if its right, we&amp;#8217;re done. If this were the case, we should
expect to have to draw about &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \frac{1}{P} = 2^N $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; times until we
have a success, and since each trial ate up N digits, we should expect
to see our file show up after about &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ N 2^N $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; digits of pi. Great, so
instead of handing you the file, I could just hand you the index the
file is located. But how many bits would I need to tell you that index.
Well, just like we know that 10^3 takes 4 digits to express in decimal,
and 6 x 10^7 takes 8 digits to express, in general it takes &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ d =
\log_b x + 1 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; digits to express a number in base b, in this case it
takes &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ d = \log_2 ( N 2^N ) + 1= \log_2 2^N + \log_2 N + 1 = N
+ \log_2 N + 1 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; digits to express this index in binary. And there&amp;#8217;s
the rub. Instead of sending you N bits of information contained in the
file, all my genius compression algorithm has manged to do is replace N
bits of information in the file, with a number that takes ( \~ N +
\log_2 N ) bits to express. I&amp;#8217;ve actually managed to make the files
larger not smaller! You may have noticed above, that even for the simple
case of &amp;#8220;alemi&amp;#8221;, all I managed to do was swap the binary&amp;nbsp;message&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;alemi -&gt; 0000101100001010110101001 with the index 3149096356 -&gt;
10111011101100110110010110100100&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;which is longer in binary! As an aside, you may have felt uncomfortable
with my estimation for how long we have to wait to see our message, and
you would be right. Just because all N digits I draw at a time don&amp;#8217;t
match up doesn&amp;#8217;t mean that the second half isn&amp;#8217;t useful. For instance if
I was looking for 010, lets say some of the digits are 101,010. While
both of those sequences didn&amp;#8217;t match, if I was looking at every digit at
a time, I would have found a match. And you&amp;#8217;d be right. &lt;a href="http://www.cs.elte.hu/~mori/cikkek/Expectation.pdf"&gt;Smarter people
than I&lt;/a&gt; have
computed just how long you should have to wait, and end up with the
better estimation &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ \text{wait time} \sim 2^N N \log 2 $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; which is
pretty darn close to our silly&amp;nbsp;estimate.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Alemi</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 14 Mar 2012 15:13:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2012-03-14:posts/pi-storage.html</guid><category>pi day</category><category>fun</category><category>probability</category><category>storage</category></item><item><title>I was born on Wednesday</title><link>http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/posts/i-was-born-on-wednesday.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Probability is a tricky thing. There are a lot of nonsensical answers to
be had. I just read &lt;a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn18950-magic-numbers-a-meeting-of-mathemagical-tricksters.html?full=true"&gt;an
article&lt;/a&gt;
about the recent &lt;a href="http://www.g4g4.com/"&gt;Gathering for Gardner&lt;/a&gt; meeting
that took place. Gathering for Gardner is a unique meeting for
mathematicians, magicians and puzzle makers where they get together and
talk about interesting things. The meetings were inspired by &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Martin_Gardner"&gt;Martin
Gardner&lt;/a&gt;, one of the
awesomest dudes of our time, who unfortunately just passed away. The
question put to the floor was the&amp;nbsp;following:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;I have two children. One is a boy born on a Tuesday. What is the
probability I have two&amp;nbsp;boys?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Think about that for a moment. Not too hard though. The answer turns out
to be surprising. Upon reading the question, I thought about it for a
long time and managed to confused myself entirely. Thinking I had gone
crazy, I wrote a little python script to test the riddle, which only
left me more convinced I had gone insane. I&amp;#8217;ve spent most of the night
thinking about it, and after making it half way to crazy, I&amp;#8217;ve come
around and am momentarily convinced the puzzle makes perfect sense. I&amp;#8217;m
going to attempt to convince you it makes perfect sense, but I plan on
doing it in steps so as to reduce the&amp;nbsp;bewilderment.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Playing&amp;nbsp;Cards&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Forget the question. Lets play a game of cards. You shuffle a deck and
deal me two&amp;nbsp;cards:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s1600/b2fv.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s320/b2fv.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s1600/b2fv.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s320/b2fv.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I accidentally flip one of them&amp;nbsp;over.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCuZ4KiQI/AAAAAAAAALA/cNa3n-rjuTg/s1600/23.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCuZ4KiQI/AAAAAAAAALA/cNa3n-rjuTg/s320/23.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s1600/b2fv.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s320/b2fv.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whats the probability that my other card is red? Well, that ones easy,
its about half. Sure, its not exactly a half, knowing that the deck is
finite and that the draws are done without replacement, knowing that the
card showing is a red one means that there are only 52/2 - 1= 26 -1 = 25
red cards out of a deck of 52-1 = 51 cards giving a probability of 49%.
But its basically a half. Lets do over, deal me two&amp;nbsp;cards:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s1600/b2fv.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s320/b2fv.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s1600/b2fv.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s320/b2fv.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Darn, I flipped one of them over&amp;nbsp;again:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s1600/b2fv.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s320/b2fv.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zDlNQLJyI/AAAAAAAAALI/WPBCX9i-Pk0/s1600/5.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zDlNQLJyI/AAAAAAAAALI/WPBCX9i-Pk0/s320/5.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Whats the probability that my other card is red? About a half still.&lt;em&gt;
(&lt;/em&gt;Sure, this time its really 26/51 = 51%). Nothing mysterious going on.
Do over again. Deal me two&amp;nbsp;cards:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s1600/b2fv.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s320/b2fv.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;a href="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s1600/b2fv.png"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://3.bp.blogspot.com/_YOjDhtygcuA/S_zCNBPs3KI/AAAAAAAAAK4/WdtzaW_A6pk/s320/b2fv.png" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I&amp;#8217;ll ask a little trickier question. Whats the probability
that both my cards are red? Ah, well its about 1/2 * 1/2 or about 1/4 =
25%. (The real answer is 24.5%) Alright smarty pants. Whats the
probability that I had a red card and a black one? Well, that ought to
be about 1/2 (Real answer 51%). All in all, I could have a red card,
then a black one (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RB&lt;/span&gt;), or a black one, then a red one (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR&lt;/span&gt;), or a red one
then a red one (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;RR&lt;/span&gt;) or a black one then a black one (&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BB&lt;/span&gt;). 4 distinct
possibilities, each of which are equally likely, so the above two
answers make complete sense. There is only one way in four to get both
red cards, but two ways out of four to have both a red and a black. So
far so good. Lets ask a different question. Now I&amp;#8217;m going to get a bit
obtuse. You deal me two cards. Now you ask&amp;nbsp;me.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Hey Alemi, do you have a red&amp;nbsp;card?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Meaning, do I have at least one red card. I respond, &amp;#8220;Yes.&amp;#8221; Now, go with
your gut. You know I have at least one red card. What do you reckon the
color of the other one is? Probably black you say? You&amp;#8217;d be correct.
Looking at our breakdown above, I could have gotten &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RR&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RB&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR&lt;/span&gt;, or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BB&lt;/span&gt; as
my cards dealt. Each was equally likely, but now you know something
else. You know that I have at least one red card, so we only have three
possibilities left, I either have &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RR&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;RB&lt;/span&gt;, or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BR&lt;/span&gt;. Each of which was
equally likely. So whats the probability that my other card is black?
About 2/3 or 67%. (Real answer: 67.5%) Alright, same situation. You deal
me two cards, I reveal that I have at least one red one. Whats the
probability that my other card is red? Well, obviously 1/3 or 33%
(Actually 32.5%) since this is the opposite question to the one directly
above, and follows from the same reasoning. Fine. No problems. All of
this makes&amp;nbsp;sense.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Offspring&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Instead of playing cards, lets return to offspring. Lets first look at a
classic probability&amp;nbsp;riddle.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have exactly two children. At least one of them is a boy. What is
the probability that the other one is a&amp;nbsp;boy?&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If I were to give you this question straightaway, most people would have
said the probability would be a 1/2. Their reasoning being that boys and
girls are equally likely. But having just led you through the playing
cards, hopefully now it makes some sense how the true answer to this
question is 1/3 or 33%. Originally my family could have been &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BB&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span class="caps"&gt;BG&lt;/span&gt;,&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GB&lt;/span&gt;,or
&lt;span class="caps"&gt;GG&lt;/span&gt;. Each of which was equally likely. Telling you I have at least one
boy means now we are dealing with only the situations &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BB&lt;/span&gt;, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;BG&lt;/span&gt; or &lt;span class="caps"&gt;GB&lt;/span&gt;,
still all equally likely, making the probability 1/3. Fine. Now, lets
reexamine the true question at&amp;nbsp;hand:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;span class="dquo"&gt;&amp;#8220;&lt;/span&gt;I have two children. One is a boy born on a Tuesday. What is the
probability I have two&amp;nbsp;boys?&amp;#8221;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Is it a half? Is it 1/3? What do you reckon? At first thought, it seems
like the Tuesday bit shouldn&amp;#8217;t enter into it at all, but on second
thought, I&amp;#8217;ve just revealed a lot more information than I did in the
previous question. I&amp;#8217;ve told you something specific about one of my
children. This is analogous to when I accidently flipped over one of my
cards, revealing not only its color but its count as well. Hopefully it
makes sense that the probability ought to be much closer to a half than
to a third. In fact the answer is 13/27 = 48.1%. With a little thought,
you should be able to come up with that number yourself. Otherwise, see
&lt;a href="http://www.newscientist.com/article/dn18950-magic-numbers-a-meeting-of-mathemagical-tricksters.html?full=true"&gt;the
article&lt;/a&gt;
I mentioned at the beginning of this post. They have a nice breakdown at
the bottom. Hopefully, at this point if you&amp;#8217;ve read this far, you&amp;#8217;d
should be wondering why this question was so mysterious to begin with,
and if thats the case, I did my job. If you think the question is
obvious, and think it would have been obvious even without the card
analogy, try and ask the boy-born-on-a-tuesday question by itself to one
of your friends. I guarantee they&amp;#8217;ll be bewildered. Its a fun problem,
and one that illustrates just how strange and counterintuitive
probability can be. If you want some other mind twisting mathematical
puzzles, try your hand at the &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Two_envelopes_problem"&gt;Two envelopes
problem&lt;/a&gt;, or
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Bertrand's_box_paradox"&gt;Bertrands&amp;#8217; box
paradox&lt;/a&gt;, or &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Birthday_problem"&gt;the
Birthday problem&lt;/a&gt;, or
everyone&amp;#8217;s favorite &lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Monty_Hall_problem"&gt;the Monty Hall
problem&lt;/a&gt;. &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/some-of-best-advice-youll-ever-receive.html"&gt;Remember
though&lt;/a&gt;,
try your hand at the problem before reading the answer. Super fun bonus
homework question: Lets do cards again. You deal me two cards, and I
reveal that I have a red heart. Whats the probability that my other card
is&amp;nbsp;red?&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Alemi</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 26 May 2010 03:17:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:thephysicsvirtuosi.com,2010-05-26:posts/i-was-born-on-wednesday.html</guid><category>odds</category><category>fun</category><category>cards</category><category>probability</category><category>birthday</category><category>monty hall</category></item></channel></rss>