<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><channel><title>The Physics Virtuosi</title><link>/</link><description></description><atom:link href="http://thephysicsvirtuosi.com/feeds/tag.laser.rss.xml" rel="self"></atom:link><lastBuildDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2010 22:22:00 -0400</lastBuildDate><item><title>Laser Launching</title><link>/posts/laser-launching.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S8-y4RmjAhI/AAAAAAAAABE/CueT0Sq1ZYc/s1600/space-war-laser.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S8-y4RmjAhI/AAAAAAAAABE/CueT0Sq1ZYc/s200/space-war-laser.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Lasers seem to be on my mind recently. Just yesterday, the class I &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TA&lt;/span&gt;
for (E&amp;amp;M for engineers) talked about the momentum carried by E&amp;amp;M waves.
This called to mind a discussion I had with a housemate a few weeks
back. He had heard somewhere that &amp;#8216;they&amp;#8217; were thinking of launching
satellites with lasers. &lt;em&gt;No way&lt;/em&gt;, I thought to myself. &lt;em&gt;Satellites are
too heavy&lt;/em&gt;. However, his question has been hovering around in my mind,
so I&amp;#8217;ve decided to try and answer it: can we use a laser to launch a
satellite into orbit? Let us begin with a few simplifying assumptions.
I&amp;#8217;m going to assume that we want our launched satellite to reach the
escape velocity of the earth. Of course, we don&amp;#8217;t want a satellite to
escape orbit, but escape velocity is calculated without considering any
kind of drag forces on our launched object. To first order then, I
expect achieving escape velocity will get our satellite into a
relatively high orbit without actually escaping earth&amp;#8217;s gravity well.
Second, I&amp;#8217;m going to assume our laser is on the ground (reusable
launching device!), and that our satellite is perfectly reflective, so
we&amp;#8217;re not going to be melting it. Finally, I&amp;#8217;m going to assume that the
laser will remain effective at targeting our object up to 15 km above
the surface, around the effective range for lasers used as guides for
&lt;a href="http://en.wikipedia.org/wiki/Adaptive_optics"&gt;adaptive optics&lt;/a&gt; in
telescopes.
Now, to the meat of the problem. First, we need to find the escape
velocity from the earth. This is defined as the velocity we would need
to give an object to overcome the gravitational energy of the earth upon
the object. This is found by setting the kinetic energy of the object
equal to the change in gravitational potential energy from the earth&amp;#8217;s
surface to infinity:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ KE=\\Delta PE $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$\\tfrac{1}{2}mv\_{esc}\^2 = \\frac{GM\_{earth}m}{R\_{earth}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
(for those interested, the gravitational potential energy at infinity is
defined to be zero). We can easily solve this for v,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$ v\_{esc}=\\sqrt{\\frac{2GM\_{earth}}{R\_{earth}}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
To me, the most remarkable feature of the escape velocity is that it is
independent of the mass of the object! We can now plug in numbers, and
find an escape velocity if \~11.2 km/s.
We now make use of our constraint, that we have to achieve this escape
velocity over 15 km. We assume the laser outputs a constant number of
photons per second, n. The force the laser provides the satellite is the
change in momentum with time,
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$F=\\frac{dp}{dt}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
How is our laser imparting momentum to our system? Well, light is
composed of photons, tiny packets of light. Each photon has momentum.
Assume each photon reflects perfectly, that is, straight backwards and
with no energy loss. Then the photon has reversed its momentum. Since
momentum is conserved, the satellite has gained a momentum of 2p. The
momentum of a photon is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$p=\\frac{h}{\\lambda}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
where h is Planck&amp;#8217;s constant. This gives
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$F=\\frac{2nh}{\\lambda}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Given a constant force, the time taken to reach some velocity is just
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$t=mv/F$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
In our case the v is the escape velocity. Now, given a constant force,
and no initial velocity, an object of mass m travels a distance d in a
time t given by
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$d=\\frac{F}{2m}t\^2$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
We can substitute our expression for t into this expression, giving
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$d=\\left(\\frac{F}{2m}\\right)\\left(\\frac{mv}{F}\\right)\^2$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$d=\\frac{mv\^2}{2F}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
What we are really interested in is n, the number of photons per second
this process takes, so we substitute our expression for the force, and
solve for n:
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$d=\\frac{mv\^2\\lambda}{4nh}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
s0
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$n=\\frac{mv\^2\\lambda}{4hd}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Now that we have the number of photons per second our laser supplies,
all that is left is to find the power of laser this would take. The
power of a laser will be given by the number of photons per second times
the energy per photon. The energy per photon is given by E=hf where f is
the frequency of our light. So, the power, P, of our laser is
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$P=nE$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; or
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$P=\\frac{mv\_{esc}\^2\\lambda f}{4d}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; so
&lt;mathjax&gt;$$P=\\frac{mv\_{esc}\^2 c}{4d}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt;
Where we have recognized that the frequency times the wavelength of a
photon is just the speed of light, c.
All that remains is to plug in numbers. A medium sized satellite might
be about 750kg, giving a laser power of 4.7*10\^14W. This is .5 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;PW&lt;/span&gt;.
According to wikipedia, the greatest power output of a continuous
operation laser is on the order of 1 kW, or \~10\^12 times less than our
necessary power! There&amp;#8217;s no way we&amp;#8217;re getting a normal sized satellite
into orbit with a laser. What about a smaller satellite? In recent years
picosatellites have proposed, with masses of \~.1kg. This gives a
necessary power of 6.2*10\^10, or 620 &lt;span class="caps"&gt;TW&lt;/span&gt;. This is still \~10\^8 times
greater than our most powerful continuous laser. In fact, reversing the
calculation, our laser could launch a satellite with a mass of \~1.6 mg.
A little googling reveals this is the same order of magnitude as a grain
of rice! Simply put, we&amp;#8217;re not going to be launching satellites with
lasers anytime&amp;nbsp;soon.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2010 22:22:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-04-21:posts/laser-launching.html</guid><category>laser</category><category>launch</category><category>satellite</category><category>physics</category></item><item><title>Laser Gun Recoil: Follow-up</title><link>/posts/laser-gun-recoil-follow-up.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Matt Springer over at &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/builtonfacts/"&gt;Built on
Fact&lt;/a&gt;s has a &lt;a href="http://scienceblogs.com/builtonfacts/2010/04/laser_rifle_recoil.php"&gt;very nice
post&lt;/a&gt;
following up on my earlier analysis of &lt;a href="http://thevirtuosi.blogspot.com/2010/04/today-id-like-to-approach-question-near.html"&gt;whether or not a laser gun would
recoil&lt;/a&gt;.
In my analysis I came to the conclusion that the momentum delivered was
much less than that of a conventional gun, but that the impulse, and
hence the force delivered, was about the same. However, that force was
delivered over a \~30ns timescale, which left open the question of
whether or not the wielder would be able to feel that recoil. While I
had thought to possibly return to this issue at some point, Matt has
beat me to it. This is fortuitous, because I wasn&amp;#8217;t sure quite where to
start with the question, while he approaches it in a very sensible,
clear manner. The gist of his post is that he compares our response to
short time scale forces to our ability to sense sound. I won&amp;#8217;t go
through his calculations, you can check those out for yourself, but he
concludes that it is very unlikely that we could feel the recoil of our
laser gun. Case closed. Though, like any good scientist, we may choose
to reopen it later if more evidence comes to&amp;nbsp;light.&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 21 Apr 2010 16:31:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-04-21:posts/laser-gun-recoil-follow-up.html</guid><category>recoil</category><category>laser</category><category>sound</category><category>momentum</category><category>gun</category></item><item><title>Would a laser gun recoil?</title><link>/posts/would-a-laser-gun-recoil-.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Today I&amp;#8217;d like to approach a question near and dear to many a geek
heart: do laser guns have recoil?
&lt;a href="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S76cWh0vVrI/AAAAAAAAAA8/3AVsx5suF0A/s1600/19990814dogfight.jpg"&gt;&lt;img alt="image" src="http://2.bp.blogspot.com/_SYZpxZOlcb0/S76cWh0vVrI/AAAAAAAAAA8/3AVsx5suF0A/s200/19990814dogfight.jpg" /&gt;&lt;/a&gt;
Let&amp;#8217;s motivate our question a little bit. I&amp;#8217;ve wondered about this
question since I saw star wars. Though I&amp;#8217;m no firearms expert, the
recoil in guns must come from conservation of momentum principles.
Momentum is conserved in a system. The gun starts with zero momentum. We
fire, give the bullet momentum, and so to keep the system at zero
momentum, the gun must gain equal and opposite momentum. That is, the
gun will move backwards. All of that was for conventional guns. Light
carries momentum, so if we fire a pulse of light, we expect our laser
gun to recoil. So yes, they do have recoil. Satisfied, dear readers?
Neither am I. The question we really mean to ask is, does a laser gun
have noticeable recoil? We need to make a few reasonable assumptions.
Let&amp;#8217;s assume that the laser gun fires a pulse with as much energy as a
bullet has kinetic energy, &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KE&lt;/span&gt;. The energy, E, of light is related to its
momentum, p, by E=pc, where c is the speed of light. This gives a
momentum of &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ E=KE=pc $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ p=\\frac{KE}{c}$$&lt;/mathjax&gt; What is the kinetic
energy of a bullet? A little searching reveals that a .22 bullet is
\~2.5g and fires with a muzzle velocity of \~330m/s. Kinetic energy is
given by &lt;span class="caps"&gt;KE&lt;/span&gt;=1/2mv\^2, where m is mass and v velocity. So, the momentum
of a laser pulse with equal energy would be &lt;mathjax&gt;$$ p=\\frac{mv\^2}{2c} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
p=\\frac{.0025kg\*(330m/s)\^2}{2\*3\\cdot 10\^8m/s} $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; &lt;mathjax&gt;$$
p=4.5\\cdot10\^{-7}kg \\cdot m/s $$&lt;/mathjax&gt; For comparison, the momentum (p=mv)
of a .22 bullet is .83 kg*m/s. The momentum of a laser gun is 2 million
times less than the momentum of a .22. But is momentum all we should
consider? I suspect the &amp;#8216;kick&amp;#8217; we feel on the recoil is directly related
to the force that the gun exerts on the holder. This means that instead
of momentum we need to consider impulse, momentum per time. We estimate
the time it takes to fire a .22 is \~.1s, so the force delivered 8.3 N.
Let&amp;#8217;s estimate the time it takes a laser gun to fire. Unfortunately, not
having a laser gun to fire (feel free to send me one, dear readers),
we&amp;#8217;re more or less going to have to guess at the firing time. Most
movies with laser guns show pulses of light (which, incidentally would
move so fast we wouldn&amp;#8217;t see them) on the order of a meter or two long.
Given the speed of light, this would give a firing time of \~30
nanoseconds. This would give a force delivered of 15 N. This is close to
what we estimated or a .22. So, if movies are to be believed (and
really, why wouldn&amp;#8217;t we believe them?), it seems like laser guns may
well have recoil. &lt;em&gt;Note: It is worth questioning if we need the same
energy for a laser as for a bullet. That could certainly change our
estimate. Maybe we&amp;#8217;ll return to this question&amp;nbsp;again.&lt;/em&gt;&lt;/p&gt;</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Jesse</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 08 Apr 2010 23:16:00 -0400</pubDate><guid>tag:,2010-04-08:posts/would-a-laser-gun-recoil-.html</guid><category>recoil</category><category>laser</category><category>momentum</category></item></channel></rss>